<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
 <chapter title="HISTORIES" n="1">

  <item id="A1">
   <bib>Alden, R[aymond] M[acdonald]. English Verse: Specimens Illustrating Its Principles and
    History. New York: Henry Holt, 1903; 2nd ed. 1929; rpt New York: AMS Press, 1970. 441 pp. Rev:
    in The Nation 77 (1903): 118–20; by Omond in The Academy 76 (1909): 976–77; in Sewanee Review 11
    (1903): 383–84. </bib>
   <notes> To the teaching critic, English Verse is probably more useful as a compendium of examples
    of verseforms than as a history or theory of English versification, even though the book intends
    to offer both these latter. Chapter One of Part One and Part Three set forth Alden's principles,
    which are that accent at equal time-intervals is the basis of English meter, that three degrees
    of accent (pri- mary, secondary, and weak) from three causes (lexical, syntactic, and metrical)
    are distinguishable, that the metrical pause is allowable, that verse is only analo- gous to
    music, that English syllables do have rudimentary and entirely relative quantity, that the
    concept of the metrical foot is worth preserving so long as it is understood as representing
    "the time-interval between the regularly recur- ring accents of the normal metre," and that in
    scansion the secondary accent if marked only complicates unduly the traditional notation, so
    that only the bi- nary levels of stressed and unstressed are to be noted. Summarized on p. 405.
    As Omond observed, Alden does not pursue the temporal theory of meter as aggressively as most,
    but his analyses do "depart considerably from mere stresses." Alden's position lies somewhere
    between the ad hoc impressionism of Saintsbury and the deductive interpretation of Omond; he
    seems most directly indebted to Schipper (A9) and Mayor (E592). Chapter Two of Part One is
    reprinted in abridged form as an Appendix to Gross (A23, pp. 235–64). Part Two is a history of
    forms; Part Three, "The Time-Element in English Verse," reprints the substance of an earlier
    article in MLN (E272). Part Four collects the views of thirteen poets and critics on "The Place
    and Function of the Metrical Element in Poetry." See also E270 and E271. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A2">
   <bib>Allen, Gay Wilson. American Prosody. New York: American Book Company, 1935; rpt New York:
    Octagon Books, 1966, 1978. 328 pp. Based on his dissertation at Wisconsin in 1934. Rev: by
    Schramm in American Literature 7 (1935): 108–10; in JEGP 34 (1935): 461–62. </bib>
   <notes> Though now somewhat out of date, this well-positioned book has not yet been superseded.
    It does not aim to advance "an ideal prosody . . . any original theories . . . or critical
    estimates," but simply to present a coherent view of the technic of American poetry up to 1900,
    as seen in both the stylistic develop- ment and the known theoretical views of eleven major
    American poets: Freneau, Bryant, Poe, Emerson, Whittier, Longfellow, Holmes, Whitman, Lowell,
    Lanier, and Dickinson. The Introduction has the considerable virtue of distinguishing terms
    clearly and the lesser vice of allowing too many of them: Allen recognizes four natural
    speech-stresses (primary, secondary, "weak secondary," and weak), "metrical stresses"
    (apparently compromise scansions of the natural stressing of the line against the abstract
    metrical pattern), and four regular metrical feet (the common ones) but up to seven additional
    ones (tri- brachs, ionics, bacchics, etc.). A short section also discusses the influence of
    British versification on American, a subject which despite its obvious impor- tance has never
    yet been thoroughly examined. Allen's study broke the neces- sary new ground, but after a half
    century of extensive scholarship it should now be possible to reappraise the whole subject of
    American versification-- both theory and praxis--in a much more systematic and sophisticated
    way. See also Eaton (E25), Gillis (E35), and Fussel (E34). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A3">
   <bib>Kaluza, Max. Englische Metrik in historischer Entwicklung dargestellt. Normannia:
    Germanisch-Romanisch Büucherei, vol 1. Berlin: E. Felber, 1909. 384 pp. Translated into English
    by A. C. Dunstan as: </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A4">
   <bib>Kaluza, Max. A Short History of English Versification From the Earliest Times to the Present Day.
    London: George Allen, 1911. 387 pp. </bib>
   <notes> The translation, which follows the original closely, is hereafter referred to as Kaluza.
    During the writing of his book, Kaluza clearly felt the lingering coolness of the long shadow
    cast by Schipper's monumental work (A9); he is at pains, in the Preface and elsewhere, to
    justify his own study, claiming that "the mass of detail in Schipper is confusing for the
    beginner, and his presentation of Old and Middle English prosody needs correction in many
    important points." In fact, however, Kaluza's own study is considerably more complicated in
    theory and more scholarly in method than Schipper's, and it is decidedly not a book for
    beginners. But no justification was needed: Kaluza has not given us a full- scale history of
    English verse-tech-nique, as did Schipper, but rather a seem- ingly indefatigable study of the
    various prosodic theories about verse—particu- larly Old and Middle English verse--that had been
    advanced up to 1900 by the German philologists. Indeed, Kaluza's title is misleading, since
    fully two-thirds of his book treats English verse before 1500. But for this single purpose--a
    synoptic, detailed account of the German theories of the Old Germanic and Old English
    alliterative line--Kaluza is valuable, and in that value superior to any other work yet written.
    After Kaluza we must go directly to the Germans. Kaluza's principles are accentual: the thesis
    and arsis (he uses these terms in their modern sense) make up the foot in syllable-counting
    verse, or the bar (takt, measure) in alliterative stress-verse. Elucidating the course of the
    theories about Old English verse, he discusses the "four-stress" (to the half-line) theory of
    Lachmann and his followers and the competing "two-stress" theory of Wackernagel et al., accounts
    that were eventually superseded by Sievers' "Five Types" system (Sievers himself was of the
    two-stress school). Kaluza adheres to the doctrines of the older four-stress school, and so a
    considerable portion of his long first section on Old English is given over to a detailed
    criticism of the Sievers theory, Kaluza substituting for it instead his own modified version
    (pp. 60–64) of two Laws, six Types, and ninety "subspecies," but nevertheless la- boring to make
    the whole system compatible with the authoritative Five Types typology. See Kaluza's monograph
    (J139) in Part 2, Section 1, below. All the German philologists were pretty well agreed that the
    oldest Indo- European meter had been well agreed that the oldest Indo-European meter had been x
    / x / x / x / x / (later to be called the iambic dimeter in classical Greek metrics), a meter
    which was divided into four bars for purposes of dancing or singing. When he came to the Middle
    English, French-derived meters of our verse, Kaluza had the candor and good sense to acknowledge
    there the pres- ence of an entirely new form, with different rules for construction and hence an
    entirely different texture and structure from that of Old English verse--all merely by the
    addition of the simple rule of syllable-counting. Appropriately, then, Kaluza views the Middle
    English alliterative verses as derived not from the Old English form but from a mixed form of
    the Latin septenary transmitted to the English by the Christian monks. On the Modern period,
    Kaluza gives only a short synopsis of the nature of the modern meters (in modern English it is
    easier than it formerly was to dispose the stresses at rhythmically equal periods of time; the
    poet, then, must create harmony out of the clash of word-stresses and metrical-accents; inver-
    sion and hovering accent were developed to reduce this difficulty, as well as elision, which
    will produce a correct metrical value for excess syllables (pp. 266–84), then traces out in
    cameo the modern development of the various metrical and stanzaic forms, especially blank verse.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A5">
   <bib>Omond, T[homas] S[tewart]. English Metrists: Being a Sketch of English Prosodical Criticism
    from Elizabethan Times to the Present Day. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1921; rpt New York: Phaeton
    Press, 1968. 327 pp. </bib>
   <notes>Rev: in TLS 1 September 1921, p. 557 (reply by Omond in the Correspon-
dence for Sept. 15, p. 596); in Notes &amp;amp; Queries series 12, vol. 8 (1921): 519; by
McKerrow in MLR 17 (1922): 436. Hereafter referred to as Omond.
Our first historical and bibliographical survey of writings on English metrics.
This final and definitive edition of Omond's work, published shortly before his
death, combines and extends his earlier two editions (below) by adding sup-
plements to the bibliographical lists and Postscript which bring the survey up
to 1920. These two earlier studies, in turn, followed Omond's original 1903
monograph on English verse-structure, A Study of Metre (E310) and were in-
tended as bibliographical appendices, but they gradually assumed larger and
larger proportions then complete attention as the research broadened and
deepened (no source-list whatsoever existing at the time). These were:
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A6">
   <bib>Omond, T[homas] S[tewart]. English Metrists. Tunbridge Wells: R. Pelton, 1903. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A7">
   <bib>Omond, T[homas] S[tewart]. English Metrists in the Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries: Being a Sketch of
    English Prosodical Criticism During the Last Two Hundred Years. London: Oxford University Press,
    1907. 268 pp. See his other metrical studies listed below in Chapter Six on Meter, beginning at
    E305. </bib>
   <notes> Prior to the present study, English Metrists offered the most succinct, thorough, and
    accessible history of English metrical theory available. Given the date of Omond's first two
    editions (A6 and A7), a comparison of his work with Saintsbury (A8) is natural, even though the
    contrasts between the two could scarcely be greater: Omond is a history of critical theorizing
    about verse- structure, while Saintsbury is in fact a history of the poets' practice; Omond's
    assumptions about the (temporal) nature of poetic meter are evident on every page of his
    criticism, whereas Saintsbury repeatedly evades the explicit and takes refuge in the ambiguous
    and unexamined; Omond believed that a quan- titative verse could be written in English, whereas
    Saintsbury rejected the pos- sibility out of hand while paradoxically insisting on the retention
    of its archaic terminology. For the serious student of English verseform, however, Omond is the
    indispensable book. English Metrists is not, however, so much a history as a bibliography; the
    text of the book is actually little more than a discursive, amplified commentary on the
    bibliographical lists at the end. So the work might more properly be thought of as discursive
    bibliography (see Chapter Three, Earlier Bibliogra- phies, below). As such, however, its value
    is in no wise diminished; for the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries especially, Omond's
    research was meticu- lous. And he regularly allows three to five pages for a discussion of a
    particu- larly important writer, a practice I have much envied, being unable to follow it here.
    I have included in the present work every full article or book which Omond cites, but there
    remain, in English Metrists, many brief notices of passages of verses, remarks, correspondence,
    and other references which I have not thought worthy of pursuit. Scholars working on future,
    more specialized studies such as the nineteenth century interest in hexameters will want to re-
    turn to these, as well as to search out others which Omond himself mentions only in passing. The
    function of the present book in relation to its predecessor, then, is twofold--extension, and
    organization. The limitations of Omond's book, in other words, form the greater part of the
    rationale for this one. To begin with, Omond's meticulous bibliographic searches end not long
    after the turn of the century (1908 for quantitative verse and, much less rigorously [Omond was
    ill], 1920 for accentual verse). The great mass of newer work published since that time has
    wanted collecting and reviewing, and so I have thought to bring Omond up to date. Moreover,
    though his researches at the British Museum and the Bodleian were prodigious, Omond frequently
    confesses himself unac- quainted to the same degree with American scholarship, particularly
    periodical. He has not, for example, searched the nineteenth-century American literary journals
    for articles on versification as he did the British. But more impor- tantly, Omond's criteria
    for inclusion now seem unacceptably narrow: he ad- mitted only (1) works on English metrics (2)
    written in English, constraints which immediately barred him from the whole field of German
    scholarship on English philology (especially Old English, which Omond had little interest in) in
    the late nineteenth century, as well as from the important treatises of Schip- per, Kaluza,
    Verrier, and others on English metrics. My own criterion has been that a work be on English
    versification (a far wider subject than merely metrics) regardless of its provenience or
    language of discourse. A truly com- prehensive theory will require a truly comprehensive search
    for information. Beyond the problem of scope, however, there is the problem of organi- zation,
    and here Omond's book must be judged to have done little to clear up the immense confusions in
    English metrical theory. The source lists of English Metrists are divided into two parts, one a
    list of attempts to write (and legiti- mize) quantitative meters in English, the other a survey
    of theories about the ordinary accentual-syllabic tradition. This scheme is useful for
    chronological reference, but not for the immediately essential purpose of keeping separate
    problems separate. Omond makes no effort in his second list to sort out the competing schools of
    theorists, a procedure which is immensely important for readers who have little knowledge of the
    field and no idea of the quandaries which await them. Too, the bibliographical lists are
    cumbersome visually, for typographical reasons, and though the citation data is exceptionally
    accurate even for very obscure works, the remarks added thereto are less informative than
    evaluative. This latter difficulty, though, betokens a broader one, and a candid review of
    English Metrists would have to weigh heavily the fact that the book is, albeit modestly, a
    tendentious one. Omond firmly accepts the tem- poral nature of English verse as the foundation
    of its meter. This principle and others are evident, and they continually shade the chronicler's
    responses and judgments. One would prefer a list of sources--beyond question, a history of
    theory--to take a more disinterested stance. Some may believe that such a stance is impossible
    in this particular field, but I for one think that the signifi- cance and cogency of a work can
    be reliably assessed without any particularly strong commitment to one theory or another.
    Certainly one has assumptions, and principles, and I have tried to state mine in the
    Introduction above. But principles ought not deter one from recognizing quality or determining
    typol- ogy. Born in Edinburgh, Omond took his M.A. at St. John's College, Ox- ford; thereafter
    he moved to Tunbridge Wells, a small town in Kent some forty miles southeast of London,
    employing himself as a barrister until his death in 1923 (March 1). He is not listed in the DNB.
    For some time, I have been trying to trace his family, library, papers, and a photograph, but so
    far without much success. His will stipulates that his papers be destroyed. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A8">
   <bib>Saintsbury, George [Edward Bateman]. A History of English Prosody From the Twelfth Century
    to the Present Day. 3 vols. London: Macmillan, 1906–10; 2nd ed. 1923; rpt New York: Russell
    &amp;amp; Russell, 1961. Rev: vol. 1 was reviewed by W. P. Ker in the Scottish Historical Review
    4 (1907): 214–16 and rpt in his Form &amp;amp; Style in Poetry (B115), pp. 316–19. Also noticed
    in Shakespeare Jahrbuch 45 (1909): 404; 48 (1912): 328. See also E528 and E529. Hereafter
    referred to as Saintsbury. </bib>
   <notes> Historically the successor to Guest (E543), the History of English Prosody represents one
    of the monuments of late Victorian criticism (as Saintsbury himself said of Patmore, the work
    "simply swarms with crotchety and temer- arious deliverances") and the most extensive effort
    ever made to trace the po- ets' craft of versifying throughout the entire course of English
    poetry. The suc- cessor to the History, when it comes, will not be written by a single hand. The
    second edition is the definitive one, containing eleven Books of historical sur- vey and fifteen
    Appendices treating specific problems. Since the latter are of more immediate interest for
    gauging Saintsbury than the former (the historical surveys are likely to be consulted only for
    specific purposes), I list the Appen- dices herewith, postponing for the moment, however, any
    discussion of Saintsbury's theories: In vol 1: 1: Equivalence, Substitution, and
    Foot-Arrangement in English; 2: Common Syllables in English, and Degrees in Quantity; 3: The
    Nature and Phenomenon of Doggerel; 4: Alliteration and its Varieties; 5: English
    Feet--1200–1600; 6: English Metres--1200–1600; 7: Pause in English--1200–1600; 8:
    Rhyme--1200–1600; 9: Vowel Music--1200–1600. In vol.3: 1: What Is a foot?; 2: Is the Basic Foot
    of English Iamb or Trochee?; 3: Trisyllabic Metres Since 1600; 4: Rhyme, 1600–1900; 5:
    Alliteration and Vowel Music, 1600–1900; 6: An Omnibus Box [Notes and Addenda]. Upon finishing
    the History, Saintsbury immediately turned his attention to the composition of a more accessible
    work, a student's manual of versifica- tion, which was intended to be "not so much an abstract
    as a parallel with a different purpose." This is his Historical Manual, still a very useful book
    (in many ways much more so than the History), cited below in the chapter on Metrics (E636);
    Saintsbury's prosodic assumptions, methods, and pronounce- ments are discussed at that point.
    Saintsbury lived a very full life (1845–1933); he held the Chair of Rhetoric and English
    Literature at the University of Edinburgh, and he has been accurately assessed by René Wellek as
    "by far the most influential aca- demic literary historian and critic of the early twentieth
    century." Over the course of his career, however, the scope (and variety) of his professional
    publi- cations is staggering. The last of the great generalists, he eschewed the precise and the
    explicit, while never hesitating an instant to deliver an ex cathedra judgment. With Saintsbury,
    evaluation came first, understanding later. He has an irrepressibly exuberant, anecdotal prose
    style that earned him the censure of his contemporaries (Hopkins called it "vulgar"); it is a
    great pleasure to read-- in small doses--but admittedly it is often fluff. On the other hand, it
    is occa- sionally incandescent, too. Saintsbury is of that class of critics censured by Eliot as
    too creative for really accurate analysis. The History of English Prosody is undeniably a great
    monolith of wide and informed reading. Yet at the same time it must surely stand as one of the
    most extravagant irrelevancies in criticism, since the instrument, the method, the theory by
    which the history is conceived, understood, brought into line, and written up is not simply
    vague or imprecise but actually non-existent-- indeed, consciously ignored and avoided.
    Saintsbury was all for Taste, Gusto, Elan (this was what Eliot noticed most); he cared not a
    straw for Precision, Detail, Method, or Proof. In the view of many, therefore, the judgments,
    de- scriptions, and conclusions of the History--in effect the whole weight of the work--are
    entirely vitiated by Saintsbury's perverse and willful refusal to ex- plain, either to himself
    or to us, the assumptions about the nature of meter and verse-structure by which those
    conclusions were reached. In versification clar- ity about assumptions is not merely
    indispensable, it is everything. See MacColl's critique at E371 and see D254. There are essays
    on Saintsbury's opinions and achievement in PMLA 59 (1944): 243–60; (by Wellek) in English
    Miscellany 12 (1961): 79–96; and in the University of Edinburgh Journal, vol. 6, no. 1 (1933),
    pp. 30–72 (with two fine photographs). See also Walter Leuba's George Saintsbury. New York:
    Twayne, 1967. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A9">
   <bib>Schipper, Jakob. Englische Metrik: in historischer und systematischer Entwicklung
    dargestellt. 2 Parts in 3 vols. Bonn: Emil Strauss, 1881–88. </bib>
   <notes> Part I: Altenglische Metrik. 1881. Part II: Neuenglische Metrik: Verslehre. 1888.
    Neuenglische Metrik: Stophenbau. 1888. Rev: in The Nation 35 (1882): 312; by Wissmann in LGRP 3
    (1882): cols. 133–39, with reply by Schipper, "Zur Zweihebungstheorie der alliterirenden
    Halbzeile: Eine Entgegung," in Englische Studien 5 (1882): 488–93; by Eugen Einenkel in Anglia
    Anzeiger 5 (1882): 30–53--which, along with a paper by Wissmann on Middle English word-stressing
    in Anglia 5 (1882): 466–500, was answered by Schipper in "Zur altenglischen Wortbetonung,"
    Anglia Anzeiger 5 (1882): 88–111, with a final salvo by Einenkel, "Erklärung gegen Schipper,"
    Anglia Anzeiger 6 (1883): 64–66; by Gummere in MLR 4 (1889): cols. 290–94; in The Nation 50
    (1890): 355–57, with a reply by Schipper to both of these, "English Metres," in MLN 6 (1891):
    cols. 241–46. Later condensed and pub- lished as: </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A10">
   <bib>Schipper, Jakob. Grundriss der englischen Metrik. Wiener Beiträge zur englischen Philologie, no. 2.
    Vienna and Leipzig: W. Braumüller, 1895. 396 pp. Rev: in Anglia Beiblatt 7 (1897): 36–37; by
    Kaluza in LGRP 17 (1896): cols. 227–31; in Archiv 97 (1896): 406–9; in Englische Studien 23
    (1897): 295–99. </bib>
   <notes> Translated into English (apparently by Schipper himself) as </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A11">
   <bib>Schipper, Jakob. A History of English Versification. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1910; rpt New York: AMS
    Press, 1971; rpt Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1973. 390 pp. </bib>
   <notes> The translation (hereafter referred to as Schipper) is reorganized as follows: Book I:
    The Line Part I: The Native Metre Part 2: Foreign Metres Division 1: The Foreign Metres in
    General Division 2: Verse-Forms Common to the Middle and Modern English Periods Division 3:
    Verse-Forms Occurring in Modern English Poetry Only Book II: The Structure of Stanzas Part 1:
    [Nature and Structure of the Stanza] Part 2: Stanzas Common to Middle and Modern English, and
    Others Formed on the Analogy of These Part 3: Modern Stanzas and Metres of Fixed Form
    Originating Under the Influence of the Renascence, or Introduced Later It has been said that
    Schipper's table of contents in the English transla- tion is the most thorough, logical, and
    minute organization of English verse- forms available anywhere; to peruse it is an education in
    itself. (Some have not thought so, however: Eleanor P. Hammond called it the product of "a mind
    which must name before it can see and feel.") The translation is heavily reor- ganized in
    structure but seems much less reworked in content besides the ob- vious trimming of examples,
    though Schipper does take account of some ar- guments on Old and Middle English metrics
    published by Luick, Ten Brink, and others after 1881. The absence of an Index in the English
    edition is a great loss. Each of the five Parts and three Divisions listed above is discussed
    else- where in the present work, since among the twenty-six chapters of HEV Schipper offers
    detailed, valuable accounts of Old English meter and the de- velopment of the modern meters in
    Middle English, as well as useful short re- views of the sonnet form, the Spenserian stanza, the
    development of blank verse and the couplet, trochaic meters, imitations of classical meters,
    varieties of rhyme--indeed on virtually every aspect of English versification. Saintsbury's
    observation that Schipper's monumental work was "one of the foundation stones of a prosodic
    library" was one of the soundest judgments he ever made in his life. Englische Metrik was not
    only the first combined his- torical survey and classification of English verseforms made on a
    truly compre- hensive scale, it was also a study carried out with such theoretical clarity and
    acumen that subsequent researchers have found very little to quarrel with even after a century.
    Schipper complained that the German edition sold poorly, and his work had too much of the German
    drive for order and detail to make it attractive to the English, but I suspect that its sheer
    presence was an incentive toward the great flood of writing about versification which took place
    around the turn of the century. The reprint edition will be one of the first acquisitions of the
    serious student of versification. The bulk of the book (about 70%--this is not obvious from the
    table of contents) discusses Old and Middle English metrics. The sections which treat modern
    stanza-forms are mainly catalogues of examples, with a few notable exceptions. This seems an
    unnatural distribution, and to some extent it simply reflects Schipper's own specialty within
    English philology, which was Middle English, but it can be justified in part on the grounds that
    the two principles of modern English meter--syllable-counting and stress-alternation--were first
    es- tablished in early Middle English, a phenomenon which is only slightly more interesting than
    its correlate, the disappearance of the Old English meter about the same time. Hence Schipper
    turns his attention squarely on what is most important. Most of Book I and Parts 1 and 2 of Book
    II concern pre-1500 forms. On Old English metrics Schipper gives one of the most judicious re-
    views of the nineteenth-century German scholarship available. He himself ad- heres to the
    zweihebungstheorie in agreement with Sievers, whose Five Types theory Schipper adopted soon
    after its appearance. His discussion of Old Eng- lish verse is mainly an exposition of Sievers
    with examples. On the hypermet- ric lines he accepts the medial-fusion explanation given by
    Luick and subse- quently endorsed by Sievers. As for the native meter in Middle English,
    Schipper generally follows Luick (see K223–26, and note K330) in tracing out the loosening form
    of the alliterative long-line (two-stress hemistichs expand to three; rhyme is added; internal
    rhyme allows a fracturing of one long-line into a short rhyming couplet) under the pressure of
    the foreign meters; he seems indeed more interested in the early ME verseforms, as in Layamon,
    than in the "Alliterative Revival," which had not yet become a bone of contention. Continuity of
    the alliterative tradition in ME is assumed throughout. The for- eign meters, however, receive a
    different treatment, being the progenitors of the modern forms. Schipper adopts the traditional
    (classical) terminology of iambic, trochaic, anapestic, and dactylic feet, even going so far as
    the obstrep- erous nomenclature for line-ends (brachycatalectic, etc.). He also fails to distin-
    guish between stress-verse and foot-verse (accentual-syllabic), so that Com- mon Meter, for
    example, more commonly known as the Fourteener, is de- rived from the seven-foot iambic line in
    Latin, the Septenary. And he has a few blind spots: the poems of the Gawain-poet, for example,
    seem scarcely mentioned at all. Yet Schipper is right to identify the foreign sources of mod-
    ern English versification as double: the influence of Medieval Latin has been se- riously
    slighted elsewhere. And the traditional account of metrical structure he gives in Chapters 6, 7,
    and 8 is cogent and useful. Altogether, it is the wide command of English literature and the
    steadi- ness of judgment that are distinctive in Schipper; he has no bold new theories to
    display, he borrows much, and his general approach may be fairly described as conservative. But
    he is remarkably good, not in spite of but in addition to the fact that he was first. I have
    been unable to trace much biographical informa- tion or (beyond hope) a photograph, but some
    information will be found in "Zum Gedächtnis Jakob Schipper's," Englische Studien 49 (1915–16):
    99–112, and the note on his election to the chair of English Philology at Vienna in Englische
    Studien 39 (1908): 318–19.</notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A12">
   <bib>Fowler, Roger. The Languages of Literature: Some Linguistic Contributions to Literature.
    London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1971. </bib>
   <notes> Fifteen essays various in subject-matter but all concerned in one way or an- other with
    the possibilities for rapprochement between a precise linguistics and the study of literature.
    For the study of metrics the key essay is "What Is Met- rical Analysis?" (see E534). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A13">
   <bib>Hollander, John. Vision and Resonance: Two Senses of Poetic Form. New York: Oxford
    University Press, 1975. 306 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Twelve essays and an Appendix on a very wide range of subjects by a distin- guished poet
    and critic, most of them previously published, many of them re- turning sooner or later to
    Hollander's first love, music--the music of, in, or about literature. Some of the finest writing
    done on versification will be found in this volume. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A14">
   <bib>Fowler, Roger, ed. Essays on Style and Language: Linguistic and Critical Approaches to
    Literary Style. London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1966. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in Foundations of Language 11 (1974): 591–94; in Essays in Criticism 16 (1966):
    457–63. Ten essays by various hands. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A15">
   <bib>Frye, Northrop, ed. Sound and Poetry: English Institute Essays, 1956. New York: Columbia
    University Press, 1957. </bib>
   <notes> These seven essays are some of those presented at two conferences on "Music and Poetry"
    and "Sound and Meaning in Poetry" at the English Institute. The volume contains an Introduction
    (E353) and six essays. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A16">
   <bib>POETICS, POETYKA, POETIKA: First International Conference on Work-in-Progress Devoted to
    Problems of Poetics, Warsaw, 1960. Ed. Donald Davie et al. Warsaw: Polish Scientific Publishers,
    1961. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by Chatman in Linguistics, no. 8 (1964), pp. 107–23. Sixty-two papers and abstracts
    in nine subject areas: Poetics and Linguistics, Versification and Sound-Texture, Problems of
    Intonation, Poetic Lexicon and Semantics, The Functions of Grammatical Elements in Poetry, The
    Poetics of Folklore, Applications of Mathematics to Poetics, Historical and Comparative Poetics,
    and Problems of Interpretation and Evaluation of Poetics. Bibliogra- phy. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A17">
   <bib>POETICS, POETYKA, POETIKA: Third International Conference of Work-in-Progress Devoted to
    Problems of Poetics, Warsaw 1964. Ed. Roman Jakobson et al. The Hague: Mouton, 1966. </bib>
   <notes> Eighteen articles on "general metrics and the metrics of Slavonic languages." Reference
    Bibliography. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A18">
   <bib>Preminger, Alex, ed. Princeton Encyclopedia of Poetry and Poetics. Enlarged edition.
    Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1974. 992 pp., incl. Supplement.</bib>
   <notes> Easily the single most valuable reference work available today for any serious reader of
    poetry. Contains over a thousand articles by distinguished specialists on subjects in four
    categories: History, Technique of Poetry, Poetics and Criticism, and the Relation of Poetry to
    Other Fields. Each article includes a short bibliography. The articles most relevant to English
    versification will be found listed under this item in Appendix D. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A19">
   <bib>Sebeok, Thomas A., ed. Style in Literature. Cambridge, Mass.: M.I.T. Press, 1960. Rev:
    there is a fine conspectus by F. L. Utley in Style 3 (1969): 95 ff; in Inter- national Journal
    of American Linguistics 28 (1962): 269–86; in Language 37 (1961): 256–66; in Word 17 (1961):
    318–44; in Archivum Linguisticum 14 (1962): 77– 83; in Romance Philology 15 (1962): 424–38. </bib>
   <notes> The proceedings of the Conference on Style held at Indiana University in April 1968, a
    meeting of minds which reverberated in the scholarly literatures of linguistics, literary
    criticism, and psychology for more than a decade. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A20">
   <bib>Wimsatt, W. K., Jr., ed. Versification: Major Language Types. Sixteen Essays. New York: New
    York University Press for MLA, 1970. 252 pp. Rev: by Beaver in Language Sciences 30 (1974):
    42–43; by Cable in Style 9 (1975): 227–30. </bib>
   <notes> A valuable collection of recent essays in comparative prosody, surveying Eng- lish (three
    essays), Classical Chinese, Japanese, Biblical Hebrew, Classical Greek and Latin, Slavic,
    Uralic, Germanic, Celtic, Italian, Spanish, French, the elements of versification, and the
    relation of verse to music. Editor's Introduc- tion. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A21">
   <bib>Chatman, Seymour, and Samuel R. Levin, eds. Essays on the Language of Literature. Boston:
    Houghton Mifflin, 1967. 450 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Unfortunately now out of print, but nevertheless a very useful anthology of thirty-one
    essays in five areas: Sound Texture, Metrics, Grammar, Literary Form and Meaning, and Style and
    Stylistics. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A22">
   <bib>Freeman, Donald C., ed. Linguistics and Literary Style. New York: Holt, Rinehart and
    Winston, 1970. </bib>
   <notes> Twenty-three articles in four sections: Linguistic Stylistics: Theory; Linguistic
    Stylistics: Method; Approaches to Prose Style; and Approaches to Metrics. Valuable editor's
    Introduction. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A23">
   <bib>Gross, Harvey, ed. The Structure of Verse: Modern Essays on Prosody. Greenwich, Conn.:
    Fawcett Publications, 1966; 2nd rev. ed. 1978. </bib>
   <notes> A useful and compact anthology (in paperback) containing an Introduction ("Prosody and
    Literary Study"), a brief epigraph to each article, Appendices (an excerpt from Alden's English
    Verse [A1] and a Glossary) and fourteen articles in three sections: Prosody: Purview, History,
    and Definitions; Theories of Meter; and Three Essays in Criticism. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A24">
   <bib>Hemphill, George, ed. Discussions of Poetry: Rhythm and Sound. Boston: D. C. Heath, 1961,
    112 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A collection of eighteen short excerpts from poets and critics (Gascoigne, Jonson,
    Milton, Marvell, Dryden, Johnson, Jefferson, Blake, Coleridge, Poe, Lanier, Hopkins, Saintsbury,
    Bridges, Young, Winters, Wellek and Warren, and Shapiro) on the art of verse, followed by a
    reprinting of the 1956 Kenyon symposium "English Verse and What It Sounds Like" (E714). Brief
    introduc- tion by the editor. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A25">
   <bib>Perkins, George, ed. American Poetic Theory. New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1972. </bib>
   <notes> Extracts from thirty-one essays by major American poets Freneau through Dickinson on the
    art of versecraft. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A26">
   <bib>Smith, G. Gregory ed. Elizabethan Critical Essays. 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1904;
    rpt 1937–71. </bib>
   <notes> The successor to Joseph Haslewood's Ancient Critical Essays upon English Poets and Poesy
    (2 vols. London, 1811–15) and still the standard edition of the prin- cipal Renaissance
    treatises on literary criticism and versification. </notes>
  </item>
 </chapter>
 <chapter title="EARLIER BIBLIOGRAPHIES">
  <item id="A27">
   <bib>Lafourcade, Françoise. "Contribution à une bibliographie chronologique pour l'étude des
    théories sur la versification anglaise de 1550 à 1950." In Hommage à Paul Dottin. Caliban
    (Annales Publiées par la Faculté des Lettres et Sciences Humaines de Toulouse). N.s. 2, fascicle
    1, no. 3 (Special Issue), 1966. pp. 271–317. </bib>
   <notes> At 772 entries, this bibliography might otherwise be considered substantial. In fact, it
    relies very heavily on Omond, repeating his mistakes along with his dis- coveries, and though
    Lafourcade adds a considerable number of new citations, many of these are only of very minor
    interest, even to the fanatical prosodist, and some are quite difficult to justify as prosodic
    at all. Annotations are brief and intermittent. The typesetters seem not to have known English,
    for in truth "errors like straws upon the surface flow." In general the minutiae of dates,
    spelling, and pagination are all completely unreliable. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A28">
   <bib>Nager, Rae Ann. "English: II. Bibliographical." Wimsatt (A20), pp. 204–16. </bib>
   <notes> Contains 126 entries, often annotated briefly, up to 1970. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A29">
   <bib>-----. "A Selective Bibliography of Recent Work on English Prosody." Style 11 (1977):
    136–70. </bib>
   <notes> A continuation of her earlier work (above); this article includes 285 annotated entries,
    1968–76. --- Omond, T. S. English Metrists. See A5. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="A30">
   <bib>Shapiro, Karl. A Bibliography of Modern Prosody. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press,
    1948. 36 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Contains 71 entries. Shapiro undertook this short bibliography as part of his duties for
    the Chair of Poetry at the Library of Congress, 1946–47; it is not, therefore, an especially
    technical or comprehensive reference work. It contains some irrelevancies (such as the first and
    last entries) but does cite most of the larger (i.e., more visible, not necessarily better)
    works on versification from about 1880 to 1940. All the entries are annotated discursively, with
    some ef- fort being made to sort the various approaches into "Temporal," "Stress," or "Mixed."
    The scholar will not be likely to examine this work more than once. </notes>
  </item>
 </chapter>
</bibliography>
