<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
 <chapter title="II: GENERAL STUDIES">
 <section title="">
  <div>
  <item id="B1">
   <bib> Aldington, Richard. "A Note on Poetry in Prose." The Chapbook, no. 22 (1921), pp. 16–24.
    [Cf. B53, B142.] </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B2">
   <bib> Allen, Donald, and Warren Tallman, eds. Poetics of the New American Poetry. New York: Grove
    Press, 1973. </bib>
   <notes> Slightly fuller than Perkins (A25), this collection includes 64 essays by 27 modern poets
    (beginning with Whitman) on poetics, poetry, and prosody. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B3">
   <bib> Baird, Alexander. "Phonetics and English Poetry." English 21 (1972): 98–100. </bib>
   <notes> Elementary linguistic account of the distinctions between (1) rhythm and me- ter, and (2)
    perfect- and near-rhyme. Scansion of "The Windhover." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B4">
   <bib> Balliet, Conrad A. "The Verse Technique of Matthew Arnold." DA 22 (1962): 2382A (Cornell). </bib>
   <notes> Examines meter, rhyme, stanzas, syntax, diction, and rhetoric, but not im- agery. Arnold
    wrote in a great variety of complex verseforms but said he pre- ferred poetry that was simple,
    plain, and direct. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B5">
   <bib> Barnes, T. R. English Verse: Voice and Movement from Wyatt to Yeats. Cambridge: Cambridge
    University Press, 1967. 324 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in MLN 30 (1969): 133–35. An introduction to English poetry, organized historically,
    with very long ex- tracts. There is a chapter on Blank Verse. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B6">
   <bib> Barnes, Thomas. "On the Nature and Essential Characters of Poetry as Distinguished from
    Prose." Memoirs of the Manchester Literary and Philosophical Society, 1 (1785). </bib>
   <notes> Cited by Omond (A5, p. 300) as separately published and dated 1786, on the basis of an
    advertisement, but no copy is known to exist. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B7">
   <bib> Bate, Walter Jackson. The Stylistic Development of Keats. New York: MLA, 1945; rpt New
    York: The Humanities Press, 1958, 1962. 214 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in MLN 61 (1946): 475–78; in JEGP 45 (1946): 468–69; in Saturday Re- view of
    Literature 29 (1946): 30. As prosodic studies of individual poets go, this full chron-ological
    examination of Keats's remarkably rapid and intense growth in the craftsmanship of verse is,
    excepting a lamentable repetitiousness of style (the book could have been shorter by a third
    without a loss), a model of method and accomplishment in the smooth synthesis of (1) detailed
    and precise description of changes in sound, meter, diction, syntax, and structure, (2) steady
    retention of the larger biographical and critical framework, and (3) a graceful and engaging
    style. In short, Bate is precise and informed without allowing either the analysis or the theory
    (or yet the biography) to become obtrusive. All the major poems re- ceive separate treatment. Of
    particular note is section 1 of Part 2 on sound- patterning. Cf. Zillman (G149). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B8">
   <bib> Beeching, H[enry] C]harles]. "Expression in Poetry." Two Lectures Introductory to the Study
    of Poetry. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1901. pp. 29–57. </bib>
   <notes> A non-technical discussion of the effects of meter, rhyme, and diction in pro- ducing "a
    heightened mode of expression," poetry. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B9">
   <bib> Belden, Henry M. "Some Technical Elements in Donne's Verse." PMLA 21 (1906): </bib>
   <notes> xxxi [Proceedings]. Abstract. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B10">
   <bib> Bellinger, Rossiter B. "Prosodical Studies in Some of Tennyson's Later Poetry." Diss., Yale
    University, 1949. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B11">
   <bib> Berg, Viola J. Pathways for the Poet: Poetry Forms Explained and Illustrated. Milford, Mi.:
    Mott Media, 1977. </bib>
   <notes> A handbook of poetic forms compiled by a writer of popular poetry contain- ing several
    hundred eccentric and novel forms, some invented by the author, such as "The Yeats,"
    "Sweetbriar," and the like. She lists 22 metrical feet; did the Greeks have this many? </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B12">
   <bib> Beum, Robert. The Poetic Art of William Butler Yeats. New York: Frederick Ungar, 1969. 161
    pp. </bib>
   <notes> Perhaps no other contemporary writer working in versification writes more gracefully than
    Robert Beum; with a minimum of technical apparatus (3 de- grees of stress--primary, secondary,
    and weak), but a maximum of perception, he examines Yeats's craft of meter, rhyme, and
    stanza-form in the major poetry after 1910. Pages 51–54 summarize Yeats's metrical development,
    and the fol- lowing two chapters treat (respectively) his handling of the iambic and trochaic
    line. There is also a chapter on his habits of composition (5), and one on the verse and prose
    of the plays (11). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B13">
   <bib> -----. "Some Observations on Spenser's Verse Forms." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 64
    (1963): 180–96. </bib>
   <notes> In quest of "a distinct view of the whole range of Spenser's verse." Three peri- ods may
    be discerned: (1) the early verse, terminating in the Shepheardes Calen- der, is markedly
    experimental (the three forms of the mature period do not ap- pear at all) and also markedly
    alliterative; (2) the mature period finds Spenser confining himself to but three forms--rime
    royal, ottava rima, and the Faerie Queene stanza of nines (this last form allows at once "an
    extraordinary smooth- ness and ceremoniousness of motion," a sustained evenness of sonority con-
    trolled by the rhymes); and (3) late work. The occasional poems with their elaborate
    versification represent special cases. Cf. B224. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B14">
   <bib> Black, Michael. "Stylistics and Donne's 'The Sunne Rising.'" Language and Literature 2
    (1974): 55–69. </bib>
   <notes> Provides separate phonetic, graphetic, phonemic, grammatical, lexical, and se- mantic
    analyses. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B15">
   <bib> Blissett, William. "Poetic Wave and Poetic Particle." University of Toronto Quarterly 24
    (1954): 1–7. </bib>
   <notes> Beyond some theorizing about the ontological status of poetry (a subject more important
    than any other in versification), based on the antinomies of point and wave in physics, Blissett
    argues that the movement of a line is more im- portant (and more intuitively evident) than its
    sound or meanings, and that the "line-criticism" as a critical method has been entirely ignored.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B16">
   <bib> Bogan, Louise. "The Pleasures of Formal Poetry." Quarterly Review of Literature 7 (1953):
    176–85. </bib>
   <notes> In the excellent symposium on "Experimental and Formal Verse," Bogan re- plies to the
    notions that "form binds" and "form is exhausted," tracing out an engaging history of changes in
    forms and concepts from the Greeks to Eliot, focused particularly on meter and rhyme. See also
    B230 and E1549. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B17">
   <bib> Boggs, W. Arthur. "A Linguistic Definition of Poetry." Bulletin of the New York Public
    Library 61 (1962): 97–100. </bib>
   <notes> Argues that an adequate definition must be framed in terms not of the tech- niques of
    poetry but of its substance--language. His own definition emphasizes the high order of
    patterning of language in verse. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B18">
   <bib> Bogholm, N. "On the Spenserian Style." Travaux du cercle linguistique de Copenhague 1
    (1945): 5–21. </bib>
   <notes> Especially good on Spenser's practices in rhyming and rhythm (pronunciation, stressing,
    idiosyncrasies). Spenser was very heavily indebted to "Dan Chaucer," and, to a lesser extent, to
    Tasso and Ariosto. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B19">
   <bib> Boos, Florence S. "Dante Gabriel Rossetti: Sex, Prosody, and Literary Antecedents." DAI 33
    (1972): 2922A (Wisconsin). </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B20">
   <bib> Booth, Stephen. An Essay on Shakespeare's Sonnets. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1969.
    Based on his dissertation, "The Structures of Shakespeare's Sonnets," at Harvard in 1964. </bib>
   <notes> Booth's general intent is to show that the sonnet presents, as the paradigm of poetic
    experience, multiple simultaneous orders, "multicity in unity," or the old concordia discors. To
    that end, the book explicates the phonetic, metrical, stanzaic-structural, rhetorical,
    imagistic, and thematic patterns in the Sonnets and so is of direct interest to the prosodist.
    But see, particularly, Section 2 of Chapter 3 ("Phonetic Structure"), Section 1 of Chapter 4
    ("Phonetic Unity and Division"), and Notes 3, 5, and 8 in the Appendix (on sound patterns and
    the work of D. I. Masson). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B21">
   <bib> Bose, Amalendu. "Shakespeare's Word-Music." Studies in Elizabethan Literature: Festschrift
    to Professor G. C. Bannerjee. Ed. P. S. Sastri. New Delhi: S. Chand, 1972. pp. 57–63. </bib>
   <notes> He eschews any interest in "mere dexterity in the manipulation of vowels and consonants,
    sibilants and labials and liquids, spondees and pyrrhics, enjambe- ment and weak-endings as
    constituting word-music at its highest" and tries to show instead (in seven pages) that
    "Shakespearean word-music goes deeper. It totally exploits the lexical value of words and
    further suggests worlds beyond worlds, glimmering vistas of thought and feelings beyond the zone
    of formu- lated thoughts and feelings, where the rest is silence but apprehension." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B22">
   <bib> Boulton, Marjorie. The Anatomy of Poetry. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1953. </bib>
   <notes> An introductory handbook and a companion to another on prose. Two chap- ters on Rhythm,
    three on Phonetic form, and four on "mental Form." Scans by stress and allows only the four
    commonest meters; emphasizes form throughout. Sensible. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B23">
   <bib> Bourne, George. "Rhythm and Rhyme." Macmillan's Magazine, June 1906, pp. 541– 49. Also in
    Living Age, November 1906, pp. 200–5. </bib>
   <notes> An apology for both by the familiar strategy of substituting an alternative word in the
    line or as the rhyme and observing the difference in effect. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B24">
   <bib> Brink, Bernhard Ten. Geschichte der englischen Litteratur. 2 vols. Berlin: R. Oppenheim,
    1877–93. Translated as History of English Literature. New York: Henry Holt, 1889–96. </bib>
   <notes> Passim. Ten Brink's specialty, like Kaluza's, lay in Old and Middle English, so his
    History is weighted on that end. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B25">
   <bib> Brooks, Benjamin Gilbert. "Coleridge's Poetical Technique." Life and Letters 10 (1934):
    594–608. </bib>
   <notes> A study of the poet's technical development, using that adjective in its broadest
    possible sense; there are occasional remarks on meter, but the principle interest is imagery,
    diction, and tone. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B26">
   <bib> Brownell, Baker. "Kinaesthetic Verse." Poetry 22 (1923): 36–40. </bib>
   <notes> On "muscularity": "the primary fact [is] that our experience of words is an im- plicit
    muscular effort in the throat." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B27">
   <bib> Buell, Robert K. Lectures on the Technique of Verse Writing. Mountain View, Calif.: The
    Author, 1939. 119 pp. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B28">
   <bib> Cadbury, William. "The Structure of Feeling in a Poem by Patmore: Meter, Phonology, Form."
    Victorian Poetry 4 (1966): 237–51. </bib>
   <notes> A full analysis and interpretation of the poem shows how aspects of form en- hance,
    enact, and express meanings beyond the lexical-semantic reach of the words. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B29">
   <bib> Callan, Edward. "W. H. Auden: The Farming of a Verse." Southern Review 3 (1967): 341–56. </bib>
   <notes> Auden's lifelong interest in the technical craft of poetry was based on his early
    realization of the freedom of constraint--the creative possibilities to be found in the
    necessities of strict metrical forms. The "dialectic of freedom and neces- sity" (in form and
    craft) thereafter became a major theme in the poetry, per- haps best exemplified in the elegies
    to Yeats and Freud. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B30">
   <bib> Chalker, John. "Aspects of Rhythm and Rhyme in Eliot's Early Poems." English 16 (1966):
    84–88. </bib>
   <notes> Eliot used metrical variations in his early work: (1) to distinguish characters,
    dramatically, and (2) to mark changes in emotional mood or atmosphere. Metrical regularity
    serves as a "counterbalance to the emotional excitement" of the verse, even as Wordsworth
    believed. To the more attentive ear, Eliot's rhythms enact his homage to the Elizabethan
    dramatists. His rhymes convey ironic or comic undercutting, implicit judgment, delayed refrain,
    or "slightly frenetic over-emphasis"; unexpected absence of rhyme expresses a failure of
    resolution and creates the frustration of anticlimax. Varieties of formal expres- siveness.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B31">
   <bib> Chapin, Elsa, and R. Thomas. A New Approach to Poetry. Chicago: University of Chicago
    Press, 1929. </bib>
   <notes> Generally follows the methods of Rickert (B182). Part I treats imagery, rhythm,
    sound-patterns, and typography; Part 2 is a minianthology of poems. There is a novel scansion
    marking system in Chapter 2 (as on pp. 26, 28, 36– 37) for those who have graph paper available,
    but probably such persons will not be much interested in the technique presented here (pp.
    10–11) of under- lining color imagery in poems with crayons. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B32">
   <bib> Chatman, Seymour, and Samuel R. Levin. "Linguistics and Literature." Current Trends in
    Linguistics, X. Ed. Thomas A. Sebeok. The Hague: Mouton, 1973. pp. 250–94. </bib>
   <notes> A long discursive bibliography and review article. Section 2.1.1 on Metrics (pp. 253–59)
    is especially thorough on Structural Metrics, as one might expect; 2.1.2 on Sound-Structures
    (pp. 259–64) surveys linguistic work on the mean- ings of sound-patterns; 2.2 on Grammar (pp.
    264–70) surveys the work on po- etic syntax and language. Long list of References at the end.
    These short chronologically ordered surveys provide succinct and coherent views of the work done
    in the 1950s and '60s. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B33">
   <bib> -----. "Linguistics and Poetics." Princeton (A18), pp. 450–57. </bib>
   <notes> A review of twentieth-century work on the phonology, metrics, diction, syn- tax,
    performance, and semantics of poetry, mentioning several of the important studies in each area.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B34">
   <bib> Ciardi, John. "On Form As a Language." Saturday Review, 31 October 1964, pp. 16–18. </bib>
   <notes> On endings, a dictum: "form tends to conclude itself by some increase in for- mality."
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B35">
   <bib> -----. "The Silences of Poetry." To the Young Writer. Ed. A. L. Bader. Ann Arbor:
    University of Michigan Press, 1965. pp. 85–104. </bib>
   <notes> Since "all the elements of a poem are engaged in a series of countermotions," therefore
    "a poem is one part against another across a silence." Ciardi proposes a symbol to mark changes
    in tone (and therefore in the technical elements-- meter and diction) in a poem. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B36">
   <bib> Clark, Arthur Melville. "Poetry And Verse." In his Studies in Literary Modes. Edinburgh:
    Oliver and Boyd, 1946. pp. 82–104. </bib>
   <notes> Following a historical review, Clark confronts his essential question: can po- etry be
    written without meter? He considers metered vs. free verse, and also meter vs. rhythm; citing
    Bridges, he concludes that meter is essential to poetry. The final ten pages explore the nature
    of rhythm in the composition of poetry and in its effects on readers. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B37">
   <bib> Clatanoff, Doris A. R. "Poetry and Music: Coleridge, Shelley, and Keats and the Musical
    Milieu of Their Day." DAI 34 (1973): 2551A (Nebraska). </bib>
   <notes> There is some minor discussion of meter and sound-patterning as the "musical components
    of language." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B38">
   <bib> Coleman, Elliott. "Poetry and Prose: The Prose Poem." University of Dayton Review 4 (1967):
    7–21. </bib>
   <notes> Shuffles after Croce in refusing to allow any distinction between prose and po- etry to
    be based on "external elements" such as meter or rhyme. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B39">
   <bib> Conklin, Groff. "James Stephens--Prosodist." English 25 (1936): 433–43. </bib>
   <notes> Versification is actually not examined directly in this essay on the Irish poet. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B40">
   <bib> Corson, Hiram. A Primer of English Verse: chiefly in its aesthetic and organic character.
    Boston: Ginn and Company, 1892. 226 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by A. H. Tolman in MLN 8 (1893): 245–47 (discusses Milton's meters). We find here a
    truly Coleridgian thesis: in contrast to the analytical, divisive process of intellect, "when
    strong feeling is in any way objectified, a unifying process sets in." The Poetic Principle,
    then, is "some principle of harmony or fusion" or unity, and its agents are the poetic elements.
    "Rhythm is a succes- sion and involution of unities, that is, unities within unities," the foot
    within the verse within the stanza. The elements of form are organic unities with the sense. The
    book takes five main topics: meter and metrical variation (conven- tional accentual basis);
    Tennyson's use of the Stanza; the Spenserian stanza; the Sonnet; and Blank Verse. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B41">
   <bib> Costello, Sister Mary Cleophas. Between Fixity and Flux: A Study of the Concept of Poetry
    in the Criticism of T. S. Eliot. Washington D.C.: Catholic University of America Press, 1947. </bib>
   <notes> An invaluable guide to the development of Eliot's thinking about the catego- ries
    "verse," "prose," and "poetry." See especially Chapters 2 and 3. The differ- entia between the
    second and third of these eventually turns out to be one of affective meaning, or intensity, not
    any formal constraint. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B42">
   <bib> Courthope, W[illiam] J. A History of English Poetry. 6 vols. London and New York:
    Macmillan, 1895–1910. </bib>
   <notes> There are no separate chapters on matters of versification except for the chap- ter on
    Milton, which is mainly devoted to that topic. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B43">
   <bib> Cowl, R. P. The Theory of Poetry in England: Its Development in Doctrines and Ideas from
    the Sixteenth Century to the Nineteenth Century. London: Macmillan, 1914. </bib>
   <notes> See "Style and Diction," pp. 187–223, and "Metre and Versification," pp. 224– 62
    (including "Functions of Metre," "Principles of Versification," and "Rhyme"). A collection of
    extracts from the principal authorities. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B44">
   <bib> Crannel, Kenneth Charles. "A Prosodic Analysis of Selected Dramatic Narratives of Robert
    Frost." DAI 31 (1971): 3682A (Northwestern). </bib>
   <notes> Examines metrical variation, sound-patterning, alliteration, rhyme, use of the dash, and
    other figures of repetition in eight poems. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B45">
   <bib> Deegan, William J. "A Study of the Poetic Craftsmanship of Thomas Gray as Shown By His
    English Poems." DA 22 (1962): 4014A (Pittsburgh). </bib>
   <notes> Examines meter, diction, verseforms, imagery, and figuration. Gray had some interest in
    imitating Old Icelandic and Celtic verseforms but knew too little of their technic. He worked
    carefully and seldom achieved spontaneity (he drew from Milton and Dryden often), but his
    greatest strength lay in his supple me- ters. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B46">
   <bib> Denton, Marilyn. "The Form of Yeats' Lyric Poetry." DA 17 (1957): 3012A (Wisconsin). </bib>
   <notes> Examination of Yeats's manuscripts reveals that poetic form was much more central to his
    composition than most critics believe. Denton reviews Yeats's published remarks on prosody and
    catalogues the poems by metrical/stanzaic form. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B47">
   <bib> Deutsche, Babette. Poetry Handbook: A Dictionary of Terms. New York: Funk &amp; Wagnalls,
    1957; 4th ed. 1974. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B48">
   <bib> Diller, Hans Jürgen. "The Function of Verse in Byron's Don Juan. In The Constance Byron
    Symposium, 1977. Salzburg: Institüt für englische Sprache und Literatur, Salzburg University,
    1978. pp. 5–20. </bib>
   <notes> The segmentation of language in verse (i.e., across lines) yields additional con- texts
    in which words can take on (and have qualified) meanings, producing polysemy. But verseforms may
    be either semantically expansive (rhymes which are different parts of speech multiply categories
    and levels of reference) or se- mantically constrictive (both sides of an ambiguity cannot be
    maintained to- gether). Segmentation in verse foregrounds its units, establishes them as con-
    ceptual correlates, and exploits their successive realization by the reader. The poem also bends
    to its ends specifically poetic signals (not available in prose) and poetically intensified
    signals (available in prose but heightened in verse). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B49">
   <bib> Dobrée, Bonamy. "Prosody, Forms of Verse, and Some Usages." The Concise Encyclopedia of
    English and American Poets and Poetry. Ed. Stephen Spender and Donald Hall. New York: Hawthorn
    Books, 1963. pp 247–69. </bib>
   <notes> A catholic view of the elements of Prosody (counting of syllables and of ac- cents,
    varieties of meters, adventitious sonal patterning), Structure (lineforms, counterpoint, Sprung
    Rhythm, free verse, ballad meter), Forms (stanzas), and Usages (genres). Copious examples.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B50">
   <bib> Drechsler, Walther. Der Stil des Macphersonschen Ossian. Diss., Berlin, 1904. </bib>
   <notes> Brief remarks on rhythm and meter, pp. 34–38, but the preponderance falls on syntax and
    figuration. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B51">
   <bib> Dukes, Ashley. "Forms of Dramatic Verse." Theatre Arts Monthly 11 (1927): 521–29. </bib>
   <notes> Verse as the essential medium of drama: a brief survey. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B52">
   <bib> Eliot, T. S. "The Borderline of Prose." The New Statesman 9 (1917): 157–59. </bib>
   <notes> "After much reflection I conclude that the only absolute distinction to be drawn is that
    poetry is written in verse, and prose is written in prose: or, in other words, that there is
    prose rhythm and verse rhythm." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B53">
   <bib> -----. "Prose and Verse." The Chapbook, no. 22 (April 1921), pp. 3–10. Cf. B1,B142. </bib>
   <notes> "Poetic content must be either the sort of thing that is usually, or the sort of thing
    that ought to be, expressed in verse," Eliot believes. Either of these alter- natives will cause
    the "prose-poem" to fade out of existence. Moreover, whereas in form we have "verse" contrasted
    to "prose," in content, length, in- tensity and such we have no term to set against "poetry."
    Long prose passages are often in sum effect intense. "I object to the term 'prose-poetry'
    because it seems to imply a sharp distinction between 'poetry' and 'prose' which I do not admit,
    and if it does not imply this distinction, the term is meaningless and otiose. . . ." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B54">
   <bib> Ellis, Virginia R. "'Authentic Cadence': The Sacramental Method of Gerard Manley Hopkins."
    DAI 30 (1969): 2481A (Brandeis). </bib>
   <notes> Hopkins sought to evoke "certainty" and "mystery" simultaneously in his po- etic texture
    as the exact correlate to his knowledge of God, an "incomprehen- sible certainty." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B55">
   <bib> Empson, William. "Rhythm and Imagery in English Poetry." British Journal of Aesthetics 2
    (1962): 36–54. </bib>
   <notes> See pp. 38–45; provocative (because eccentric) suggestions by a non- theoretical yet very
    perceptive reader of poetry who is "in favour of rhyme and metre." Empson inquires into the
    origins of rhyme (he has not read Draper [L27–28]); speculates about tonal accent (pitch) in
    Chinese, English, and Classical verse; argues (from Tennyson and Housman) that quantity is of-
    ten important in English verse, especially since most of the major poets were taught Latin at
    school, so that much of their major verse uses "stress and quan- tity at once"; proposes "jammed
    stress," where several strong syllables in a line are "rolled together" as one stress in
    scansion; approves of four degrees of stress; emphasizes the paucity of our theories in the face
    of the instinctive, acute, unconscious human perception of rhythm; and bemoans the abandon- ment
    of the traditional stress-metric in vers libre, especially in W. C. Williams. Yet, "if the
    rhythms of English are loose, rich, and confused, as one can hardly deny, how far is poetry in
    English likely to gain from strict metres?" </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B56">
   <bib> Epstein, E. L. "Hopkins's 'Heaven-Haven': A Linguistic-Critical Description." Essays in
    Criticism 23 (1973): 137–45. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B57">
   <bib> Erdman, David. "Byron's Poetic Technique." Diss., Princeton University, 1937. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B58">
   <bib> Esenwein, J[oseph] Berg, and M. E. Roberts. The Art of Versification. Springfield, Mass.:
    The Home Correspondence School, 1913; 2nd ed. 1916. </bib>
   <notes> An introduction which has the virtues of clarity and thoroughness. Its metrical
    principles are accentual. Second edition adds a chapter on vers libre. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B59">
   <bib> -----. "The Essence of Verse." TLS, 3 June 1926, p. 361 (Leading article). </bib>
   <notes> The title is unfortunately rather apt: the article erects an immense edifice of
    generalizations without any close argumentation at all. Exceedingly discursive. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B60">
   <bib> Farr, Thomas A. "Some Observations on the Poetic Function in Sophisticated and Folk Verse."
    Language and Style 10 (1977): 162–72. </bib>
   <notes> Applies Levin's theory of coupling (B129) to Shakespeare's Sonnet 138, a folk ballad, and
    a folk song. Not surprisingly, the sonnet shows the most couplings. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B61">
   <bib> Fenyo, Jane K. "The Sounds of Poetry." DA 28 (1968): 2644A (C.U.N.Y.). </bib>
   <notes> Constructs a precise, thorough, ordered methodology for describing the sonal patterning
    in a given poem. The procedure covers three steps: pre-prosodic analysis of six grades of pause
    and stress and three grades of duration, all the data being plotted on a Basic Chart; prosodic
    analysis, serially pre-metric then metric, wherein tone-color ("phoneme keys") and pitch-change
    ("tonality tunes") data are added on a pre-metric Position Chart, followed by reduction of the
    six grades of stress to the two in the traditional account of meter, plotted as a Metric Score,
    and notation of the duration, pitch, and loudness features on a DPL Strip; and an optional
    performance analysis, in which preferred values on the DPL are denoted on a Performance Strip.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B62">
   <bib> Fletcher, John Gould. "Miss Lowell's Discovery: Polyphonic Prose." Poetry 6 (1915): 32–36. </bib>
   <notes> Laudatory remarks on her Sword-blades and Poppy Seed, poems "printed as prose, or as
    prose and verse interspersed . . . . leaving the reader to determine the movement of the rhythm
    and the division into lines." He thinks traditional meters worn threadbare and vers libre barren
    of orchestral sound-quality. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B63">
   <bib> Flosdorf, James W. "The Poetry of Sir John Suckling: A Study of His Versification,
    Rhetoric, and Themes." Diss., University of Rochester, 1960. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B64">
   <bib> Foott, David. "A Technical Reappraisal of T. S. Eliot's 'Love Song of J. Alfred Prufrock.'"
    Linq: Literature in North Queensland 1 (1972): 30–35. </bib>
   <notes> A study of critical value judgments of artistic technique could mine some very useful
    source-material here. One recalls what John Crowe Ransom did to similar pieces. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B65">
   <bib> Ford, S. Gertrude. Lessons in Verse-Craft. London: C. W. Daniel, 1919. 125 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A beginner's manual. The author has a penchant for French forms. Regrettably the paper
    the volume is printed on is of rather high quality. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B66">
   <bib> Forrest-Thompson, Veronica. "Levels in Poetic Convention." Journal of European Studies 2
    (1972): 33–51. </bib>
   <notes> This is a study, quite convoluted in its articulation, in interpretation theory,
    therefore poetic semantics. But the subject is form, and the cautious end of ex- amining three
    broad types of interpretation strategies is that "it is essential to preserve a level of poetic
    organization that has nothing to do with meaning." See particularly the penultimate and
    antepenultimate paragraphs. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B67">
   <bib> Fowler, Roger. "Linguistics and the Analysis of Poetry." Fowler (A12), pp. 219–37. </bib>
   <notes> In support of the position that "formal description not only leads to, but is, a
    statement of meaning," Fowler gives detailed analyses of grammar, phonology (including meter),
    and lexis in a Cummings poem. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B68">
   <bib> Franco, June W. "'The Living Skein': A Stylistic Study of Dylan Thomas." DAI 39 (1978):
    1586A (North Texas State). </bib>
   <notes> Examines meter, syntax, sound, and diction and concludes that the later poetry is
    superior to the earlier. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B69">
   <bib> Frank, Armin P. "'A Poem Should . . . Be': Mimetic and Didactic Modes of Poetry." Bulletin
    of the Dept. of English, University of Calcutta 12 (1976–77): 1– 17. </bib>
   <notes> After the last word of the title should be added the words: "About Poetry." Frank
    identifies two types of poems about poetry, one describing an event and the other enacting "an
    event in language." And the medium for the dance, the mimetic enactment, is of course the body
    of the poem, its corporeal substance- -its versification. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B70">
   <bib> Friedmann, Thomas. "Marvell's 'Coy Mistress' and Williams' 'Trees': Grammar and Phonology
    in the Critical Context." Junction 1972 (Brooklyn Coll.), pp. 60– 65. </bib>
   <notes> Integration of theme, tone, sound, grammar, and lexis. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B71">
   <bib> Friend, Joseph H. "Teaching the 'Grammar of Poetry.'" College English 27 (1966): 361–67. </bib>
   <notes> "Grammar" is used in its widest possible sense here to mean all the manifold functions of
    words in poems. Practical suggestions on the pedagogical value of technical analysis. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B72">
   <bib> Frye, Northrop. "Verse and Prose." Princeton (A18), pp. 885–90. </bib>
   <notes> See also s.v. "Polyphonic Prose" and "Prose Poem." A very cogent redaction of the
    material in The Well-Tempered Critic (below); Frye distinguishes three basic verbal
    rhythms--discursive, metrical, and associational. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B73">
   <bib> -----. The Well-Tempered Critic. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1963. </bib>
   <notes> Frye distinguishes three primary verbal rhythms: the rhythm of verse, the rhythm of prose
    (more complex), and the "associative rhythm"--fragmentary in logic and syntax--of ordinary
    speech. These three influence each other to produce six other hybrid forms: oratorical or
    rhetorical prose (prose influenced by verse) and euphuism (more extreme: prose influenced by
    association); cou- plets and blank verse (verse influenced by prose) and intentional doggerel
    (more extreme); tribal chants, college cheers, and free verse (associative rhythm influenced by
    verse); the lyric (verse influenced by the associative rhythm) and its more extreme form, here
    termed "echolalia"; "free prose" (associative rhythms influenced by prose); and aphoristic or
    wisdom writing (prose influ- enced by associative rhythms). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B74">
   <bib> Fujimura, Thomas H. "Dryden's Poetics: The Expressive Values of Poetry." JEGP 74 (1975):
    195–208. </bib>
   <notes> As a corrective to some recent work on figurative language in Dryden, this author
    reasserts Dryden's own priorities of poetic expressiveness--prosody and diction. Three aspects
    of prosody are distinguished: "harmony of numbers," mimetic rhythm, and the connections of meter
    and thought in syntax. Har- monious sounds were important to Dryden, and his praise of Virgil
    suggests some attention even to quantity in English verse. He also believed that a rhythm might
    carry its own weight of meaning, and hence that each poetic genre had its own appropriate
    prosody. In syntax, Dryden steadily moved away from the couplet form. Diction, however, he
    thought more important even than prosody. Words were to be selected which were " apt,
    significant, and sounding," and of these three, sonority of sound was easily the chief: be- yond
    everything else, Dryden was concerned not with the referential or se- mantic values of his
    words, but with the aesthetic. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B75">
   <bib> Fuller, Roy. "Ear versus Eye." The New Statesman and Nation n.s. 53 (1957): 474–75. </bib>
   <notes> Skeptical of public poetry readings. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B76">
   <bib> Garnier, C.-M. "A Metrical Study of the Lyrical Parts in Shelley's Prometheus Unbound."
    Revue de l'enseignement des langues vivantes, 1937, pp. 97–102, 145–57. </bib>
   <notes> Examines stanza-forms, meters, and rhymes. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B77">
   <bib> Gatlin, Hallie L., III. "Structure and Technique in the Poetry of Thomas Hardy." DA 29
    (1968): 1867A (Iowa). </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B78">
   <bib> Gayley, C. M., and C. C. Young. The Principles and Progress of English Poetry. New York:
    Macmillan, 1904; 2nd ed. 1916, with first four and last two words of the title transposed. </bib>
   <notes> The Introduction offers concise expositions of "The Rhythm of Verse: Foot and Metre,"
    "Tonality in Verse," and "Stanzaic and Structural Forms." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B79">
   <bib> Giodano, Frank, Jr. "Rhythm and Rhyme in 'Self-Dependence.'" English Language Notes 13
    (1975): 29–35. </bib>
   <notes> Shifts in meter and alternations of rhyme "create an undercurrent of dishar- mony and
    turmoil that reinforce the speak-er's confusion; in contrast, the pas- sages concerning Nature
    show firm regularity and orderly variety of form." "This confrontation of metrical patterns . .
    . rhythmically reproduces the speaker's effort to measure himself by Nature's standard and to
    emulate it." Arnold achieves sprezzatura. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B80">
   <bib> Gopnik, Irwin, and Myrna Gopnik. "Toward a Theory of Style: The Law of Maximal Form." Style
    1 (1967): 197–214. </bib>
   <notes> The Law postulated identifies "poetic" utterances as those in which "the lin-
    guistic-poetic devices of the language tend to exhibit the maximal possible or- dering."
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B81">
   <bib> Gordon, Ralph. The Technique of Verse. New York: The City College Co-operative Store, 1933.
    56 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A student's manual, with sections on "Meter and Rhythm," "Verse Forms," and "Tone Color."
    He admits only the four simple meters. For its class the book is solid, and a teacher may still
    find it useful to recommend to beginning students. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B82">
   <bib> Graves, Robert. Contemporary Techniques of Poetry: A Political Analogy. Tunbridge Wells and
    London: Leonard and Virginia Woolf at the Hogarth Press, 1925. </bib>
   <notes> Chapters on Diction, Metre, Rhyme, Texture, and Structure. Graves adapts the political
    analogy of Conservatives versus Liberals to discuss the state of modern poetry. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B83">
   <bib> Gray, Thomas. "Metrum." In The Works of Thomas Gray in Prose and Verse. Ed. Edmund Gosse. 4
    vols. New York: A. C. Armstrong &amp; Son, 1885. Vol. 1, pp. 323–409. </bib>
   <notes> Gray's MS notes (written ca. 1760) for his projected History of English Poetry are
    organized in the Works as six essays, two on meter and stanza, three on the origin and
    development of rhyme, and one chiefly on Lydgate. These are, re- spectively: (1) "Observations
    on English Metre," (2) "The Measures of Verse," (3) "Observations on the Pseudo-Rhythmus"
    [Rhyme], (4) "Some Observations on the Use of Rhyme," (5) "Additional Observations and
    Conjectures on Rhyme," and (6) "Some Remarks on the Poems of John Lydgate." On metrics Gray
    tenders his judgment that though the old manuscripts are corrupt, the fault lay with the
    scribes; the poets show by variance of or- thography that they knew how to make the meter run
    smooth. Puttenham (E614) is chastised for misunderstanding "Riding Rhyme" and "Rhyme Do- grell,"
    the former of which Gray takes to be iambic in meter but admitting any other foot in any
    position and with no regularity in length of line. The second essay classifies fifty-nine meters
    by line-length, stanza-form, and rhyme-scheme. Rhyme is traced back to the Germanic tribes, with
    Otfrid noticed, be- sides early examples in Hadrian and St. Augustine, and Gray thinks that the
    custom spread from the Franks to all the other European nations north and south (he follows
    Hickes closely on this); he denies the French learned rhyme from the Arabs, but rather proposes
    Church hymns and Latin verses by the monks as the source of rhyme in Provençal. This latter view
    is however re- nounced in the fourth essay, where Gray concludes the Saxons in England must have
    learned rhyme from the Britons across the Channel rather than from the Franks (though the Welsh
    versification had been very advanced from time immemorial) since we see rhyme copiously after
    the Conquest. On Lydgate Gray offers extensive notes of literary history; the only prosodic
    matter is the discussion of the state of the language in Lydgate's day, when the great
    enlargement of foreign words still preserving their native pro- nunciations allowed a "great
    facility in rhyming" that was later and is now lost to us. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B84">
   <bib> Grindrod, Charles F. Studies in Rhyme and Rhythm. London: Elkin Mathews, 1905. 135 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Irrelevant to verse theory: a collection of poems. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B85">
   <bib> Gross, Harvey. "The Aesthetic Function of Prosody." Centennial Review of Arts and Sciences
    7 (1963): 204–18; revised and rpt as Chapter 1, "Prosody as Rhythmic Cognition," of his Sound
    and Form in Modern Poetry (E38). </bib>
   <notes> Gross conceives of prosody as the study of "rhythmic form in poetry," rhythm being
    "expressive" of "the curve of feeling, the shape and form of an emo- tion," "felt time." So much
    for critical rigor. The views here are derived (heavily) from Suzanne Langer. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B86">
   <bib> Guérard, Albert. Robert Bridges: A Study of Traditionalism in Poetry. Cambridge, Mass.:
    Harvard University Press, 1942; rpt New York: Russel &amp; Russel, 1965. </bib>
   <notes> Chapter six, "Form and Style" (pp. 106–19) discusses meter, speech-rhythms, sound
    devices, word-order, diction, archaisms, and imagery. Appendix A, "Bridges' Prosody" (pp.
    269–84) briefly explores the work in four meters: Ac- centual-Syllabic, Accentual, Quantitative,
    and Syllabic. See also s.v. "Meter" in the Index. See also E86 and E211. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B87">
   <bib> Hamilton, George R. "Verse and Poetry." Essays by Divers Hands (Transactions of the Royal
    Society of Literature) n.s. 20 (1943): 84–98. </bib>
   <notes> Along the continuum, "we cannot fix a precise borderline [that] does not im- pair the
    value of the distinction." The special virtue of verse-structure is to en- hance a
    "contemplative" mood. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B88">
   <bib> Harnack, H. Andrew. "George Herbert's 'Aaron': The Aesthetics of Shaped Typology." English
    Language Notes 14 (1976): 25–32. </bib>
   <notes> "Taken together, these repetitions of metrical lines, rhyme-words [only five words
    repeated throughout five stanzas], and stanza forms set up a series of vis- ual and auditory
    reverberations which complement the theme of the poem . . . . Structurally the poem is a formal
    analogue" to its typological theme. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B89">
   <bib> Hartog, Sir P. J. On the Relation of Poetry to Verse. English Association Pamphlet no. 64.
    Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1926. 27 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Traces out three positions which have been taken, historically, on the crucial question,
    "Why is poetry written in verse?": (1) "poetry" is synonymous with "verse"; (2) poetry is a
    certain kind of content, regardless of the form of the work, and (3) poetry embraces all those
    works with a certain kind of content and also written in verse. Lengthy Notes. A very astute and
    provocative essay. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B90">
   <bib> Havens, Raymond D. "Structure and Prosodic Pattern in Shelley's Lyrics." PMLA 65 (1950):
    1076–87. </bib>
   <notes> Sprezzatura--and failings thereof--in the lyric mode. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B91">
   <bib> Heilman, Robert B. "Poetic &amp; Prosaic: Program Notes on Opposite Numbers." Pacific
    Spectator 5 (1951): 454–63. </bib>
   <notes> Only of passing interest. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B92">
   <bib> Henson, Clyde E. The Gist of Poetics. New York: Twayne, 1965. 128 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A discursive introduction; Chapter 2 treats meter, Chapters 3 and 4 stanzas. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B93">
   <bib> Highet, Gilbert. "Rhythm in Poetry" and "Melody in Poetry." A Clerk of Oxenford: Essays on
    Literature and Life. New York: Oxford University Press, 1954. pp. 125–33, 134–41. </bib>
   <notes> Good illustrations of effects; elementary. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B94">
   <bib> Hill, Archibald A. "An Analysis of 'The Windhover': An Experiment in Structural Method."
    PMLA 70 (1955): 968–78; rpt in his Constituent and Pattern in Poetry. Austin: University of
    Texas Press, 1976. pp. 28–38. </bib>
   <notes> Response by </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="B95">
   <bib> William Mat-chett, PMLA 72 (1957): 310–11. See also Hill's refocillation in Texas Studies
    in Literature and Language 7 (1965): 349–59. </bib>
   <notes> The great virtue of this linguistic explication is that it is completely self- conscious:
    Hill explains his principles and procedures even as he applies them to the Hopkins poem,
    justifying them, thereby, both pragmatically and formally. He works his way through the
    micro-structure of the text, sorting out alternative readings on the basis of the semantic
    implications of intonational patterns and also the substitution principle of information theory.
    But is there not an obvious logical circularity in the claim that "the quickest way to
    demonstrate the meaning [of an ambiguous phrase] is to give it the proper stress and juncture
    pattern by reading it aloud"? </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B96">
   <bib> Hillyer, Robert. First Principles of Verse. Boston: The Writer, 1938; rpt 1957. </bib>
   <notes> One cannot imagine any justification for reprinting this book. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B97">
   <bib> Hoffsten, Ernest G. "Swinburne's Poetic Theories and Practice." Sewanee Review 13 (1905):
    54–60. </bib>
   <notes> Short, random core-samples of meters, stanzas, and sound-effects. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B98">
   <bib> Hollander, John. Introduction to Selected Poems of Ben Jonson. New York: Dell- Laurel,
    1961; revised and expanded into Chapter 8 of his Vision and Resonance (A13), pp. 165–86. </bib>
   <notes> Passim. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B99">
   <bib> Holmes, Martin. Shakespeare and Burbage: The Sound of Shakespeare as Devised to Suit the
    Voice and Talents of His Principal Player. Chichester: Fillimore, 1978. 205 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Frequent remarks on meter, rhyme, and the melodic line, passim, especially in Chapter 7.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B100">
   <bib> Hope, Alec Dervent. The Structure of Verse and Prose. Sydney: Sydney Teachers' College,
    1938. </bib>
   <notes> Pamphlet. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B101">
   <bib> Howell, A. C. "A Note on Ben Jonson's Literary Methods." SP 28 (1931): 710–19. </bib>
   <notes> With Jonson matter preceded manner: he seems to have written out his poetry first as
    prose, then worked it into verse. He considered first what he wanted to say, how the idea had
    been treated by the classical authors, what notes he had at hand in his commonplace book--then
    turned to his versifying. He also re- lied heavily on short bits of translation. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B102">
   <bib> Hudson, Theodore R. "Technical Aspects of the Poetry of Langston Hughes." Black World 22,
    11 (1973): 24–45. </bib>
   <notes> Among many other technical features Hudson notes the crucial influences of the blues,
    gospel hymns, and folk ballads on the poet's meter. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B103">
   <bib> Hynes, Sam. "Poetry, Poetic, Poem." College English 19 (1958): 263–67. </bib>
   <notes> Conceptual analysis. Hynes catches Brooks and Warren claiming that poetry denotes simply
    a relative degree of verbal compression, but that approach ne- glects Form. Definitions based on
    poetic language or diction are equally unhelp- ful. Solution: poetry is "a collective term for
    all poems"; a poem is "a discourse in the form of an arrangement of lines" of "more highly
    organized sound pat- terns." The relative value of poems, then, can be judged by their degree of
    "symbolic exten- sion. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B104">
   <bib> Ikegami, Yoshihiko. "On Poetical License: Linguistic and Semantic Deviation in Poetry."
    Anglica (Osaka) 5 (1963): 23–40. </bib>
   <notes> "License" is defined as "a certain range to a linguistic symbol in which it may be
    different without the difference becoming meaningful." The licenses in po- etry may occur at the
    phonological, morphological, syntactic, graphic, or metalinguistic level, those on the
    phonological level being meter, rhyme, allit- eration, and juncture. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B105">
   <bib> Irwin, John T. "The Crisis of Regular Forms." Sewanee Review 81 (1973): 158–71. </bib>
   <notes> "Doesn't the organic theory that a unique experience should generate an en- tirely new
    surface structure have the poetic process backwards?" "A regular form is not a ready-made
    container into which an emotion is poured." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B106">
   <bib> Isenberg, Arnold. "The Technical Factor in Art." Journal of Philosophy 43 (1946): 5– 19. </bib>
   <notes> Attacks Croce's thesis that the aesthetic idea precedes (and surpasses in value) its
    externalization in a medium. For Isenberg the physical medium is an indis- pensable part of the
    creative process. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B107">
   <bib> Jenkinson, Editha. The Art of Writing Verse: The Malory Introduction to Prosody. London: E.
    Macdonald, Ltd., 1920. 62 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A very slight work even for a primer; she explicitly follows R. F. Brewer (E489).
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B108">
   <bib> Johnson, Charles F. Forms of English Poetry. New York: American Book Company, 1904. 356 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A primer organized by forms. His principles: metrical feet are units "which di- vide the
    time of utterance into equal parts" and which "are marked by the presence of an accented
    syllable which serves to individualize them." Classical meter, on the other hand, used
    "quantity, or time occupied in pronouncing the vowel, not accent, [to mark] the pronunciation
    units." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B109">
   <bib> Johnson, Dr. Samuel. The Lives of the English Poets. 4 vols. London, 1779, 1781; 2 vols.
    London: Oxford University Press, 1906; reset 1952; rpt 1973. </bib>
   <notes> For Johnson's estimation of the prosodic skill of his predecessors, see, in vol. 1: pp.
    38, 48–51 (Life of Cowley); 117, 131–33 (Life of Milton); 293–94, 329–32 (Life of Dryden). In
    vol. 2: pp. 314–15, 326–27 (Life of Pope), 358 (Life of Thomson). Cowley he censures for
    irregularity of numbers; Milton is given credit for a second-order performance, his blank verses
    being weakened by the want of rhyme; Dryden, despite indolence, "tuned the numbers of English
    po- etry"--"he found it brick, and he left it marble"; Pope's consummate craft can scarcely be
    surpassed; and Thomson's originality earns a slightly better place for his blank verses.
    Johnson's disdain of "representative meter" [prosodic mimesis, both by sound and meter] appears
    at i, 51 and ii, 314; he thinks its legitimate province very small: "verse can imitate only
    sound and motion." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B110">
   <bib> Johnson, Wendell Stacy. "Some Functions of Poetic Form." JAAC 13 (1955): 496– 506. </bib>
   <notes> The article opens by questioning the notion of "content vs. form" and even the isolation
    of the latter: "there is no pure and independent form . . . . while formal relationships can be
    perceived without reference to the semantic func- tion of language . . . they cannot be
    determined, nor can they be analyzed, without referring to the meaning of words." For the
    analysis of poetry, then, "the primary objects which can be related formally are sounds, with
    their properties of quality and extension," rather than syntax, meter, or rhyme. The formal
    elements of poetry may serve three purposes: "organizing, intensifying, and complementing or
    creating of the total communication"; this latter function has three categories, or modes: "the
    reinforcing of description by evocation of an external sensible effect" (onomatopoeia and
    "sense-evoking rhythms" belong here); "the reinforcement of idea by structural embodiment" (as,
    for example, the musical theme of Stevens' "Peter Quince" becomes con- trolling musical
    structure); and "the creation of sense through contrast between sound and statement," i.e.,
    tension or irony. The communicative function, then, has three modes, evoking, embodying, and
    tensioning. Also objectionable are our inept notation systems for marking abstract relations of
    formal elements, "particularly in the foot system which Saintsbury defended" in metrics. In sum,
    "poetic form has virtually no value, no interest for the reader, except as it is related to the
    semantic aspect, as it is understood to function." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B111">
   <bib> Jones, H. S. V. "Language and Versification." A Spenser Handbook. New York: F. S. Crofts,
    1930. pp. 394–405. </bib>
   <notes> Very elementary. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B112">
   <bib> Kamel, Rose. "The Making of a Poem: A Stylistic Study of the Pre-war Poetry of Stephen
    Spender." DAI 32 (1971): 3310A (Temple). </bib>
   <notes> Traces the development of a more flexible voice in rhythm, syntax, diction, and tone.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B113">
   <bib> Keary, C. F. "Some Thoughts on the Technique of Poetry." Fortnightly Review 86 (1906):
    811–26. </bib>
   <notes> With elegance and insight Keary reiterates the centrality of the study of tech- nique in
    criticism. Here he examines the two aspects of verse which seem most artificial to the layman,
    lining and rhyme, showing their necessity, func- tions, happy successes. "Verse is in fact
    neither an accident nor a choice, not a trick nor a translation, but a necessity for certain
    moods of thought and, therefore, certain modes of speech." The value of this essay has not
    dimin- ished. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B114">
   <bib> Kebirungi, Emma. "Verse and Poetry." Dhana (Uganda) 6, 1 (1976): 46–49. </bib>
   <notes> The emphasis here hovers between the view that "poetry" is a certain charac- teristic
    content, regardless of its mode of presentation, and the view that verse is somehow essential to
    "poetic" articulation. But "poetry envelops more ele- ments within it than verse. Verse is a
    technique in poetry . . . . Verse, never- theless, is not all poetry." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B115">
   <bib> Ker, W. P. Form and Style in Poetry. Ed. R. W. Chapman. London: Macmillan, 1928. </bib>
   <notes> W. P. Ker's Clark and London University Lectures have been important and influential
    steadily since their publication, and this collection is required read- ing for the prosodist
    (the attentive reader will notice that Ker is the source for several titles of later books on
    prosody). Of the Clark Lectures, "Various Meanings of 'Form' in Poetry" is the most relevant; of
    the London Lectures, numbers 1, 4, and 10 concern Form (especially the last of these: "Relation
    Between Forms of Verse and Forms of Poetry"); 5, 15, and 16 concern Poetic Diction; 11 and 12
    treat metrical types and their ancestry; and 13 and 14 ex- plore stanzaic patterns. The
    Appendices include two essays on Spanish versifi- cation (see L75), a review of Saintsbury (A8),
    and a brief essay on the Dantean hendecasyllable (L1144). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B116">
   <bib> Kimmey, John L. "Order and Form in Herrick's Hesperides." JEGP 70 (1971): 255–68. </bib>
   <notes> An argument that poetic form itself is the ordering-principle of Herrick's vol- ume of
    poems. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B117">
   <bib> Kiparsky, Paul. "The Role of Linguistics in a Theory of Poetry." Daedalus 102 (1973):
    231–44; rpt in Language as a Human Problem. Ed. E. Haugen and M. Bloomfield. New York: W. W.
    Norton, 1974. pp. 223–46. </bib>
   <notes> An important general and non-technical essay presenting the notion that "a good number of
    what we think of as traditional and arbitrary conventions [in poetry] are anchored in
    grammatical form, and seem to be, at bottom, a con- sequence of how language itself is
    structured." The principle underlying poetic form is repetition, and as Kiparsky shows, the same
    abstract pattern (e.g., abab) may be filled by various linguistic elements so as to produce
    different surface schemas in the poem: if the elements are phonological, then the schema will be
    rhyme or alliteration; if stress or quantity, then meter; if syntactically equivalent phrases,
    then parallelism. A theory is sketched out and some surprising conclu- sions derived, e.g.,
    "identity of sound is neither a necessary nor a sufficient condition for rhyme and
    alliteration." Kiparsky examines at close range syntax, meter, and sound. A synoptic, heuristic,
    immensely provocative essay. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B118">
   <bib> Kivimaa, Kirsti. Aspects of Style in T. S. Eliot's "Murder in the Cathedral". Turku: Turun
    Yliopisto, 1969. </bib>
   <notes> Brief remarks on rhythm (stress-verse), rhyme, and alliteration, pp. 78–85, be- sides
    entire sections on Syntax and Vocabulary. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B119">
   <bib> La Drière, J. Craig. "Poetry and Prose." Dictionary of World Literary Terms. Ed. Joseph T.
    Shipley. Boston: The Writer, 1970. pp. 242–46. </bib>
   <notes> This edition "completely revised and enlarged." Earlier editions are entitled Dictionary
    of World Literature. (New York: The Philosophical Library, 1943; 2nd ed. 1953.) </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B120">
   <bib> Lane, Lauriat, Jr. "Finding a Voice: Thoreau's Pentameters." Emerson Society Quarterly 60
    (1970): 67–72. </bib>
   <notes> On his stylistic development. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B121">
   <bib> Lea, Kathleen. "The Poetic Powers of Repetition." Proceedings of the British Academy 55
    (1969): 51–76. </bib>
   <notes> The question considered: Why is it that sheer repetition per se is sometimes effective,
    sometimes disastrous in poems? </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B122">
   <bib> Leech, Geoffrey N. A Linguistic Guide to English Poetry. London: Longman, 1969. 240 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by W. O. Hendricks in Lingua 25 (1971): 165–77; by Roger Fowler in Language and
    Style 3 (1970): 238–40. A partial successor to Shapiro and Beum (B195), Leech's handbook is the
    end product of the great surge of linguistic interest in poetry in the Sixties. What Leech has
    produced is a conventional handbook on the language, sound, me- ter, imagery, and figuration of
    poetry, yet entirely re-thought and re-written throughout from the standpoint of linguistics and
    on the basis of the most re- cent research. The result, for students and nonspecialists, is that
    everything old is refurbished and given fresh finish. Excellent for introductory purposes, but
    not as a continual reference, and best not read straight through. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B123">
   <bib> -----. "Literary Criticism and Linguistic Description." Dutch Quarterly Review of
    Anglo-American Letters 7 (1977): 2–22. </bib>
   <notes> Besides examining the important question of the precise relation of these two
    enterprises, the essay offers detailed phonemic, metrical, and stylistic analyses of Keats's
    "Ode to a Nightingale" in comparison with Leavis's critical judgments of the poem. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B124">
   <bib> Leibowitz, Herbert A. "A Stylistic Analysis of Hart Crane's Poetry." DA 30 (1969): 2029A
    (Columbia). </bib>
   <notes> Some attention to syntax, meter, and stanza. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B125">
   <bib> Leider, Emily W. "Plainness of Style in King Lear." Shakespeare Quarterly 21 (1970): 45–53. </bib>
   <notes> Vocabulary, syntax, meter. Lear she finds a stylistic exercise not in plainness but in
    flexibility and decorum. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B126">
   <bib> Levenston, E. A. "A Scheme for the Inter-Relation of Linguistic Analysis and Poetry
    Criticism." Linguistics, no. 129 (1974), pp. 29–47. </bib>
   <notes> Confronting the question of the uses of linguistic method for the criticism of poetry,
    Levenston offers an answer by setting the three traditional realms of linguistics--phonology,
    grammar, and semantics--against each other, produc- ing a schema of nine possible approaches to
    poetry, with extended commen- tary. A very sensible and heuristic anatomy. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B127">
   <bib> Levin, Samuel R. "The Conventions of Poetry." Literary Style: A Symposium. Ed. Seymour
    Chatman. London: Oxford University Press, 1971. pp. 177–93. Discussion follows, pp. 193–96. </bib>
   <notes> "A poem is an aesthetic object composed of language." The linguistic elements of the poem
    convey sense by performing their ordinary cognitive function, but the conventions of the poem
    (those treated here: meter, rhyme, the line, en- jambement, and caesura) "have no linguistic
    significance . . . . the function they perform is a purely aesthetic one." This latter function
    is ultimately cognitive (i.e., information-producing) as well, but the distinction is
    nonetheless crucial: in verse, the linguistic elements perform two functions at once. Meter, for
    ex- ample, is "an abstract schema of periodicity" filled by various linguistic con- stituents.
    ("The rhythm is more than simply a realization of the meter; it is an amalgam of the meter and
    the particular suprasegmental features required by the sentences of the poem.") The line is
    conventionally defined sometimes by the meter but usually by the sound devices, or else a pause.
    When the pause indicates a strain between language (syntax) and convention (the line), it should
    be considered enjambement [stipulative definition]. By the same logic caesura is not a syntactic
    pause at mid-line but rather the force that through the green line drives the meter. Rhyme is a
    pre-cognitive aesthetic (i.e., uni- fying) convention which may or may not interact with
    meaning-bearing mor- phemes. All these conventions serve to mark the text as poetic and to
    "deautomatize" its language, preventing habituated perfunctory responses by the reader, forcing
    him back to the text with sharpened attention. An excep- tionally tough-minded, incisive paper,
    which revoked some conventionalities [sic] and so stirred a lively discussion, q.v. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B128">
   <bib> -----. "Internal and External Deviation in Poetry." Word 21 (1965): 225–39. </bib>
   <notes> Deviation might be said to be the primary attribute of poetic form. Two types occur:
    internal (deviation against the norm established by the poem as a whole) and external (the
    language itself being the norm). Features used systematically in poetry--e.g., meter, rhyme,
    typography--become conventions, but internal deviation against them is still possible.
    Phonological deviation--i.e., an unusual distribution of sounds--is mainly external, as is
    lexical ("poetic diction"), though other types do occur. The problem in explaining external
    syntactic de- viation is the discernment of the correct norm, which can only be a generative
    grammar (Levin repeats the arguments of his earlier essay [F126] in large part). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B129">
   <bib> -----. Linguistic Structures in Poetry. Janua Linguarum, no. 23. The Hague: Mouton, 1962.
    Pages 51–58 are reprinted in Freeman (A22, pp. 197–205) as "Coupling in a Shakespeare Sonnet." </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in Language 42 (1966): 639–49; in American Speech 38 (1963): 137–40. Levin's
    monograph represents the first full-scale application of Jakobson's dic- tum on equivalence as
    the informing principle of poetic structure (see L65). Levin's theory attempts to account for
    the "special unity of structure" charac- teristic of poetry by schematizing its use of
    "equivalent positions as settings for equivalent phonic and/or semantic elements" ("positions"
    are defined as "those places in the linguistic chain where alternation is possible"). Of
    equivalences, then, he specifies two types: Type I: Positional a. syntagmatic (syntactic) b.
    conventional (prosodic) Type II: Natural a. semantic (similar or opposite) b. phonic (echoic).
    That is, poetry offers two types of seriatim "slots" (syntactic and prosodic) to be filled by
    the available ("vertical") alternatives in the language. Filling of the correlate syntagmatic
    positions with equivalent semantic units produces what we normally think of as rhetorical
    devices such as parallelism and antithesis, and filling with sound produces schemes and
    sound-patterning. Filling of the prosodic matrix with semantic units that are equivalent
    produces metrical heightening or emphasis, and filling with sound units the various types of
    rhyme as discussed by Wimsatt. The crux of Levin's theory is that "poetic" structure is a result
    of these couplings of Type II to Type I equivalences: possi- bilities are screened then matched
    and fitted into positions. Is more coupling therefore "more poetic" a priori? Not necessarily.
    The couplings apparently must be integrated variously with other elements in the poem, and there
    does seem to be a saturation point (Swinburne comes to mind at once). Levin gives a full-scale
    specimen analysis of a Shakespearean sonnet. Cf. B60. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B130">
   <bib> Livingston, Richard Alan. "'Making the Whole Most Musicall': A Study of Prosodic Elements
    and Patterns of Sound in the Poetry of Henry Vaughan." DAI 38 (1978): 5498A (Northwestern). </bib>
   <notes> Examines metrical technique, stanza- and rhyme-patterns, and sound- patterning. Concludes
    that Vaughan achieved simplicity, complexity, transpar- ency, unity, and intensity. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B131">
   <bib> Locock, C. D. "Notes on the Technique of Meredith's Poetry." Englische Studien 46
    (1912–13): 86–97. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B132">
   <bib> Logan, Conrad T., and C. B. Parks. "Rhythm and Rhyme Tests." English Journal 17 (1928):
    678–81. </bib>
   <notes> The shrewd student of verseform may take some interest in this elementary article which
    gives rhymes (asking us to find the correct one) and rhythms (fifteen lines, each given in a
    regular and an irregular form). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B133">
   <bib> Logan, Harry M. "Some Applications of Linguistic Theory to Poetry." Humanities Association
    Bulletin 21 (1970): 40–47. </bib>
   <notes> Urges a unified critical and linguistic attention to poetry, covering such mat- ters as
    line-structure, syntax, intonation, metrics. Analyzes Frost's "The Span of Life." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B134">
   <bib> Long, Mason. "Verse Form." In his Poetry and Its Forms. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons,
    1938. pp. 34–70. </bib>
   <notes> Elementary and irrelevant. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B135">
   <bib> Lord, John B. "Syntax and Phonology in Poetic Style." Style 9 (1975): 1–31. </bib>
   <notes> An examination of syntactic organization, observations on the concept of the line, and
    distinctive-feature analyses. Poetry, Lord concludes, is "hyper- ordered language." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B136">
   <bib> Lotspeich, C. M. "Poetry, Prose, and Rhythm." PMLA 37 (1922): 293–310. </bib>
   <notes> The differentia of prose and poetry "rests upon a difference in the nature of two mental
    processes: in poetry the intellectual content is furnished by the process of direct
    apprehension, or immediate understanding; in prose it is furnished largely by indirect
    comprehension, or judgment and reflective thought." The implica- tion: thinking interferes with
    naturally rhythmic activities. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B137">
   <bib> McFarland, Thomas. "Poetry and the Poem: The Structure of Poetic Content." Literary Theory
    and Structures: Essays in Honor of W. K. Wimsatt. Ed. Frank Brady et al. New Haven: Yale
    University Press, 1973. pp. 81–113. </bib>
   <notes> Superimposed, as it were, on the Western critical distinctions between the terms
    "poetry," "prose," and "verse" is a long tradition distinguishing "poetry," in the sense of an
    "unbounded current of feeling," and "poem," as a sharply defined artifact. The former we tend to
    associate with "content" and the latter with "form," but the author proposes three other terms
    instead, in order to elucidate some further distinctions--substantia, ens, and essentia.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B138">
   <bib> Mackail, J[ohn] W[illiam]. "The Definition of Poetry." In his Lectures on Poetry. London:
    Longmans, Green, 1911, 1914. pp. 1–22. </bib>
   <notes> A lucid review and critique of the kinds and purposes of definitions of poetry. "The
    essence of poetry technically . . . is not that it is rhythmical. All elevated or impassioned
    language is that. The essence of poetry technically is that it is patterned language." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B139">
   <bib> -----. "The Study of Poetry." Rice Institute Pamphlets. 2, 1 (1915): 1–52. </bib>
   <notes> See section 2, "What is Poetry?" In any search for the specific differentia of poetry "it
    is not enough to say that it is language which possesses design and has decorative value. All
    beautiful, dignified, and elevated language has that." The crucial feature of poetry is that "in
    it structure and decoration are insepa- rable." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B140">
   <bib> McLeod, Stuart R. "Problems of Poetry and Dramaturgy in Modern Verse Drama." DA 29 (1968):
    904A (Florida, 1961). </bib>
   <notes> Discusses the successes and failures of modern dramatists at finding new verse- forms
    that could be appropriate for our age as well as rich in sound and im- agery and powerfully
    persuasive emotionally and intellectually. Lorca is found to be the most successful. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B141">
   <bib> Manierre, William R. "Versification and Imagery in The Fall of Hyperion. Texas Studies in
    Literature and Language 3 (1961): 264–79. </bib>
   <notes> Mainly imagery, but some close reading uncovers subtle effects in syntax, stressing, and
    sound. Esp. pp. 265–66, 277. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B142">
   <bib> Manning, Frederic. "Poetry in Prose." The Chapbook, no. 22 (1921), pp. 10–15. Cf. B1, B53. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B143">
   <bib> Martin, C. G. "W. B. Yeats: An Unpublished Letter." Notes &amp; Queries 203 (1958): 260–61. </bib>
   <notes> In response to an admirer's request for a recommen-dation of a book on pros- ody (or
    verse-making?), Yeats replied briefly that he didn't know of one and couldn't remember having
    read one. For instruction, he recommends the Elizabethan lyricists. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B144">
   <bib> Martland, Agatha M. "A Study of the Transition in Subject Matter, Imagery, Rhythm, and
    Rhyme Reflected in the Poetry of W. B. Yeats, 1899–1914." Thesis, New York University, 1955. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B145">
   <bib> Masson, David. "Prose and Verse: De Quincey." British Quarterly Review, 1854; rpt in his
    Essays Biographical and Critical, Chiefly on English Poets. London, 1856. pp. 447–75. </bib>
   <notes> Especially pp. 452–53 and the end: Masson makes a valuable distinction in this essay
    between the view of verse as an "essential condition" of any one class or degree of thoughts and
    the view of verse as an optional form for any thought. But he will not allow that thoughts come
    first, fully formed in the mind, at which point they may or may not be cast into a metered mold;
    rather, the meaning, "is conditioned beforehand by the form of the expression selected."
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B146">
   <bib> Maynard, Theodore. "The Patterns of Poetry." A Preface to Poetry. New York: The Century
    Co., 1933. pp. 67–176. </bib>
   <notes> Sections on form, meter, rhyme, stanza, sonnet, and "setforms." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B147">
   <bib> Mégroz, R[udolphe] L. "Technical Developments." Modern English Poetry, 1882– 1932. London:
    Ivor Nicholson &amp; Watson, 1933. </bib>
   <notes> Mégroz takes Hopkins and Pound to be the two crucial influences of the pe- riod, so the
    preponderance of the chapter explicates their theories and prac- tices, but the late pages
    discuss many minor poets, developments in colloquial diction in poetry, poetic narratives, and
    the use of verse in the theater. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B148">
   <bib> Messing, Gordon M. "The Linguistic Analysis of Some Contemporary Nonformal Poetry."
    Language and Style 2 (1969): 323–29. </bib>
   <notes> The absence of formal patterning in three poems allows the hasty generaliza- tion that
    modern poetry can only be approached, by the linguist, through se- mantics. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B149">
   <bib> Meyerstein, E. H. W. "Concealed Verse in Pope's Prose." TLS, 17 July 1937, p. 528. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B150">
   <bib> Miles, Josephine. "Styles in Lyric." Style 5 (1971): 226–30. </bib>
   <notes> Identifies the lyric with "language musically accompanied, measure marked by musically
    pitched accents," and with the play of atemporal relations across a temporal sequence. Pitch,
    stress, timbre give logopoeia, phanopoeia, melopoeia. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B151">
   <bib> Morgan, Kenneth S. "Formal Style in The Faerie Queene." DA 27 (1967): 3846A (Princeton). </bib>
   <notes> Examines the patterning of rhetorical figures in the poem in correlation with the other
    formal elements, meter, line, rhyme, and stanza. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B152">
   <bib> Morrison, James M. "Wallace Stevens and the Forms of Lyric Poetry." Diss., Harvard
    University, 1969. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B153">
   <bib> Muir, Kenneth. "Verse and Prose." Contemporary Theater. Ed. John R. Brown and Bernard
    Harris. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1962. pp. 97–115. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B154">
   <bib> Mulder, William. "Freedom and Form: Robert Frost's Double Discipline." South Atlantic
    Quarterly 54 (1955): 386–93. </bib>
   <notes> Some attention to meter, rhyme, and tones. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B155">
   <bib> Murphy, Charles D. "John Davies's Versification of Sidney's Prose." PQ 21 (1942): 410–14. </bib>
   <notes> Davies undertook a systematic versifying of De Mornay's theological treatise translated
    by Sidney and Golding, producing verse that is wincingly clumsy. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B156">
   <bib> Nist, John. "Linguistics and the Esthetics of English." Costerus 1 (1972): 183–205. </bib>
   <notes> In search of a synthetic account of "the esthetic dimension of the English lan- guage,"
    Nist identifies three major areas: theory, prosody, and phonesthemics. About prosody he
    identifies four "lies" told to schoolboys, as well as the error of "metrical fundamentalism,"
    the belief that English prosody is unitary rather than tripartite. Its true parts are Meter,
    Cadence, and Rhythm. Schematically: Semantic Component -> Abstract Meter -> Content Norm
    Grammatical Component -> Specific Cadence -> Mapping Function Phonological Component -> Actual
    Rhythm -> Expressive Value Examples of phonesthemes in Shakespeare, Hopkins, and Tennyson.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B157">
   <bib> Nowottny, Winifred. The Language Poets Use. London: The Athlone Press, 1962; rpt "with
    corrections," 1965. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in JEGP 62 (1963): 784–86; in Review of English Studies n.s. 14 (1963): 432–34; in
    Archiv 200 (1963): 230–32; in Studia Neophilologica 35 (1963): 303– 5; in English Studies 45
    (1964): 76–78; in Die Neueren Sprachen n.s. 13 (1964): 54–55; in Linguistics 33 (1967): 125–36.
    One of the most valuable studies available on the thorny subject of "poetic language." Mrs.
    Nowottny demonstrates, through a number of exhibits and extended asides, the complex
    inter-relations of vocabulary, syntax, meter, and sound in poems which in their joint effect and
    issue create a "language" of "a recognizably higher degree of patterning" than that of our
    quotidian speech. Alternatively, we may say, she shows the manifold elements and designs of the
    semantic construct that is a poem. Chapter 2 tackles the chimera Poetic Dic- tion; chapter 5
    treats the "artificial" forms of meter and stanza (explicating the famous elegy on the death of
    the Countess of Pembroke); chapter 1 offers a fresh discussion of semantic "mimicry" in
    onomatopoeia and other sound- effects. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B158">
   <bib> Olson, Elder. "General Prosody: Rhythmik, Metrik, Harmonics." Diss., University of Chicago,
    1938. </bib>
   <notes> Apparently also published by the University of Chicago Libraries in a private edition
    (lithoprint). Olson, later one of the Chicago School critics, wrote his dissertation in search
    of "principles upon which any verse, if it is to be verse, must found." Those would be the
    principles of a general prosody, as opposed to those of all the ex- tant treatises in special
    (i.e., language-specific) prosodies, which Olson believes are mistaken to assume "that a
    difference of language entails a difference of principle" and "to exhibit conventions rather
    than forms, and to arrive, not at principles, but at rules." Olson's own principles are that
    "prosody is not a sci- ence but a part of the analysis of diction in rhetoric and in poetics . .
    . it is not a matter of rules, nor of notations, nor a history of prosodic conventions, but
    rather, an enumeration of the modes in which speech-sounds may be com- bined for the
    embellishment of diction, together with an explanation of such devices in terms of the functions
    of diction itself." The principle of all verse- structure is "proportionality" (it is "sensibly
    regular"); the atomic element of general prosody is the syllable, which may be arrayed in
    regular sequences ac- cording to any of its five characteristics--syntactic position, duration,
    intensity (accent), pitch, and entity. The most elementary groupings of syllables are termed
    primary ratios ("feet"), are marked by the presence and absence of em- phasis, and yield
    primitive rhythms; the next larger groupings, demarcated arbi- trarily and not by emphasis, are
    termed post-primary ratios and yield post-primary rhythms ("meter"). The "foot" is defined
    (formally) as a unit consisting of one arsis and one thesis (unemphatic and emphatic members),
    but these members may be actually constituted (materially) by more than one syllable, creating
    simple (iambic and trochaic) and compound feet; conversely, a foot containing in an anapestic
    line is an anapestic foot, not an iambic substitution (the defini- tion is formal not actual). A
    long Appendix provides sample analyses, such as the following, where t stands for thesis, a for
    arsis: Red River, Red River . . . . . . . . t a t a t a t a The method for finding out the
    rhythm is ad hoc: one must know the form in advance, or else find some unequivocal feet as
    indicators. I know of only one application of Olson's system, that by Reeve (G79). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B159">
   <bib> Omond, T. S. "Is Verse a Trammel?" The Gentleman's Magazine n.s. 14 (1875): 344–54. </bib>
   <notes> Responding to earlier criticism, Omond denies that verse is any shackle, primitive form,
    or unnecessary ornament. On the contrary: "under the inspi- ration of high imaginings," man has
    always "expressed himself in regular peri- ods"; this is a law for all verse known to man. And
    this law of "rhythmical ex- pression" has nothing to do with lineation or print; the proper
    distinction, as Shelley said, is not between verse and prose, but simply between "measured and
    unmeasured language." In short, some sort of metering principle is a sine qua non for verse.
    Omond can then defend Whitman as a poet, despite his free-verse lines, on the grounds that
    whenever his thought becomes most passionate and in- tense, "the language instantly assumes a
    metrical cadence." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B160">
   <bib> Onions, C. T., and Derek A. Day. "Prosody." In Cassell's Encyclopaedia of World Literature.
    Ed. S. H. Steinberg. 2 vols. New York: Cassell, 1953; rpt in 3 vols. New York: William Morrow,
    1973. Vol. 1, pp. 466–70. </bib>
   <notes> A useful introductory essay having international scope and providing an excel- lent short
    bibliography. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B161">
   <bib> Packard, William. [Editorial Preface.] New York Quarterly. no. 12 (1972), pp. 3–12. </bib>
   <notes> A mere list of technical terms with definitions. Better: "real art always involves the
    risk of sacrifice by an extraordinary individual." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B162">
   <bib> Parker, Marion H. Language and Reality: A Course in Contemporary Criticism. London:
    Frederick Muller, 1949. </bib>
   <notes> Slight, but see the sections on "Configuration Words," "Rhythm," and "Word Order."
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B163">
   <bib> Parsons, Roger L. "Renaissance and Baroque: Multiple Unity and Unified Unity in the
    Treatment of Verse, Ornament, and Structure." DA 19 (1959): 2958A </bib>
   <notes> (Wisconsin). Adapts Wülfflin's fourth category, "multiplicity-unity," to describe the
    contrast between sixteenth- and seventeenth-century verse in terms of syntax, imagery, and
    stanza construction. In Renaissance verse syntax reinforces the line; in Baroque verse it
    counterpoises it. Renaissance verse is built up out of co- ordinate wholes; Baroque verse
    heightens the dominance/subordination of its stanzaic elements. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B164">
   <bib> Peck, James W. "Variation in Milton's Samson Agonistes: A Study of Its Occurrence in
    Syntax, in Diction, in Phonology, and in Metrics." DAI 31 (1971): 3517A (Alabama). </bib>
   <notes> Examines 881 variations in these four dimensions in a sample of 306 lines, in search of a
    variance in their distribution in "climactic" vs. "non-climactic" passages (429 and 452
    variations, respectively). Results are very tentatively af- firmative. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B165">
   <bib> Perloff, Marjorie G. The Poetic Art of Robert Lowell. Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell University
    Press, 1973. </bib>
   <notes> Mainly explication and interpretation, but Chapter 3, "The 'Life-Blood of a Poem': The
    Uses of Syntax," enumerates several distinctive syntactic/stylistic features of Lowell's,
    including dynamic verbs balanced against qualifying ad- jectives or phrases. Note also some
    sound and stress patterns, pp. 170–75. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B166">
   <bib> Perry, Bliss. A Study of Poetry. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1920. 396 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Chapter IV, "The Poet's Words," is long and now elementary. Chapter V on "Rhythm and
    Meter" explores the "conflict and compromise" of "timers" and "stressers," the rhythm of prose,
    concepts of quantity and stress, the analogy with music, and "enjoyment." That this exposition
    continues to be modestly relevant may be demonstrated by Cable (J42). Chapter VI on "Rhyme,
    Stanza, and Free Verse" sensibly defines rhyme and stanza as other varieties of rhythm. Part II
    of the book treats the Lyric. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B167">
   <bib> Perry, Mary Frances. "Linguistics as a Basis for Literary Criticism." DAI 25 (1965): 5921A
    (Indiana). </bib>
   <notes> Abstracted in Linguistics, no. 20 (1966), pp. 20–21. Analysis of rhyme, syntax, lexis,
    and sound-patterns in twelve poems by Snod- grass, Cummings, Masters, Frost, Engle, and Bogan,
    based on phonemic tran- scription of recordings alongside the texts. Resolution of ambiguity for
    eluci- dation of interpretation is judged the primary value of linguistic analysis. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B168">
   <bib> Petofi, Janos S. "Some Problems of the Linguistic Analysis of Poetic Works of Art." Actes
    du Xe congres international des linguistes. Ed. A. Graur et al. Bucarest: Ed. Acad. R.S.R.,
    1969–70. Vol. 3, pp. 105–6. </bib>
   <notes> A succinct outline of all the components requisite for a "general theory of po- etics."
    "Investigating the linguistic structure of a poetic work of art we can speak of a linguistic
    sign-component (including the syntactic and the semantic subcomponents) and a musical one
    (including the rhythmic and the euphonic sub- components). Both of them can be composed to build
    a linear and a hierarchical structure." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B169">
   <bib> Press, John. The Fire and the Fountain. New York: Oxford University Press, 1955. </bib>
   <notes> Chapter 4, pp. 94–143, discusses music and poetry, rhythm and meter, phras- ing, sound
    and sense. The tone is discursive, urbane, and engaging, and Press touches on a great many poets
    without arguing any single thesis. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B170">
   <bib> Priestley, F. E. L. Language and Structure in Tennyson's Poetry. London: Andre Deutsch,
    1973. </bib>
   <notes> There are remarks on versification passim; see s.v. "Metrics," "Rhyme," and "Experiments
    in Stanza Forms" in the Index. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B171">
   <bib> Ramratnam, Malati. "Studies in the Craftsmanship of W. B. Yeats." DAI 34 (1974): 4281A
    (Brandeis). </bib>
   <notes> Mainly on diction. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B172">
   <bib> Ransome, Arthur. "Kinetic and Potential Speech." Oxford and Cambridge Review 16 (1911):
    135–44. </bib>
   <notes> Taking the analogy from physics, Ransome defines poetry as a mixture of ki- netic and
    potential speech, purely kinetic (exerted, expressed) speech being prose and purely potential
    speech being music. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B173">
   <bib> Ranta, Jerrald. "Counting and Formal Analysis." JAAC 29 (1971): 453–66. </bib>
   <notes> Urges the use of an analysis which takes into consideration the "mathematical"
    relationships and patterns of poems, on the grounds that such a procedure has been commonplace
    for traditional (metered) forms of poetry and will therefore inform us about the new
    (twentieth-century, unmetered) poetry as well, which as yet we do not understand. Sample
    analyses of poems by Stevens and William Carlos Williams. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B174">
   <bib> Rathe, Armin. "Zum Vers-, Strophe-, und Gedicht-Bau im Werk von W. H. Auden." Diss.,
    University of Manchester, 1969. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B175">
   <bib> Raymond, G[eorge] L[ansing]. Poetry as a Representative Art. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons,
    1885; 5th rev. ed. 1903. </bib>
   <notes> Chapters on "elocution" and force, pitch, duration, timbre; meanings of sounds and
    meanings of words; and the idea of representation. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B176">
   <bib> Redlay. "Essay on Rhyme." Literary Chronicle, no. 114 (21 July 1821), pp. 458–59. </bib>
   <notes> Divides literary language into three domains, the "rhythmical, metrical, and prosaical."
    Curiously, he believes the historical order of these modes to be prose, metrical prose, blank
    verse, and finally rhyme. Of these, rhyme is de- fended as the highest mode of human utterance.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B177">
   <bib> -----. "On Metrical Prose." Literary Chronicle, no. 117 (11 August 1821), pp. 503–4; no.
    121 (8 September), pp. 565–66. </bib>
   <notes> In the second and third installments we discover that though rhyme is the acme of
    utterance, mere mortals can only attain excellence in measured prose. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B178">
   <bib> Rees, Thomas R. The Technique of T. S. Eliot: A Study of the Orchestration of Meaning in
    Eliot's Poetry. The Hague: Mouton, 1974. Based on his dissertation, "The Orchestration of
    Meaning in T. S. Eliot's Early Poetry (1910–1922)," DA 27 (1966): 484–85A (Tulane). </bib>
   <notes> A valuable study of Eliot's technical development over his entire career. Rees analyzes
    sound patterns, meter, and rhythms, showing how Eliot ground and worked his tools of craft for
    the sake of meaning. Moreover, we see clearly how Eliot continually expanded his repertoires,
    adopted new models, and even radically altered his styles and principles throughout his working
    life, the several major styles having distinctly different prosodic (besides structural,
    imagistic, or thematic) bases. See also the condensation, </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B179">
   <bib> -----. "The Orchestration of Meaning in T. S. Eliot's Four Quartets." JAAC 28 (1969):
    63–69. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B180">
   <bib> Reese, Jack E. "Sound and Sense: The Teaching of Prosody." College English 27 (1966):
    368–73. </bib>
   <notes> A sensible suggestion that students most successfully learn the facts of prosody- -sound
    devices and metrical forms--not as rote facts but as expressive devices, which establish or
    augment the meaning of a poem, displaying the "insepara- bility of form and content." Sample
    analyses from MacLeish, Tennyson, Housman, and Shakespeare. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B181">
   <bib> Richards, I. A. "Poetic Form." Practical Criticism: A Study in Literary Judgment. New York:
    Harcourt, Brace, &amp; World, 1929; 2nd ed. 1948. pp. 225–34. </bib>
   <notes> Here Richards examines and demolishes two assumptions about form in po- etry which
    appeared in his test protocols. The first is "the notion that regularity is the merit of verse;
    Richards acknowledges the concept of metrical tension-- "departures from and returns to the
    pattern"--but dismisses it too as suggesting a distinction between the rhythm/sound of words and
    their meanings. Any such distinction he adamantly denies. The second assumption, then, is "the
    notion that poetic rhythm is independent of sense." For any who believe that sound patterns in
    verse have independent meaning or value, Richards offers his famous "dummy" of stanza XV of
    Milton's "On the Morning of Christ's Nativity." Throughout, Richards insists on the
    irrefrangibility of Form and Meaning. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B182">
   <bib> Rickert, Edith. New Methods for the Study of Literature. Chicago: University of Chicago
    Press, 1927. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in TLS, 26 May 1927, p. 370; by Allen Tate in New Republic 50 (1927): 281–82; in
    JEGP 27 (1928): 133–35; in Review of English Studies 4 (1928): 120–21. Chapter 5 (pp. 147–88)
    treats Rhythm, chapter 6 (pp. 189–239) Tone Pat- terns, and chapter 7 (pp. 240–59) Visual
    Devices. In retrospect it is difficult to see why Ms. Rickert should adopt such a defensive tone
    about her graphic, or schematic, techniques: they seem not so much controversial as trivial. Her
    sta- tistical analyses, too, seem tepid in comparison with the complex linguistic work of four
    decades later. See her odd graphs and charts facing p. 180, on pp. 226–27, and 256–57, then
    consider the judgment of one of her critics: "No kind of statistical study will open the
    student's mind to the poet's evaluation of human life." These methods were also applied by
    Chapin and Thomas (B31). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B183">
   <bib> Rickey, Mary Ellen. "Herbert's Technical Development." JEGP 62 (1963): 745–60. </bib>
   <notes> Since Herbert's entire corpus of English verse spans only six or seven years, about all
    that can be said of his development concerns the poems added to The Temple from 1629–33, as
    opposed to those known to have been written before 1629. In the former he increased his use of:
    (1) figurative titles, (2) multiple- stanza-form poems, (3) more subtle hieroglyphs, (4)
    contrapuntal structures, (5) longer and more elaborate stanzas, (6) controlled feminine endings,
    (7) stanza-linking, and (8) carefully modulated variation, while also decreasing his use of the
    sonnet form. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B184">
   <bib> -----. "Prosody." Utmost Art: Complexity in the Verse of George Herbert. Lexington:
    University of Kentucky Press, 1966. pp. 133–47. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in English 16 (1967): 148–49; in JEGP 66 (1967): 452–55; in Notes &amp; Queries 14
    (1967): 351–52. Discovers among all the stanzaic and rhyme virtuosity "a stability of tech-
    nique." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B185">
   <bib> Rieser, Max. Analysis of Poetic Thinking. Tr. Herbert M. Schueller. Detroit: Wayne State
    University Press, 1969. </bib>
   <notes> Includes: "Poetic Thinking as a Regressive Phenomenon: The Roots of Rhythm and
    Sound-Symbolism," pp. 15–29; "The Psychic Function of Rhythm and Rhyme," pp. 30–38;
    "Onomatopoeia as a Substitute for Things," pp. 71–82; "The Chief Characteristic of Poetic
    Sentence-Structure: The Rus- tic and the Primitive," pp. 123–35. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B186">
   <bib> Rodgers, David. "The Function of Form in Poetry." Renascence 19 (1967): 151–55, 167. </bib>
   <notes> Collects quotations from a number of sources for brief, general remarks. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B187">
   <bib> Routh, James E. The Theory of Verse. Atlanta, 1948. 156 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Apparently privately printed (typescript on wire-laid paper), this volume col- lects
    three essays previously printed (E323, D253, J258) and expands them into a full theory of
    verse-structure, ranging from the basis of rhythm in physiology (Scripture's work) to a theory
    of meter, with additional chapters on line- length, rhyme, stanza, diction, subject, free verse,
    prose rhythms, etc. Routh's theory is that verse differs from prose in (1) rhythm, (2)
    vocabulary, and (3) subject-matter. "The essential quality of verse then is the placing of
    accents at fixed intervals of time." He allows secondary stresses (promoted or suppressed for
    the meter) and metrical pauses; his scansions distinguish verse-accent (ic- tus), word-accent,
    and sense- (sentence) accent, and these are all found to co- incide in four cases out of five.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B188">
   <bib> Schiller, Daniel H. "W. B. Yeats: The Evolution of a Prosodic Style." DAI 38 (1977): 2780A
    (Columbia). </bib>
   <notes> An argument that Yeats's versification was "far more complex and far less tra- ditional"
    than has been usually assumed. Furthermore, the conventionally ac- cepted stages of Yeats's
    development (early-romantic, middle-symbolic, late- naturalistic) are not borne out by
    examination of his prosodic development, if we keep to the strict chronology of composition;
    what we find is a steady os- cillation between polarities, a dialectic of fixity and flux, which
    includes "three phases of radical looseness and ambiguity" very close to free verse. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B189">
   <bib> Schlauch, Margaret. "Linguistic Aspects of Emily Dickinson's Style." Prace filologiczne 18
    (1963): 201–15. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B190">
   <bib> Schoeck, Richard J. "Mathematics and the Language of Literary Criticism." JAAC 26 (1968):
    367–76. </bib>
   <notes> Reminds us of the long tradition of speaking of the "numbers" of poetry. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B191">
   <bib> Schulze, Fritz W. "Strophe, Vers, und Rime in Edward Taylors Meditations." Literatur und
    Sprache der Vereinigten Staaten. Ed. Hans Helmcke et al. Heidelberg: Carl Winter, 1969. pp.
    11–33. </bib>
   <notes> Taylor was a man of action, force, and power in his verse-making, as were Donne and
    Herbert; he sought force of expression, as did Shakespeare, and did not shrink from "unliterary"
    forms. He treated strict form as he did theological typology--as a basis for freedom rather than
    restraint. His metrical, stanzaic, and rhyme forms reveal in him an animal power, a literary
    barbarism. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B192">
   <bib> Scott, Fred N. "The Most Fundamental Differentia of Poetry and Prose." PMLA 19 (1904):
    250–69. </bib>
   <notes> Not imagination, emotion, insight, or even meter, but this: poetry is expres- sive, prose
    communicative. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B193">
   <bib> Sedelow, Sally Y., W. A. Sedelow, and T. Ruggles. "Some Parameters for Computational
    Stylistics: Computer Aids to the Use of Traditional Categories in Stylistic Analysis." Literary
    Data Processing Conference. Ed. Jess B. Bessinger, Jr., et al. New York: MLA, 1964. pp. 211–29. </bib>
   <notes> The section "Rhythm, Texture, and Form" on pp. 215–20 describes a pro- gram for isolating
    single characteristics which are patterned in a text while ex- cluding all others. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B194">
   <bib> Shapiro, Karl. "Prosody as the Meaning." Poetry 73 (1949): 336–51. </bib>
   <notes> Beginning with the conviction that criticism is "a variety of experience which has
    nothing in common with the art experience, and indeed may be its oppo- site," Shapiro sets out
    to show that the rhythmic organization or prosody of a poem is its "meaning." He analyzes a bit
    of Cummings and offers six conclu- sions: (1) "poetry is not language, but language sui generis
    which can be under- stood, paraphrased, or translated only as poetry"; (2) "a linguistic sense
    is car- ried over to a poem from prose and plays a minor part in the workings of the poem"; (3)
    "the poet thinks as poet not as thinker"; (4) "the translation of a poem is a near
    impossibility"; (5) "paraphrase is a total impossibility"; and (6) "rhythm is perhaps closer or
    as close to 'meaning' in poetry as linguistic sense." Would anyone mistake this for formalist
    criticism? </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B195">
   <bib> Shapiro, Karl, and Robert Beum. A Prosody Handbook. New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1965. 214
    pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in Michigan Quarterly Review 6 (1967): 136. A reviewer will be met with patient
    forbearance when he announces that a book, which he publicly owns first fired his passion for a
    subject he made his career, is an excellent book, an inimitable book, durable, and chock-full of
    in- sights, good sense, taste and discrimination, wide reading . . . . et cetera. Such a
    response will make it all the harder for him to be heard, and hence for the merits of a very
    solid book to be known. So too will the price of the book, which in this case is unreasonable,
    and prohibits wider undergraduate use of the best handbook of verseforms in print. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B196">
   <bib> Shelley, Percy Bysshe. A Defence of Poetry [1821]. In Essays, Letters from Abroad,
    Translations and Fragments. Ed. Mary Shelley. London, 1840; rpt in Shelley's Critical Prose. Ed.
    Bruce R. McElderry, Jr. Lincoln, Nebraska: University of Nebraska Press, 1967. </bib>
   <notes> Paragraphs 5–8 of Part I give us some glimpses of Shelley's views on sound and meter, as
    well as his constant reminder that "the popular division into prose and verse is inadmissible in
    accurate philosophy." On sound and sense he is not entirely clear ("sounds as well as thought
    have relation both between each other and towards that which they represent, and a perception of
    the order of those relations has always been found connected with a perception of the or- der of
    those relations of thoughts") or novel. On meter he is more of both: "poetry in a more
    restricted sense expresses those arrangements of language, and especially metrical language,
    which are created by that imperial faculty, whose throne is curtained within the invisible
    nature of man [the imagination]. And this springs from the nature itself of language . . . ."
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B197">
   <bib> Shephard, Esther. "An Inquiry into Whitman's Method of Turning Prose into Poetry." MLQ 14
    (1953): 43–59. </bib>
   <notes> The method has interesting implications; Pope used it as well. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B198">
   <bib> Siegel, Eli. "Impediment in Poetry." University of Kansas City Review 20 (1954): 253–57. </bib>
   <notes> "How freedom and obstruction meet in lines of poetry is one of the richest technical
    questions in the art . . . . When impediment in poetry is not care- fully, wholly, boldly, even
    willingly seen, there can be no successfully artistic dealing with it . . . . The more it is
    poetry, the more the triumph and the im- pediment merge." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B199">
   <bib> Simonetti, Francis A. "A Study of the Poetic Technique of Theodore Roethke: The Lost Son
    and Other Poems." DAI 33 (1972): 765A (Ball State). </bib>
   <notes> Chapter 4 discusses general matters of versification. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B200">
   <bib> Sinclair, J. M. "When Is a Poem Like a Sunset?" Review of English Literature 6 (1965):
    76–91. </bib>
   <notes> "When it is composed in an oral tradition." Recognizing oral transmission of poetry as
    radically different from transmission of written texts, Sinclair devises an ingenious informal
    experiment in transmission and then analyzes the results. He postulates three general categories
    or types of changes in transmission: "analogy, the influence of the immediate language
    environment; revision, the influence of the modern speaker's habits of language; and
    approximation, the in- fluence of his inexact memory for detail." Intriguing. See also TLS, 3
    June 1965, p. 455, and 10 June, p. 475. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B201">
   <bib> Sitwell, Edith. "Notes on Shakespeare." A Poet's Notebook. London: Macmillan, 1944. pp.
    104–47. </bib>
   <notes> A plentitude of examples showing rhythmic and sound patterns in the verse which produce
    an immense variety of effects. Notice also the collection of quotations (Chapter 3), "Notes on
    Technical Matters," pp. 18–31. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B202">
   <bib> Smith, Barbara Herrnstein. Poetic Closure: A Study of How Poems End. Chicago: University of
    Chicago Press, 1968. </bib>
   <notes> The second chapter of this brilliant study treats closure and the formal struc- ture of
    sonnets, strict stanzaic forms, couplets, blank verse, and free verse. In contrast to what we
    might otherwise have expected, Smith shows that no for- mal structure per se entails closure:
    "there is no formal principle which in itself can prevent a poem from continuing indefinitely."
    Structural repetition, stan- zaic forms, meter, and rhyme may produce effects which can be
    exploited by the poet to achieve closure, but they do not themselves necessitate it. Sonnet
    structure will round off one sonnet but does not prohibit a series of sonnets, for example. The
    couplet at the end of the Shakespearean Sonnet enhances closure by the strategy of "terminal
    modification," but if the thematic structure is weak no formal structure can be successful
    alone. In couplet verse the cou- plet has the status of a single formal unit and is therefore
    equivalent to all the other devices of systematic repetition; in itself its closural resources
    are very limited. Blank verse achieves closure best by abandoning blank verse, as at the end of
    the scenes in Shakespeare. Free verse, perhaps surprisingly, offers re- sources fully comparable
    to those in the other modes. In general, as the con- straints of formal structure weaken,
    thematic material must take on a greater burden in effecting closure. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B203">
   <bib> Smith, Chard Powers. Patterns and Variation in Poetry. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons,
    1932. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: By Croll in MLN 49 (1934): 54–55; in TLS, 9 February 1933, p. 81 (leading article);
    in Poetry 42 (1933): 54–56. Very unjustly neglected, probably because of a very effusive style,
    but well worth an afternoon's inquiry. The great virtue of the book is that underneath
    considerable talk of "organic rhythms," "rhythm and imagination the two es- sentials," and the
    like, Smith fixes on the abstract notion of pattern as the crux of verse-structure. He
    recognizes the antinomian relation of repetition and variation, and he makes a strong effort to
    systematize all the various prosodic elements as varieties of a single complex poetic pattern.
    The treatment of me- ter is especially good: Smith recognizes the tension between "prose stress"
    and "metrical accent" [ictus] very clearly and derives therefrom five varieties of verse in
    English: (1) verse in which accent and stress virtually coincide, (2) verse where stresses fall
    evenly on certain of the accents, (3) faint distortion of the meter by the stress, (4)
    independent stress pattern, and (5) independent prose movement. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B204">
   <bib> Smith, I. Gregory. "Laws of Poetry." Contemporary Review 114 (1918): 312–16. </bib>
   <notes> Rambles from its subject, which is the rules and law underlying phenomena. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B205">
   <bib> Sobel, Emilie. "Rhythm, Sound, and Imagery in the Poetry of Gerard Manley Hopkins." In
    Between Reality and Fantasy: Transitional Objects and Phenomena. Ed. Simon A. Grolnick and L.
    Barkin. New York: Aronson, 1978. pp. 425–45. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B206">
   <bib> Spingarn, Lawrence P. "Poetry and Prose: Verse as a Literary Catalyst." Queen's Quarterly
    66 (1959): 441–48. </bib>
   <notes> Suggests, by opening a great chest of instances, examples, and literary lore, that
    "poetry" and "prose" are by no means polar opposites but in fact interpermeate each other often.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B207">
   <bib> Steger, Cecelia H. "Phonological Patterning and Syntactic Structure in the Literary
    Criticism for Fifteen Poems by Emily Dickinson." Diss., New York University, 1977. </bib>
   <notes> Whether or not this thesis indirectly or directly illuminates these patterns in the poems
    themselves I do not know. Is there more patterning in the criticism than in the poetry? </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B208">
   <bib> Stevenson, Robert Louis. "On Style in Literature: Its Technical Elements." Contemporary
    Review 47 (1885): 548–61; rpt in his Essays in the Art of Writing. London: Chatto &amp; Windus,
    1905, 1917. </bib>
   <notes> Emphasizes that "the motive and end of any art whatever is to make a pat- tern." Pattern,
    web, is the desideratum for all art. Hence, "all that we have a right to ask of any prosody is,
    that it shall lay down a pattern for the writer." Result: "added difficulty, added beauty."
    Stevenson has a keen perception of the counterpoint of rhythm on meter, the great virtue of
    variety, and the sub- tle but important sound of the language. The elements of style:
    word-choice, pattern, rhythmic variety in phrasing, and melodious sound-patterns. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B209">
   <bib> Sutherland, James. The Medium of Poetry. London: The Hogarth Press, 1934. 168 pp. Rev: in
    MLR 30 (1935): 95–96. </bib>
   <notes> These discursive observations on the poet's handling of his matter and modes employ the
    term "medium" in a relatively broad sense. But see chapters 4 and 6 on form. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B210">
   <bib> Swart, J[acobus]. "Sackville's Poetic Technique." Thomas Sackville: A Study in
    Sixteenth-Century Poetry. Groningen: J. B. Wolters, 1949. pp. 99–120. </bib>
   <notes> The sixth chapter treats irregularities in meter, use of monosyllables and disyl- lables,
    rabbate, grammar, and archaisms. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B211">
   <bib> Thorpe, Clarence D. "Some Notes on the Differentiae of Prose and Poetry, with Special
    Reference to the Theory of Coleridge." Papers of the Michigan Academy of Sciences, Arts, and
    Letters 14 (1930): 567–600. </bib>
   <notes> Most directly a very long inquiry into Coleridge's notion that the fundamental
    differentia of poetry and prose is not external form but internal mental state, i.e., passion.
    But the essay ranges into the fields of the twentieth century as well in search of specimens.
    Meter is discussed on pp. 580–83. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B212">
   <bib> Tillotson, Geoffrey. "Pope and the Common Reader." Sewanee Review 66 (1958): 44–78. </bib>
   <notes> Traces Pope's efforts (and achievements) at writing that sort of verse which speaks from
    the very center of common English usage--the easy, familiar use of the mother tongue that is
    instinct in us all. Pope's efforts lay mainly in dic- tion (varying registers to suit the
    subject), syntax (naturalness of word-order), meter (which allowed both conciseness and
    complexity), and rhyme (allowing latitude within the rule). For his craft Pope's especial skills
    were inventiveness and imagination. A long essay both for and about the general reader. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B213">
   <bib> Trisolini, Anthony G. "An Analysis of the Structure of Hart Crane's The Bridge." DA 20
    (1959): 2441A (Northwestern). </bib>
   <notes> "Structure" here includes sound-stratum, on which level a miming or mirror- ing of theme
    can be perceived: the verse is relatively smooth when the pro- tagonist is in a balanced state
    of mind but rougher when he is disturbed. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B214">
   <bib> Turco, Lewis. Poetry: An Introduction Through Writing. Reston, Virginia: Reston Publishing
    Co., 1973. </bib>
   <notes> The title is deceptive: the book is actually a typology of Prosodies (at least nine, by
    my count), Schemes, Tropes and Figures, and Genres. Examples, ex- ercises, Bibliography, and
    Index. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B215">
   <bib> Untermeyer, Louis. The Forms of Poetry: A Pocket Dictionary of Verse. 2nd ed. New York:
    Harcourt, Brace &amp; World, 1926. 173 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A well-known handbook, arranged alphabetically. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B216">
   <bib> V., A. W. "Voice and Verse." Notes &amp; Queries 184 (1943): 344. </bib>
   <notes> In search of a distinctive prosodic voice for every poet. There is an additional note at
    185 (1943): 20–21, and a response by "Psychologist" at 185 (1943): 28, who tries to make the
    original suggestion look ludicrous, ludicrously. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B217">
   <bib> Van Doorn, Willem. "Mainly about the Prose-Poem." English Studies 3 (1921): </bib>
   <notes> 129–37. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B218">
   <bib> Viereck, Peter. "Strict Form in Poetry: Would Jacob Wrestle With a Flabby Angel?" Critical
    Inquiry 5 (1978): 203–22. </bib>
   <notes> Wired prose by a practicing poet on the palimpsest of the "non-word language of rhythm"
    underneath the verbal/syntactic/semantic layer of language. Heav- ily emphasized also are the
    biological and psychological correlates of rhythm: "rhythm and probably also rhyme are not
    luxury but . . . our very anatomy." Proposes "crisscross rhyme"--the sound ending one line and
    beginning the next or another close by. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B219">
   <bib> Vogel, Joseph F. Dante Gabriel Rossetti's Versecraft. University of Florida Monographs,
    Humanities, no. 34. Gainesville: University of Florida Press, 1971. Based on his dissertation,
    "Studies of Form and Meaning in the Poetry of D. G. Rossetti," at Florida in 1965. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in South Atlantic Bulletin 37 (1972): 74–76; in Victorian Studies 16 (1972): 235–37;
    in English Language Notes 10 (1972): 60–61. A patient, non-tendentious study of Rossetti's
    handling of metrical, stanzaic, and sonal structures, with a separate chapter on "The Blessed
    Damozel." Ros- setti was prosodically conservative, both in theory and practice, and Vogel
    sketches out a case that Rossetti's versecraft was, if not more virtuoso than Swinburne's, at
    least more subtly diverse. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B220">
   <bib> Von Hallberg, Robert. Charles Olson: The Scholar's Art. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard
    University Press, 1978. Based on his dissertation at Stanford University in 1975. </bib>
   <notes> Passim. Chapter 5 (pp. 170–204) offers the most sustained treatment of pro- sodic
    matters, especially Olson's stylistic development, but notice also the sec- tion on "Process
    Poems: Prosody and Syntax" in Chapter 2 (pp. 65–73) and the one on "Discursive Form" (pp.
    141–50) in Chapter 4. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B221">
   <bib> Waaub, Jean-Marie. "A Few Notes on Poetic Technique." Revue des langues vivantes 27 (1961):
    83–116. </bib>
   <notes> These very extensive "notes" on metrical technique are careful, methodical, and thorough:
    from a set of disputed scansions the author derives most of the principles of modern metrics,
    such as the distinction between meter and rhythm, the Relative Stress Principle (not all the
    stresses in a line are equally stressed, nor are the unstressed equally unstressed--what counts
    is relative con- tiguous values), a double-tiered scansion system (two degrees of metrical
    ictus, five degrees of rhythmical stress), varieties of pauses ("rests," "breaks," "links"), the
    effects of word-length on tempo in the line, degrees of enjambment, sonal texturing, and the
    effects of such texturing (quantity, density, pattern) on tempo also. All of this exemplified in
    essentially only one Henry Treece poem. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B222">
   <bib> Wain, John. "On the Breaking of Forms." Encounter 45 (1975): 49–56. </bib>
   <notes> Remarks on the uses and dangers of form in poetry, especially "mimetic" form. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B223">
   <bib> Wharton, Thomas. The History of English Poetry from the Close of the Eleventh to the
    Commencement of the Eighteenth Century. 3 vols. London: J. Dodsley, 1774–81. </bib>
   <notes> Section 25 offers some valuable information on metrical treatises written by the
    graduates of Oxford in the early fifteenth century, vis à vis the term poeta laureatus.
    Otherwise there are useful and interesting remarks on versification scattered abroad, passim.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B224">
   <bib> Watkins, W. B. C. "The Kingdom of Our Language." Hudson Review 2 (1949): 343–76. </bib>
   <notes> A thoroughgoing defense of Spenser's technical craft, with an extended com- parison to
    Shakespeare. Cf. B13. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B225">
   <bib> Wellek, René, and Austin Warren. "Euphony, Rhythm, and Metre." Theory of Literature. New
    York: Harcourt, Brace &amp; World, 1949; 3rd rev. ed. 1963. pp. 158–73; rpt in Gross (A23), pp.
    21–41. </bib>
   <notes> This chapter amply contributes to the lucidity of the whole. Wellek distin- guishes at
    once between performance and pattern (metrics can be based on the latter), (pure) sound and
    meaning ("there is no 'musical' verse without some general conception of its meaning"), and
    inherent vs. relational features of sound (the former form the substance of euphonics, the
    latter of rhythmics and met- rics). Rhyme is anatomized to show the variety of possible
    approaches, and mi- metic (onomatopoeic) sound--discussed at some length--is divided into three
    related problems: "actual imitation of physical sounds," "elaborate sound- painting," and "sound
    symbolism." Theories of rhythm may be classed into those that require some notion of periodicity
    au fond and those broader ones which do not. Worse, "the very foundations and main criteria of
    metrics are still uncertain, and there is an astonishing amount of loose thinking and con- fused
    or shifting terminology even in standard treatises." The types of metrical analysis are the
    graphic (longs and shorts; simply inapplicable), the musical (merely records a performance), and
    the acoustic (objective laboratory analysis of sound; ignores meaning and subjective
    perception). Insisting that meaning is indispensable to metrical theory, Wellek approves of the
    statistical methods and radical assumptions of the Russian Formalists: "The fundamental unity of
    rhythm is, then, not the foot but the whole line . . . . Verse is conceived as an elaborate
    contrapuntal pattern between the superimposed metre and the ordi- nary rhythm of speech."
    Altogether, the emphasis in this account falls on the primacy of meaning in versification
    theory. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B226">
   <bib> Welsh, Andrew. "Melos and Opsis." DAI 31 (1970): 2407A (Pittsburgh). 271 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Elaborating Northrop Frye's distinction between these two fundamental modes, the aural
    and the visual imaginations, Welsh inquires into their primitive origins, finding there eight
    roots of lyric: riddle, emblem, image, vortex, ideo- gram, charm, chant, and rhythm. It is this
    last (Chapter 9) which interests us: Welsh discusses stress rhythms in Skelton and Wyatt. See
    also the discussion of rhyme on pp. 226–32, and of stress-rhythms in Beowulf and later, pp.
    232–49. B227 In Welsh's subsequent book based on this dissertation, Roots of Lyric (Prince- ton:
    Princeton University Press, 1978), the chapter on Rhythm (pp. 190–242) is completely revamped,
    the section on Skelton being expanded, augmented by a following discussion of Wyatt's meter, and
    prefaced by a long commen- tary on the development of the pentameter line, for which material
    Welsh draws heavily upon Thompson (E91). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B228">
   <bib> Werner, W. L. "Poe's Theories and Practice in Poetic Technique." American Literature 2
    (1930): 157–65. </bib>
   <notes> Poe was diligent about sound-patterns, careless about his rhymes, inordinately
    conservative in meter, modern and sensible about diction and syntax, and ir- regular about
    stanza-form. Werner concludes that Poe had a good ear for sound and rhythm but lacked the
    requisite discipline (or skill?) to confine himself to strict forms. Critique by Allen (G2).
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B229">
   <bib> Whitehall, Harold. "From Linguistics to Poetry." Frye (A15), pp. 134–46. </bib>
   <notes> Brief illustration of the valuable--if not indispensable--assistance linguistics can lend
    to poetic criticism of Sound Patterns (e.g., the C-V-C description of syl- lables), Rhyme
    (vis-à-vis the Great Vowel Shift), Metrics (isochronic, iso- accentual, isosyllabic, and
    isosyntactic systems), and Syntax. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B230">
   <bib> Wilbur, Richard. "The Bottles Become New, Too." Quarterly Review of Literature 7 (1953):
    186–89. </bib>
   <notes> In the fascinating symposium on "Experimental and Formal Verse." Wilbur produces a
    brilliant defense of the uses and virtues of Form. "No poetry," he thinks, "can have any
    strength unless it continually bashes itself against the re- ality of things." No "poems made
    out of poetry." And how can the abstract, gesturing form reproduce the reality? How can it be
    that "paradoxically it is respect for reality which makes a necessity of form"? How can the
    poet's com- bat with form enhance his expression? By difficulty. "In each art the difficulty of
    the form is a substitute for the difficulty of direct apprehension and expression of the
    object." A sort of distraction, then, or subtler flank attack. Take rhyme, for example: "the
    presence of potential rhymes sets the imagination working," providing unexpected possibilities
    and directions to pursue. Or in meter: surely the poet using meters and stanzas to get at the
    Real will prefer the "for- midably meaningless" to the "alien." By such means does the poet find
    his freedoms in restraint. Cf. B16 and E1549. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B231">
   <bib> Williams, Juanita S. Prosody as Ritual; an Experiment. Nashville, Tenn., 1962; Lexington:
    University of Kentucky Press, 1963. 124 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Not a critical study but original poetry submitted as her Master's Thesis at Vanderbilt.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B232">
   <bib> Willige, Eckhart. "Formal Devices in Robert Frost's Short Poems." Georgia Review 15 (1961):
    324–30. </bib>
   <notes> Elementary analysis of meter, rhyme-patterns, and syntax. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B233">
   <bib> Wimsatt, W. K., Jr. "In Search of Verbal Mimesis (Supplement to 'Laokoön: An Oracle
    Reconsulted')." Yale French Studies 52 (1975): 229–48; rpt in his Day of the Leopards. New
    Haven: Yale University Press, 1976. pp. 57–73. </bib>
   <notes> A seminal essay: Wimsatt here confronts directly the nature of the verbal me- dium itself
    in its effort to mime (express, represent) reality, as opposed to its other function--to refer
    to the external world. Distinguishing between the gra- phemic and phonetic forms of language,
    Wimsatt collects eight types of verbal iconicity, together with luminous examples. The schema
    deployed here is pro- vocative, and more than worthy of book-length treatment. The issue raised
    is very likely the most crucial one in all of poetics. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B234">
   <bib> -----. "Verbal Style: Logical and Counterlogical." PMLA 65 (1950): 5–20; rpt in his The
    Verbal Icon: Studies in the Meaning of Poetry. Lexington: University of Kentucky Press, 1954;
    rpt London: Methuen, 1970. pp. 201–17. </bib>
   <notes> Taking his cue from Fowler's Modern English Usage, Wimsatt notes the figures of speech
    available in prose and their concomitant faults if overused. In poetry, the "figures" are meter,
    rhyme, alliteration, etc., and even though we do not have good terms for the faults of taking
    them to excess, still they are, Wimsatt argues, distinctly meaningful verbal signs, signs which
    construct a matrix of meaning that is "counterlogical." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B235">
   <bib> Winter, D. "Verse and Prose." JEGP 5 (1903–5): 271–86. </bib>
   <notes> The common (hence confused) usage of the terms "Poetry" and "Prose" fails to distinguish
    between essences and media; in regard to the former, the proper antithesis is Poetry vs.
    Non-poetry, while for the latter the terms should be Verse vs. Prose. Can the formal devices of
    Verse produce effects not obtainable in Prose? No. They can produce other effects, but not
    necessarily better ones. Most of the world's masterpieces are writ in verse simply on account of
    con- vention (tradition). Indeed, prose is the more difficult medium because the rules in
    versifying are aids to composition. Prose allows greater freedom, naturalness, and individuation
    of rhythms. And "nearly all versification is to some extent a process of fitting thoughts to a
    form of expression, instead of fitting the expression in every detail to the thought." A
    wonderfully refreshing, sober, sensible piece of heresy. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B236">
   <bib> Wion, Philip K. "The Poetic Styles of Edmund Spenser." DA 29 (1968): 919A (Yale). </bib>
   <notes> Includes a chapter on diction and one on meter and syntax. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B237">
   <bib> Witkiewicz, S. I. "The Theory of Pure Form in Poetry." Polish Perspectives 20 (1977):
    38–40. </bib>
   <notes> Ravings. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B238">
   <bib> "Words Connected with the Technique of Poetry." Word Study 6, 1 (1930): 1–2. Etymologies of
    poetry, meter, rhythm, etc. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B239">
   <bib> Youngblood, Sarah Helen. "W. B. Yeats: The Mature Style." DA 19 (1959): 1764A (Oklahoma). </bib>
   <notes> Chapters on diction, imagery, versification, syntax, and structure. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="B240">
   <bib> Zillman, Lawrence John. The Elements of English Verse: A Manual and Workbook for Students
    of Poetry and Verse Writing. New York: Macmillan, 1935. 148 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A general handbook, the most interesting feature of which is a schematic analysis-sheet
    for noting technical features of poems. Allows three degrees of stress ("accented,
    half-accented, unaccented") and six metrical feet--the com- mon four as well as spondaic and
    pyrrhic for variation. Chapter 5 on "Rhyth- mical Effects" is good on metrical treatment of
    syllables. </notes>
  </item>
  </div>
 </section>
 </chapter>
</bibliography>
