<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="THE POEM: ELEMENTS AND STRUCTURES">
        <section title="Sound">
            <div title="Pronunciation">
                <item id="C1">
                    <bib> Bartling, Gustav. Rhymes of English Poets of the XIXth Century. Diss.,
                        Rostock, 1874. 26 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>So far as I know an untapped cask of examples of rhymes which earlier
                        English poets thought acceptable but which seem unnatural to us now, after
                        changes in pronunciation. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C2">
                    <bib> Bronstein, Arthur J. "The Vowels and Diphthongs of the Nineteenth
                        Century." Speech Monographs 16 (1949): 227-42. </bib>
                    <notes> Based on his dissertation at New York University in 1948. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C3">
                    <bib> Cercignani, Fausto. Shakespeare's Works and Elizabethan Pronunciation.
                        London: Oxford University Press, 1980. 448 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Treats not only pronunciation and spelling but also meter, rhyme, and
                        puns. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C4">
                    <bib> Davies, Constance. English Pronunciation from the Fifteenth to the
                        Eighteenth Century. London: J. M. Dent, 1934. </bib>
                    <notes> Rev.: in Review of English Studies 12 (1936): 372-74; in TLS, 23 May
                        1935, p. 330. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C5">
                    <bib> DeBoer, Kathryn B. "The Rhymes of Philip Freneau: A Reflection of
                        Eighteenth- Century American Pronunciation." Speech Monographs 33 (1966):
                        50-56. </bib>
                    <notes/>
                </item>


                <item id="C6">
                    <bib> Dierberger, Joseph. John Drydens Reime: Ein Beitrag zur Geschichte der
                        englischen Tonvokale. Diss., Freiburg, 1895. 115 pp. </bib>
                    <notes/>
                </item>


                <item id="C7">
                    <bib> Dobson, E. J. English Pronunciation 1500-1700. 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon
                        Press, 1957; 2nd ed. 1968. 1010 pp. + Bibliography, Appendices. Rev: in MLN
                        74 (1959): 356-63; in Shakespeare Quarterly 11 (1960): 488-89. </bib>
                    <notes> by Kökeritz in Language 37 (1961): 150-61; in MLR 53 (1958): 228-31; in
                        English Studies 39 (1958): 138-41; in Review of English Studies n.s. 9
                        (1958): 303-12; in TLS, 24 May 1957, p. 324; in Essays in Criticism 8
                        (1958): 422-28; in Anglia 76 (1958): 443-48; in American Speech 33 (1958):
                        111-15. The standard authority. The first volume surveys the work of the
                        Eng- lish orthoepists and phoneticians between 1500 and 1700 and is valuable
                        for cross-checking evidence of spelling or pronunciation from poems against
                        the authorities of the period (note the prefatory principles of
                        transliteration). Vol- ume 2 provides a systematic Phonology. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C8">
                    <bib> -----. "Milton's Pronunciation." Language and Style in Milton. Ed. Ronald
                        D. Emma and John T. Shawcross. New York: Frederick Ungar, 1967. pp. 154-92. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C9">
                    <bib> Ellis, Alexander J. On Early English Pronunciation, with Special Reference
                        to Shakespeare and Chaucer. 5 vols. Early English Text Society, Extra
                        Series, nos. 2, 7, 14, 23, and 55. London: Trüubner, 1869-89. Published
                        jointly by the EETS, the Chaucer Society, and the Philological Society. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C10">
                    <bib> Gabrielson, Arvid. Edward Bysshe's Dictionary of Rhymes as a Source of
                        Information on Early Modern English Pronunciation. Uppsala and Stockholm:
                        Almqvist &amp; Wiksells, 1930; 87 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Rev: in Archiv 160 (1931): 262-63; in MLR 27 (1932): 99-101; in English
                        Studies 16 (1934): 226-28. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C11">
                    <bib> -----. Rime as a Criterion of the Pronunciation of Spencer, Pope, Byron,
                        and Swinburne; a Contribution to the History of the Present English Stressed
                        Vowels. Uppsala: Almqvist &amp; Wiksells, 1909. 211 pp. </bib>
                    <notes/>
                </item>


                <item id="C12">
                    <bib> Haase, Gladys D. "Spencer's Orthography: An Examination of a Poet's Use of
                        the Variant Pronunciations of Elizabethan English." Diss., Columbia
                        University, 1952. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C13">
                    <bib> Hanley, Miles L. Index to Rimes in American and English Poetry, 1500-1900.
                        Madison, Wis.: Microcard Foundation, 1959. </bib>
                    <notes> The set of microcards simply reproduces a card-file (over 100,000 cards)
                        of rimes drawn from a large number of miscellanies and anthologies; no
                        analysis or synthesis. The work was unfinished at the author's death.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C14">
                    <bib> Hultzen, Lee S. "Seventeenth Century Intonation." American Speech 14
                        (1939): 39- 43. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C15">
                    <bib> Jones, Daniel. The Pronunciation of English. Cambridge: Cambridge
                        University Press, 1909; 2nd ed. 1924; 4th ed. revised and enlarged, 1956. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C16">
                    <bib> Kökeritz, Helge. Mather Flint on Early Eighteenth-Century En-glish
                        Pronunciation. Uppsala: Almqvist &amp; Wiksells, 1944. 189 pp. </bib>
                    <notes/>
                </item>


                <item id="C17">
                    <bib> -----. Shakespeare's Pronunciation. New Haven: Yale University Press,
                        1953. </bib>
                    <notes> Rev: in Shakespeare Quarterly 5 (1933): 413-15; by Hallet Smith in Yale
                        Review 43 (1953): 121-25; in College English 16 (1954-55): 198-99; in MLR 49
                        (1954): 367-68; by A. A. Hill in Language 29 (1953): 549-61; by H. Whitehall
                        in Kenyon Review 16 (1954): 322-28; in South Atlantic Quarterly 52 (1953):
                        273; in JEGP 54 (1955): 418-21; in MP 52 (1955): 275-76; in Review of
                        English Studies n.s. 6 (1955): 404-14; in English Studies 36 (1955): 78-83;
                        in Anglia 74 (1956): 260-65; in Archiv 193 (1956):56; in Études Anglaises 9
                        (1956): 34-38. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C18">
                    <bib> Lange, Alexander F. "The Vowel Signs and Sounds in Tottel's Miscellany."
                        Diss., University of Michigan, 1892. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C19">
                    <bib> Matthews, William. "English Pronunciation and Shorthand in the Early
                        Modern Period." University of California Publications in English 9 (1943):
                        135-214. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C20">
                    <bib> Moore, Samuel. Historical Outlines of English Sounds and Inflections.
                        Revised by Albert H. Marckwardt. Ann Arbor: G Wahr, 1951, 1960. (Originally
                        published as Historical Outlines of English Phonology and Middle English
                        Grammar. Ann Arbor: G. Wahr, 1919, 1925.) </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C21">
                    <bib> Scholl, Evelyn H. "New Light on Seventeenth Century Pronunciation from the
                        English School of Lutenist Song Writers." PMLA 59 (1944): 398-445. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C22">
                    <bib> Söderholm, Torbjörn. The End-Rhymes of Marvell, Cowley, Cra-shaw,
                        Lovelace, and Vaughn: A Study of Their Reflection of the Pronunciation of
                        Stressed Vowels and Diphthongs in the Mid-Seventeenth Century. Abo, Finland:
                        Abo Akademi, 1970. Rev. in Language 50 (1974): 742-48; in English Studies 56
                        (1975): 513-18. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C23">
                    <bib> Sturzen-Becker, Astrid. "Some Notes on English Pronunciation about 1800."
                        Studia Neophilologica 14 (1942): 301-30. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C24">
                    <bib> Sweet, Henry. A History of English Sounds: from the Earliest Period.
                        London: Trübner, 1874; 2nd ed. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1888. </bib>
                    <notes> Rpt from the Transactions of the Philological Society, 1873-74, pp.
                        461-623. See also an abstract of his paper on </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C25">
                    <bib> "Quantity and Sentence-Stress in English" in the Transactions for 1880,
                        Abstracts of Proceedings, March 19, pp. 26-27. </bib>
                    <notes> A classic work in historical phonology. The prosodist will be interested
                        in the sections on Stress and Quantity in Old, Middle, and Modern
                        English--(respec- tively) sections, 356-411, 609-40, and 939-44. Précis:
                        "But in practice it is im- possible fully to harmonize the natural quantity
                        and stress of a language with the artificial quantity and stress of metre;
                        one or the other must go to the wall." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C26">
                    <bib> Venezky, R. L. "A Study of English Spelling-to-Sound Correspondences on
                        Historical Principles." DA 26 (1966): 3942A (Stanford). </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C27">
                    <bib> Viétor, Wilhelm. Shakespeare's Pronunciation. 2 vols. Vol. 1: A
                        Shakespeare Phonology, with a Rime-Index to the poems as a pronouncing
                        vocabulary. Vol. 2: A Shakespeare Reader in the old spelling and with a
                        phonetic transcription. Marburg: Elwert, 1906; rpt (vol. 1 only) New York:
                        F. Ungar, 1963. </bib>
                    <notes> Rev: in MLR 2 (1907): 74-77; in Shakespeare Jahrbuch 43 (1907): 263-69.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C28">
                    <bib> Wijk, Axel. Rules of Pronunciation for the English Language: An Account of
                        the Relationship Between English Spelling and Pronunciation. London: Oxford
                        University Press, 1966. 160 pp. </bib>
                    <notes/>
                </item>


                <item id="C29">
                    <bib> Withington, Robert. "Elizabethan Pronunciation." Notes &amp; Queries 164
                        (1933): 102-3. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C30">
                    <bib> -----. "Some Shakespearean Rhymes." Notes and Queries 158 (1930): 457-59. </bib>
                    <notes> As evidence for pronunciation. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C31">
                    <bib> Zachrisson, Robert E. English Pronunciation at Shakespeare's Time as
                        Taught by William Bullokar. Uppsala and Leipzig: Almqvist &amp; Wiksells,
                        1927. </bib>
                    <notes> Rev: in English Studies 18 (1936): 39-43. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C32">
                    <bib> -----. Pronunciation of English Vowels 1400-1700. Göteborg, 1913; rpt New
                        York: AMS Press, 1971. 232 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>See also: C205, C214, C321, K8-9, K49, K77, K126, K141, K155, K201, K256,
                        K385, K401. </notes>
                </item>
            </div>
            <div title="GENERAL STUDIES">


                <item id="C33">
                    <bib> Axelrod, Joseph. "Cummings and Phonetics." Poetry 65 (1944): 88-94. </bib>
                    <notes> The visual deployment of type in the eighth poem of 1 x 1 is a movement
                        not toward graphic design, as many would have it, but a strategic evocation
                        of sound patterns themselves. Cummings never relinquished a "direct concern
                        with sound." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C34">
                    <bib> Beardsley, Monroe, C. "Style: Semantic and Phonetic." In his Aesthetics:
                        Problems in the Philosophy of Criticism. New York: Harcourt, Brace &amp;
                        World, 1958. pp. </bib>
                    <notes>220-37, 254-59. This fourteenth section of the book includes five
                        subsections: (1) Style as Detail of Meaning (2) Qualities of Style (3) The
                        Sound of Poetry (4) Verse (5) Sound and Sense. In the third of these,
                        Beardsley provides a schematization of structural rela- tionships in the
                        sound-stratum of a poem which is more cogent than anything else I have seen:
                        3 Structure----------------------Sound | | 6 | 2 1 | 5 | |
                        Texture----------------------Meaning 4 There are, then, six relations, which
                        Beardsley groups as Sound Quality (tim- bre), Sound Similarity (sonal
                        mimesis or "homophony"), and Sound Pattern (meter). The account which he
                        gives of meter is the traditional one also ar- ticulated in his seminal
                        essay written with Wimsatt (E700). "A stressed syllable introduces a kind of
                        phonetic punctuation in the flow of speech, and breaks up that flow into
                        groups, or feet." Verse consists of two independant organization
                        systems--meter and line. The function of line-division lies in "dividing up
                        the flow of prose into rhythmic sections, thereby introducing new and
                        sometimes very significant emphases and suggestions--slowing it down in
                        smaller units," though divisions on the page are not real unless they
                        "correspond in some way to differences that can be performed and heard."
                        Meter, however, is "neither necessary nor sufficient" to verse. On sonal
                        mimesis Beardsley is willing, cautiously, to go as far as Ran- som,
                        asserting that poetic language seems to aspire to a condition of total mi-
                        mesis, wherein the sound of the words would "dramatize and enact" their
                        meaning. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C35">
                    <bib> Berry, Francis. Poetry and the Physical Voice. New York: Oxford University
                        Press, 1962. </bib>
                    <notes> Rev: in TLS, 16 February, 1962, p. 104; in Critical Quarterly 4 (1962):
                        265-67; in Quarterly Journal of Speech 50 (1964): 92. From his earlier study
                        of poetic Grammar, Berry extends his horizons to the wider significance of
                        the concept of voice in poetry. We know that every man alive has a
                        distinctive voice, in terms of pitch, duration, volume, timbre, into-
                        nation, overtones, register, reverberation, and echo. We know that a man's
                        voice may change over time. We know that poets are supremely sensitive to
                        the textures of sound. And in the case of some poets we have recorded infor-
                        mation--written or taped--on the nature of their physical speech. We may as-
                        sume that a poet's intonational idiolect will be manifested in his lines,
                        when he is not writing under a persona. Hence, the poet's physical voice
                        ought to be recoverable from his surviving poetry. What a pity it is that
                        Berry did not con- sider the now largely forgotten speculations of Eduard
                        Sievers on precisely this point, intonational idiolects, which he termed
                        schallanalyse. </notes>
                </item>



                <item id="C36">
                    <bib> Berry's thesis was rehearsed in his earlier "The Poet's Voice: The
                        Influence of the Poet's Physical Voice on his Work and its Typical
                        Grammatical Forms." Poetics I (A16), pp. 453-61. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C37">
                    <bib> Birkhoff, George D. "The Musical Quality in Poetry." In his Aesthetic
                        Measure. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1933. pp. 170-90 </bib>
                    <notes>; rpt in his </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C38">
                    <bib> A Mathematical Theory of Aesthetics and Its Application to Poetry and
                        Music. Rice Institute Pamphlets, vol. 19, no. 3 (1931), pp. 189-342. </bib>
                    <notes> In Birkhoff's system the measure of aesthetic value is that of O order
                        to com- plexity, or M = O/C. He reviews the theories of Sylvester (E402) and
                        Poe (E315), then derives an equation for measuring sound-patterning, M = O
                        -- C aa + 2r + 2m – 2ae – 2ce = ---------------------------- C aa = number
                        of alliterations (&lt;4), -- 58 -- whereShort TOC Long TOC Help Indexes 2r =
                        number of rhymes (doubly weighted, as one sees), 2m = musical vowels, 2ae =
                        alliterative vowels 2ce = consonantal excess. The first stanza of "Kubla
                        Khan" scores a resounding .83, while, happily, E. A. Guest scores a
                        miserable .45. See also the author's </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C39">
                    <bib> -----. "The Present Status of Esthetic Measure." Scientific Monthly 46
                        (1938): 351-57. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C40">
                    <bib> Black, Michael. "The Musical Analogy." English 25 (1976): 111-34. </bib>
                    <notes> Remarkably minute explication of "the poem as it unfolds itself, phrase
                        by phrase," as "each following phrase develops, modifies, or opposes what
                        has gone before," shows that the evolving pattern of sound, qua sound,
                        bodies forth the meaning in a manner that is "something analogous to
                        thematic transformations." The changes in the metaphoric progressions, too,
                        "are felt directly as progressions of analogies with sensation: visual,
                        auditory, tactile, ki- netic." Texts: "Spelt from Sibyl's Leaves," "Marina.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C41">
                    <bib> Burke, Brother Fidelian. "A Theory for the Classification of Figures in
                        the Qualitative Structure of Sound in Verse." Thesis, Catholic University of
                        America, 1952. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C42">
                    <bib> Burke, Kenneth. "On Musicality in Verse, as Illustrated by Some Lines of
                        Coleridge." Poetry 57 (1940): 31-40; rpt in his The Philosophy of Literary
                        Form. Baton Rouge: L.S.U. Press, 1941; rev. ed. New York: Vintage, 1957,
                        1967. pp. 296-304. </bib>
                    <notes> A very sensible observation that much of the sonal texturing or
                        "musicality" of verse inheres not in overt echoes of identical sounds but
                        rather in concealed al- literations and repetitions of phonemes in the same
                        family, e.g. d n t --- th (voiced) and --- th (unvoiced) b m p --- v --- f
                        The four primary types of sonal figuration are repetition, chiasmus,
                        augmenta- tion, and diminuition. All of these are common in Coleridge, as is
                        the ablaut rhyme (heaven-haven). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C43">
                    <bib> Burklund, Carl E. "Melody in Verse." Quarterly Journal of Speech 39
                        (1953): 57-60. </bib>
                    <notes> No part of versification has been "so meagerly explained" as melody.
                        Always working very close to his examples, Burklund emphasizes the central
                        concept of repetition and identifies some patterns: ABBA, ABC/ABDC, and
                        AABA/BCCDB. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C44">
                    <bib> Chancellor, Paul. "The Music of The Waste Land." Comparative Literature
                        Studies 6 (1969): 21-32. </bib>
                    <notes> Of the several essays on the "music of ideas" in Eliot, that grand
                        nebulous subject, this one comes closest to a direct consideration of the
                        "purely aural qualities" of the poetry; see pp. 22-23. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C45">
                    <bib> Chatman, Seymour. "Linguistics, Poetics, and Interpretation: the Phonemic
                        Dimension." Quarterly Journal of Speech 43 (1957): 248-56. </bib>
                    <notes> A survey of the applications of (1) segmental and (2) suprasegmental
                        phonol- ogy to poetics. On the first level Chatman devalues the importance
                        of "sound symbolism"--i.e. specific phonemes having associated meanings--but
                        empha- sizes the neglected counterview, that "segmental sounds occur in
                        patterns and clusters which have aesthetic effects if not readily
                        discernable meanings." He also upholds the concept of "formal
                        saliency"--i.e., a sound-pattern will inten- C46 sify the lexical import of
                        a phrase regardless of whether it denotes exuberance or grief--and the
                        importance of unusual patterning of sound, e.g. "transitional probabilities"
                        of tempo in Keats. On the suprasegmental level, Trager-Smith's elucidation
                        of pitch, stress, and juncture can resolve ambiguities of interpreta- tion.
                        J. C. McLaughlin is nearly contemptuous in reply (44 (1958): 175-78),
                        accusing Chatman of demonstrating (1) causes, not effects, which are (2)
                        true but trivial. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C47">
                    <bib> Collins, Fletcher, III. "The Functions of Sound in Modern Poetry." DAI 39
                        (1978): 848A (Wisconsin). </bib>
                    <notes> Studying timbre, intonation, stress, and duration, Collins identifies
                        four func- tions--symbolic, emphatic, paralinguistic, and
                        aesthetic--concluding that the whole field is "still largely in the
                        prescientific stage." Given the high precision of some other studies in
                        comparision with this one, one sees why that is so. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C48">
                    <bib> Cook, Harold E. "The Musicality of Poetry." Bucknell Review 9 (1961):
                        303-17. </bib>
                    <notes> To speak of melody in verse is to draw on the analogy of the serial
                        ordering of pitches in music, and Cook appropriates the names of the notes
                        to indicate the melodic contours (pitch patterns) of lines of verse. Also
                        discussed at length are the other three elements of music--rhythm, harmony,
                        and timbre. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C49">
                    <bib> Cope, Jo Ann. "The Shape and Color of Sound: Auditory Organization in the
                        Poems of Dylan Thomas." Thesis, University of Texas, 1964. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C50">
                    <bib> Craig, Anne T. "Sound Magic in Poetry." Poet-Lore 29 (1918): 596-605. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C51">
                    <bib> D., T. "On the Sweetness of Versification." Blackwood's Magazine 7 (1820):
                        641-44. </bib>
                    <notes> The meaning of this old idiom of approbation the author finds to be "the
                        artful collocation of sounds," especially rhyme and assonance. But the other
                        pattern receives the whip near the end, where the author spurns "the
                        egregious and palpable affectation. . . . the disgusting habit of
                        alliteration." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C52">
                    <bib> Davison, Dennis. "Word and Sound in Yeats's 'Byzantium.'" Theoria 7
                        (1955): 111-14. </bib>
                    <notes> A critique of Masson's analysis of this poem (C89) complaining of
                        inattention to the Irish features of Yeats's voice, a methodology that
                        Masson himself criti- cizes, ignorance of the probabilities for random
                        occurence of patterns, and unreasonable conflation of sounds being analyzed.
                        Cf. Venter (C106). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C53">
                    <bib> Dougherty, Adelyn. "Structures of Sound in Wallace Stevens' 'Farewell to
                        Florida.'" Texas Studies in Literature and Language 16 (1975): 755-64. </bib>
                    <notes> Rather mechanical analysis of (1) the rhythm of the poem, using La
                        Drière's (E570) scansion system, (2) "quantitative structure" of sound, and
                        (3) "qualita- tive structure" (the patterning of sound in six sensitive
                        positions in the line, such as line-end, before the caesura, ends of rhythm
                        groups, and on stressed syllables). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C54">
                    <bib> E., A. "On Quality of Sound." TLS 19 (May 1921, p. 323. </bib>
                    <notes> Citing mellifluous examples, the author wonders aloud why certain
                        sequences of sonants are pleasing; he notes the more firmly established laws
                        for harmony and contrast of colors in music and suggests that the same
                        should be worked out for combinations of sound. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C55">
                    <bib> Eisenson, Jon, J. Fisher, and S. Sucher. "The Affective Value of English
                        Speech Sounds." Quarterly Journal of Speech 26 (1940): 589-94. </bib>
                    <notes> Forty-nine isolated sounds were rated as either Pleasant, Indifferent,
                        or Un- pleasant by student subjects in this experiment. Five sounds were
                        found to be Pleasant, two Indifferent, and two Unpleasant; after statistical
                        significance tests and after removal of the Indifferent category, fourteen
                        sounds were Pleasant, five Unpleasant. See next entry. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C56">
                    <bib> -----. "A Second Study in the Affective Value of Speech Sounds." Quarterly
                        Journal of Speech 29 (1943): 457-64. </bib>
                    <notes> Which sounds will (congenitally vs. adventitiously) deaf persons
                        consider pleasant and unpleasant? Respectively, m, n, /i/, and /ei/; zh and
                        wh. Rela- tively few sounds were judged downright disagreeable. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C57">
                    <bib> Ellis-Fermor, Una. "Some Functions of Verbal Music in Drama." Shakespeare
                        Jahrbuch 90 (1954): 37-48. </bib>
                    <notes> Observations on the general sense of ambience or mood, as well as the
                        "hints" and "impressions of character," which may be conveyed by the verbal
                        medium of Shakespearean drama considered purely as sound-stratum.
                        Exemplified in All's Well and Coriolanus. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C58">
                    <bib> Forrest, W. C. Literary Kinesthesia: The Artistic Import of Sensuous
                        Perception Concerned with the Articulatory Stratum of Literature in the
                        Light of Recent Critical Theory and Poetic Practice." DA 21 (1961): 3088A
                        (St. Louis University). </bib>
                    <notes> "The articulatory stratum of its speech stream is artistically present
                        in the total meaning of the poem." Includes a chapter on stress and metrics.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C59">
                    <bib> Franklin, V. P. "Tennyson's Use of ss in Blank Verse." MLN 14 (1899):
                        cols. 20-22. </bib>
                    <notes> Cites over fifty instances of -ss- occurring in Tennyson's poetry, in
                        direct con- tradiction to the Laureate's statement that he never allowed
                        such a repetition. But then our Homer only nodded these fifty times in 5000
                        lines. Comparative statistics for Milton and Arnold. Cf. L. L. (C69) and
                        Shewan et al. (C100). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C60">
                    <bib> Garrison, Joseph M., Jr. "'Our Singing Strength': The Texture of Voice in
                        the Poetry of Robert Frost." Frost: Centennial Essays. Ed. Jac L. Thorpe.
                        Jackson: University Press of Mississippi, 1974. pp. 340-50. </bib>
                    <notes> Insists that the sound of words rather than their visual form is crucial
                        in certain poems. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C61">
                    <bib> Givler, Robert C. "The Psycho-physiological Effect of the Elements of
                        Speech in Relation to Poetry." Psychological Monographs, vol. 19 no. 2
                        (1915): pp. 1-132. </bib>
                    <notes> This odd study attempts to measure the motor response of individuals to
                        the sounds in lines of verse, as compared with norms of nonsense syllables
                        and "transmogrified" lines of verse, via the method of measuring subtle
                        variations in finger-tapping movements on the sounds of stressed syllables
                        in iambic lines. The issue is whether or not the sounds of poetry produce
                        some greater amount of, or gestalt of, "effect" in auditors than the sum
                        total of nonpoetic sounds in equivalent "dummy" configurations. The author
                        had hopes of dis- covering a "tonal calculus." No conclusion is reached (see
                        p. 128). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C62">
                    <bib> Grimes, Dorothy G. "Phonemes, Distinctive Acoustic Features, and
                        Phonesthemes in Dylan Thomas's Collected Poems: A Chronological Study." DAI
                        39 (1978): 1518A (Auburn). </bib>
                    <notes> Trager-Smith transcription and computer tabulation of phonemes and
                        distinc- tive features in the poetry, sorted by three chronological periods
                        in Thomas's development. Thomas used sonal mimesis most effectively in his
                        middle pe- riod, and he seems to have had certain preferences among sounds.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C63">
                    <bib> Hevner, Kate. "An Experimental Study of the Affective Value of Sounds in
                        Poetry." American Journal of Psychology 49 (1937): 419-34. </bib>
                    <notes> In a preliminary study, ingenious sound dummies of poems were
                        constructed, very similar in sound but semantically empty, and subjects then
                        matched these to descriptive adjectives. Agreement on which sounds were
                        mellifluous was generally good. In the main study similar matching was
                        performed on a far more complex model--a dummy eight-line pentameter stanza
                        rhyming a b a b b c b c in which simple patterns of light vs. dark vowels
                        and smooth vs. harsh consonants were deployed, three to a stanza, the
                        patterning recognizably re- petitive but also varied, the test sounds placed
                        only on stressed syllables. Common metrical variations of the pentameter
                        were also built in to test the influence of meter, and the inflections of
                        the reader's voice were also consid- ered. A fascinating curiosity. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C64">
                    <bib> Hewitt, Elizabeth K. "The Muse on Your Right: An Exploration of Opaque
                        Metaphor." Language and Style 12 (1979): 131-45. </bib>
                    <notes> On the relation of sound to meaning in metaphor. Hewitt draws upon
                        neuro- physiology research of the past century to try to show that the best
                        ("opaque" rather than "transparent") metaphors constitute a "coupling" [her
                        term, and Levin's though she does not draw upon him] between aural
                        complexity and semantic density or opacity. In short, the left hemisphere of
                        the brain responds to the verbal/semantic aspects of the metaphor [all
                        speech, in fact] while the right one responds to the nonverbal, purely aural
                        patterning. That is why an appeal to either side of the brain is
                        unsatisfying to us; in the best verbal art both hemispheres are engaged
                        simultaneously. Further, poets may turn this neurological state of affairs
                        to advantage, whenever the sense of their verse is particularly formidable,
                        "by fusing parts or series of difficult lines with a strong sound pattern
                        which persuades us, even when we cannot see clearly the sense pattern, that
                        the lines have an integrity, a wholeness as poetry." These two features,
                        sonal and semantic complexity, may be set as the axes of a Cartesian graph
                        for purposes of mapping relations of poems. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C65">
                    <bib> "Hibernicus." "Liquid Lines." Notes and Queries 173 (1937): 316. </bib>
                    <notes> Lines dense in l or m sounds are often "pointed" with one strong and
                        con- trasting consonant. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C66">
                    <bib> Honan, Park. "Matthew Arnold and Cacophony." Victorian Poetry 1 (1963):
                        115-22. </bib>
                    <notes> Despite all critical justifications and apologetics, Arnold's discordant
                        imagery and word-sounds were an important, intentional aspect of his
                        aesthetic. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C67">
                    <bib> Howarth, R. G. "Sound in Slessor's Poetry." Southerly 16 (1955): 189-96. </bib>
                    <notes> Analysis of sound and rhythm in three poems. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C68">
                    <bib> Hymes, Dell. "Phonological Aspects of Style: Some English Sonnets." Sebeok
                        (A19), pp. 109-31 (see the summary remarks on this paper by René Welleck,
                        pp. 412-13); rpt in Chatman and Levin (A21), pp. 33-53. </bib>
                    <notes> An extension of Lynch's work on "summative words" in sonnets (C78):
                        Hymes surveys the recent literature, giving the whole question of the sound-
                        meaning nexus in poetry and in language a much more penetrating and careful
                        consideration than his predecessors, then concludes from analysis of ten
                        son- nets each from Wordsworth and Keats that the phenomenon Lynch
                        postulated is generally valid (six of the twenty had an unquestionable
                        summative word, seven had some approximation of one, and five had none).
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C69">
                    <bib> L., L. "Ss Avoided in Verse." Notes and Queries 167 (1934): 398-99. </bib>
                    <notes> Discussion of lines in Tennyson and others, showing effects and
                        difficulties of too many s's, especially ending one word and beginning the
                        next. Cf. Franklin (C59) and Shewan et. al. (C100). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C70">
                    <bib> La Drière, Craig. "Structure, Sound, and Meaning." Frye (A15), pp. 85-108. </bib>
                    <notes> "The elements of which literary structures are composed are of course
                        the lin- guistic elements of sound and meaning." In the older tradition, all
                        the relations between these elements were classed as Grammar (i.e.
                        Linguistics), Rhetoric, Logic, or Poetics (Aesthetics). The latter, poetic,
                        function is simply "coherence of structure" per se, and thus the poetic
                        impulse will organize any or all of the aspects of language available to it
                        indiscriminately and without any a priori or- der; these aspects are sound,
                        qua sound, and meaning. The purely aesthetic structuring may be of the
                        intrinsic features of sounds, or of meanings, usually both, and the
                        structuring of the one may lie in parallel, contrast, counterpoint, or other
                        relation to that of the other. At present, however, we know the ele- ments
                        and structures of sound far better than any of those for meaning. Yet, La
                        Drière concludes, "the semantic structure of poetry is more like the poetic
                        structure of sounds than it is like the semantic structures of logic, or of
                        rheto- ric, or even of grammar so far as those exist." At a high level of
                        abstraction, the essay ranges widely; the reader may wish to begin on p. 97.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C71">
                    <bib> Lehmann, Ruth R. "Henry Vaughan and Welsh Poetry: A Contrast." PQ 24
                        (1945): 329-42. </bib>
                    <notes> Pp. 337-39 discuss cynghanedd in Vaughan and Hopkins. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C72">
                    <bib> Locock, C[harles] D[elatry]. Notes on the Technique of English Poetry
                        London: H. &amp; W. Brown, 1938. 32 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Pamphlet. A compressed statement of some inductive "rules" for the melody
                        of verse, specifically in the endings of blank verse lines and in various
                        sequences of vowel sounds (beyond question some sequences are more sonorous
                        than others). He also suggests that much of the "melodious" effect of a
                        verse line depends on the position of the line in the stanza. All of this
                        merits further pursuit. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C73">
                    <bib> Logan, H. M. "The Computer and the Sound-Texture of Poetry." Language and
                        Style 9 (1976): 260-79. </bib>
                    <notes> We may never be able to extract the god from the machine but we can
                        adapt its immense capacity for counting and sorting great masses of data.
                        Logan pro- gram tabulates (1) the rank-order of frequencies of consonants
                        (are certain dis- tributions of sounds "poetic"?), (2) the patterns of sonal
                        repetition, and (3) dis- tinctive-feature distributions in poetic texts.
                        This last analysis is explored fur- ther than the other two. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C74">
                    <bib> Lord, John B. "Of Frost, Cats, Poetry, and Distinctive Feature Analysis."
                        Language and Style 11 (1978): 173-80. </bib>
                    <notes> Systematic analysis of the distinctive acoustic (as opposed to
                        articulatory) fea- tures of the sounds in a short versifying exercise by
                        Frost (or is it an exercise in "the sound of sense"?) seems to show, if we
                        can believe it, that he was inter- ested in manipulating not whole
                        sound-patterns but isolable features of indi- vidual sounds. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C75">
                    <bib> -----. "Two Phonological Analysis of Poe's 'To Helen.'" Language and Style
                        3 (1970): 147-58. </bib>
                    <notes> A phonemic-semantic relationship analysis and a distinctive-feature
                        analysis of the poem reveal some trivially obvious features and some that
                        are neither: two themes in the poem are supported by
                        sound-patterning--Helen-classic and poet- wanderer--and two unobtrusive
                        prepositions--from and within--turn out to have unusual significance. Lord's
                        presentation, though technical, is simple in design and very clear. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C76">
                    <bib> Lukanitsch, Ruth M. "The Relationship of the Figures of Sound to the
                        Rhythm in Certain Poems of Gerard Manley Hopkins." DAI 25 (1964): 696A
                        (Northwestern). </bib>
                    <notes> An examinination of (1) the functions which sonal patterns serve within
                        the contexts of four Hopkins poems, (2) some broader generalizations which
                        may be derived, tentatively, therefrom, and (3) the effects which such
                        patterns have on the rhythm of the verse. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C77">
                    <bib> Lynch, James J. "The Sound of Lyric Poetry." Langue et Litterature. Paris:
                        Société d’Édition "Les Belles Lettres," 1961. pp. 415-16. </bib>
                    <notes> Briefly notes possible strategies for sound analysis. Notices that in
                        some pen- tameters of Shakespeare's Sonnet 60, metrically unstressed
                        syllables have higher acoustic intensity than those stressed. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C78">
                    <bib> -----. "The Tonality of Lyric Poetry: An Experiment in Method." Word 9
                        (1953): 211-24. </bib>
                    <notes> Lynch devises a procedure for assessing the degree of "compound phonetic
                        ef- fects" in poems: by marking each occurrence of a phoneme as 1 and adding
                        1 every time the phoneme (a) falls under metrical ictus, (b) bears
                        linguistic stress, or (c) is conspicuously repeated, a ratio of its
                        quantitative to qualitative im- portance may be derived. In Keats's sonnet
                        on Chapman's Homer, five vowels and two consonants predominate, and six of
                        these seven appear in what is the thematically summative word of the poem,
                        "silent." Thus the purely aural pattern peaks at precisely the same nexus as
                        the semantic. Lynch looks for confirmation of this principle in seven other
                        poets. But note that he reads the Keats poem with standard American
                        pronunciation. See Hymes (C68). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C79">
                    <bib> McFadden, George. "Dryden and the Numbers of His Native Tongue." Essays
                        and Studies in Language and Literature. Ed. Herbert H. Petit. Pittsburgh:
                        Duquesne University Press, 1964. pp. 87-109. </bib>
                    <notes> Extended analysis of Dryden's sense of the term "numbers," as meaning
                        not so much meter or syllabic regularity as "word-sound" in general,
                        especially sonal texture. Dryden's "numbers" thus compares very closely with
                        Eliot's "auditory imagination." And even more extended and minute analysis
                        reveals Dryden's frequent choice of a word for its contribution to a
                        mellifluous Vergillian sound-pattern. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C80">
                    <bib> McLane, Lucy N. "Sound Values in 'The Cloud.'" English Journal 22 (1933):
                        412-14 and Quarterly Journal of Speech 19 (1933): 224-27. </bib>
                    <notes> Effects of sonal patterns, especially in the s-sound. Note: "The
                        numerous iam- bic feet in a poem extremely anapestic in its effect . . .
                        originally fitted into the four-three iambic bars of the music." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C81">
                    <bib> Masson, David I. "Free Phonetic Patterns in Shakespeare's Sonnets."
                        Neophilologus 38 (1954): 277-89. </bib>
                    <notes> Detailed consideration of the methods and value of this article may be
                        found in Stephen Booth's An Essay on Shakespeare's Sonnets (B20), pp. 66-69
                        and 193- 95. Masson here extends his analysis of the more diffused sonal
                        patternings in verse to Shakespeare, eschewing a battery of statistics in
                        favor of a batallion of terms instead. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C82">
                    <bib> -----. "The Keatsian Incantation: A Study of Phonetic Patterning." John
                        Keats: A Reassessment. Ed. Kenneth Muir. Liverpool: Liverpool University
                        Press, 1958. pp. 159-80. </bib>
                    <notes> Tripartite: Masson (1) establishes the nature of Keats's pronunciation,
                        along with (2) a correlate prefatory synopsis of his own concepts and
                        terminology for sound-patterning [Occam ], in order to (3) perform a
                        detailed analysis of "con- catenation"--"tightly-linked or extended chains
                        of sound, analogous to the repetition or inversion of a melodic line in
                        music"--in the late Odes and The Eve of St. Ages, especially the seventh
                        stanza of the "Ode to a Nightingale" and the nineteenth of the Eve. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C83">
                    <bib> -----. "Some Problems in Literary Phonaesthetics." In Literature and
                        Science: Proceedings of the Sixth Triennial Congress [of the International
                        Federation for Modern Languages and Literatures], Oxford, 1954. Oxford:
                        Basil Blackwell, 1955. pp. 61-64. </bib>
                    <notes> Masson prefers using the term "phonaesthetics" to denote not the study
                        of sonal mimesis but rather the study of all the "effects and functions of
                        sound in literature." Toward this end the employment of statistics,
                        psychoanalysis, articula- tion measurement, and tabulation (profiling) of
                        data will be of no help whatso- ever, while the use of research on
                        cerebral-neural processes, child language acquisi- tion, phonetics, and
                        linguistics will, he judges. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C84">
                    <bib> -----. "Sound and Sense in a Line of Poetry." British Journal of
                        Aesthetics 3 (1963): 70-72. </bib>
                    <notes> Hopkins' line "And frightful a nightfall folded rueful a day" shows a
                        theme of sound which is manifested in three sonal motifs and two submotifs.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C85">
                    <bib> -----. "Sound in Poetry." Princeton (A18), pp. 784-90. </bib>
                    <notes> Very likely the best available synopsis of this area, but better used as
                        reference than as introduction; the categories will overwhelm the novice.
                        Treats Sound as Structure, Texture, and Function, followed by a historical
                        Survey of sound- patterning in Classical (Greek and Latin), Romance (French,
                        Italian, Spanish), English, Germanic (Dutch), and Slavonic verse. The
                        Functional Typology correlates five Aspects with eighteen Types: Types
                        Aspects To Types 1 Formal Stucture A - C A Structural Emphasis 2 Sense D - H
                        B Underpinning 3 Scene I - K C Counterpoising 4 Feeling L - O D Rubricating
                        Emphasis 5 Aesthetic Flavor P - R E Tagging F Correlation G Implication H
                        Diagramming I Sound-Representation J Illustrative Mime K Illustrative
                        Painting L Passionate Emphasis M Mood Evocation N Expressive Mime O
                        Expressive Painting P Ebullience Q Embellishment R Incantation See also s.v.
                        "Phonetic Equivalence" (pp. 617-18), "Tone-Color" (pp. 857- 58), "Echo" (p.
                        212), and "Repetition" (pp. 699-701). Note too L102 and L485-86. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C86">
                    <bib> -----. "Sound-Repetition Terms." Poetics I (A16), pp. 189-99. </bib>
                    <notes> Masson sorts into twenty categories perhaps two hundred terms, which
                        very quickly overwhelm even the most assiduous reader. Is this an index of
                        the paucity of our cranial capacities? </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C87">
                    <bib> -----. "Thematic Analysis of Sounds in Poetry." Proceedings of the Leeds
                        Philological and Literary Society, Literary and Historical Section 9 (1960):
                        133-47; rpt in Chatman and Levin (A21), pp. 54-68. </bib>
                    <notes> Five extended analyses of sound-patterning in poems, intended to show a
                        correlation between certain localized patterns (or motifs) of sound and
                        thematic elements and their development. The first twenty-six lines of
                        Paradise Lost, Donne's seventh Holy Sonnet, a German poem, a Swiss poem, and
                        two stanzas from Victor Hugo are the exhibits. Though some generalizations
                        are drawn, however, the emphasis falls on the mechanism--if such it may be
                        called--of analysis. The introductory discussion of "Bond Density" and
                        pattern-types is more generally systematic. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C88">
                    <bib> -----. "Vowel and Consonant Patterns in Poetry." JAAC 12 (1953): 213-27;
                        rpt in Chatman and Levin (A21), pp. 3-18. </bib>
                    <notes> Masson posits three fundamental types of sound patterning in poetry:
                        sequence (AB . . . AB), chiasmus (AC . . . BA), and bracket (AB . . . A or B
                        . . . AB), each of which may be compounded nearly to infinity by
                        subpatterning. Sonal expressiveness he finds may arise from three sources:
                        acoustic, kin- aesthetic, or lexical (i.e., associative, either
                        normal-lexical, nonce-lexical, or im- pressed elements). Copious examples
                        from all the European poetries. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C89">
                    <bib> -----. "Word and Sound in Yeats's 'Byzantium.'" ELH 20 (1953): 136-60. </bib>
                    <notes> Attention to verbal repetition, rhyme, vowels, consonants, and
                        patterning (es- pecially in the first two lines), and a review of Grammont's
                        and Macdermott's theories of sonal mimesis or expressiveness--the question
                        of what sounds are considered appropriate for what situations or subjects.
                        See Davison (C52). See also Masson's "The 'Musical Form' of Yeats's
                        Byzantium.'" Notes and Queries C90 198 (1953): 400-1. And cf. Venter (C106).
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C91">
                    <bib> Mooney, Stephen L. "New Devices in Sound Repetition." Word Study 24, no. 4
                        (1949): 1-4. </bib>
                    <notes> Mooney's analysis of the permutations of syllabic echoing results in a
                        table that ought to be more widely reprinted. He offers terminology as well,
                        explicating "near rhyme," consonance, "alliterative assonance," "analyzed
                        rhyme," "sus- pended rhyme," and "apocapated rhyme." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C92">
                    <bib> Addenda by Jeremy Ingalls, "Chromatic Rhyme," in 25, 1 (1949): 1-3 </bib>
                    <notes> (she proposes that term as a categorical for all varieties of
                        near-rhyme); John Caffrey, in 25, 2 (1949): 3; and Jacques Barzun, W. H.
                        Archer, Frank David- son, and Laurence Perrine, in 25, 4 (1950): 2-3. The
                        commentators, as usual, are completely incapable of reaching agreement on
                        terminology. Caffrey's let- ter, however, shows clearly that the matter is
                        much more complex than Mooney suggests. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C93">
                    <bib> Moynihan, William T. "'The Hewn Voice': Auditory Techniques." The Craft
                        and Art of Dylan Thomas. Ithaca, N. Y.: Cornell University Press, 1966. pp.
                        121- 55. </bib>
                    <notes> In his late poems Dylan Thomas came to view sound as the aesthetic
                        principle in poetry that superseded all others. Her Moynihan details
                        Thomas's develop- ing craft and control in (1) meter and intonation ("from a
                        poetry of strong metrical stress to a poetry of flowing, rhapsodic
                        cadence"); (2) phonemic sym- bolism (vowels especially are given values and
                        associations in the context of a poem); and (3) agnomination or "affinitive
                        patterning" (a larger configuration spun out of the sounds of a few key
                        words). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C94">
                    <bib> Nist John. "Gerard Manley Hopkins and Textural Intensity: A Linguistic
                        Analysis." College English 22 (1961): 497-500. </bib>
                    <notes> Phonemic analysis of "Spring and Fall." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C95">
                    <bib> -----. "Sound and Sense: Some Structures of Poetry." College English 23
                        (1962): 291-95. </bib>
                    <notes> Some elementary exhibitions of rhyme, alliteration, assonance,
                        consonance, and onomatopoeia, to show that "sound is its own sense," and
                        some not-at-all- elementary exhibition of distinctive-feature control and
                        "textural intensity" in po- etry. The seven distinctive-feature oppositions
                        (polarities, scales) are: vocal- ity/consonantality, tenseness/laxness,
                        interruption/continuity, grav- ity/acuteness, compactness/diffusion,
                        nasality/orality, and stri- dency/mellowness. Why has no one else extended
                        such an analysis? </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C96">
                    <bib> Oras, Ants. "Spenser and Milton: Some Parallels and Contrasts in the
                        Handling of Sound." Frye (A15), pp. 109-33; rpt in Chatman and Levin (A21),
                        pp. 19-32. </bib>
                    <notes> Comparison of sound-patterning. The most significant discovery is that
                        Spencer consistently prefers consonant clusters first in a syllable (letting
                        it taper off at the end), whereas Milton achieves his subtle but extensive
                        effect of mas- siveness by preferring consonant clusters at the ends of
                        syllables and also lines. The Miltonic syllable, over and over again, is a
                        crescendo of phonetic force. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C97">
                    <bib> Ricks, Christopher. "Sound and Sense in Paradise Lost." Essays by Divers
                        Hands (Transactions of the Royal Society of Literature), n.s. 39 (1977), pp.
                        92-111. </bib>
                    <notes> Not an essay for theory, categories, or the technae of technic, but
                        rather the closest of appreciative and discriminating readings of Miltonic
                        lines vis à vis their sounds and sense. Ricks sets Milton's style and method
                        against Shake- speare's and aligns it somewhat with Johnson's. A superb
                        essay on our greatest poetic stylist by perhaps our finest living critical
                        stylist. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C98">
                    <bib> Roblee, Louise and M. F. "The Affective Value of Articulate Sounds."
                        American Journal of Psychology 23 (1912): 579-83. </bib>
                    <notes> Fifteen women rated the pleasantness of initial vowels and final
                        consonants in nonsense syllables on a scale of 1 to 7. Most pleasant were l
                        and the a of "fa- ther"; most disagreeable were the schwa and g. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C99">
                    <bib> Schlauch, Margaret. Modern English and American Poetry: Techniques and
                        Ideologies. London: C. A. Watts, 1956. 200 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Part Two, p. 129-75, contains a chapter each on Sound and Rhythm, provid-
                        ing elementary notes on sonal and metrical analysis of verse. The treatment
                        of meter is mundane enough to escape our attention and also eccentric (she
                        al- lows the molossus, spondee, choriambus, etc.). But the analysis of sound
                        (in both chapters) is both rigorous and accessible; the fundamental phonemic
                        transcription system is provided, justified, and explained, followed by
                        analyses of varieties of rhyme. The section on vowel harmonics (based on
                        sound- spectrograms) is particularly interesting. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C100">
                    <bib> Shewan, A., Paget Toynbee, Henry Broadbent, and George G. Loane.
                        "Sibilation in Poetry." Correspondence in TLS, 10 January-7 February 1924,
                        pp. 23, 40, 65, 79. </bib>
                    <notes> Shewan's initial queries about the extent of s's allowed in a verse line
                        by the major poets is not answered or even pursued by the other
                        correspondents. But cf. Franklin (C59) and L. L. (C69). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C101">
                    <bib> Sonstroem, David. "Making Earnest of Game: G. M. Hopkins and Nonsense
                        Poetry." MLQ 28 (1967): 192-206. </bib>
                    <notes> The similarities of technical devices between the devout poet and the
                        playful versifier (Edward Lear) arise from the fact that in nonsense poetry
                        the ar- rangement of the words is governed by sound (not grammar), a fact
                        which has extremely interesting implications for understanding the process
                        of composition. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C102">
                    <bib> Takaku, Shin-ichi. "Arbitrariness of Word Sound and the Creative Process
                        of Poems." Studies in English Literature (Tokyo), English Number (1971), pp.
                        164- 65. (Abstract) </bib>
                    <notes> Cites examples to show that poets can find unexpected resources for
                        poetic composition in the seemingly intractable arbitrariness of the sounds
                        of words in the language. The restraints of the "givens" become an asset:
                        "the crystaliza- tion . . . is executed by means of free association within
                        the confines of pros- ody." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C103">
                    <bib> Thorndike, Edward L. "Euphony and Cacophony of English Words and Sounds."
                        Quarterly Journal of Speech 30 (1944): 201-7. </bib>
                    <notes> Experiments with both the visual and aural forms of (1) legitimate
                        words, (2) nonsense words, and (3) separate sounds. Results are
                        inconclusive. But among the recognizable words, on a scale of preference
                        from +16 to -16, the most odious words (-13) were "abut" and "belch."
                        "Bobolink," in contrast, did very well indeed (+12). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C104">
                    <bib> -----. "Experiments in Euphony." Psychological Bulletin 31 (1934): 679-80. </bib>
                    <notes> Brief abstract of a paper read at the 1934 American Psychological
                        Association annual convention, the gist of which is that the pleasantness or
                        unpleasantness of words is mainly a matter of wider cultural associations
                        rather than anything inherent in the sounds themselves. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C105">
                    <bib> Tilley, Edmond A. "Phonemic Differentiation Analyses of Poems by Sir
                        Thomas Wyatt and Others." DAI 33 (1972): 1697A (Iowa). </bib>
                    <notes> Patterns of distinctive features in fourteen sonnets and ten strambotti
                        by Wyatt are compared with those in one sonnet each by Petrarch, Surrey,
                        Spenser, Shakespeare, and Owen. Three types of patterns are discovered--two
                        types of "initial-terminal symmetry" and one of "mirror symmetry." Wyatt
                        uses the first two but not the third. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C106">
                    <bib> Venter, J. A. "Phonic Patterning in 'Sailing to Byzantium.'" English
                        Studies in Africa 10 (1967): 40-46. </bib>
                    <notes> A brief, diffuse, metacritical essay which laments the lack of an
                        adequate nota- tion for poetic sound-patterns, discusses a few stray lines,
                        and even omits the full phonetic transcription of the poem it is based on.
                        Cf. Masson (C89) and Davison (C52). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C107">
                    <bib> Wagner, Linda L. "The Significance of Sound." Laurel Review 6 (1966):
                        3-12. </bib>
                    <notes> The value of Denise Levertov's work lies in her deep interest in "an
                        intense melopoeia" including, as its elements, idiomatic speech, a "rhythmic
                        norm" and its center a "horizon note" based on the length and weight of
                        heard sylla- bles, long vowels, monosyllables, short lines, and assonance.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C108">
                    <bib> Yoshida, Minoru. Style in the Sound of English Poetry. Tokyo: Tokyo Gakuen
                        Women's Junior College, 1971. </bib>
                    <notes> Revised by Robert M. Ogden, this typescript essay examines the "styles"
                        (i.e. types, patterns) of sound in verse, but unfortunately no typology or
                        organiza- tional scheme whatsoever is given, so the author simply cites a
                        great many ex- amples at random in his chapters on Chaucer and Spenser;
                        Shakespeare; Mil- ton; Donne, Dryden, and Pope; Poe and Whitman; and Eliot.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C109">
                    <bib> -----. "Word-Music in English Poetry." JAAC 11 (1952): 151-59. </bib>
                    <notes> Identifies (and exemplifies, copiously) six types of sonal repetition
                        which may appear either initially, medially, or finally within the line: (1)
                        single sounds, (2) sound-groups, (3) syllables, (4) words, (5) word-groups,
                        and (6) mixed forms. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C110">
                    <bib> Yung, Kai Kin. "Poetic Harmony: Some Johnsonian Views." The New Rambler:
                        Journal of the Johnson Society of London 18 (1977): 19-32. </bib>
                    <notes> Attempts to explicate Johnson's three definitions of "harmony" in the
                        Diction- ary by examining his statements elsewhere and the practice of
                        various poets on (1) order or "logical" structure, (2) sound
                        harmony--avoidance of haitus, con- sonant clusters, and monosyllabic lines,
                        (3) regularity of form, and (4) poetic diction. </notes>
                </item>

            </div>
            <div title="ALLITERATION, ASSONANCE, CONSONANCE">

                <item id="C111">
                    <bib> Collitz, Klara H. "Alliteration in American English." American Speech 7
                        (1932): 204- 18. </bib>
                    <notes> A useful list of banal, blatant, blundering, botches of bad
                        alliterations, mainly from newspapers. If aesthetics treats of the
                        beautiful, is its province not also that of the ugly? </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C112">
                    <bib> Dundes, Alan. "The Henny-Penny Phenomenon: A Study of Folk Phonological
                        Aesthetics in American Speech." Southern Folklore Quarterly 38 (1974): 1-9. </bib>
                    <notes> Fascinating research into "folk phonological esthetics." Dundes finds
                        preferen- tial consonant patterns in the formation of the three types of
                        reduplicative phrases--identical (e.g. beep beep), ablaut (zig zag), and
                        rhyme (mumbo jumbo). By far the most common initial sound is h. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C113">
                    <bib> Ellinger, Johann. "Zur Alliteration in der modernen englischen
                        Prosadichtung." Englische Studien 19 (1894): 360-80. </bib>
                    <notes> Lists of occurrences in Charlotte Bronté and Wilkie Collins. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C114">
                    <bib> Hornstein, Lillian H. "Reduplicatives Redivivus: From Ack-Ack through
                        Go-Go to Zig-Zag and a Little Beyond." In Studies in Honor of J. Alexander
                        Kerns. Ed. Robert C. Lugton and M. G. Salter. Janua Linguarum, Series Major,
                        no. 44. The Hague: Mouton, 1970. pp. 59-64. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C115">
                    <bib> Pound, Louise. "The Kraze for 'K.'" American Speech 1 (1925): 43-44. </bib>
                    <notes> On the "present slump toward alliteration" in advertising jargon.
                        Kopious klutzy klangers. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C116">
                    <bib> Prick van Wely, F. P. H. "Apt Alliteration's Artful Aid." Englische
                        Studien 47 (1914): 185-96. </bib>
                    <notes> Addenda and corrigenda to Willert (C126). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C117">
                    <bib> Schwarz, Mia. Alliteration im englischen kulterleben neuerer Zeit. Diss.,
                        Greifswald, 1921. 79 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Rev: in Englische Studien 59 (1925): 103-4. Cf. Spies (C121). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C118">
                    <bib> Seitz, Karl. Zur Alliteration in Neuenglischen. Itzehoe: G. J. Pfingsten,
                        1883 (Part 1), 1884 (Part 2). 36 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>A seemingly endless collection of examples from both literature and
                        proverbs, alphabetically arranged. C119 Rev: by E. Regel in Englische
                        Studien 8 (1885): 389-93. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C120">
                    <bib> -----. Die Alliteration im Neuenglischen vor und bei Shakespeare. Marne:
                        Altmüller, [1875]. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C121">
                    <bib> Spies, Heinrich. "Alliteration und Reimklang im modernenglischen
                        Kulturleben." Englische Studien 54 (1920): 149-58. </bib>
                    <notes> Varieties of alliterating, rhyme-formed, and ablaut-formed phrases found
                        in books, advertisements, linguistic usage, etc. Many examples. Cf. Schwartz
                        (C117). C121a Strait, H. Alliter, or the Melody of Language. New York: G. A.
                        C. Van Beuren, 1836. 16 pp. "Alliter" is the art of arranging letters
                        melodiously, letters representing sounds [sic]. There are two laws--all
                        vowels alliter together, and all consonants alliter alone--and two
                        kinds--precedent and succedent [rhyme]--lf alliter. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C122">
                    <bib> Thun, Nils. Reduplicative Words in English: A Study of Formations of the
                        Types "Tick-tick," "Hurly-burly," and "Shilly-shally." Uppsala, 1963. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C123">
                    <bib> Wescott, Roger W. "Types of Vowel Alternation in English." Word 26 (1970):
                        309-43. </bib>
                    <notes> A study of one aspect of the general phenomenon of phoneme alternation,
                        which the author dubs apophonology, as compared to phoneme repetition, which
                        is termed echoistics. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C124">
                    <bib> Wheatley, Henry B. "A Dictionary of Reduplicated Words in the English
                        Language." Transactions of the Philological Society, 1865 (Appendix). Also
                        published separately at London, 1866. 104 pp. </bib>
                    <notes/>
                </item>


                <item id="C125">
                    <bib> Willert, Hans. Alliterierende Bindungen in der neuenglischen
                        Bibelübersetzung. Berlin, 1897. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C126">
                    <bib> -----. Die alliterierenden Formeln der englischen Sprache. Halle: Max
                        Niemeyer, 1911. 609 pp. See addenda at C116. </bib>
                    <notes> IN POETRY </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C127">
                    <bib> Adams, Percy G. Graces of Harmony: Alliteration, Assonance, and Consonance
                        in Eighteenth-Century British Poetry. Athens: University of Georgia Press,
                        1976. Rev: in TLS, 10 February 1978; in Style 12 (1978): 68-70; in Arizona
                        Quarterly 34 (1978): 181-83; in South Atlantic Bulletin 18 (1978): 87-88; in
                        The Scriblerian 10 (1977): 181-83. </bib>
                    <notes> A timely yet durable book: Adams has caught us at a blind spot--we have
                        had no full-scale study of the three commonest forms of structural sound-
                        patterning--and his gracefully harmonious rectification of our lapse spans a
                        gulf much wider than 1660-1800; indeed, though his primary focus is the
                        eight- eenth century, his reach extends with ease from Chaucer to the
                        present, and even beyond English. Chapter 1 presents definitions, a
                        wide-ranging survey of the importance of these devices, and a long
                        side-glance at "phonetic symbol- ism" (pp. 24-35): Chapter 2 treats Dryden;
                        3, Pope; 4, the minor 18th century poets; and 5, 19th and 20th century
                        poets, especially Browning. Adams wears much learning lightly (do not fail
                        to see the three long background Notes in the footnotes to chapter 1),
                        matching the neatness and precision of informed scholarship with a colorful,
                        dapper style and a keen ear for poetic resonance. Note the definitions of
                        the three key terms given on pp. 3, 9, and 15: signifi- cant patterning is
                        confined to stressed syllables. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C128">
                    <bib> -----. "'Harmony of Numbers': Dryden's Alliteration, Consonance,
                        Assonance." Texas Studies in Literature and Language 9 (1967): 333-43;
                        revised as chapter 2 of his Graces of Harmony (above). </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C129">
                    <bib> -----. "This Historical Importance of Assonance to Poets." PMLA 88 (1973):
                        8-18; revised as part of chapter 1 of his Graces of Harmony (C127). Replies
                        by N. B. Smith (pp. 1182-83) and W. B. Finnie (pp. 1183-84); rejoinder by
                        Adams (pp. </bib>
                    <notes>1184-85). See also Finnie (K116) and Adams (K2). Assonance has been
                        neglected in literary studies because it is more difficult to perceive
                        (modern readers are uncertain of the sounding of historical vowels), but
                        Adams adduces innumerable examples from classical Greek, Roman, French,
                        German, British, and American poets to justify the equal rights of as-
                        sonance, then considers the question of "sound symbolism." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C130">
                    <bib> -----. "Pope's Concern with Assonance." Texas Studies in Literature and
                        Language 9 (1968): 493-502 </bib>
                    <notes>; revised as chapter 3 of his Graces of Harmony (C127). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C131">
                    <bib> Astley, Russell. "Stations of the Breath: End Rhyme in the Verse of Dylan
                        Thomas." PMLA 84 (1969): 1595-1605. </bib>
                    <notes> Over the course of his career Thomas moved from an intense interest in
                        con- sonance, to later, more subtle patterns of assonance, and, near the
                        end, back to true rhyme. In general his last-line sounds are not easy
                        near-rhymes but a highly sophisticated, complex, and exacting system of
                        varieties of consonance which he developed. These, "dreary to enumerate,"
                        Astley maps out here: from Yeats Thomas learned consonance; from Owen he
                        learned "zero conso- nance" (all syllables ending in open (though different)
                        vowels have identity of absence of following consonants) and "frame rhyme"
                        (alliteration + conso- nance); to these Thomas added "partial consonance"
                        and "close consonance" to complete his inventory. (All terms are Astley's.)
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C132">
                    <bib> Bengough, S. E. "The Use of Alliteration in Shakespeare's Poems."
                        Poet-Lore 5 (1893): 190-94. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C133">
                    <bib> Bolwell, Robert. "Notes on Alliteration in Spencer." JEGP 15 (1916):
                        421-22. </bib>
                    <notes> Haggling with De Selincourt over whether or not w-allitera-tion suggests
                        "vastness and desolation", B. finds that only 30 of the 225 w-alliterations
                        in Book I of The Faerie Queene give such an impression. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C134">
                    <bib> Colum, Padraic. "Assonance in English Verse." The Forum and Century 94
                        (1935): 384-86. </bib>
                    <notes> Lobbies for its increased use in English and Irish verse, seconding
                        Larminie's motion (E192). Slight. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C135">
                    <bib> Diekhoff, John S. "Critical Activity of the Poetic Mind: John Milton."
                        PMLA 55 (1940): 748-72. </bib>
                    <notes> Especially section III, "Tone-Color," on alliteration: p. 764 ff.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C136">
                    <bib> Douglas-Lithgow, R. A. "English Alliteration from Chaucer to Milton."
                        Transactions of the Royal Society of Literature, series 2, vol. 18 (1897),
                        pp. 115-50. </bib>
                    <notes> Follows J73 and K91, extending the history of the form in England and
                        Scot- land from Chaucer's time into (primarily) the sixteenth and
                        seventeenth cen- turies. These later instances of alliteration the author
                        terms "Neo-Alliteration" so as to distinguish them from the Pre-Chaucerian
                        staple form, since their function is essentially ornamental rather than
                        structural. Copious examples but a paucity of discussion. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C137">
                    <bib> Dunlap, Elizabeth. "Sound and Sense in 'Pied Beauty.'" Hopkins Quarterly 3
                        (1976): 35-38. </bib>
                    <notes> Patterns of alliteration in the poem connect qualities and their
                        opposites in a relation of similitude, with theological implications.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C138">
                    <bib> Geniusas, A. "The Role of 'Sound' Repetitions in the First Act of Richard
                        II." Voprosy leksikologii. Ed. V. J. Biensieks. Riga: LVU, 1967. pp. 183-94. </bib>
                    <notes> Describes the local effects, especially of alliteration. Notice also the
                        preceding article (pp. 159-82) by the same author on "The Role of Lexical
                        and Syntacti- cal Repetitions in the First Act of Richard II," which shows
                        the general in- creases of emphasis achieved by these devices; the echoing
                        particularly occurs in one character's quick, sharp responses to the lines
                        of another. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C139">
                    <bib> Goldsmith, Ulrich K. "Alliteration." Princeton (A18), pp. 15-16. </bib>
                    <notes> An excellent synopsis having international scope. See also s.v.
                        "Assonance," "Consonance," and "Onomatopoeia." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C140">
                    <bib> -----. "Words Out of a Hat? Alliteration and Assonance in Shakespeare's
                        Sonnets." JEGP 49 (1950): 33-48. </bib>
                    <notes> Supporting Stoll (C166) against Skinner (C160), the author (1) sketches
                        in the general sixteenth-century context for the use of alliteration, (2)
                        distinguishes ten varieties of alliteration, some with subvarieties, all
                        copiously exemplified, and (3) argues for the close relation of alliteration
                        and assonance. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C141">
                    <bib> Griffin, Robert J. "Notes on 'Musical' Devices in Sackville's Verse."
                        Neuphilologische Milleilungen 63 (1962): 119-36. </bib>
                    <notes> Pope admired Sackville's verse. Griffin finds considerable phonetic
                        repetition, augmentation, diminution, and reversal in the Complaint, and the
                        verse of the Induction "so relentlessly alliterative as to seem reminiscent
                        of Anglo-Saxon verse." And in order to show pitch-patterning in assonance,
                        Griffin sets the vowels of one stanza on a musical staff, using the phonetic
                        distinction high/mid/low. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C142">
                    <bib> Jackson, Elizabeth. "Quantitative Measurement of Assonance and
                        Alliteration in Swinburne: A Reply to B. F. Skinner." American Journal of
                        Psychology 55 (1942): 115-23. </bib>
                    <notes> Criticism of Skinner (C161) for counting only ictic alliterations, for
                        excluding repeated whole words, for construing the "coefficient of
                        alliteration" on the basis of single sounds rather than on the basis of
                        whole lines, for not giving extra weight to multiple alliterations, for
                        taking too small a sample, for ignor- ing combinations of effects, and for
                        denigrating the intentionality of so overt a device as alliteration.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C143">
                    <bib> Kennedy, Evory. "On the Principles and Uses of Alliteration in Poetry." In
                        The Afternoon Lectures on Literature and Art Delivered in the Theatre of the
                        Museum of Industry, Dublin. Third Series. London: Bell and Daldy, 1866. pp.
                        89-128. </bib>
                    <notes> Literary history, with long extracts. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C144">
                    <bib> Koziol, Herbert. "Die Alliteration in der modernen englischen Dichtung."
                        Archiv 184 (1943): 49-53. </bib>
                    <notes> No matter how much English poets may sneer at "rum, ram, ruf, by
                        letter," alliteration is a common device, though its function is now
                        ornamental rather than structural (cohesive). Koziol likens it to eye-rhyme
                        and onomatopoeia: the outer form is intended to show the inner. Examples.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C145">
                    <bib> -----. Elemente englischer Sprachkunst. Vienna: Wilhelm Braumüller, 1976.
                        174 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>A compendium of examples of verbal figuration and ornament, mainly allit-
                        eration and other varieties of echoing, in alliterative and rhymed verse and
                        prose. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C146">
                    <bib> Leavitt, Jay A. "On the Measurement of Alliteration in Poetry." Computers
                        and the Humanities 10 (1976): 333-42. </bib>
                    <notes> Devises a computer-program to rank texts on density of alliteration.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C147">
                    <bib> Loane, George G., et al. "Some Varieties in Alliteration." TLS, 22
                        August-3 October 1918, pp. 392, 405, 418, 429, 441, 456, 469. </bib>
                    <notes> The first and fourth letters offer many examples with interesting
                        comments on the relative success of mimesis and expressiveness when certain
                        ideas are tagged by certain alliterating sounds. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C148">
                    <bib> McNally, James. "Varieties of Alliteration in Whitman." Walt Whitman
                        Review 13 (1967): 28-32. </bib>
                    <notes> Identifies four additional types of alliteration--rhetorical (i.e., to
                        point up par- allelisms or inversions), terminal (at line-end in successive
                        lines), integral (within single words), and interlinked (the second pattern
                        begun before the first is completed). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C149">
                    <bib> Masson, David I. "Dryden's Phonetic Rhetoric: some Passages from his
                        Original Poems." Proceedings of the Leeds Philological and Literary Society,
                        Literary and Historical Section 11 (1964): 1-5. </bib>
                    <notes> A short demonstration of Dryden's surprisingly keen ability to let his
                        allitera- tions carry part of his poem's argument. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C150">
                    <bib> -----. "Wilfred Owen's Free Phonetic Patterns: Their Style and Function."
                        JAAC 13 (1955): 360-69. </bib>
                    <notes> A schema of varieties of non-structural alliteration and assonance in
                        Owen, somewhat weighted by Masson's characteristic penchant for
                        nomenclature. Owen is best at creating complexes of phonetic subpatterns,
                        and he seems to prefer assonance of the "short u." Altogether, it is
                        remarkable to what degree he labored for order and beauty in the design of
                        his aesthetic objects, given the starkness of his subject and the horror of
                        his situation. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C151">
                    <bib> Opitz, George. Die Stabreimenden Wortbindungen in den Dichtungen Walter
                        Scott's. Diss., Breslau, 1893. 69 pp. </bib>
                    <notes/>
                </item>


                <item id="C152">
                    <bib> Oras, Ants. "Lyrical Instrumentation in Marlowe: A Step Towards
                        Shakespeare." In Studies in Shakespeare. Ed. Arthur D. Matthews and Clark M.
                        Emory. University of Miami Publications in English and American Literature,
                        vol. 1. Coral Gables: University of Miami Press, 1953. pp. 74-87. </bib>
                    <notes> An extension of an earlier study of assonantal verse-endings in Surrey
                        (below) to Marlowe. These endings allowed Marlowe to embed sonnet-like
                        structures in the running verse of his dramas. They also had the stylistic
                        effect of weighting the ends of the lines so much that their middles seem
                        comparatively empty. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C153">
                    <bib> -----. "Surrey's Technique of Phonetic Echoes: A Method and Its
                        Background." JEGP 50 (1951): 289-308. </bib>
                    <notes> Though stiff, Surrey's blank verse shows us "a certain severe dignity,"
                        espe- cially in vowel echoing, which Surrey is better at than we think he
                        is. His limitation in using assonance (consonance also, to some degree)
                        subtly is that he confines it nearly always to ictic (stressed) syllables,
                        rarely letting the reso- nances of the echoes flow all across the verse. But
                        in elevated passages (of blank verse, remember) Surrey allows a very copious
                        usage of rhyme and near- rhyme. This wide attention to vocalic echo is
                        preserved in the MS revisions made for Tottel's edition of Surrey's poetry,
                        and its presence in those poems put into Tottel's Miscellany had a
                        demonstrable effect on the verse of Surrey's contemporaries and successors.
                        His music was noticed, emulated, and refined. What were his sources? Not
                        Virgil or Wyatt but the Italian writers of versi sciolti. An admirable
                        essay. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C154">
                    <bib> Pirkhofer, Anton M. "'A Pretty Pleasing Pricket'--On the Use of
                        Alliteration in Shakespeare's Sonnets." Shakespeare Quarterly 14 (1963):
                        3-14. </bib>
                    <notes> Three matters are addressed: (1) devising an adequate system for
                        analyzing al- literative patterning (double, triple, and quadruple echoes of
                        single alliteration, double alliteration (these are all horizontal
                        patterns), and vertical patterns span- ning two, three, four, and more
                        lines); (2) the adequacy of such information as evidence for dating and
                        chronology; and (3) correlations with thematic devel- opment in the poem.
                        Sonnets 1 and 129 are analyzed closely. Shakespeare was more skillful and
                        subtle at alliteration than his contemporaries; his patterns in general are
                        "as remote from inane plethora as they are from indiscriminate or-
                        namentation." He was particularly adept at interlace and at loading the
                        crucial, summative couplet of the sonnet with the weighty ore of
                        alliteration. Chronologically his technique developed toward wider spans of
                        echoing. N.B.: Pirkhofer only counts alliterations on metrically stressed
                        syllables. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C155">
                    <bib> Scott, Fred N. "Vowel Alliteration in Modern Poetry." MLN 30 (1915):
                        233-37. </bib>
                    <notes> Vocalic alliteration is not exactly the same thing as assonance, but
                        seems, from Professor Scott's examples and statistics, to be rather common.
                        Unfortunately, though, the letters alliterate more frequently than the
                        sounds, spellings of vow- els being so erratic in English, so that when
                        Scott finds himself pressed for an explanation, he exhumes the sonority
                        theory and the glottal-catch theory of Classen (L322), preferring the
                        latter. Such an extremity seems not only un- likely but also unnecessary.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C156">
                    <bib> Shimane, Kunio. "'Speech Framed to Be Heard': The Function and Value of
                        Sound Effects in The Wreck." Readings of "The Wreck": Essays in
                        Commemoration. Ed. Peter Milward and Raymond V. Schoder. Chicago: Loyola
                        University Press, 1976. pp. 142-53. </bib>
                    <notes> Opening with a reminder that Hopkins' pronunciation differed from our
                        own, the author comes to his point, the manifold effects of Hopkins'
                        principles sound-device, consonant clusters. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C157">
                    <bib> Shirley, Charles G., Jr. "Alliteration as Evidence in Dating a Poem of
                        Thomas Churchyard: An Exploratory Computer-aided Study." MP 76 (1978-79):
                        374-77. </bib>
                    <notes> "To Bed I Goe," dated ca. 1580. The computer searched not only for in-
                        tralinear patterns but also for "anticipation" and "carry-over" of
                        alliterants. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C158">
                    <bib> Siegel, Eli. "Assonance Is Like This." New York Quarterly, no. 2 (1970),
                        pp. 82-90. </bib>
                    <notes> Uses, origins, applications. The principle: "sameness-in-difference."
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C159">
                    <bib> Siemt, O. Der Stabreim bei Henry Wadsworth Longfellow. Liegnitz, 1897. 43
                        pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Rev: in Englische Studien 27 (1900): 148. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C160">
                    <bib> Skinner, B. F. "Alliteration in Shakespeare's Sonnets: A Study in Literary
                        Behavior." Psychological Record 3 (1939): 186-92. </bib>
                    <notes> Replies by Stoll (C166): and Goldsmith (C140). Computation of
                        Shakespeare's actual alliterations in one hundred of his son- nets, deletion
                        of those echoes deriving from the repetition of whole words for rhetorical
                        or thematic purposes [a questionable choice in method on Skinner's part],
                        and comparison of the resultant figures with those that would result from
                        completly random echoing reveals very little variance between the two. Con-
                        clusion: "there is no significant evidence of a process of alliteration in
                        the be- havior of the poet. . . ." Only alliterations on ictic syllables
                        were counted. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C161">
                    <bib> -----. "A Quantitative Estimate of Certain Types of Sound-Patterning in
                        Poetry." American Journal of Psychology 54 (1941): 64-79. Reply by Elizabeth
                        Jackson (C142). </bib>
                    <notes> Comparison of the instances of alliteration and assonance in ictic
                        syllables of the first five hundred lines of Atalanta in Calydon with
                        expected random fre- quencies reveals the obvious: Swinburne's echoing is
                        anything by unpremedi- tated. Assessment of degree of intention, however, is
                        something else. Skinner tabulates not only frequencies of echo by line but
                        also the distribution of the spans of echoing; the functional limit of span
                        seems to be four syllables though echoes do occur as far away as eight
                        syllables from the original. Swinburne uses more alliterations and at wider
                        spans than Shakespeare does (the "coefficient of alliteration" for the
                        former is four times that for the latter), but on the other hand he seems
                        not to develop consonance at all and actively suppresses asso- nance.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C162">
                    <bib> -----. "Reflections on Meaning and Structure." I. E. Richards: Essays in
                        His Honor. Ed. Reuben Brower, et al. New York: Oxford University Press,
                        1973. pp. </bib>
                    <notes>199-209. A response to Jakobson and Jones (C105). Still interested in the
                        nature of meaning when intentionally deployed in a pre-determined (poetic)
                        structure, Skinner reviews the statistical evidence on actual vs.
                        theoretical probabilities for random occurrence of alliteration in
                        Shakespeare and Swinburne, and he also constructs an interesting
                        "density-of-meaning scansion" for the typical Shakespearian sonnet. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C163">
                    <bib> Spencer, Virginia E. Alliteration in Spencer's Poetry, Discussed and
                        Compared with Alliteration as Employed by Drayton and Daniel. Diss., Zurich,
                        1898. 96 + 48 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>(In two Parts in paper covers.) Using the scheme established by Regel in
                        his essay on Layamon (K311), Spencer catalogues examples of consonant and
                        vowel alliteration by: 1. Etymological Relation 2. Association A. Concrete
                        ideas B. Abstractions, or abstract + concrete C. Emphasis D. Contrast 3.
                        Grammatical Relation A. Substantives, with modifiers B. Verb or Adjective,
                        with modifiers C. Substantive + Verb (Subject + Predicate) D. Verb +
                        Substantive (Predicate + Object) </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C164">
                    <bib> Steffen, Paul. Die Alliteration bei Tennyson. Diss;, Kiel, 1905. 83 pp. </bib>
                    <notes> Bibliography. Tennyson's alliterations are sorted into categories of
                        abstract metrical and structural patterns. Except for a brief introduction,
                        this is the typical German "lists-of-types-and-instances" dissertation.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C165">
                    <bib> Stephens, W. H. "Alliteration in Strokes." Poetry Review 26 (1935):
                        307-10. </bib>
                    <notes> One can only wish that the sole copy of this essay had lain at the
                        library in Al- exandria, or in one of the monasteries in front of Henry the
                        Eighth's soldiers. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C166">
                    <bib> Stoll, E. E. "Poetic Alliteration." MLN 55 (1940): 388-90. </bib>
                    <notes> A sharp rejoinder to B. F. Skinner on alliteration in Shakespeare's
                        sonnets (C160), criticizing his methods and conclusions. Skinner's
                        tabulations of oc- currences led him to conclude that the alliterative
                        effects were mainly random; Stoll insists they are artful, noting that in
                        order for alliteration in one line to be conspicuous, its consonants must be
                        suppressed (unobtrusive) in others, which is what the tabulation showed--low
                        frequencies in a number of lines. Further, Skinner confined his analysis to
                        the single line, whereas it is commonly known that poetic alliteration
                        extends itself more widely. And even though it is im- portant to bear in
                        mind the base-line of the chances for random occurrence, poetry proceeds by
                        appearance and effect not by frequencies or probabilities. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C167">
                    <bib> Wimberly, Lowry C. "'Sewing the Silken Seam.'" Poet-Lore 30 (1919):
                        567-78. </bib>
                    <notes> Notes a common alliterative formula in the English and Scottish
                        traditional ballads. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C168">
                    <bib> Wright, George T. "Alliteration." New York Quarterly, no. 9 (1972): pp.
                        117-21. </bib>
                    <notes> Commonplaces . </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C169">
                    <bib> Wright, N. B. "Measuring Alliteration: A Study in Method." Computers in
                        the Humanities. Ed. J. L. Mitchell. Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press,
                        1974. pp. 82-93. </bib>
                    <notes> Starting from a thoughtful, keen appraisal of some shortcomings in the
                        ex- perimental method of B. F. Skinner (C160 and C161), Wright applies
                        several other procedures in search of a text-scanning program which will
                        accurately identify significant alliteration. Those tried here turn out to
                        be inadequate in comparison with what one learns by a careful and perceptive
                        reading of the poem. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C170">
                    <bib> Zeuner, [?]. Die Alliteration bei neuenglischen Dichtern. Diss., Halle,
                        1880. </bib>
                    <notes/>
                </item>


            </div>
            <div title="RHYME">




                <item id="C171">s <bib> Bolinger, Dwight L. "Rime, Assonance, and Morpheme
                        Analysis." Word 6 (1950): 117-36. </bib>
                    <notes> If one screens out for the moment the etymology and diachronic
                        development of morphemes and examines them synchronically, wholly new and
                        significant clusters of association and similitude (based on rhyme/assonance
                        of a base morpheme) appear, many of which are quite striking, though the
                        interperme- ability of meanings in the language is so extensive that
                        certitude is quickly re- duced to a kind of pattern game. But "if we can
                        show enough regularity in use, a rime or an assonance should be, or come
                        very near to being, a mor- pheme." If so, that would be very significant.
                        See also p. 130 ff on phon- esthemes. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C172">
                    <bib> Eckhardt, Eduard. "Reim und Stabreim im Dienste der neuenglischen
                        Wortbildung." Englische Studien 72 (1938): 161-91. </bib>
                    <notes> Examples of alliteration and rhyme in the formation of catch phrases,
                        clichés, and expressions, for example "fair and square." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C173">
                    <bib> Kirchner, Gustav. "Der Reimklang in Englischen (Nachtraäge)." Zeitschrift
                        für Anglistik und Amerikanistik 7 (1959): 281-87. </bib>
                    <notes> Examples of phrases created by rhyme-formation. Note the evidence cited
                        here for the phenomenon in other languages as well. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C174">
                    <bib> Koziol, Herbert. "Zu den Reim- und Ablautbildungen im Englischen."
                        Englischen Studien 73 (1938): 158-59. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C175">
                    <bib> Luelsdorff, Philip A. "Repetition and Rhyme in Generative Phonology."
                        Linguistics 44 (1968): 75-89. </bib>
                    <notes> Writes rules for Repetition in general and End-, Initial-, and
                        Internal-Rhyme in particular. Most interesting is the argument that such
                        rules ought to apply at the deep-structure level not at the surface.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C176">
                    <bib> Marchand, Hans. "Motivation by Linguistic Form: English Ablaut and Rime
                        Combinations and Their Relevancy to Word-formation." Studia Neophilologica
                        29 (1957): 54-66. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C177">
                    <bib> Müller, Max. Die Reim- und Ablautkomposita des Englischen. Diss.,
                        Strassburg, 1909. 105 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>A list of examples of two particular types of formulaic phrases often
                        formed idiomatically in English: (1) rhyme-formation, i.e. C1 V1 C1 + C2 V1
                        C1, e.g. "hodge-podge," and (2) ablaut-formation, which is C1 V1 C1 + C1 V2
                        C1, e.g. "pitter-patter." C177a Nishihara, Tadayoshi. "Rhyming in Word- and
                        Phrase-Structure, Proverbs, and Prose in Present-Day English. Studies in
                        English Language and Literature 17, nos. 2-3 (1977): 67-89. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C178">
                    <bib> Stetson, R. H. "Rhythm and Rhyme." Psychological Review Monograph
                        Supplements 4 (1903): 413-66. </bib>
                    <notes>(Series also titled Harvard Psychological Studies, vol. 1.) Experiments
                        with simple sounds to discern what effects rhyme has on a rhythmical line;
                        beats were represented by simple clicks, end-rhyme by two simultaneous
                        clicks differing in pitch. Conclusions (p. 464) note both advan- tages and
                        disadvantages of rhyme, which is here taken as "a highly specialized form of
                        [rhythmic] recurrence." IN POETRY </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C179">
                    <bib> Adams, Stephen. "Ezra Pound and Provençal Melopoeia." Four Decades of
                        Poetry 2 (1978): 27-48. </bib>
                    <notes> An instructive exposition of what Pound learned, achieved, and failed to
                        achieve in his exercises at translating the sonant arabesques of the
                        troubadour stanzas. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C180">
                    <bib> Ahrend, Evelyn R. "Riming -ing and -in." American Speech 8 (1933): 71-72.
                        Addendum by A. Dickson, p. 76. </bib>
                    <notes> Notes occurrences in Keats and Wordsworth, dismay at those by Amy
                        Lowell, and recognition of the commonness of the practice by Grandgent and
                        Wyld. Conclusion: not a proper practice in "serious" nineteenth-century
                        poetry. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C181">
                    <bib> Aldington, A. E. "Is Rhyme Indispensable?" Westminster Review 169 (1908):
                        554- 58. </bib>
                    <notes> One can more readily imagine the answer (No) than one can imagine taking
                        the question seriously. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C182">
                    <bib> Antz, E. L. "Rhyme and the Enjoyment of Poetry." Thesis, Columbia
                        University, 1926. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C183">
                    <bib> Benton, Joel. "About Rhyme." Lippencott's Magazine 43 (1889): 901-4. </bib>
                    <notes> Rhyme not an essential element to verse. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C184">
                    <bib> Bercovitch, Sacvan. "Cotton Mather Against Rhyme: Milton and the
                        Psalterium Americanun." American Literature 39 (1967): 191-93. </bib>
                    <notes> Mather's attack on rhyme in verse in the preface to his translation of
                        the Psalms represents the first influence of Milton on the New World. Mather
                        himself chose the septenary couplet rather than blank verse for the meter of
                        his metrical psalter. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C185">
                    <bib> Beum, Robert. "The Rhyme in Samson Agonistes." Texas Studies in Literature
                        and Language 4 (1962): 177-82. </bib>
                    <notes> That Milton returned to rhyme in his late drama is much less troubling
                        than the fact that the specific rhymes themselves show no discernable or
                        consistent pattern. The only rationale we can provide is that they appear
                        "in areas of in- creasing tension, in major and minor climaxes." Cf. Cohen
                        (C199). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C186">
                    <bib> -----. "Yeats the Rhymer." Papers on English Language and Literature 1
                        (1965): 338- 50. </bib>
                    <notes>rpt as chapter 8 of his The Poetic Art of William Butler Yeats (B12).
                        Numerous examples of Yeats's virtuosity. His chief characteristics seem to
                        be a striking abundance of near-rhymes and a paucity of feminine rhymes. He
                        liked the naturalness and the slight dissonance of the slant rhyme, and the
                        particular emphasis and attention which it drew to the line-end: the rhymes
                        alone often carry a surprising amount of the poem's argument. And Yeats
                        developed his sure touch for the near-rhyme without any major, sustained
                        tradition for it be- hind him. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C187">
                    <bib> Biddle, Horace P. "Analysis of Rime." In his Prose Miscellany. Cincinatti:
                        R. Clarke &amp; Co., 1881. pp. 73-89. </bib>
                    <notes> Notices inconsistencies in the the rhyming dictionaries of Bysshe, John
                        Walker, and Tom Hood, then gives some phono-logical analysis of types of
                        rhyme. Biddle's principle is that rhyme is "no essential part of poetry, but
                        is a mere question of taste." He would allow all vowels to rhyme
                        interchangeably, as with the great range of harmonic chords possible in
                        music. Some final pages on music and rhyme in song. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C188">
                    <bib> Bieman, Elizabeth. "Comic Rhyme in Marlowe's Hero and Leander." nglish
                        Literary Renaissance 9 (1979): 69-77. </bib>
                    <notes> In part an inquiry into standards: on what grounds may we assume that
                        rhymes are intended as comic? On (1) wrenching of accent, (2) contrivance of
                        a string of monosyllabic words to fit a polysyllable (this is the principle
                        strategem in Byron as well as Marlowe), and (3) incongruities in diction,
                        register, meta- phor, or image. Source? Pulci and Ariosto. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C189">
                    <bib> Boos, Florence and William. "A Source for the Rimes of Poe's 'The Raven':
                        Elizabeth Barrett Browning's 'A Drama of Exile.'" Mary Wollstonecraft
                        Journal 2, 2 (1974): 30-31. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C190">
                    <bib> Brown, Huntington. "The Modern Development of Middle English -ly, -lie in
                        Rhyme." Harvard Studies and Notes in Philology and Literature 17 (1935):
                        43-45. </bib>
                    <notes> Surprisingly, the suffix -ly (from OE -lic(e)) has only rarely been
                        rhymed with the final vowel -e, unlike the -ly, -lie ending (from OF) which
                        is often rhymed with -i, sometimes also -e. This oddity suggests a very late
                        retention of secon- dary stress on the OE-derived -ly; instances such as
                        advisedly/be only appear in the ninteenth century. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C191">
                    <bib> Brownstein, Rachel M. "Byron's Don Juan: Some Reasons for the Rhymes." MLQ
                        28 (1967): 177-91. </bib>
                    <notes> Byron's "brilliant, outrageous" rhymes reveal an intense interest in the
                        word, contrary to Eliot's view, and they serve important ends: showing
                        "ingenious compliance with arbitrary laws"; presentation of "the alogical as
                        if it were logi- cal"; ironic or comic rhyme-yoking of dissimilar things;
                        and "tightening" of the constant, controlling octave stanza. Lively.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C192">
                    <bib> C., R. J. "Yeats's 'The Wild Swans at Coole.'" Explicator, 2, 4 (1944) </bib>
                    <notes>, question 20. Inquires as to the poet's pronunciation of the rhymes in
                        this poem and in "Under the Round Tower." Answers supplied in 3, 1 (1944),
                        item 5 and 3, 2 (1944), item 17. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C193">
                    <bib> Carpenter, Frederic I. "Emily Dickinson and the Rhymes of Dream."
                        University of Kansas City Review 20 (1953): 113-20. </bib>
                    <notes> E. D. used imperfect rhymes to indicate the tensions of fantasy vs.
                        reality, life vs. death, and beauty vs. banality. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C194">
                    <bib> Chapman, R. W. "On Rhyme." The Portrait of a Scholar and other Essays.
                        London: Oxford University Press, 1920. pp. 28-39. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C195">
                    <bib> Clark, Arthur Melville. "The Difficulty of Rhyming." In his Studies in
                        Literary Modes. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1946. pp. 166-77. </bib>
                    <notes> A more abstract meditation on the nature of language as the metier of
                        poetry, with its inherent constraints for thinking, verbalizing, and the
                        making of po- ems. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C196">
                    <bib> -----. "Rhyme and No Rhyme." In his Studies in Literary Modes. Edinburgh:
                        Oliver and Boyd, 1946. pp. 178-210. </bib>
                    <notes> A discursive general review of the uses and effects, chiefly in English
                        but also in the continental languages, both ancient and modern. Judges the
                        appropri- ateness of rhyme for various poetic genres and types--e.g.,
                        narrative, dramatic, lyric, philosophical. Historically informed (there is a
                        long digression on Dry- den). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C197">
                    <bib> Clark, Arthur Melville, and Harold Whitehall. "Rhyme." Princeton (A18),
                        pp. 705-10. </bib>
                    <notes> A very cogent review essay taking an international perspective and
                        treating Nature and Functions then History. See also s.v. "Perfect Rhyme,"
                        "Near Rhyme," "Rime Riche," "Initial Rhyme," "Eye Rhyme," "Rhyme-
                        Counterpoint," "Rhyme Scheme," and the more general essay "Sound in Po-
                        etry" (C85). Then see L159. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C198">
                    <bib> Clark, Elizabeth M. "A Study of Rhymes in Browning." Poet-Lore 2 (1890):
                        480-86. </bib>
                    <notes> For those interested, there are 34,746 rhymes in the Riverside edition
                        of Browning; Clark thinks 322 (1%) of them "bad"--i.e., "imperfect" or
                        "forced." And many of these are apparently used in only a few poems to
                        present or de- scribe "rough, odd, uneducated, or unbalanced characters."
                        Cf. C282. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C199">
                    <bib> Cohen, Michael. "Rhyme in Samson Agonistes." Milton Quarterly 8 (1974):
                        4-6. </bib>
                    <notes> Cohen notes some of the functions of rhyme and near-rhyme in the play
                        but can offer little to add to Beum (C185): and certainly no new or cogent
                        expla- nation. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C200">
                    <bib> Colman, Elizabeth L. "The Sense of Sounds: An Investigation of Verbal
                        Music in Shakespeare's Late Plays." DAI 33 (1972): 270A (George Washington). </bib>
                    <notes> Treats five types of "verbal music": musical structure, sound effects,
                        song, rhyme, and use of prose. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C201">
                    <bib> Combs, Bruce E. "A Linguistic Analysis of Rime with Studies in Chaucer,
                        Donne, and Pope." DAI 30 (1970): 4963A (Oregon). </bib>
                    <notes> The traditional typology and taxonomy for rhyme are too inexact, cumber-
                        some, and inconsistent to be serviceable. From a phonological point of view,
                        the rhyme-structure begins with the core syllable and generates therefrom
                        to- ward the right, allowing for stress-shift. Combs examines the historical
                        pro- nunciation of final -e in Chaucer and the rhyme-pair -y/ -ie in Donne,
                        as well as variation of rhyming precision in Pope. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C202">
                    <bib> Cook, A. S. "English Rimes." MLN 3 (1888): cols. 417-25. </bib>
                    <notes> Discussion and inventory of the thousand or so triplet-rhymes in Rose's
                        early- nineteenth-century translation of Ariosto. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C203">
                    <bib> Covington, Dale R. "'Echo to the Sense.': A Study of Semantic Elements in
                        Pope's Rime." DA 28 (1968): 4121A (Vanderbilt). </bib>
                    <notes> As a correlate to the "counterlogical" rhymes in Pope described so
                        incisively by Wimsatt, Covington describes an even more prevalent type, the
                        rhymes "which are so semantically coordinated with [Pope's] verse logic that
                        they stand as glosses, direct or oblique, upon his couplet sense," producing
                        an effect of semantic miniaturization of couplet logic within the rhyme
                        words. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C204">
                    <bib> De Selincourt, B. "Rhyme in English Poetry." Essays and Studies 7 (1921):
                        7-29. </bib>
                    <notes> A very illuminating discussion of the nature of rhyme in English verse;
                        perhaps the best part of the essay is the comparison (pp. 10-12) between
                        English, Clas- sical, and French verse-structures as they allow for and
                        encourage--or discour- age--rhymes. Rhyme in English is "readily dispensed
                        with" even though its main function is to "reinforce accent"; hence "the art
                        of versification in Eng- lish might almost be summed up in the one
                        word--compensation." "The deli- cacies and intricacies of the subject" are
                        indeed "inexhaustible." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C205">
                    <bib> Dewey, Thomas B. "Some 'Careless' Seventeenth-Century Rhymes." Bulletin of
                        the New York Public Library 69 (1965): 143-52. </bib>
                    <notes> Curious whether John Cleveland made appropriate or "careless" (rough)
                        rhymes, Dewey examines seventeenth-century and modern authorities on
                        pronunciation, then compares Cleveland to Cowley, Crashaw, Vaughan, and
                        Waller. All five turn out to be careful and conventional in their rhyming.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C206">
                    <bib> Diekhoff, John S. "Rhyme in Paradise Lost." PMLA 49 (1934):539-43. </bib>
                    <notes> Citations of rhymes: there are seventeen couplets, forty-five rhymes
                        separated by one line, fifty-two separated by two, and twenty-seven by
                        three, over twenty instances of "caesural rhyme" (words just before the
                        caesura in succes- sive lines), and several internal rhymes. Additional
                        citations are provided by Purcell (C271). See also Oras (C263). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C207">
                    <bib> Dobrée, Bonamy. "An Experiment with Rhyme." Life and Letters 10 (1934):
                        66-72. </bib>
                    <notes> What happens when rhyme is added to blank verse, or deducted from rhymed
                        verse? Even allowing for slight divergences in sense, does echo of ending
                        im- prove verse, or not? Several experimental transformations suggest that:
                        (1) the better the poem, the less it needs rhyme, (2) lyrics need rhyme but
                        metaphysi- cal poems do not, and (3) rhyme can intensify poetic effect.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C208">
                    <bib> Dodge, R. E. Neil. "An Obsolete Elizabethan Mode of Rhyming." Shakespeare
                        Studies by Members of the Department of English of the University of
                        Wisconsin. Madison: University of Wisconsin, 1916. pp. 174-200. </bib>
                    <notes> Rhyming a stressed final syllable (masculine ending) with an unstressed
                        double or triple one (feminine). Examples from Chaucer to Chapman. The
                        author's rather feeble grasp of Elizabethan pronunciation and stressing
                        obviates a num- ber of his examples. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C209">
                    <bib> Eckhardt, Eduard. "Lord Byrons komische Reime." Englische Studien 70
                        (1935): 198-208. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C210">
                    <bib> Fehse, Klaus-Dieter. Die Reimtechnik im Elisabethanischen Vers-drama.
                        Salzburg Studies in English Literature, Elizabethan Studies, vol. 12, no. 3.
                        Salzburg: Institute für engslische Sprache und Literature, Universität
                        Salzburg, 1973. </bib>
                    <notes> Based on his dissertation at Saarbrücken in 1969, "Der Reim und seine
                        Funktion im englischen Drama vor 1600." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C211">
                    <bib> French, Roberts W. "Rhyme and the Chorus of Sampson Agonistes." Laurel
                        Review 10 (1970): 60-67. </bib>
                    <notes> Two functions are served by the rhymes of the Chorus's speeches: one is
                        ironic, undercutting their credibility ("they state their confusions in
                        assured rhymes, as though they were speaking imperishable truths"); the
                        other occurs at the conclusion, conveying a sense of wisdom gained,
                        finality, and tranquility. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C212">
                    <bib> Fussell, Paul, Jr. "A Note on 'The Windhover.'" MLN 64 (1949): 271. </bib>
                    <notes> Samuel Chew's objection to the "ugliness" of the run-over "king-/dom . .
                        . riding" rhyme should be mitigated by the fact that the rhyme helps fulfil
                        the regular Petrarchan scheme, which Chew apparently failed to notice. But
                        one could perceive the scheme quite clearly and still judge the rhyme a
                        strained one; Fussell's comment is irrelevant. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C213">
                    <bib> Garrod, H. W. "Aberration in Rhyme." TLS, 14 April 1927, p. 265. </bib>
                    <notes> Notes instances of apparent manual or mental slips in rhyming; Spenser
                        for ex- ample rhymes play with support and resort, but the first of these
                        clearly should be sport. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C214">
                    <bib> Gates, Norman T. "Orthographical Rhyme Forms in the Works of Samuel
                        Rowlands." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 76 (1975): 77-87. </bib>
                    <notes> This poet (1570-1630) manipulated variant spellings shamelessly,
                        idiosyncrati- cally, and inconsistently in order to achieve eye-rhymes. Many
                        examples. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C215">
                    <bib> Geokjian, Gregory F. "The Function and Effect of Rhyme." DAI 31 (1971):
                        4714A (Pittsburgh). </bib>
                    <notes> An inductive approach to The Rape of the Lock, Paradise Lost, and Hugh
                        Selwyn Mauberley. "The primary function of rhyme is the creation of
                        meaning." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C216">
                    <bib> Gostusky, Dragutin. "The Third Dimension of Poetic Expression or Language
                        and Harmony." Musical Quarterly 55 (1969): 372-83. </bib>
                    <notes> Valéry thought that language--given its serial, linear syntactic
                        structure--could never equal the simultaneously multivalent communication
                        system that is mu- sic, but the finely honed, close reasoning here may
                        indeed persuade us that "poetry has all of the elements of musical melody"
                        (in the acoustic-tonal structure of its phonemes) and "the richness of
                        musical tone-colors, the logic of cadence, the subtlety of modulation, and
                        the symbolic values of harmony" (in rhyme). The history of rhyme is mapped
                        out, and considerable importance is placed on the visual effect of rhymes
                        (i.e. as vertical structures). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C217">
                    <bib> Graves, Robert. "Rhyme." In his The Common Asphodel. London: Hamish
                        Hamilton, 1949. pp. 5-6. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C218">
                    <bib> Haid, Karl. Der Spaltreim in der englischen Literatur des XIX.
                        Jahrhundrets. Diss., Heidelberg, 1912. 137 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>[This must mean "split" rhyme, since he instances both mosaic (two
                        monosyl- lables with a disyll.) and double rhyme, i.e. bound me/sound me. At
                        Chicago, PE1076 or so] </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C219">
                    <bib> Hayes, James J. "A Rime-Index to Marlowe's Poems and Plays, With
                        Conclusions Therefrom." Diss.; University of Iowa, 1939. Abstracted as "A
                        Study of Marlowe's Rimes" in University of Iowa Doctoral Dissertations,
                        Abstracts, and References 3 (1943): 256-61. </bib>
                    <notes> Lists extensive data on the probable sounds of Marlowe's vowels; he
                        seems to have spoken a Kentish dialect. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C220">
                    <bib> Herbert, T. Walter. "The Grammar of Rimes." Sewanee Review 48 (1940):
                        362-77. </bib>
                    <notes> Good rhymes, like living things, are mixed equally, as Donne might have
                        said- -equally of inevitability and of vigorous novelty. Syntactic variety
                        is indispen- sable. Herbert tabulates the distribution of syntactic
                        categories in the rhymes of fifty poems in iambic pentameter couplets by
                        fifteen major poets and then "grades" the results (by three different sets
                        of criteria). Browning shows great- est variety, followed by Chaucer and
                        Pope; Keats and Swinburne show great- est monotony. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C221">
                    <bib> -----. "Near-Rhymes and Paraphones." Sewanee Review 45 (1937): 433-52. </bib>
                    <notes> An apologia, with side-glances at Ransom and Dickinson. Paraphony is
                        defined as the "modulation between two dissimilar sounds" in a run of
                        rhymes. Link- rhyme is a run of three rhymes, the second picking up the
                        first consonant and the third the last consonant of the first.
                        Dissonance-consonance preserves the vowel sound though both initial and
                        final consonants change. In suspended rhyme the final consonants are the
                        same no matter what precedes them and re- gardless of whether accented or
                        not. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C222">
                    <bib> Hibberd, Dominic. "Wilfred Owen's Rhyming." Studia Neophilological 50
                        (1978): 207-14. </bib>
                    <notes> Owen was the first English poet to use pararhyme (repetition of both
                        initial and final consonantal sounds in the rhyming syllable--i.e. C1 V2 C1)
                        at line-end throughout an entire poem. He devised the technique by himself
                        and first em- ployed it in 1917, using it strictly in the beginning but
                        relaxing somewhat by 1918, the year of his best work. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C223">
                    <bib> Hill, Archibald A. "A Phonological Description of Poetic Ornaments."
                        Language and Style 2 (1969): 99-123. </bib>
                    <notes> A formulation in linguistic terms of the conditions for both true- and
                        near- rhyme in English verse, with extensive simplified phonetic
                        explanations; sum- mary on pp. 114-15. Various deviant forms are also
                        treated, though many of these are obviated by mere variances in
                        pronunciation. In contrast to rhyme, alliteration, assonance, and repetition
                        prove relatively easy to define (pp. 116, 117, 119). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C224">
                    <bib> Hollander, John. "Rhyme and the True Calling of Words." In his Vision and
                        Resonance (A13), pp. 117-34. </bib>
                    <notes> A lambent excursus on the manifold ends of rhyme. There is something
                        here for everyone: those who must insist on precision will find a
                        clean-well-lighted anatomy of functions and effects (mnemonic, schematic
                        [structural], musical [textural], and semantic); those solaced by lands yet
                        unexplored will be able to map out the entire region of sound-to-spelling
                        relations that Hollander ges- tures toward; those (readers of the present
                        book) desperate for amusement will be delighted by Hollander's feats of
                        etymological legerdemain; those energized by polarities will be attracted to
                        his rhyme-distance continuum; those of lapi- dary inclination will value his
                        foils for the rare occasional rhyme. Altogether, the crucial features of
                        rhyme turn out to be accentuation and sequential order. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C225">
                    <bib> Howard, Dorothy G. "Folk Jingles of American Children: A Collection and
                        Study of Rhymes Used By Children Today." Diss., New York University, 1939. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C226">
                    <bib> Hussey, Richard. "A Note on Pope's Homer: ii, The Rhymes." Notes &amp;
                        Queries 187 (1944): 278. </bib>
                    <notes> Notes the exceptions to true rhyme (mono- or disyllabic words with final
                        syl- lable fully accented). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C227">
                    <bib> Johnson, Marsue M. "The Well-Rimed Daniel: An Examination of Delia and A
                        Defense of Ryme." DA 26 (1966): 4661A (Arkansas). </bib>
                    <notes>Mainly thematic, but some attention to rhyme, quantitative meters, and
                        syntax. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C228">
                    <bib> Johnson, William C. "Rhyme and Repetition in Spenser's Amoretti." Xavier
                        University Studies 9 (1970): 15-25. </bib>
                    <notes> These two devices are used to establish semantic connections,
                        relationships, and matrices not only within the lines of each sonnet but,
                        more importantly, between the sonnets in the sequence. Patterning of "key
                        words" even more than rhymes implies the intentionality of both the order
                        and the unity of the sequence. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C229">
                    <bib> Kellett, E. E. "Rhyme and Reason." The Spectator 155 (1935): 544-45. </bib>
                    <notes> Emphasizing the restrictiveness of having to search out a rhyme for the
                        poet who aims for a perfected articulation, Kellett argues further that easy
                        and banal rhymes become frozen into the language of a nation, corrupting the
                        "national character" and thought with a clutter of trivialized echoes.
                        "Words associated in rhyme become inextricably associated in thought."
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C230">
                    <bib> Kennedy, X. J. "Rime." New York Quarterly, no. 6 (1971), pp. 128-33. </bib>
                    <notes> "Writing in rime is like wearing a hairshirt: it irritates your skin, it
                        mortifies the hell out of you." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C231">
                    <bib> Kenner, Hugh. "Pope's Reasonable Rhymes." ELH 41 (1974): 74-88. </bib>
                    <notes> Not only do the most common rhymes seem the most obvious and facile,
                        they also suggest certain predetermined, necessary, invariable semantic
                        relationships in the language or even, almost, in the world beyond
                        referential language; "every real language, every language accessible to
                        poets, affirms hints of a shattered perfection. Order, congruence, universal
                        truths, these a poet might hint at by careful exploitation of such few
                        congruous rhymes as his tongue placed at his disposal." Pope was a master at
                        this, especially in The Rape of the Lock, but a further beguiling sidelight
                        on the whole issue appears in the pecu- liar artifical languages devised by
                        Bishop Wilkins and others and so faddish in the eighteenth century. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C232">
                    <bib> Knowlton, Edgar C. "Sir Philip Sidney on Italian Rhymes." Notes &amp;
                        Queries 214 (1969): 455-56. </bib>
                    <notes> Sidney's claim in the Defense that Italian has no masculine rhymes is
                        false. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C233">
                    <bib> Körtge, Woldemar. Über die Reimtechnik bei Robert Burns. Diss., Göttingen,
                        1922. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C234">
                    <bib> Koretz, Gene H. "The Rhyme Scheme in Herbert's 'Man.'" Notes &amp; Queries
                        201 (1956): 144-46. </bib>
                    <notes> "Of the 169 poems in The Temple, 'Man' is the only one in which the
                        rhyme scheme is consistently varied in stanzas of equal length," but Koretz
                        finds a motivation for its rhyme-scheme in some aspects of Renaissance
                        cosmology and Christian doctrine. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C235">
                    <bib> Krueger, John R. "On the Rimes in Nursery Rimes." Southern Folklore
                        Quarterly 31 (1967): 291-95. </bib>
                    <notes> Application of dialectology and historical phonology to explicate many
                        of the seemingly improbable rhymes. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C236">
                    <bib> Krumm, Hermann. Die Verwendung des Reims in dem Blankvers des englischen
                        Dramas zur Zeit Shakespeare's, 1561-1616. Leipzig, 1889. </bib>
                    <notes> Part 1: "Der Reim in dem fünfüssigen Jambus des vor-Shake-speareschen
                        Dramas." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C237">
                    <bib> Lake, D. J. "Rhymes in Pericles." Notes &amp; Queries 214 (1969): 139-43. </bib>
                    <notes> Assonance in the place of true rhyme is extremely rare in Shakespeare,
                        but its frequency in Pericles and a comparable usage in a contemporary play,
                        The Tra- vailes of Three English Brothers, when analyzed in detail, suggests
                        that one of the co-authors, George Wilkins, was the author of a considerable
                        portion of Peri- cles. Metrical evidence is also examined. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C238">
                    <bib> Landrum, Grace W. "More Concerning Chapman's Homer and Keats." PMLA 42
                        (1927): 986-1009. </bib>
                    <notes> Mainly on rhyme and diction; metrics is set aside with the observation
                        that Keats did not follow Chapman's septenaries. A very minute examination
                        of Keats's lax and Chapman's utterly wanton rhyme-practice ensues; since
                        Keats could not have known what we know of Elizabethan pronunciation,
                        doubtless he found Chapman's liberties extreme, but in general his own
                        excesses are his own. Chapman's influence has perhaps been overrated.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C239">
                    <bib> Lanz, Henry. "The Physical Basis of Rime." PMLA 41 (1926): 1011-23. </bib>
                    <notes> An early draft of his later monograph: </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C240">
                    <bib> -----. The Physical Basis of Rime: An Essay on the Aesthetics of Sound.
                        Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1931; rpt Westport, Conn.: Greenwood
                        Press, 1968; 365 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Rev: in TLS, 14 May 1931, p. 384; by Baum in South Atlantic Quarterly 30
                        (1931): 327-29; in Review of English Studies 8 (1932): 357-59; in
                        Philosophical Review 42 (1933): 636-38. This hefty volume was originally
                        conceived as an inquiry into the acoustical- phonetic basis of rhyming, and
                        experimental researches were indeed carried out. But the results is more
                        discursive than anything else, Lanz rarely de- scending to specific
                        analysis. However, the work is by no means limited solely to English poetry;
                        Lanz makes every effort to be truly comparative in method. Chapter 6
                        discusses rhythm, 8, free verse. Perhaps the most useful chapter to us now
                        is 5, which outlines a number of major theories about the nature of rhyme.
                        But there are valuable examples throughout, and the Bibliography is also
                        noteworthy. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C241">
                    <bib> LePage, P. V. "Some Reasons for Rhyme in 'Musée des Beaux Arts.'" Yearbook
                        of English Studies 3 (1972): 243-48. </bib>
                    <notes> Just as life contains "random episodes of suffering, so the poem has its
                        random episodes of rhyme." And the metrical movement in the poem--from "good
                        prose almost seeming to carry out the threat of order" to a faint, ambiguous
                        pattern of mixed rising meters--parallels the movement on the thematic level
                        of quotidian events, from free choice to determinism. Somewhat muddled.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C242">
                    <bib> Levins, Peter. Manipulus Vocabulorum. A Dictionarie of English and Latine
                        wordes, set forthe in suche order, as none heretofore hath ben, the
                        "Englishe" going before the "Latine," necessary not onely for Scholers that
                        want varietie of words, but also for such as use to write in English Meter.
                        London, 1570. Ed. Henry B. Wheatley. Early English Texts Society, Original
                        Series, no. 27. London: Trübner, 1867. </bib>
                    <notes> This is the first rhyming dictionary to appear in English. Wheatley
                        provides a useful short Preface, corrections (there were many errata), and
                        an alphabetical Index longer than Levins's original, which is organized
                        (roughly) according to the order of the vowels, and includes short phrases
                        as well as single words. See Weisker (C312). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C243">
                    <bib> L[oane], G[eorge] G. "Final s Disregarded in Rhyme." Notes &amp; Queries
                        173 (1937): 98, 448; 176 (1938): 214; 186 (1944): 27. </bib>
                    <notes> Cites several examples and suggests that fastidious printers may have
                        altered many more. Cf. these notes with another in TLS, 15 January 1938, p.
                        44 enti- tled "Final -s in Rhyme," where he cites examples of plurals which
                        "spoil" the rhyme. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C244">
                    <bib> Loesch, Katharine T. "The Shape of Sound: Configurational Rime in the
                        Poetry of Dylan Thomas." Speech Monographs 35 (1968): 407-24; </bib>
                    <notes>expanded and rpt in </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C245">
                    <bib> Studies in Interpretation. Ed. Esther M. Doyle and V. H. Floyd. Amsterdam:
                        Rodopi N.V., 1972. pp. 33-66. </bib>
                    <notes> "Configurational" rhyme is defined on p. 36, for those who prefer a
                        paragraph to a mere adjective such as "polysyllablic" or "permutational." An
                        exceedingly elaborate anatomy of "After the Funeral" is performed
                        thereafter, but this ap- proach shows not the slightest sign of utility,
                        much less heuristics, except for the interesting schematic on p. 52. Spatial
                        deployment is a useful means of de- noting complex sonal "family
                        resemblances." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C246">
                    <bib> Maas, P. "A Note on F. Simpson's Statement." MLR 39 (1944): 179. </bib>
                    <notes> Confirms that Shakespeare avoided rhyming a masculine with a feminine
                        ending. Cf. 291 and C295. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C247">
                    <bib> McEuen, Kathryn A. "Emerson's Rhymes." American Literature 20 (1948):
                        31-42. </bib>
                    <notes> Though Emerson wrote many admittedly defective rhymes, he also wrote a
                        great many perfect rhymes in complex patterns; perhaps, then, he should be
                        seen as a pioneer in rhyming voiced and unvoiced consonants, visual rhymes,
                        and "suspended" (slant) rhymes. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C248">
                    <bib> -----. "Whittier's Rhymes." American Speech 20 (1945): 51-57. </bib>
                    <notes> Recollection of Whittier's New England pronunciation will legitimize
                        some of his rhymes, and though admittedly both his ear and education were
                        deficient, his derelictions seem more the result of indulging freedoms hoary
                        with age in English poetry than any simple, personal, desperate groping for
                        a rhyme. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C249">
                    <bib> McLean, L. Mary. "The Riming System of Alexander Pope." PMLA 6 (1891):
                        134-60. </bib>
                    <notes> Mainly an index of masculine, feminine, and false rhymes in Pope, but a
                        fre- quency-of-occurrence list is also given. Of 7874 rhymes, 6847 are true,
                        6732 being masculine, and 115 feminine. Of the 1027 false rhymes 379 are eye
                        rhymes. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C250">
                    <bib> Marsh, George P. Lectures on the English Language, First Series. New York:
                        Charles Scribner's Sons, 1859; 4th ed. rev. and enlarged, 1863. pp. 499-570. </bib>
                    <notes> In Lectures 23, 24, and 25, Marsh makes the case in full for the old
                        view that English, being a positional rather than an inflectional language,
                        suffers a pau- city of rhyme words. Taking, then, a very broad purview, he
                        urges a return to the devices of the archaic Anglo-Saxon
                        poetry--alliteration, assonance, conso- nance, internal rhyme--as well as a
                        wider employment of Romance and Lati- nate words. Also sketched is the
                        history of accent-shift in English. Final note: in Marsh (p. 553) one can
                        see the clearest example of the semantic shift in the term consonance during
                        the last century. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C251">
                    <bib> Matthews, J. Brander. "An Inquiry as to Rhyme." The Bookman 8 (1898):
                        32-38. </bib>
                    <notes> Citing Herbert Spencer's Principle of Economy of Attention, Matthews ex-
                        amines the conventional dictum that although many rhymes are not techni-
                        cally perfect still they are "allowable" (in contrast to some others, less
                        exact, which would be simply inadmissable), rejecting that idea entirely.
                        Conserva- tive, he judges that if a rhyme be not white it must be black.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C252">
                    <bib> -----. "Rhyme and Reason." The Galaxy 18 (1874): 618-24. </bib>
                    <notes> Observations and examples of end-rhymes, complex internal rhyming, worn-
                        out rhymes, bouts rimés (given the rhyme scheme, can you fill out the lines?
                        interesting specimen of a remanufactured Byron stanza here), extravagances,
                        and impossible rhymes (month, silver, chimney, orange; coffee lees with
                        Mephi- stopheles??). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C253">
                    <bib> Maynard, Theodore. "The Reason for Rhyme." The Freeman 8 (1924): 469-70. </bib>
                    <notes> An urbane defense of its difficulty and value. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C254">
                    <bib> Miller, Edwin S. "Rime Counterpoint." Annali Instituto Universitario
                        Orientale, Napoli, Sezione Germanica 2 (1959): 187-90. </bib>
                    <notes> The "counterpointing" arises from varying the vowel sounds of the rimes
                        while holding the final consonants identical through them all, or vice
                        versa. Many varieties of the phenomenon, with many examples. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C255">
                    <bib> Miller, J. Hillis. "The Linguistic Moment in 'The Wreck of the
                        Deutschland.'" The New Criticism and After: John Crowe Ransom Memorial
                        Lectures. Ed. Thomas D. Young. Charlottesville: University of Virginia
                        Press, 1976. pp. 47-60. </bib>
                    <notes> "Linguistic moment" meaning that point at which "language as such . . .
                        be- comes a matter to be interrogated, explored, thematized in itself."
                        Language qua language was crucial to Hopkins because the structure of
                        languages was derived from the divine Logos, even as Nature was derived from
                        the Godhead; therefore, "everything else, his vision of nature and the self
                        in their relations to God, hangs on the question of the nature of language."
                        So too the nature of rhyme--similarity-within-difference--becomes a metaphor
                        for the relation of man to God, and hence a central focus of this central
                        poem. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C256">
                    <bib> -----. "The Univocal Chiming." In his The Disappearance of God: Five
                        Nineteenth- Century Writers. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press,
                        1963. pp. 276- 317; </bib>
                    <notes>rpt in Hopkins: A Collection of Critical Essays. Ed. Geoffrey H. Hartman.
                        Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall, 1966. pp. 89-116. An exposition of
                        Hopkins' beliefs and practices in rhyme. Since rhyme gener- ally finds the
                        subtly similiar in otherwise-dissimilar things, it may be seen as a general
                        and metaphysical principle. "There is one possible mode of harmony and only
                        one. By gradually extending the empire of this principle, Hopkins puts the
                        world together, escapes his isolation, and conquers that proximity to God
                        for which he longs." The harmony of all things in the world is found in
                        their rhyming, and thus the complete extension of this principle into every
                        corner of versification is "the fundamental method of Hopkins' poetry." Ex-
                        tended analysis of "Pied Beauty." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C257">
                    <bib> Monk. "Should a Poet Be a Philologist?" MLN 3 (1888): col. 469. </bib>
                    <notes> On the legitimacy of the rhyme-word twat in Browning. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C258">
                    <bib> Nemoianu, Virgil. "Levels of Study in the Semantics of Rhyme." Style 5
                        (1971): 246-64. </bib>
                    <notes> A purely phonetic analysis of rhyme is markedly inferior to a semantic
                        analysis; in a semantic typology of rhyme three levels are discernible: (1)
                        on the diffuse level one perceives the "channeling" from the sonorous
                        stratum to the seman- tic stratum which the rhyme effects, and one can
                        distinguish degrees of rhymedness in poems; (2) on the vertical level the
                        rhyme establishes the princi- ples of recurrence and analogy wherein each
                        rhyme-couple, by generating a narrow "framework" of semantic oppositions or
                        categories, constructs one part of the stylistic-semantic field comprised by
                        the whole text. (3) on the horizontal level the chief effect of the presence
                        of a rhyme is "the disintegration of word- order." In terms of content, four
                        situations obtain: (1) the classical rhyme suggests semantic similarity via
                        sonal; (2) ironic rhyme reverses that direction; (3) sub- stantial rhyme
                        controls the ordering of content within the line by its inherent semantic
                        weight or "brilliance"; (4) secondary rhymes, by contrast, are unob-
                        strusive and weak. These four content relationships correspond to the four
                        functions of rhyme--(1) Demarcation between lines, (2) Break of syntactic
                        or- der, (3) establishment of Parallelism, and (4) Cementation of the
                        aesthetic ob- ject--in the following manner: (secondary = ) D
                        &lt;------------&gt; P ( = classical) | | (substantial = ) B
                        &lt;------------&gt; C ( = ironic) The first two functions are diremptive,
                        the latter two cohesive. Breaking op- poses Cementation as Demarcation
                        opposes Parallelism, while Demarcation is reinforced by Breaking and
                        Parallelism by Cementing (fusion). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C259">
                    <bib> -----. "Swift si istoria rimei engleze." Revista de Istorie si Teorie
                        Literara 16 (1967): 441-48. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C260">
                    <bib> Ness, Frederic W. The Use of Rhyme in Shakespeare's Plays. Yale Studies in
                        English, vol. 95. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1941. 168 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Based on his dissertation of the same title at Yale in 1940. Rev: by J.
                        W. Draper in MLN 57 (1942): 379-80; in JEGP 42 (1943): 587-89; in MLR 38
                        (1943): 50-51; see also Tannenbaum (C305). Still the best available study on
                        the nature (types), distribution, and causes for the decline of rhyme in
                        Shakespeare. (For a definition of the ten varieties of rhyme isolated here
                        and a catalogue of all occurrences in the canon go directly to Appendix B.)
                        Ness concludes that Shakespeare decreased his reliance on rhyme not in
                        response to any contemporary critical or theatrical fashion but because as
                        he matured he came to see its effects as distinctly limited (mainly to
                        augmentation and to clinching or tying off a speech or scene). See also
                        chapter 5 and Appendix C for an analysis of metrical variation, rhyme forms,
                        and structure in the couplets of each play. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C261">
                    <bib> Newcomer, Alphonso G. "License in English Rhyme." The Nation 68 (1899):
                        63- 65, 83-85. </bib>
                    <notes> As if there were some question of permissibility or decorum, Newcomer
                        de- fends the use of off-rhyme. Examples. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C262">
                    <bib> "On the Use of Rhyme." The Dublin Inquisitor 1 (1821): 249-55. </bib>
                    <notes> Approbation for its use, and a thumbnail history as well. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C263">
                    <bib> Oras, Ants. "Echoing Verse Endings in Paradise Lost." South Atlantic
                        Studies for S. E. Leavitt. Ed. Thomas B. Stroup and Sterling A. Stoudemire.
                        Washington, D. C.: Scarecrow Press, 1953. pp. 175-90. </bib>
                    <notes> A landmark study which takes its origin in the data of Diekhoff (C206)
                        and then proceeds to demonstrate that end-rhyme in Paradise Lost is merely
                        part of a larger, firmer, more complex, more subtle pattern, "a
                        co-ordinated, highly organized treatment of terminal phonetic echoes" which
                        Milton learned from Italian versi sciolti. Oras gives a detailed analysis of
                        phonic patterning in Paradise Lost, Book I ll. 1-83. and ll. 547-62, and
                        Book VI, ll. 56-74. Such proof of Milton's attention to the ends of his
                        verses implies that he had a firm sense of the line as metrical unit, as
                        well as the verse-paragraph. Finally, his echoing technique may also be
                        considered the "assonantal equivalent of his rhyming technique in Lycidas."
                        Cf. Pohjola (C270). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C264">
                    <bib> -----. "Intensified Rhyme Links in the Faerie Queene: An Aspect of
                        Elizabethan Rhymecraft." JEGP 54 (1955): 39-60. </bib>
                    <notes> This essay should be a full counterweight to the prosodic platitude that
                        identi- cal rhyme or rime riche is a technical fault: Oras identifies three
                        groups of fifteen types and one miscellaneous group of five principal types
                        of "phonetic corre- spondences preceding the lst metrically stressed vowel,"
                        then gives a detailed typological and statistical analysis of each. Oras
                        more than amply makes his point that Spencer considered multiple
                        correspondences a richening of the aural texture of his verse. Orderly,
                        sensitive, elaborate, undogmatic analysis. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C265">
                    <bib> -----. "Milton's Early Rhyme Schemes and the Structure of Lycidas." MP 52
                        (1954): 12-22. </bib>
                    <notes> Seeking to revise the older view of Miltonic rhyming as desultory and
                        vestig- ial, Oras documents a "calculated complexity" of rhyme
                        architechtonics in Ly- cidas; the poem varies its verse paragraphs,
                        subpatterns of rhyme, strategies of experimentation, and structural
                        "blurring" with artful sprezzatura, each para- graph imitating in its
                        crescendo movement the movement of the poem as a whole. Milton seems to have
                        learned these devices in his study of Italian verse, especially Tasso's
                        pastoral drama Il Rogo di Corinna and the Italian madrigal. Df. Wittreich
                        (C318). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C266">
                    <bib> Pace, George B. "On the Octave Rhymes of 'The Windhover.'" English
                        Language Notes 2 (1965): 285-86. </bib>
                    <notes> Though the eight terminal words in the octave rhyme aaaaaaaa, if one
                        exam- ines the stress-pattern of the repeating -ing endings, one finds it to
                        be /xx//xx/, or, by analogy, the Petrarchan abbaabba. This brilliant
                        strategy "pre- vents the effect of identical rhyme." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C267">
                    <bib> Pendlebury, B. J. The Art of the Rhyme. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons,
                        1971. 107 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Calling itself "a comparatively slight study," this book focuses on the
                        functions of rhyme ("pointing" and "binding"). Not a historical approach.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C268">
                    <bib> Perloff, Marjorie. Rhyme and Meaning in the Poetry of Yeats. The Hague:
                        Mouton, 1970. 249 pp </bib>
                    <notes>Based on her dissertation, DA 26 (1965): 6721A. Rev: in Georgia Review 26
                        (1972): 249-78; in University of Toronto Quarterly 41 (1972): 263-74; in MP
                        69 (1971): 87-91. The work consists of roughly 150 pages of text and 100
                        pages of appended ta- bles of forms and statistics. Similar to Dougherty
                        (D273) yet considerably denser in both fact and generalization, Perloff's
                        work is invaluable for the study of semantic patterning in rhyme. Of the 386
                        poems in the Variorum Yeats, only 16 are in blank verse, and as Delmore
                        Schwartz noticed, rhymecraft was apparently indispensable for Yeats's
                        creativity. Perloff establishes some ten se- mantic categories of rhyme
                        (open to some question, I think), which allow her to explore the strategies
                        of advance and development which rhymes provided Yeats in the writing of a
                        poem. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C269">
                    <bib> Pettigrew, Richard C. "Poe's Rime." American Literature 4 (1932): 151-59. </bib>
                    <notes> Poe's actual practice in rhyming was flagrantly inconsistent with his
                        critical dicta censuring "license." He often resorted to slant rhyme,
                        variance of pro- nunciations, contrived proper names, rich rhymes, and heavy
                        internal rhyme. But most distressing of all is the "fundamental poverty" of
                        his rhymes, so glar- ingly obvious, expected, and repetitious. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C270">
                    <bib> Pohjola, Eeva. "Echoing Verse Endings in Milton's Poetry." Diss.,
                        University of Helsinki, 1964. Cf. Oras (C263). </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C271">
                    <bib> Purcell, J. M. "Rime in Paradise Lost." MLN 59 (1944): 171-72. Additions
                        to Diekhoff (C206). </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C272">
                    <bib> Reid, S. W. "Composotorial Spelling and Literal Rhyme: The Example of
                        Jaggard's B." The Library, 5th series, vol. 30 (1975): 108-15. </bib>
                    <notes> It is fairly clear that compositor B, at least, sometimes altered the
                        spellings of rhymes in his copy-text (quarto) for similarity of orthography
                        as well as of sound. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C273">
                    <bib> "Rhyme nor Reason." Notes &amp; Queries, series 3, vol. 10 (1866): 67,
                        116-17, 236. </bib>
                    <notes> Suggested etymologies. Cf. Rankin (E74). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C274">
                    <bib> Richardson, Charles F. "Morals of the Rhyming Dictionary." Yale Review,
                        n.s. 2 (1912-13): 269-81. </bib>
                    <notes> The author's original intent of showing "the perversion of sense for the
                        sake of the rhyme," due to the paucity of useful rhymes in English turns
                        into a peram- bulating review of successes and failures in a number of
                        Classical, Romance, and English poets. Also Shakespeare's pronunciation.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C275">
                    <bib> -----. A Study of English Rhyme. Hanover, N.H.: "Printed for Class-Room
                        Use," 1909. 211 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>And also alliteration and assonance. The bulk is historically organized,
                        from Caedmon to the late nineteenth century, with some note of classical
                        antece- dents. A primer. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C276">
                    <bib> Rickert, William E. "Rhyme Terms." Style 12 (1978): 35-46. </bib>
                    <notes> An extensive survey of prosody manuals produced a list of their
                        inconsistent terms for 10 primary and 38 secondary characteristics of rhyme.
                        From this compilation Rickert produces a long-overdue and exceedingly simple
                        codifi- cation: "Rhyme, Slant Rhyme, and eight primary and nine secondary
                        terms." He may now add himself to his lists. Bibliography. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C277">
                    <bib> -----. "The Sound, Structure, and Meaning of Rhyme: An Oral Correlative
                        Study in Modern Poetry." DAI 35 (1975): 4730A (Michigan). </bib>
                    <notes> Three purposes are pursued here: establishing a typology of varieties of
                        rhyme, discriminating the functions of rhyme (melody, structure, and
                        meaning), and determining the proper place of rhyme within a philosophy of
                        performance. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C278">
                    <bib> Rickey, Mary Ellen. Rhyme and Meaning in Richard Crashaw. Lexington:
                        University of Kentucky Press, 1961; rpt New York: Haskell House, 1973. 99
                        pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Based on her dissertation, "A Study of the Rhymes of the Metaphysical
                        Poets, with Particular Reference to Richard Crashaw." DA 15 (1955): 1621A
                        (Florida State). Rev: in New Mexico Quarterly 31 (1962): 267-68; in Review
                        of English Studies n.s. 13 (1962): 437-38; in JEGP 61 (1962): 921-22; in
                        Études Anglaises 16 (1963): 385; in Notes &amp; Queries 10 (1963): 76.
                        Though this monograph lacks the scope of a full-length work of scholarship,
                        its thesis is carefully reasoned. Analysis reveals that Crashaw's rhyme
                        vocabu- lary was surprisingly small, yet he frequently elaborated only a few
                        rhymes (and often the same words) into enormously complex schemes; these
                        preferential repetitions of words and sequences reveal that certain words
                        became, in rhyme, "compressed versions of the complexes of association"
                        which were central to Crashaw's thinking. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C279">
                    <bib> -----. "Rhymecraft in Edward and George Herbert." JEGP 57 (1958): 502-11. </bib>
                    <notes> Tabulation of stanza-patterns and rhyme-schemes for both George Herbert
                        and Edward, Lord Herbert of Cherbury shows that the older brother (Edward)
                        had greater range (44 patterns in 62 stanzas) though a smaller corpus
                        (George used 48 patterns in 169 stanzas). Both poets easily outdistance
                        their contem- poraries in inventiveness; only Donne and Wyatt compare. Too,
                        both of the brothers show similar characteristics: pattern poems, the
                        echo-device, rare stanza-forms, and shifts of form within a poem. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C280">
                    <bib> -----. "Vaughan, The Temple, and Poetic Form." SP 59 (1962): 162-70. </bib>
                    <notes> In stanza-form but especially in rhyme-devices Vaughan is more heavily
                        in- debted to Herbert than is the case for any other two major English
                        poets. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C281">
                    <bib> Ritchie, Frank. "Rhyme." Longman's Magazine 37 (1900-1): 114-24. </bib>
                    <notes> Interesting observations here: rhymes can serve as evidence for
                        historical pro- nunciation; in the case of imperfect rhymes often
                        "similarity of spelling is now accepted as covering the want of any real
                        identity in the vowel sounds"; more than a fifth of the imperfect rhymes in
                        a thousand lines are in words where the vowel is followed by an -r; Tennyson
                        thought the utility of rhyme to be that "it helps the memory"; and the
                        spelling of rhyme with an -h is both recent and erroneous, based on false
                        etymology with rhythm (of Greek origin)--the old spelling for echoing sound
                        was rime, with the variant rhime meaning simply "verse." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C282">
                    <bib> Rolfe, W. J. "Browning's Mastery of Rhyme." Poet-Lore 5 (1893):258-66. </bib>
                    <notes> Follows Clark (C198), but claims that many of the alleged "bad" rhymes
                        are actually eye-rhymes. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C283">
                    <bib> Routh, James E., Jr. "Thomas Kyd's Rime Schemes and the Authorship of
                        Soliman and Perseda and of The First Part of Jeronimo." MLN 20 (1905):
                        49-51. </bib>
                    <notes> Concludes from this internal evidence that Kyd wrote the former but not
                        the latter; he may have learned the device from Garnier. the Ur-Hamlet is
                        also dis- cussed. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C284">
                    <bib> Russell, B. Eugene. "Dialectical and Phonetic Features of Edward Taylor's
                        Rhymes: A Brief Study Based on a Computer Concordance of His Poems."
                        American Literature 43 (1971): 165-80. </bib>
                    <notes>Based on his dissertation, DAI 31 (1971): 6567A (Wisconsin). Criticism
                        has always disparaged Taylor's rhymecraft, but computerized analysis reveals
                        that a great many of his seemingly inept rhymes may be accounted for by (1)
                        the standard features of Taylor's Leicestershire dialect, and (2) systematic
                        application of a rule which allows "as near-rhymes or off-rhymes words which
                        end in consonants that differ by only one phonetic feature, either place or
                        manner of articulation." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C285">
                    <bib> Sapir, Edward. "The Heuristic Value of Rhyme." Queen's Quarterly 27
                        (1920): 309- 12; rpt in Selected Writings of Edward Sapir on Language,
                        Culture, and Personality. Ed. David G. Mandelbaum. Berkeley: University of
                        California Press, 1949. pp. 496-500. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C286">
                    <bib> Schramm, Wilbur L. "A Characteristic of Rime." PMLA 50 (1935): 1223-27. </bib>
                    <notes> Acoustic measurements show that part of the "melody of verse" inheres in
                        the fact that rhymes tend to be pronounced at the same pitch even when that
                        re- quires some articulatory effort. This research is summarized in:
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C287">
                    <bib> -----. "The Melodies of Verse." Science n.s. 82 (1935): 61-62. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C288">
                    <bib> Sellers, W. H. "Wordsworth and Spender: Some Speculations on the Use of
                        Rhyme." Studies in English Literature 1500-1900 5 (1965): 641-50. </bib>
                    <notes> Not technical analysis but an inquiry into the motivations and contexts
                        deemed appropriate for rhyme: in both poets, when the subject is considered
                        elevated or sublime, rhyme is abdicated in favor of blank verse. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C289">
                    <bib> Shen, Yao. "Three Phonostylistic Features of Browning's End-Rhymes."
                        Studies in Honor of Albert H. Marckwardt. Ed. James E. Alatis. Washington,
                        D.C.: Teachers of English to Speakers of Other Languages, 1972. pp. 151-66. </bib>
                    <notes> These are voicing (beneath/breathe), juncture (equine/weak wine), and
                        stress-shift (dust hole/just whole). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C290">
                    <bib> Simonetti, Francis A. "Prosody as a Unifying Element in 'Huswifery.'" Ball
                        State University Forum 14 (1973): 30-31. </bib>
                    <notes> Patterns of rhyme and assonance unify the imagery in Edward Taylor's
                        poem. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C291">
                    <bib> Simpson, Percy. "The Rhyming of Stressed with Unstressed Syllables in
                        Elizabethan Verse." MLR 38 (1943): 127-29. </bib>
                    <notes> Following Legouis and Stein on this practice in Donne, Simpson notes
                        that Marlowe and Shakespeare avoid it; Peele uses it, as well as Chapman and
                        Jon- son. No final explanation is offered. See addendum by Maas (C246), then
                        cf. G. C. M. Smith (C295). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C292">
                    <bib> Sinclair, Giles M. The Aesthetic Function of Rime in Dryden's Verse.
                        University Microfilms Publication no. 5734. Ann Arbor: University
                        Microfilms, 1953. </bib>
                    <notes> His dissertation at Michigan in 1953. A detailed analysis of the
                        rhyme-words in Absolom and Achitophel in terms of sense, word-class, and
                        syllabicity (single or double) in order to differentiate the couplets into
                        (1) co-ordinate, (2) subordinate, or (3) continuation forms. In comparison
                        with Pope and Goldsmith, Dryden uses more continued forms and prefers rhymes
                        which are different parts of speech and differ in syllabic length. The
                        "counterlogical" semantic relationship established in the rhyme-words is
                        emphasized. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C293">
                    <bib> Skelton, Robin. "Celt and Classicist" The Versecraft of Louis NacNeice."
                        In Time Was Away: The World of Louis MacNeice. Ed. Terence Brown and Alec
                        Reid. Dublin: Dolmen, 1974. pp. 43-53. </bib>
                    <notes> "At one point or another, [MacNeice] has used almost all the rhyming and
                        near-rhyming devices of Welsh and Irish poetry." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C294">
                    <bib> Smith, Fred M. "Mrs. Browning's Rhymes." PMLA 54 (1939): 829-34. </bib>
                    <notes> Defends her much-criticised rhyme practices as experimentation, a
                        pattern perfectly acceptable in other nineteenth-century poets such as
                        Emerson and Dickinson. Examples of her masculine and feminine consonantal
                        and assonan- tal rhymes. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C295">
                    <bib> Smith, G. C. Moore. "The Use of an Unstressed Extra-Metrical Syllable to
                        Carry the Rime." MLR 15 (1920): 300-3. </bib>
                    <notes> Following Schipper's examples from Wyatt, Smith cites numerous examples
                        in Peele. Cf. Simpson (C291). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C296">
                    <bib> Smith, Paul R. "Studies in Spenser's Rimes." DA 22 (1962): 3188A (Florida,
                        1955). </bib>
                    <notes> Spenser's love of ornament and elaboration led him to employ the musical
                        de- vice of theme-and-variation in his rhymes, a sound-patterning that
                        reaches deep into the lines from the rhymes, complex rhyme patterns, and
                        frequent repetitions. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C297">
                    <bib> Snyder, Edward D. "Poe and Amy Lowell." MLN 43 (1928): 152-53. </bib>
                    <notes> Miss Lowell's approbation of rhymes at unexpected intervals in her
                        "poly- phonic prose" is paralleled by remarks by Poe in "The Rationale of
                        Verse" on the virtues of rhyme at "unanticipated intervals." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C298">
                    <bib> Steffan, T. Guy. "MS Rhyme Revision of Canto I of Don Juan." Notes &amp;
                        Queries 193 (1948): 244-26. </bib>
                    <notes> In the work of polishing the complex ottava rime stanzas of the first
                        Canto into finished luster, Byron generally preferred to retain a rhyme-word
                        when he was forced to recast a line, and when he was forced to change an
                        entire rhyme he usually did so in the final couplet, since that alteration
                        had the least effect else- where in the stanza. A very interesting study.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C299">
                    <bib> Stovall, Floyd. "Feminine Rimes in The Faerie Queene." JEGP 26 (1927):
                        91-95. </bib>
                    <notes> Statistics and interpretation: Spencer eschewed feminine rhymes almost
                        en- tirely in Books I-III as undignified but reversed his policy and allowed
                        them very liberally in Book IV, with the usage declining steadily thereafter
                        through Book VII. Where they do appear, such rhymes fall most frequently on
                        lines 1 and 3 or the stanza. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C300">
                    <bib> Strachan, L. R. M. "Pope's Rhymes." Notes &amp; Queries 182 (1942): 51. </bib>
                    <notes> "Wars/ears" (Essay on Criticism) was a bad rhyme even by Pope's own
                        standards. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C301">
                    <bib/>
                    <notes> Deleted. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C302">
                    <bib> Stratton, Clarence. "Emerson's Rhymes." Word Study, December 1944, pp.
                        2-4. Reply, April 1945, pp. 7-8. </bib>
                    <notes> Finds over 800 false rhymes in Emerson's verse--an average of three per
                        page. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C303">
                    <bib> Stryjewski, Kurt. Reimform und Reimfunktion: Untersuchungen zum Problem
                        des reinen und unreinen Reims in der englischen Dichtung des 20
                        Jahrhunderts. Breslau: Priebatsch, 1940. 112 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Rev: in Archiv 182 (1943): 57-59. Far more sophisticated than the usual
                        treatment: the author (a student of Wilhelm Horn) examines the ways in which
                        the language plays with sound through rhymes, via their Klangkorper,
                        construing similarity and difference si- multaneously, the effect of rhyme
                        being related to that of the joke. Structurally the rhyme weights the
                        movement of the line toward its end and leads it into other lines, unlike
                        alliteration. The impediment of the rhyme-sound forces the poet to think in
                        terms of the larger stanzaic architecture. The dialectic of "pure" and
                        "impure" rhymes is carried on deep in the structure of the lan- guage--e.g.
                        in sound-shifts--and though most poets are inclined toward con- servatism in
                        rhyming (since legitimacy here is defined socially), some poets are fairly
                        radical--e.g. Keats. Rhyme also entails a balance of strophic unity against
                        echo-purity. The twentieth century, though, has been content with only ap-
                        proximate echo. This is a study showing both a subtle understanding and also
                        methodological expertise. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C304">
                    <bib> Taboureux, Etienne. "Of Rhyme in English Verse." Revue de l'enseignement
                        des langues vivantes 15 (1899): 169-76, 215-22. </bib>
                    <notes> A straightforward review of types, presumably for foreign students.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C305">
                    <bib> Tannenbaum, Sanuel A. "Shakspeare's Rimes." Shakespeare Association
                        Bulletin 16 (1941): 255-56. </bib>
                    <notes> A review of Ness (C260); Tannenbaum's stricture is that Ness ignored the
                        scholarly work on the subject, and so he appends a bibliography on rhyme in
                        Shakespeare. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C306">
                    <bib> Tatlock, J. S. P. "The Hermaphrodite Rhyme." MLN 32 (1917): 373. </bib>
                    <notes>Also: </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C307">
                    <bib> -----. "Hermaphrodite Rhyme." Saturday Review of Literature 9 (1932): 161. </bib>
                    <notes> Response by G. Fraser, "Chaucer's Accents," on p. 242. Tatlock uses the
                        term for a masculine-feminine rhyme-pair (i.e. a stressed syllable rhymed
                        with an unstressed). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C308">
                    <bib> Taylor, David W. "End-Words in Richard Wilbur's Poems." Publications of
                        the Arkansas Philological Association 4 (1978): 25-32. </bib>
                    <notes> An interesting corollary phenomenon to rhyme: the final words in the
                        lines of Wilbur's poems (the poet confesses it) may offer an elliptical
                        synopsis or ironic commentary on the argument of the poem. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C309">
                    <bib> Turner, Albert. "The Sound of Grief: A Reconsideration of the Nature and
                        Function of the Unrhymed Lines in Lycidas." Milton Quarterly 10 (1976):
                        67-73. </bib>
                    <notes> Working systematically through the rhymes of the poem, Turner shows that
                        the ten unrhymed lines are all strategically placed structurally and that
                        all ten endings are slant rhymes with other important internal sound
                        repetitions in their local environments. These practices originate in Tasso.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C310">
                    <bib> Untermeyer, Louis. "The Future of Rhyme." Saturday Review of Literature 1
                        (1924): 278, 314. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C311">
                    <bib> -----. "Rhyme and Its Reasons." Saturday Review of Literature 9 (1932):
                        30-31. </bib>
                    <notes> A notice of Lanz's book (C240) and a rhyming dictionary by Burges
                        Johnson, followed by an exposition of seven varieties of rhyme--full or
                        perfect, imper- fect, "suspended" (final consonants identical, initial
                        consonants differ, vowels differ), alliteration, assonance, and "analyzed"
                        (exchange or reversal of the vowel or consonant over four lines). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C312">
                    <bib> Weisker, Ernst. Über Zweck und Einrichtung, Reime und Accentangabe,
                        Worschatz und Quelle des ersten frühneuenglischen Reimlexicons (Manipulus
                        Vocabulorum, 1570). Diss., Göttingen, 1902. 32 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>A study of Levins (C242). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C313">
                    <bib> Welland, D. S. R. "Half-Rhyme in Wilfred Owen: Its Derivation and Use."
                        Review of English Studies n.s. 1 (1950): 226-41. </bib>
                    <notes> Half-rhyme (e.g. cold/called) was used prior to Owen by Hopkins,
                        Dickinson and Vaughan; possibly he learned the technique from Welsh, but a
                        more likely source is the French poet/prosodist Jules Romains. Functionally
                        it both suited Owen's temperament and conveyed the sense of frustration,
                        dissonance, and unease so appropriate for the war-poems. Moreover, Owen
                        chooses his rhyme-pairs so that almost invariably there is a drop in pitch
                        from the first to the second, the drop that we associate with despair, or
                        incompletion. . . . </notes>
                </item>
                <item id="C313a">
                    <bib> Wesling, David. The Chances of Rhyme: Device and Modernity. Berkeley:
                        University of California Press, 1980. 170 pp. </bib>
                    <notes/>
                </item>


                <item id="C314">
                    <bib> Whitehall, Harold. "Pararhyme in Three Poems." West Africa Journal of
                        Education 11, no. 2 (1967): 90-93. </bib>
                    <notes> The term is used as an unbrella for all sound-repetition; nine varieties
                        are cited and illustrated in sample poems by Hopkins, Owen, and Thomas.
                        Identifies four major periods of rhyme-practice in English. Interestingly,
                        "full rhyme is not indigenous to any European language" and "the majority of
                        the world's poetic literatures have never used it." Simplified explanations.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C315">
                    <bib> Wicker, Nancy R. "The Golden Echo: A Linguistic Study of the Thought and
                        Poetry of Gerard Manley Hopkins." DAI 38 (1978): 6751A (Pennsylvania). </bib>
                    <notes> In the philosophical framework of Hopkins' beliefs, love equals God, God
                        equals beauty, and beauty is manifested in rhyme. Hence the complex pat-
                        terning of sounds and figures becomes a mode of bodying forth the spiritual
                        design of creation. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C316">
                    <bib> Wimsatt, W. K., Jr. "One Relation of Rhyme to Reason: Alexander Pope." MLQ
                        5 (1944): 323-38; </bib>
                    <notes>rpt in his The Verbal Icon. Lexington: University of Kentucky Press,
                        1954; rpt London: Methuen, 1970. pp. 153-68. Rpt also in Discussions of
                        Poetry: Form and Structure. Ed. Francis Murphy. Boston: D. C. Heath, 1964.
                        pp. 148-59. A classic essay on the semantic functions of rhyme, especially
                        in Chaucer and Pope. Wimsatt sets himself the task of explicating the
                        "counterpattern of alogi- cal implication" established in rhyme (as examplar
                        of all formal devices in verse) against or above the lexical-logical
                        meanings built up by the words in the lines. Indeed, his point is precisely
                        that the "logic" of the verse-forms must run counter to the sense of the
                        lines or else the whole complicate tissue of "tension and resilience" is
                        lost. Rhyme-structures examined are homoeoteleuton, true rhyme, and chi-
                        asmus. Of Pope, Wimsatt concludes that his rhymes are characterized chiefly
                        by the use of different parts of speech or by the same parts of speech used
                        in different functions. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C317">
                    <bib> -----. "Rhetoric and Poems: Alexander Pope." English Institute Essays,
                        1948. Ed. D. A. Robertson, Jr. New York: Columbia University Press, 1949 pp.
                        179- 207; </bib>
                    <notes>rpt in his The Verbal Icon. Lexington: University of Kentucky Press,
                        1954. pp. 169-87; rpt London: Methuen, 1970. Section I of the essay
                        enumerates five possible relations of theory to poems; the essay thereafter
                        expands on that relation chosen by the Augustans. Princi- pally Wimsatt
                        discusses rhetoric (figures) and rhyme in Puttenham and Pope, pointing out
                        the central paradox that rhyme represents in Augustan poetics: though a very
                        fixed and accepted convention, it was nonetheless considered "barbarous."
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C318">
                    <bib> Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. "Milton's 'Destin'd Urn': the Art of Lycidas."
                        PMLA 84 (1969): 60-70. </bib>
                    <notes> An argument that (1) the rhymes in Lycidas extend continuously into one
                        in- tegral, highly intellectual pattern, (2) the rhymes at the end of the
                        poem dovetail into those at the beginning to complete the circular
                        structure, (3) leaving only three unrhymed lines in the whole poem--one for
                        each of the three major thematic crises, (4) the whole amounting to a
                        coherent progres- sion from disorder to order. Precedent: the madrigal
                        tradition. There is a sub- sequent exchange: </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C319">
                    <bib> Low, Anthony, and Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr. "Circular Rhymes in Lycidas?"
                        PMLA 86 (1971): 1032-35. </bib>
                    <notes> Low objects that the rhymes are much too far apart to ring in the
                        reader's ear, and that not only did Milton not intend them as one continuous
                        pattern, he seems to have deliberately avoided continuous stanza-linking.
                        Cf. Oras (C265). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C320">
                    <bib> Wolfe, Ralph H., and Edgar F. Daniels. "Rime and Idea in Donne's Holy
                        Sonnet X." American Notes &amp; Queries 5 (1967): 116-17. </bib>
                    <notes> The focus on Death in this Sonnet does not blur a broader focus on the
                        Christian's faith in a life beyond death; both are held in place by a
                        momentary ambiguity over the proper pronunciation of the final syllable in
                        the rhyme- word of the penultimate line, eternally. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C321">
                    <bib> Wyld, Henry C. Studies in English Rhymes from Surrey to Pope: A Chapter in
                        the History of English. London: John Murray, 1923; rpt New York: Russell
                        &amp; Russell, 1965. </bib>
                    <notes> Rev: in JEGP 23 (1924): 456-58. An indispensable historical study of
                        rhyming practice and accuracy in English verse. Wyld set himself the mammoth
                        task of identifying those historical changes in pronunciation and spelling
                        wich obscure older perfect rhymes to our eyes; given the great bulk of data,
                        his book struggles for organization, and is in fact less useful for
                        reference (there is a rhyme index) than it is to read straight through.
                        After an introductory review of the validity of various kinds of evidence,
                        four chapters cite pronunciational changes--vowel quality and quantity,
                        consonant quality, and whole words--giving numerous examples. Organization
                        is by sound, not by author or spelling. Entirely non-technical treatment: no
                        phonetic transcriptions. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C322">
                    <bib> Zschech, Fritz. Die Kritik des Reims in England. Berliner Beiträge zur
                        germanischen und romanischen Philologie, 50, germanische Abteilung, no. 37.
                        Berlin: Emil Ebering, 1917. 166 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Collects and summarizes the views of 47 major and minor English critics,
                        from Ascham down to the end of the eighteenth century, on rhyme in English
                        verse, unfortunately without untangling the knotted-up skein of usages that
                        the term has accrued. Organized by critic, giving brief synopses, with a
                        full chapter on Dryden. Bibliography. Cf. E228. </notes>
                </item>

            </div>
            <div title="SONAL MIMESIS">

                <item id="C323">
                    <bib> Bentley, Madison, and E. J. Varon. "An Accessory Study of 'Phonetic
                        Symbolism.'" American Journal of Psychology 45 (1933): 76-86. </bib>
                    <notes> A series of four informal experiments modelled after Sapir. In the first
                        three, only three subjects were used, in the fourth, twenty-six. Affirmative
                        conclu- sions. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C324">
                    <bib> Bolinger, Dwight L. "Word Affinities." American Speech 15 (1940): 62-73. </bib>
                    <notes> On the interesting phonemenon of "reverse onomatopoeia," wherein "not
                        only is the word assimilated to the sound, but the sound is also assimilated
                        to the 'wordness' of the word." Words are imitative of sounds and natural
                        proc- esses, but more importantly, they are more like other words (being
                        related conventionally) than like things, so they come to take on
                        "affinitive sugges- tiveness"; they change so as to resemble each other,
                        even as old people long married come to resemble each other. Their
                        similarities of sound and induced similarities of meaning come to form
                        larger constellations of affinity, via affix- ing, visual simularity, rhyme
                        and alliteration, consonance, and pairing. Many examples to add to
                        Jespersen's. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C325">
                    <bib> Brown, Roger W., A. H. Black, and A. E. Horowitz. "Phonetic Symbolism in
                        Natural Languages." Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology 50 (1955):
                        388-93. </bib>
                    <notes> English subjects were asked to match the order of English antonym pairs
                        with translations of the pairs in Czech, Chinese, and Hindi ordered
                        randomly. They guessed right twice as often as they guessed wrong, and in
                        fact performed slightly better when given written translations than when
                        they heard them read aloud. See Maltzman, Morrisett, and Brooks (C338), and
                        also Brown and Nuttall's revised experiment (next entry). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C326">
                    <bib> Brown, Roger W., and Ronald Nuttall. "Method in Phonetic Symbolism
                        Experiments." Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology 59 (1959): 441-45. </bib>
                    <notes> Procedural refinements over Brown, Black, and Horowitz (above),
                        including deletion of one language (Czech). More precise results suggests
                        more subtle limitations of symbolism in language. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C327">
                    <bib> Butcher, Andrew. "'Brightness,' 'Darkness,' and the Dimensionality of
                        Vowel Perception." Journal of Phonetics 2 (1974): 153-60. </bib>
                    <notes> Finds some support for this single-dimension continuum as a description
                        of vowel quality. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C328">
                    <bib> Carton, Irving S. "Initial /SL/ in English." DA 17 (1957): 1078A
                        (Columbia). </bib>
                    <notes> Compilation of 250 words beginning with sl- reveals a semantic field
                        com- prising 15 overlapping "meaning areas," including: stigmatization,
                        inertia, vis- cidity, smoothness, percussion, and declivity. Statistical
                        analyses and discussion of phonestheme theory included. In short, this
                        initial cluster does convey a range of varied--though narrow and fairly
                        fixed--associations. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C329">
                    <bib> DeVito, Joseph A., and J. A. Civikly. "Some Semantics of Repetition: An
                        Experiment in Phonetic Symbolism." Journal of Communication 22 (1972):
                        39-47. </bib>
                    <notes> A peculiar study: subjects were to select nonsense syllables to match
                        simple visual forms displaying the specific sets of semantic dimensions
                        rounded/angular, complete/incomplete, and homogeneous/heterogeneous. Not
                        surprisingly, repetition in the structure of the syllable correlated with
                        higher order in the figures. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C330">
                    <bib> Firth, J. R. "Modes of Meaning." Essays and Studies n.s. 4 (1951): 118-49. </bib>
                    <notes> Firth illustrates the categories of phonetic, prosodic (suprasegmental),
                        syntactic, and collocational meaning--these are distinct modes wholly
                        isolable from the higher levels of linguistic organization--in Swinburne.
                        See pp. 121-23 for his discussion of phonesthemes, which he insists are not
                        instances of sound- symbolism but simply of "the association of sounds and
                        social and personal at- titudes." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C331">
                    <bib> -----. "The Use and Distribution of Certain English Sounds." English
                        Studies 17 (1935): 8-18. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C332">
                    <bib> Heise, David R. "Sound-Meaning Correlations Among 1,000 English Words."
                        Language and Speech 9 (1966): 14-27. </bib>
                    <notes> Conflicting results. Tests based on the thousand most common English
                        words revealed a firm correlation between the attitudinal meanings of
                        phonemes and lexemes (words). But the same results were not found when
                        artificially con- trived words were used. One of the possible
                        interpretations of this situation is that a given phoneme takes part in
                        several spheres of meaning, dependent on context, rather than only one.
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C333">
                    <bib> Hill, Archibald A. "Sound-Symbolism in Lexicon and Literature." Studies in
                        Linguistics in Honor of George L. Trager. Ed. M. Estellie Smith. The Hague:
                        Mouton, 1972. pp. 142-47. </bib>
                    <notes> Caveats and strictures. Hill admits that the phenomenon exists but
                        argues that its influence is very limited (in language) and localized (in
                        texts). What we be- lieve is symbolism is often mere association of
                        paralanguage. And in logical terms its occurrences in lexicon and in
                        literature are necessarily related. Liter- ary symbolism may be "lexical,"
                        "contentive," or "grammatical." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C334">
                    <bib> Householder, F. W. "On Linguistic Primes." Word 15 (1959): 231-39. </bib>
                    <notes> See pp. 237-38. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C335">
                    <bib> -----. "On the Problem of Sound and Meaning, An English Phonestheme." Word
                        2 (1946): 83-84. </bib>
                    <notes> Synopsis of a study of the clusters of meanings associated with the
                        schwa in English stressed monosyllables: nine clusters are identified,
                        unfortunately rather extensive in semantic range, but one general
                        signification seems to be the pe- jorative. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C336">
                    <bib> Iritani, Toshio. "A Study of the Expressive Values of Non-linguistic
                        Sounds and their Influence on the Articulation of Perceived Objects." DA 23
                        (1962): 3491A (Clark). </bib>
                    <notes> The results of these experiments, in which subjects ere asked to name
                        refer- ents, judge the degree of expressiveness (in several dimensions, e.g.
                        size), and judge the appropriateness (as names) of thirty-five arbitrary
                        sound-patterns, were equivocal. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C337">
                    <bib> Jespersen, Otto. "Symbolic Value of the Vowel I." Rpt in his Linguistica:
                        Selected Papers in English, French, and German. Copenhagen: Levin &amp;
                        Munksgaard, 1933. pp. 283-303. </bib>
                    <notes> The old master thinks sound-symbolism more authentic and more extensive
                        than most would admit, and so here proceeds to give twenty pages of exam-
                        ples for a connotation of "small, slight, insignificant, or weak" attached
                        to the sound /i/. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C338">
                    <bib> Maltzman, Irving, L. Morrisett, Jr., and L. O. Brooks. "An Investigation
                        of Phonetic Symbolism." Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology 53 (1956):
                        249- 51. </bib>
                    <notes> A supplementary experiment to that by Brown, Black, and Horowitz (C325):
                        replaced the English words in the English-Japanese word-pair matching test
                        with Croatian to test for universal phonetic symbolism, which was not con-
                        firmed. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C339">
                    <bib> Marchand, Hans. "Phonetic Symbolism in English Word-formation."
                        Indogermanische Forschungen 64 (1958-59): 146-68. 256-77. </bib>
                    <notes> N.B.: Marchand is interested only in the factors affecting
                        word-formation, not in words which have acquired some phonetically mimetic
                        force by association. The study is a seemingly exhaustive set of notes on
                        initial, final ("rhyme- formation"), and medial ("ablaut-formation")
                        constructions, their relatives, and association (symbolism), the great bulk
                        of the study being given over to the initial forms. C340 See also his
                        Categories and Types of Present Day English Word-Formation. 2nd ed. Munich,
                        1969. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C341">
                    <bib> Markel, Norman N., and Eric P. Hamp. "Connotative Meanings of Certain
                        Phoneme Sequences.' Studies in Linguistics 15 (1961): 47-61. </bib>
                    <notes> Examination of the initial clusters gl-, sp-, fl-, sm-, and st-, via the
                        semantic- differential procedure, yields inconclusive results: sm- seems to
                        be the most odious to us. The authors propose replacing "phonestheme" with
                        "psycho- morph" to denote a series of phonemes which, though not a morpheme,
                        do carry culturally associated meaning. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C342">
                    <bib> Masson, D. I. "Synaesthesia and Sound Spectra." Word 8 (1953): 39-41. </bib>
                    <notes> A supplement to Reichard et al. (C347). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C343">
                    <bib> Moore, Charles A. E. "A Preliminary Study of the Emotional Effects of
                        Letter- Sounds," Quarterly Journal of Speech 24 (1938): 134-49. </bib>
                    <notes> An experiment in which subjects correlated a list of terms for emotions
                        with a list of sensical and nonsensical sentences. Fourteen sounds were
                        tested, with some high correlations. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C344">
                    <bib> Newman, Stanley S. "Further Experiments in Phonetic Symbolism." American
                        Journal of Psychology 45 (1933): 53-75. </bib>
                    <notes> Three experiments, the first of which was performed by Sapir, the first
                        and second of which affirm the existence of fairly stable and well-defined
                        scales of vocalic symbolism correlated with largeness-smallness and
                        brightness-darkness. In the third, two groups of words denoting largeness
                        and smallness are ana- lyzed by the phonetic indices obtained in the
                        preceding experiments, but "the actual distribution of sounds in the two
                        denotative categories [turns out to be] fairly random, as far as phonetic
                        symbolism is concerned. . . . the phonetic content of English words takes
                        practically no account of magnitude- symbolism." That is, symbolism is not
                        produced by association within a given semantic class. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C345">
                    <bib/>
                    <notes> Deleted. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C346">
                    <bib> Plath, Warren J. "The Relative Frequency of English Consonantal Patterns."
                        Zeitschrift für Phonetik und allgemeine Sprachwissenschaft 11 (1959): 67-87. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C347">
                    <bib> Reichard, Gladys A., R. Jakobson, and E. Werth. "Language and
                        Synaesthesia." Word 5 (1949): 224-33. </bib>
                    <notes> Irresistibly interesting. See also the follow-up study by Masson (C342).
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C348">
                    <bib> Sapir, Edward. "A Study in Phonetic Symbolism." Journal of Experimental
                        Psychology 12 (1929): 225-39; rpt in his Selected Writings of Edward Sapir
                        on Language, Culture, and Personality. Ed. David G. Mandelbaum. Berkeley:
                        University of California Press, 1949. pp. 61-72. </bib>
                    <notes> The classic study which inaugurated an entirely new field of interest
                        among American psychologists, the study of the relation of sound and meaning
                        in lan- guage. Sapir, wanting to know if native speakers instinctively
                        discerned de- grees of magnitude in speech-sounds regardless of meaning,
                        constructed sets of minimal-pairs of nonsense syllables contrasting one
                        phonetic feature (mainly /a/ with /i/) and asked subjects to specify which
                        of the pair was the larger and which the smaller. Sapir speculated that the
                        causes of symbolism might be "acoustic or kinesthetic or a combination of
                        both . . . the factor of linguistic interference being set aside [very
                        significantly] for the present." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C349">
                    <bib> Solomon, L. N. "Search for Physical Correlates to Psychological Dimensions
                        of Sound." Journal of the Acoustical Society 31 (1959): 492-97. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C350">
                    <bib> Stevens, C., J. A. DeVito, and N. Issacson. "Phonetic Symbolism and
                        Audience Perception." Southern Speech Journal 34 (1969): 185-86. </bib>
                    <notes> Predominance of front vowels over back vowels is associated by hearers
                        with lower competence, reliability, and energy. Tense and lax vowels were
                        also tested on a number of scales. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C351">
                    <bib> Taylor, Insup K. "Phonetic Symbolism Re-Examined." Psychological Bulletin
                        60 (1963): 200-9. </bib>
                    <notes> Following a critical review of the literature on the subject (suggesting
                        faults in experimental design) and a synopsis of the author's earlier work,
                        Taylor for- mally states her theory that phonetic symbolism is not to be
                        found in any anal- ogy of the physical properties of sound to the physical
                        properties of real objects (as a universal linguistic phonemenon) but rather
                        in the "language habits" spe- cific to each language [the term is undefined,
                        but seems to mean no more than "conventions"], so that the basic process is
                        one of association rather than imi- tation: "once a certain sound has thus
                        become associated with a certain mean- ing, then within that language a
                        cluster of words of similar meaning may come to employ similar sounds." See
                        the detailed criticism of this theory by Weiss (C361), especially his point
                        that Taylor's view begs the whole question. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C352">
                    <bib> Taylor, Insup K. and Maurice M. "Another Look at Phonetic Symbolism."
                        Psychological Bulletin 64 (1965): 413-27. </bib>
                    <notes> A cogent, informative, and predominantly nonpartisan review essay. The
                        authors formulate an incisive hierarchy of seven logically ordered questions
                        about phonetic symbolism, considered both subjectively and objectively and
                        both in single languages and as a linguistic universal, questions for which
                        they map out answers by reviewing the relevant literature on each
                        thoroughly. Near the end (after p. 424) they reassert their own theory
                        provocatively. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C353">
                    <bib> -----. "Phonetic Symbolism in Four Unrelated Languages." Canadian Journal
                        of Psychology 16 (1962): 344-56. </bib>
                    <notes>Based on the first author's dissertation at Johns Hopkins. Phonetic
                        symbolism is discernable in all four languages (English, Japanese, Korean,
                        and Tamil) but is not a universal linguistic phonomenon. The con- notation
                        tested for was (spatial) size. In English, the length of the syllable is
                        significant for suggesting size but stressing is not. Left-to-right ranking
                        for small to large: initial consonants / t d f v z g / vowels / I schwa u /
                        final consonants / t d g z v f /. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C354">
                    <bib> Tedford, W. H., and C. S. Synott. "Use of the Semantic Differential with
                        Poetic Forms." Psychological Record 22 (1972): 369-73. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C355">
                    <bib> Tolman, Albert H. "The Expressive Power of English Sounds." The Atlantic
                        Monthly 75 (1895): 478-85. </bib>
                    <notes>Expanded into: C356 "The Symbolic Value of English Sounds" in his The
                        Views About Hamlet and Other Essays. Boston: Houghton Mifflin 1904. pp.
                        143-72. Happily, there are careful distinctions here--between expressive
                        sound and ex- pressive versification, for example. Four kinds of sonal
                        miming or expressive- ness are defined: muscular imitation, muscular
                        analogy, sound imitation [ono- matopoeia], and sound analogy. Excellent
                        examples illustrate, and all four types are subsumed under a single general
                        principle: "likeness of motion." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C357">
                    <bib> -----. "The Laws of Tone-Color in the English Language." Andover Review 7
                        (1887): 326-37. </bib>
                    <notes> And, more importantly, in poetry (particularly Poe's "The Bells"). Many
                        ex- amples, though not systematically arrayed. Tolman considers the
                        expressive features to be pitch in vowels and duration ("prolongation") in
                        consonants. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C358">
                    <bib> Voronin, S. V. [Dissonance Onomatopes] and [Some Remarks on the r- Sound
                        in English Onomatopes]. Voprosy struktury anglijskogo jazyka v sinxronii i
                        diaxronii. Ed. I. P. Ivanova. Leningrad: Leningrad University Press, 1967.
                        pp. 49-59, 60- 65. (In Russian; summaries in English, pp. 59 and 65). </bib>
                    <notes> Demonstrates that words expressive of harsh, rough, jarring, grating, or
                        vi- brating sounds have the distinctive and indispensable feature of the
                        folled r. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C359">
                    <bib> Weiss, Jonathan H. "Further Study of the Relation Between the Sound of a
                        Word and Its Meaning." American Journal of Psychology 76 (1963): 624-30. </bib>
                    <notes> Retesting of Wertheimer's hypothesis (C362) revealed an unnoticed
                        differen- tial between the symbolism of nouns and verbs, which brings to
                        mind Jesper- sen's observation that words denoting movement would be the
                        most likely symbolic. Conclusion: "phonetic symbolism cannot be seen as
                        having in any sense an existence prior to, or independent of, meaning
                        categories, but must instead be considered a psychological response,
                        initiated or suggested by (word) meanings, which then allows such meanings
                        to becomes attached to otherwise meaningless sounds." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C360">
                    <bib> -----. "Phonetic Symbolism and Perception of Connotative Meaning." Journal
                        of Verbal Learning and Verbal Behavior 7 (1968): 574-76. </bib>
                    <notes> Experiments reported here did not find any correlation between high
                        degree of phonetic symbolism (sound of the word judged appropriate to its
                        meaning) and relative "extremeness" of connotation. (If that hypothesis had
                        been veri- fied, it would suggest that phonetically symbolic words are more
                        perceptible, hence would be naturally selected as the language evolves,
                        making the lan- guage increasingly richer in that respect, rather than
                        increasingly abstract.) Verbs are shown higher in symbolic power than either
                        nouns or adjectives. Criticizes the method of Wertheimer (C362). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C361">
                    <bib> -----. "Phonetic Symbolism Re-Examined." Psychological Bulletin 61 (1964):
                        454- 58. </bib>
                    <notes> A critique of the literature review, assumptions, methodology, and
                        conclusions of Taylor's theory (C351) that phonetic symbolism is
                        language-specific and not really symbolism at all, but rather an
                        assimilation of certain words to words with a similar connotation. Weiss
                        objects that this theory begs the whole question, contains an unexamined
                        assumption, and is based on highly selective evidence. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C362">
                    <bib> Wertheimer, Michael. "The Relation Between the Sound of a Word and Its
                        Meaning." American Journal of Psychology 71 (1958): 412-15. </bib>
                    <notes> Two hypotheses, both confirmed: (1) words "fitting" their meanings
                        should have more clear-cut tertiary qualities, which will appear at the
                        extremes of the Osgood semantic-differential scales; and (2) such words when
                        continuously re- peated aloud [as we did when children] should retain their
                        meaning for the speaker longer before lapsing than non-fitting words would.
                        But see Weiss (C359-60). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C363">
                    <bib> Whorf, Benjamin Lee. Language, Thought, and Reality. Ed. John B. Carroll.
                        Cambridge, Mass.: M.I.T. Press, 1956. </bib>
                    <notes> On two short pages (267-68) Whorf makes three deft points: humans "seem
                        to associate the experiences of bright, cold, sharp, hard, high, light (in
                        weight), quick, high-pitched, narrow. . . with each other, and conversely .
                        . . dark, warm, yielding, soft, blunt, low, heavy, slow, low-pitched, wide,
                        etc."; we are likely to notice if the words for such experiences share
                        similar characteristics (esp. vowel features) with them, but we usually do
                        not notice a relation of contrast or conflict; even if a word has a "sharp"
                        sound, if it denotes "tender- ness" it will be heard as "sounding,"
                        subjectively and culturally, tender. See also: B156, C171, L13-14, L16,
                        L18a, L25, L84, L98, L107-8, L145, L152, L157-58, L163, L338-39, L433, L732,
                        L779-80, L889, L1230, L1312, L1455, L1579, L1585, L1708. IN POETRY
                        (ONOMATOPOEIA) </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C364">
                    <bib> Agrawala, D. C. "Complexity in Hopkins's Onomatopoeic Coinages." Literary
                        Criterion (Mysore) 7 (1967): 1-5. </bib>
                    <notes> Of all the various methods of word-formation, Hopkins preferred the ono-
                        matopoeic one; of all the various purposes for such words, he seems to have
                        preferred the purely sonal and metrical functions to the semantic ones; the
                        fact is that "the sound of a new word by Hopkins is no guide to the meaning
                        of it." There is a diremption of sound and sense. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C365">
                    <bib> Anderson, Gary L. "Phonetic Symbolism and Phonological Style: A Model
                        Grammar." Current Trends in Stylistics. Ed. B. B. Kachru and H. F. W.
                        Stahlke. Edmonton (Canada): Linguistic Research Inc., 1972. pp. 163-81. </bib>
                    <notes>Based on his </notes>
                </item>



                <item id="C366">
                    <bib> Master's Thesis at St. Cloud (Minnesota) State College, 1970: "Phonetic
                        Symbolism: A Study of the Affective Content of English Phonemes." </bib>
                    <notes> This important new approach to the problem of phonetic symbolism offers
                        much more refined results than the crude traditional terminology by treating
                        the symbolic potential of the phoneme as a regular element in generative
                        pho- nology. Assuming that "while phonemes always 'have meaning' they are
                        not always expressive of their meaning," Anderson proposes tagging each
                        phoneme with an "Affect" feature, which operates by regular rules unless it
                        is "masked" by other lexical features. Rules are derived. Since the
                        symbolism of a mor- pheme does not appear in isolation but only within
                        structures, four possible relations may obtain between its lexical features
                        (meaning) and phonological features, giving four degrees of "fit" between
                        the two: PHONOLOGICAL MAKE-UP - + MEANING - -- random +- Appropriate fit but
                        non-poetic + -+ Only appropriate fit in poetry ++ “poetic” Other Stylistics
                        Rules mark repetitions of symbolic features to produce a hier- archy of
                        eight degrees of value for types of structural repetition within or across
                        lines. Anderson's treatment is a quantum leap over the methodology of
                        earlier studies. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C367">
                    <bib> Bengough, S. E. "The Music of Language, as Illustrated in Shakespeare's
                        Venus and Adonis." Poet-Lore 4 (1892): 562-67. </bib>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C368">
                    <bib> Bugge, John. "Rhyme as Onomatopoeia in 'The Dry Salvages.'" Papers on
                        Language and Literature 10 (1974): 312-16. </bib>
                    <notes> In the second section of the third of the Four Quartets "Eliot seems to
                        have in- tended that the line endings of each sestet, taken in sequence,
                        should echo certain prominent sounds made at regular intervals by the surf."
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C369">
                    <bib> Ehrenpreis, Irvin. "The Style of Sound: The Literary Value of Pope's
                        Versification." The Augustan Milieu. Ed. Henry K. Miller et al. Oxford:
                        Clarendon Press, 1970. pp. 232-46. </bib>
                    <notes> A critique. Ehrenpreis makes the salient point that imitative effects in
                        poetry are critically valued almost automatically these days, just as
                        "purely musical qualities" used to be, but without any critical recognition
                        of the structural and narrative sacrifices that are necessary in order to
                        achieve mimesis. And is the minesis all that effective in most cases?
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C370">
                    <bib> Epstein, E. L. "The Self-Reflexive Artefact: The Function of Mimesis in an
                        Approach to a Theory of Value for Literature." Style and Structure in
                        Literature. Ed. Roger Fowler. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1975. pp. 40-78. </bib>
                    <notes> Elaboration of a full-scale theory of verbal mimesis: "there are
                        basically only two types of formal relationship to content, mimetic and
                        nonmimetic." The latter show two subtypes, absolutely nonmimetic (total
                        absence of grammatical or- ganization at any level; possibly a nonexistent
                        type) and relatively nonmimetic (showing some phonological organization such
                        as sound-patterning, figures, or meter, but unrelated to any analogous
                        lexical-semantic structure). Mimetic re- fers to "the presence of analogous
                        schemata in the lexical level and one or both of the lower levels of syntax
                        or phonology (or graphemics)," and also shows two subtypes, objective
                        (miming of objects or processes) and subjective (miming of "sequences of
                        emotion": the mind imitating its own activities, observing it- self).
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C371">
                    <bib> Fenderson, Lewis H. "The Onomato-Musical Element in Paradise Lost."
                        College Language Association Journal 9 (1966): 255-64. </bib>
                    <notes> Adduces a number of examples in Milton which are said to be mimetic,
                        with- out explanation how or why. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C372">
                    <bib> Gibson, Walker. "Sound and Sense in G. M. Hopkins." MLN 73 (1958): 95-100. </bib>
                    <notes> Explanations advanced for alliteration and convoluted consonant clusters
                        in Hopkins: the latter produce the desired effect of a man in torment, under
                        stress, speaking passionately, while the former, by displaying different
                        meanings under the same sound, projects perfectly a sense of the joint
                        necessity of both the unique individuality of all things and their union
                        under God's hand. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C373">
                    <bib> Green, Andrew J. "Essay in Miniature: Onomatapoetic {?} Preferences."
                        College English 4 (1943): 320. </bib>
                    <notes> Enthusiastic approbation for this device. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C374">
                    <bib> Herbert, T. Walter. "Sound and Sense in Two Shakespeare Sonnets."
                        Tennessee Studies in Literature 3 (1958): 43-52. </bib>
                    <notes> Full analyses of Sonnets 12 and 30 in support of two propositions: (1)
                        similarity in word-sounds implies some similarity in meanings; (2) hearing
                        word-sounds associated with some aspect of a previous context calls up that
                        aspect or con- text. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C375">
                    <bib> Hrushovski, Benjamin. [Do Sounds Have Meaning? The Problem of
                        Expressiveness of Sound-Patterns in Poetry.] Ha-Sifrut/Literature 1 (1968):
                        410- 20. </bib>
                    <notes> (In Hebrew; English summmary on p. 444). Identifies four types of
                        sound-meaning relationships: onomatopoeia (the sound of the word denotes its
                        meaning), expressive sounds (an abstraction from the sound of the words is
                        parallel to an abstraction from the meaning), focusing sound-pattern (no
                        relation exists between specific sounds and words, but the re- lation of
                        sounds in a word-pattern is parallel to the relation of meanings in the
                        pattern), and neutral sound-pattern (sonal patterning in itself is perceived
                        as aes- thetically pleasing, and no sound-meaning correlation at all is
                        intended). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C376">
                    <bib> Lenoski, Daniel S. "The Symbolism of Sound in W. B. Yeats: An
                        Explanation." Études Irlandaises 3 (1978): 47-55. </bib>
                    <notes> The early Yeats's theories of sound symbolism and incantation. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C377">
                    <bib> Liggins, E. M. and H. W. Piper. "Sound and Sense in a Shakespearean
                        Sonnet." Langue et Littérature. Paris: Société d'Édition "Les Belles
                        Lettres," 1961. p. 417. </bib>
                    <notes> In the first quatrain of sonnet 2, "dental plosives with short vowels
                        and difficult transitions, all associated with age," contrast with "labials,
                        lip-rounded conso- nants with long-vowels and easy transitions, associated
                        with the young man's beauty." The final couplet, however, is phonetically
                        smooth, effecting the resolution it asserts. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C378">
                    <bib> Lotspeich, C. M. "The Metrical Technique of Pope's Illustrative Couplets."
                        JEGP 26 (1927): 471-74. </bib>
                    <notes> Analyzing the five couplets in Pope's Essay on Criticism beginning with
                        the fa- mous line "the sound must seem an echo to the sense," Lotspeich
                        interprets the line to mean that sounds are important not in being mimetic
                        but insofar as they "modify the metrical movement of the whole line." And
                        "sense" he takes to mean not only thoughts or images but moods and feelings
                        as well. So the rhythm must parallel the contour of our emotive responses.
                        Very muddy lan- guage here. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C379">
                    <bib> Macdermott, Mary M. Vowel Sounds in Poetry: Their Music and Tone-Color.
                        Psyche Monographs, no. 13. London: Kegan Paul, 1940; rpt Folcroft Pa.:
                        Folcroft Library Editions, 1973. 148 pp. </bib>
                    <notes>Rev: in MLR 38 (1943): 387-89. Highly technical phonetic analysis of
                        vowels in some 250 passages of verse us- ing the difference between points
                        of articulation (front, mid, or back) to test for association with various
                        connotations. The aspects "long" versus "short" and open versus closed are
                        ignored, as are consonant clusters. The effects of the metrical pattern on
                        stressing and reducing vowel intensity are also taken into account. In part
                        the assumptions and methodology here are open to ques- tion (sorting verse
                        into Good Verse and Bad Verse, for example), but there is useful information
                        here: see pp. 11-19 and 88-93. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C380">
                    <bib> Mace, D. T. "The Doctrine of Sound and Sense in Augustan Poetic Theory."
                        Review of English Studies n.s. 2 (1951): 129-39. </bib>
                    <notes> The rise of science and deterministic philosophy in the seventeenth
                        century, the explicit analogy between poetry and music so central to the
                        Renaissance, and the Augustan social doctrine of "correctness" all led to
                        the doctrine of "harmony of Numbers" in Baroque poetic theory, a doctrine
                        all the more cu- rious because it entailed a complete emphasis on sound over
                        sense, on sound as pure sensuous pleasure, and hence on the irrational over
                        the rational in poetry. In contrast, the Augustan view, as seen in Pope's
                        statements in the Essay on Criticism, represented "a transformation of that
                        tradition [so as] to bring poetic imitation in accord with nature as
                        revealed by Hobbes." Meaningless sound, so esteemed in the seventeenth
                        century, had reversed its fortunes entirely by 1711. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C381">
                    <bib> McNally, James. "Suiting Sight and Sound to Sense in 'Meeting at Night'
                        and 'Parting at Morning.'" Victorian Poetry 5 (1967): 219-24. </bib>
                    <notes> The reinforcement of sense by rhymes and sound-patterning is treated on
                        pp. 223-24. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C382">
                    <bib> Moynihan, William T. "The Auditory Correlative." JAAC 17 (1958): 93-102. </bib>
                    <notes> Moynihan, who has read the major psychological experiments on sound sym-
                        bolism, offers here a number of short, clarified examples in poetry of vowel
                        features (high-low, front-back) suggesting non-linguistic features such as
                        size or shape (large-small, round-angular, smooth-rough), then turns to the
                        Paget- Johannesson-Blackmur theory of "language as gesture" (i.e., language
                        evolved as the tongue, mouth and speech-organs imitated gestures in the
                        external world). Sapir, for example, thought that sounds which suggested
                        size corre- lated roughly with the size of the mouth-cavity required to make
                        them. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C383">
                    <bib> Murdy, Louise B. Sound and Sense in Dylan Thomas's Poetry. The Hague:
                        Mouton, 1966. 172 pp. Based on her dissertation at Florida in 1963. </bib>
                    <notes> Rev: in JAAC 27 (1968): 104-5; in Etudes Anglaises 21 (1968): 433-34. A
                        study valuable both for theory and criticism. Brief, yet methodologically
                        as- tute, the work analyzes stress and sound patterns in relation to
                        meaning, in 28 poems over Thomas's career, tracing patterns of development:
                        Thomas's poetry evolves from an earlier idiom that is "staccato in its
                        rhythm and compressed . . . to a later poetry that is legato in its rhythm
                        and expansive--often uncompli- cated--in its sense"; from highly regular
                        meters to more diverse, varied, ir- regular stress-patterns; from strongly
                        end-stopped to usually enjambed lines and larger units of thought; from
                        sound used to point up a phrase or line, through sound used to contrast or
                        characterize passages, to sound-patterns highly autonomous, extended, and
                        complicate; from an early style dense in consonants and plosives to a late
                        reliance on vocalic resonance and extension; Throughout, Thomas used his
                        tools of stress, pitch, intensity, and pattern to body forth, chiefly, his
                        sense. Very extensive Bibliography and Appendices of sound-graphs from
                        Thomas's many recordings. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C384">
                    <bib> Paulson, Kristoffer F. "Rochester and Milton: The Sound, Sense, and
                        Sources of Pope's Portraits of Bufo, Atticus, and Sporus in An Epistle to
                        Dr. Arbuthnot." Papers on Language and Literature 12 (1976): 299-310. </bib>
                    <notes> Pope went a little further in developing kinesthetic mimesis than his
                        sources (Rochester and Milton) for the three lampoons in Arbuthnot: the
                        patterning of sibilants in one passage draws the lips into a sneer and
                        produces unmistakable hissing; the frequent plosives in another passage on
                        the spitting Sporus force the reader to spit himself in dramatic
                        affirmation. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C385">
                    <bib> Pope, Alexander. An Essay on Criticism [1711]. In The Twickenham Edition
                        of the Poems of Alexander Pope. Ed. John Butt. 6 vols. New Haven: Yale
                        University Press, 1939-67. Vol. 1, Pastoral Poetry and An Essay on
                        Criticism. Ed. E. Audra and A. Williams. </bib>
                    <notes> The spectacular mimetic effects in 11. 337-83 of the Essay (pp. 276-84
                        here), though now a locus classicus, are still not entirely understood,
                        despite studies by Mace (C380) and Lotspeich (C378), and the Twickenham text
                        provides copi- ous notes on sources. It is important to remember that in
                        this passage not only does Pope skewer the features of incompetent
                        versification (hiatus, monosyl- labic clutter, filler words, easy rhymes,
                        pretentious alexandrines) for all to see, and not only does he remind us
                        that the verse must enact, sonally and metri- cally, what it describes, but
                        he also insists, first and last, that Numbers are not the final value of
                        verse--what counts above all is the Thought. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C386">
                    <bib> Ransom, John Crowe. "Positive and Near-Positive Aesthetics." Kenyon Review
                        5 (1943): 443-47; rpt in his Beating the Bushes. New York: New Directions,
                        1972. pp. 72-79. </bib>
                    <notes> Beginning at the eighth paragraph, Ransom faces squarely the possibility
                        of sounds in poetry suggesting meaning, knocking it flat to the ground: "I
                        am compelled to believe that the sound effects . . . are remarkable but do
                        not 'promote' any particular meaning at all." His method of proof entails
                        replacing the phonemes in the lines with very similar ones in the same
                        order, but mak- ing up different words, then asking if the supposed meanings
                        remain. This is a visible blow, yet one may remember that in logic,
                        arguments by analogy have no logical validity. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C387">
                    <bib> Ray, Robert H. "Spatial and Aural Patterns in 'The Windows.'" George
                        Herbert Journal 1 (1978): 38-43. </bib>
                    <notes> The steady increase in nasals through the three stanzas of the poem, and
                        espe- cially in the rhyme-sounds, enacts the "ringing" in the ear being
                        discussed (Ray misreads the sense of the passage). </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C388">
                    <bib> Richter, Fred A. "The Phonestheme: Phonological Structures in Narrative,
                        Dramatic, and Lyric Poetry." DAI 32 (1972): 5768A (Auburn). </bib>
                    <notes> Computerized analysis of the distinctive features in the sound-patterns
                        of po- ems by Shakespeare, Pope, and Thomas. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C389">
                    <bib> Ricks, Christopher. "Atomology." Balcony: The Sydney Review, no. 1 (1965),
                        pp. 5-9. </bib>
                    <notes> A delicately subtle defence of the virtue of all types of arbitrariness
                        in poetic sound-devices, from assonance to palindromes. Indeed, in the face
                        of the cold sense of philosophy (most directly Locke), poets have always
                        clung to the nec- essary fiction that the sounds of words are magically
                        accurate and adumbrative names, and anything but arbitrary assignments.
                        Ricks' wonderful examples show that poets exploit both the visual and the
                        aural arbitrariness of word- shapes for "manifesting significance." </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C390">
                    <bib> Sadler, J. D. "Onomatopoeia." Classical Journal 67 (1972): 174-77. </bib>
                    <notes> Several hundred examples of echoic words from Greek, Latin, and
                        (primarily) English. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C391">
                    <bib> Salper, Donald R. "Onomatopoeia, Gesture, and Synaesthesia in the
                        Perception of Poetic Meaning." Studies in Interpretation, Volume 2. Ed.
                        Esther M. Doyle and V. H. Floyd. Amsterdam: Rodopi, 1977. pp. 115-23. </bib>
                    <notes> Notes three theories of phonetic symbolism: Onomatopoeia (vowel sounds
                        imitate sounds in nature); Gesture (the movements of the vocal muscles
                        imitate motions in nature); and Synaesthesia (heard sounds trigger other
                        sensory im- pressions--pure sound symbolism). Then suggests another
                        variety--Kinesthesia. A careful analysis of Dr. Johnson's strictures on
                        "representative meter" in The Life of Pope discloses that he misunderstands
                        the phonetic causes of Pope's mimetic effects in the Sisyphus passage in The
                        Odyssey. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C392">
                    <bib> Scher, Steven P. "Notes toward a Theory of Verbal Music." Comparative
                        Literature 22 (1970): 147-56. </bib>
                    <notes> Onomatopoetic effects are here termed "word-music." See schema on p.
                        151. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C393">
                    <bib> Stein, Arnold. "Structures of Sound in Milton's Verse." Kenyon Review 15
                        (1953): 266-77. Excerpted from his Answerable Style. Minneapolis: University
                        of Minnesota Press, 1953. </bib>
                    <notes> In Stein's view, modern criticism has erred in its fixation on semantic
                        content, which regulates style to a dependent position. He finds Milton's
                        verbal harmo- nies more subtle and sweeping than Donne's, elaborating on
                        imitative sound- patterning in five examples (ranging from such elementary
                        mimetics as "the extravagant mouthing necessary to read the words" to more
                        sophisticated fugues of vocalic enunciation, "propelled outward with great
                        energy and then sustained in a widening sound"), taking the trouble to
                        scourge D. R. Roberts (N113) repeatedly for "shallow" analysis, and
                        concluding finally that the sounds are in fact not imitative at all, but
                        constitutive: "the pattern of sound does not reinforce an already
                        established meaning so much as it helps shape and modulate that meaning."
                    </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C394">
                    <bib> Ullmann, Stephen. Language and Style: Collected Papers. Oxford: Basil
                        Blackwell, and New York: Barnes &amp; Noble, 1964. </bib>
                    <notes>Esp. pp. 67-71, but see s.v. "onomatopoeia," "rhyme," and "rhythm" in the
                        Index. </notes>
                </item>


                <item id="C395">
                    <bib> Woodring, Carl R. "Onomatopoeia and Other Sounds in Poetry." College
                        English 14 (1953): 206-10. </bib>
                    <notes> A sturdy defense of sonal mimesis against the Ransomites; Woodring is
                        happ. to admit that single sounds have little color of their own but insists
                        that patterns of sound have much, both mimetically and kinesthetically. See
                        also: B157, B185, B196, B222, B225, B233, C45, C62, C83-84, C88-89, C127,
                        C129, C149, E23, C46, C104, E553, E696, E1047, E1340, F108, K111, K268,
                        L18a, L39, L104, L163, L796-97, L889, L1360, L1445, M131, M166, M198, M217,
                        M242. </notes>
                </item>
            </div>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</bibliography>
