<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
 <chapter title="">
  <item id="D1">
   <bib>Chomsky, Noam, and Morris Halle. The Sound Pattern of English. New York: Harper &amp; Row,
    1968. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by McCawley in International Journal of American Linguistics 40 (1974): 50–88. The
    generative phonology underlying the metrical work of Halle and Keyser (E775–77) et al. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D2">
   <bib>Crystal, David. The English Tone of Voice: Essays in Intonation, Prosody, and Paralanguage.
    London: Edward Arnold, 1975. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D3">
   <bib>-----. Prosodic Systems and Intonation in English. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
    1969. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D4">
   <bib>Crystal, David, and Randolph Quirk. Systems of Prosodic and Paralinguistic Features in
    English. The Hague: Mouton, 1965. 94 pp. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D5">
   <bib>Fichtner, Edward G. "The Trager-Smith Levels of English: A Reinterpretation." International
    Journal of Applied Linguistics in Language Teaching 10 (1972): 21–33. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D6">
   <bib>Firth, J. R. "Sounds and Prosodies." Transactions of the Philological Society, 1948, pp.
    127–52. </bib>
   <notes>Rpt in his Papers in Linguistics 1935–1951. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1957. pp.
    121–38. Rpt in Phonetics in Linguistics: A Book of Readings. Ed. W. E. Jones and J. Laver.
    London: Longman Group, 1973. pp. 47–65. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D7">
   <bib>Hall, G. Stanley and J. Jastrow. "Studies of Rhythm." Mind 11 (1886): 55–62. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D8">
   <bib>Hill, T. "The Technique of Prosodic Analysis." In Memory of J. R. Firth. Ed. C. E Bazell et
    al. London: Longmans, 1966. pp. 198–226. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D9">
   <bib>Jones, Daniel. An Outline of English Phonetics. 9th ed. Cambridge: W. Heffer &amp; Sons,
    1972. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>

  <item id="D10">
   <bib>Joos, Martin. Acoustic Phonetics. Baltimore: Linguistic Society of America, 1948. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D11">
   <bib>Knowles, G. "The Rhythm of English Syllables." Lingua 34 (1974): 115–47. </bib>
   <notes> "A theory of rhythm includes a theory of grouping and a theory of timing. . . .grouping
    and timing cannot be identified in any single phonetic feature. . . . the pattern of prominence
    must be taken as a whole." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D12">
   <bib>Kurath, Hans. A Phonology and Prosody of Modern English. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan
    Press; Heidelberg: Carl Winter, 1964. 158 pp. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D13">
   <bib>Ladefoged, Peter. Three Areas of Experimental Phonetics. London: Oxford University Press,
    1967. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D14">
   <bib>Lehiste, Ilse. "Rhythmic Units and Syntactic Units in Production and Perception." Journal
    of the Acoustical Society 54 (1973): 1228–34. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D15">
   <bib>-----. Suprasegmentals. Cambridge, Mass.: M.I.T. Press, 1970. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D16">
   <bib>Liberman, Mark. "The Intonational System of English." Diss., M.I.T., 1975. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D17">
   <bib>Liddell, Mark H. The Elements of Sound and Their Relation to Language. Illinois Studies in
    Language and Literature, vol. 27, no. 1. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1940. 136 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in English Studies 25 (1943): 157–60. Work in experimental phonetics which follows
    the author's 1902 work on metrics (E424). He follows D. C. Miller and Helmholtz here. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D18">
   <bib>Lieberman, Philip. Intonation, Perception, and Language. Cambridge, Mass.: M.I.T. Press,
    1967. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D19">
   <bib>-----. "On the Acoustic Basis of the Perception of Intonation by Linguists." Word 21
    (1965): 40–54. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D20">
   <bib>-----. "A Study of Prosodic Features." Current Trends in Linguistics, XII: Linguistics and
    Adjacent Arts and Sciences. Ed. Thomas A Sebeok. 4 vols. The Hague: Mouton, 1975. Part 4, pp.
    2419–50. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D21">
   <bib>Palmer, F. R. Prosodic Analysis. London: Oxford University Press, 1970. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D22">
   <bib>Pike, Kenneth L. The Intonation of American English. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan
    Press, 1945. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D23">
   <bib>-----. "Practical Phonetics of Rhythm Waves." Phonetica 8 (1962): 9–30. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D24">
   <bib>Pitts, Ann. "A Prosodic Analysis of a Chanted Formulaic Sermon." Rackham Literary Studies,
    no. 9 (1978), pp. 89–96. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D25">
   <bib>Pulgram, Ernst. Syllable, Word, Nexus, Cursus. The Hague: Mouton, 1970. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D26">
   <bib>Quirk, Randolph, et al. "Studies in the Correspondence of Prosodic to Grammatical Features
    in English." Proceedings of the Ninth International Congress of Linguists. The Hague: Mouton,
    1964. pp. 679–91. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D27">
   <bib>Robins, R. H. "Aspects of Prosodic Analysis." Proceedings of the University of Durham
    Philological Society, series 8, vol. 1, series B, no. 1 (1957), pp. 1–12. Rpt in Phonetics in
    Linguistics: A Book of Readings. Ed. W. E. Jones and J. Laver. London: Longman Group, 1973. pp.
    262–77. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D28">
   <bib>Robson, Ernest M. "An Orthographic Way of Writing English Prosody." Visible Language 9
    (1975): 357–72. </bib>
   <notes> A system is devised to visually display the suprasegmental features of pitch, apparent
    amplitude, and time in print by mixing elevation, darkness, and horizontal length of letters in
    various typefaces. The prosodic cues are thus most conspicuously marked. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D29">
   <bib>Scripture, E. W. "Observations on Rhythmic Action." Studies from the Yale Psychological
    Laboratory. Ed. E. W. Scripture. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1889. Vol. 7, pp. 102–8. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D30">
   <bib>-----. "Studies in Melody in English Speech." Philosophische Studien 19 (1902): 590–615. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D31">
   <bib>Tibbitts, Ernest L. "Evidences of Semantic Determinants of Prosodic Features in English."
    Proceedings of the Seventh International Congress of Phonetic Sciences. Ed. André Rigault and
    René Charbonneau. The Hague: Mouton, 1972. pp. 1047–51. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D32">
   <bib>Trager, George L., and Henry Lee Smith, Jr. An Outline of English Structure. Studies in
    Linguistics Occasional Papers, no. 3. Norman, Oklahoma: Battenburg Press, 1951; </bib>
   <notes> rpt Washington, D. C.: American Council of Learned Societies, 1956; rpt New York: Johnson
    Reprint Corp., 1970. 91 pp. Hereafter referred to as Trager-Smith. The widely endorsed
    structural-linguistic description of the phonology and morphology of the English language
    (though soon after challenged by transformational-generative grammar, of course). The core of
    the Trager-Smith system is the identification of four discrete levels of stress (i.e. primary,
    secondary, tertiary, weak), pitch (highest, high, normal, low), and juncture (internal, and
    word-, phrase-, and clause-terminal). The four-level description of stress was immediately
    seized by prosodists and applied to metrics with its two-level (bivalent, on-off, yes-no) ictic
    system, since it was apparent that the two medial degrees of stress could be "promoted" or
    "demoted" depending on context to either fully stressed or weak. See the subsection on
    Structural Metrics beginning at E709. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D33">
   <bib>Uldall, Elizabeth. "Dimensions of Meaning in Intonation." In Honour of Daniel Jones. Ed.
    David Abercrombie et al. London: Longmans, Green, 1964. pp. 271–79. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D34">
   <bib>Wallin, J. E. W. "Researches on the Rhythm of Speech." Studies from the Yale Psychological
    Laboratory. Ed. E. W. Scripture. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1901. Vol. 9, pp. 1–142. </bib>
   <notes> Concludes that a variable quantity exists in all languages. The ratio of long syllables
    to short in spoken verse is 1.7:1. STRESS </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D35">
   <bib>Abercrombie, David. "Some Functions of Silent Stress." Edinburgh Studies in English and
    Scots. Ed. A. J. Aitken et al. London: Longmans, 1971. pp. 147–56. </bib>
   <notes> An important argument for its bearing on metrical theory. Accepting Pike's view of
    English as "stress-timed" (originally suggested by Sir Joshua Steele) and Ladefoged's definition
    of stress as "a gesture of the respiratory muscles," Abercrombie argues that this gesture "has
    nothing to do with loudness"--i.e., the pause is completely phonological and not
    extra-linguistic. Some of its functions are: syntactic, emphatic, terminal, tentative, and
    rhetorical. In verse, these silent stresses or metrical pauses (1) insure a regular number of
    beats in the line, and (2) serve as line-end markers. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D36">
   <bib>Allen, George D. "The Location of Rhythmic Stress in English: An Experimental Study."
    Language and Speech 15 (1972): 72–100, 179–95. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D37">
   <bib>Arnold, G. F. Stress in English Words. Amsterdam: North Holland, 1957. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D38">
   <bib>-----. "Stress in English Words." Lingua 6 (1957): 221–67, 397–441. </bib>
   <notes> D39 Baker, Robert G., and Philip T. Smith. "A Psycholinguistic Study of English Stress
    Assignment Rules." Language and Speech 19 (1976): 9–27. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D40">
   <bib>Beaver, Joseph. "A Note on the Ordering of the Nuclear Stress Rule." Papers in Linguistics
    3 (1970): 405–9. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D41">
   <bib>Berman, Arlene, and Michael Szamosi. "Observations on Sentential Stress." Language Research
    Report No. 5. Cambridge, Mass.: Language Research Foundation, 1971. pp. 119–74;</bib>
   <notes>rpt in Language 48 (1972): 304–25. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D42">
   <bib>Bierwisch, Michael. "Two Critical Problems in Accent Rules." Journal of Linguistics 4
    (1968): 173–78. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D43">
   <bib>Blackie, John Stuart. "On the Place and Power of Accent in Language." In his Horae
    Hellenicae. London: Macmillan, 1874. pp. 320–94. </bib>
   <notes> An indefatigable excursus on the nature of accent in languages, from Classical Greek to
    nineteenth-century English, with a correlate effort at defining and distinguishing the role of
    quantity vs. that of accent. Blackie denies that Greek accent was in any respect different from
    English stress and sketches the history of the "confusion" through Erasmus, Vossius, Gally and
    Foster, Horsley, Munro, and others. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D44">
   <bib>Bolinger, Dwight. "Accent is Predictable (If You're a Mind-Reader)." Language 48 (1972):
    633–44. </bib>
   <notes> D44a -----. "Contrastive Accent and Contrastive Stress." Language 37 (1961): 83-96; rpt
    in his Forms of English (next entry), pp. 101-17. D44b -----. Forms of English: Accent,
    Morpheme, Order. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1965. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D45">
   <bib>-----. "Intersections of Stress and Intonation." Word 11 (1955): 195–203. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D46">
   <bib>-----. "Stress and Information." American Speech 33 (1958): 5–20. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D47">
   <bib>Bresnan, Joan W. "Sentence Stress and Syntactic Transformations." Language 47 (1971):
    257–81. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D48">
   <bib>-----. "Stress and Syntax: A Reply." Language 48 (1972): 326–42. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D49">
   <bib>Chiba, T. A Study of Accent: Research into its Nature and Scope in the Light of
    Experimental Phonetics. Tokyo: Fuzanbo, 1935. 123 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in Quarterly Journal of Speech 23 (1937): 313–18. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D50">
   <bib>Chomsky, Noam, Morris Hall, and Fred Lukoff. "On Accent and Juncture in English." For Roman
    Jakobson. The Hague: Mouton, 1956. pp. 65–80. </bib>
   <notes> Criticizes the Trager-Smith system. See also the response: D50a D51 </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D51">
   <bib>Percival, Keith. "A Rule Restated." General Linguistics 4 (1959): 70–72. </bib>
   <notes> Cook, Mary Jane. "Phonetic and Phonemic Properties of Stress in English." DA 22 (1962):
    3653A (Texas). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D52">
   <bib>Cygan, Jan. "Preliminaries to the Study of the English Word-Stress." Studia Anglica
    Posnaniensia 6 (1974): 117–24. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D53">
   <bib>Danielsson, Bror. Studies in the Accentuation of Polysyllabic Latin, Greek, and Romance
    Loan- Words in English. Stockholm Studies in English, no. 3. Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell,
    1948; Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1948. 664 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in JEGP 50 (1951): 537–38; in Anglia 70 (1951): 123–26; in Language 28 (1952):
    140–41; in MLN 67 (1952): 266–67; in MLR 45 (1950): 360–62. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D54">
   <bib>Davis, Edwin B. "English Stress Accent." College English 5 (1943): 136–41. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D55">
   <bib>Eliason, N. E., and R. C. Davis. The Effect of Stress upon Quantity in Disyllables: An
    Experimental and Historical Study. Indiana University Publications, Science Series, no. 8.
    Bloomington, Ind.: Indiana University Press, 1939. 56 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in JEGP 40 (1941): 392–93; in MLQ 1 (1940): 266–67. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D56">
   <bib>Ellis, Alexander J. "On the Physical Constituents of Accent and Emphasis." Transactions of
    the Philological Society, 1873–74, pp. 113–64. </bib>
   <notes> An important nineteenth-century study of stress in English, German, French, Italian,
    Latin, and Greek, which also influenced Mayor (E591). See sections 17–22 on English: Ellis
    distinguishes as primary features length, pitch (frequency), force (amplitude, loudness), form
    (timbre), and glide. Accent is the result of specific variances in pitch and force; emphasis
    adds to these the expressive uses of form and length. A capsule definition: English accent may
    be defined as fixed force and free pitch. Interestingly, Ellis gives a very detailed synopsis of
    the system of Sir Joshua Steele (E394). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D57">
   <bib>Fry, Dennis B. "The Dependence of Stress Judgments on Vowel Formant Structure." Proceedings
    of the Fifth International Congress of Phonetic Sciences. Basel: Karger, 1965. pp. 306–11. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D58">
   <bib>-----. "Duration and Intensity as Physical Correlates of Linguistic Stress." Journal of the
    Acoustical Society 27 (1955): 765–68. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D59">
   <bib>-----. "Experiments in the Perception of Stress." Language and Speech 1 (1958): 126–52. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D60">
   <bib>Fuchs, Anna. "'Normalzer' und 'Kontrastiver' Akzent." Lingua 38 (1976): 293–312. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D61">
   <bib>Fudge, Erik. "English Word Stress: An Examination of Some Basic Assumptions." Essays on the
    Sound Pattern of English. Ed. Didier L. Goyvaerts and Geoffrey K. Pullum. Ghent: Story-Scientia,
    1975. pp. 277–323. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D62">
   <bib>Gärding, Eva, and L. J. Gerstman. "The Effect of Changes in the Location of an Intonation
    Peak on Sentence Stress." Studia Linguistica 14 (1960): 57–59. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D63">
   <bib>Gage, William W. "Syntax of English Stress: Interpretation of Three Approaches." Linguistic
    Studies in Memory of R. S. Harrell. Ed. Don G. Stuart. Washington, D.C.: Georgetown University
    Press, 1967. pp. 47–59. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D64">
   <bib>Gilbert, A. J. "The Treatment of Unstressed Syllables in Eighteenth-Century English."
    Diss., University of Lancaster, 1974. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D65">
   <bib>Gimson, A. C. "The Linguistic Relevance of Stress in English." Zeitschrift für Phonetik und
    allgemeine Sprachwissenschaft 9 (1956): 143–49; rpt in Phonetics in Linguistics: A Book of
    Readings. Ed. W. E. Jones and J. Laver. London: Longman Group, 1973. pp. 94–102. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D66">
   <bib>Göes, Alvar N. The Stress System of English. Acta Universitatis Upsaliensis, no. 19.
    Stockholm, 1974. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D67">
   <bib>Halle, Morris. "Stress Rules in English: A New Version." Linguistic Inquiry 4 (1973):
    451–64; rpt in Essays on the Sound Pattern of English. Ed. Didier L. Goyvaerts and G. K. Pullum.
    Ghent: Story-Scientia, 1975. pp. 261–76. </bib>
   <notes> --- Halle, Morris, and Samuel Jay Keyser. English Stress: Its Form, Its Growth, and Its
    Role in Verse. See E777. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D68">
   <bib>Harris, Patricia M. "The Effect of Accentuation and Syllabification upon Vowel Sounds in
    Syllabic Patterns." DAI 34 (1974): 7211A (North Carolina). </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D69">
   <bib>Hemphill, George. "Accent, Stress, and Emphasis." College English 17 (1956): 337–40. </bib>
   <notes> Historical variations in the definitions of these three terms. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D70">
   <bib>Hoard, James E., and Clarence Sloat. "Variation in English Stress Placement." New Ways of
    Analyzing Variations in English. Ed. Charles-James N. Bailey and Roger W. Shay. Washington,
    D.C.: Georgetown University Press, 1973. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D71">
   <bib>Hultzen, Lee S. "Stress and Intonation." General Linguistics 1 (1955): 35–42. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D72">
   <bib>Jassem, Wiktor. "Stress in Modern English." Bulletin de la société polonaise de
    linguistique 9 (1952): 21–49. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D73">
   <bib>Jeaffreson, J. W. "Stress and Rhythm in Speech." Transactions of the Philological Society,
    1938, pp. 73–95. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D74">
   <bib>Johnson, C. Douglas. "Unbounded Expressions in Rules of Stress and Accent." Glossa 4
    (1970): 185–96. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D75">
   <bib>Katayama, Y. " . . . Semantic Influence on Stress Perception." The Study of Sounds. Tokyo:
    Phonetic Society of Japan, 1966. pp. 374–87. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D76">
   <bib>Kingdon, Roger. The Groundwork of English Stress . London: Longmans, 1958. Rev: in Études
    Anglaises 13 (1960): 467–69. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D77">
   <bib>Kiparsky, Paul. "Metrical Structure Assignment Is Cyclic." Linguistic Inquiry 10 (1979):
    42–41. </bib>
   <notes> Extension and revision of Liberman and Prince (D83). See Chen (L1542). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D78">
   <bib>Ladefoged, Peter, et al. "Syllables and Stress." Miscellanea Phonetica 3 (1958): 1–14; rpt
    in Phonetics in Linguistics: A Book of Readings. Ed. W. E. Jones and J. Laver. London: Longman
    Group, 1973. pp. 204–17. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D79">
   <bib>Langendoen, D. Terence. "Some Problems in the Description of English Accentuation." Essays
    on the Sound Pattern of English. Ed. Didier L. Goyvaerts and Geoffrey K. Pullum. Ghent:
    Story-Scientia, 1975. pp. 205–18. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D80">
   <bib>Lee, Gregory. "English Word Stress." Papers from the Fifth Regional Meeting of the Chicago
    Linguistic Society. Ed. Robert L. Binnick et al. Chicago: University of Chicago Department of
    Linguistics, 1969. pp. 389–406. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D81">
   <bib>-----. "English Word Stress and Phrase Stress." Essays on the Sound Pattern of English. Ed.
    Didier L. Goyvaerts and Geoffrey K. Pullum. Ghent: Story-Scientia, 1975. pp. </bib>
   <notes> 219–47. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D82">
   <bib>Lehto, Leena. English Stress and Its Modification by Intonation: An Analytic and Synthetic
    Study of Acoustic Parameters. Helsinki, 1969. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D83">
   <bib>Liberman, Mark, and Alan Prince. "On Stress and Linguistic Rhythm." Linguistic Inquiry 8
    (1977): 249–336. </bib>
   <notes> As if philology (here, phonetics) had failed historically to rescue (i.e. explicate)
    meter, now metrics will come to the aid of its substantive, phonology. In a major theoretical
    statement, the authors propose a theory wherein the stressing of English syllables is
    determined, on the deep level, by "the alignment of linguistic material with a 'metrical grid,'"
    a process which is "reminiscent of the traditional picture of verse scansion, so that the theory
    as a whole deserves the name 'metrical.'" Thus, in the Liberman-Prince procedure, one simply
    marks relative prominence at the constituent level, then allows the standard Compound and
    Nuclear Stress Rules to apply to the derivation of both word-stress and phrase-stress. But there
    are cases in which stressing shifts unexpectedly in order to preserve alternation of stressed
    and unstressed syllables (i.e. to avoid contiguous clashing stresses); this phenomenon the
    theory accounts for via an optional Rhythm Rule, whereby the metrical grid realigns itself
    systematically, a process the authors term "scansion." Intriguing . . . that the structure of
    verse could explicate the structure of the language. See Nanni (D98), Kiparsky (E826), and Chen
    (L1542). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D84">
   <bib>Lieberman, Philip. "Some Acoustic Correlates of Word Stress in American English." Journal
    of the Acoustical Society 32 (1960): 451–54. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D85">
   <bib>Lunney, Henry W. M. "Location of Stress: Classé's Experiment Reinstrumented." Zeitschrift
    für Phonetik, Sprachwissenschaft und Kommunikationsforschung 27 (1974): 320–27. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D86">
   <bib>Lutstorf, Heinz T. The Stressing of Compounds in Modern English. Bern, 1960. Rev: in
    English Studies 44 (1963): 60–62. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D87">
   <bib>McAllister, Robert. "The Nuclear Stress Rule and the Description of English Stress."
    Proceedings of the Seventh International Congress of Phonetic Sciences. Ed. André Rigault and
    René Charbonneau. The Hague: Mouton, 1972. pp. 966–73. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D88">
   <bib>McCarthy, John J. "On Stress and Syllabification." Linguistic Inquiry 10 (1979): 443–66. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D89">
   <bib>McClean, Michael D. "The Acoustic Parameters of Stress In Relation To Syllable Position,
    Speech Loudness, and Rate." Proceedings of the Seventh International Congress of Phonetic
    Sciences. Ed. André Rigault and René Charbonneau. The Hague: Mouton, 1972. pp. 974–77. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D90">
   <bib>Macdonald, R. Ross. "A Brief Note on Stress on Prepositions in English." Georgetown
    University Working Papers on Language and Linguistics 6 (1975): 75–78.</bib>
   <notes>Also in the same journal: </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D91">
   <bib>-----. "Prepositions and Stress in English." 8 (1975): 46–52. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D92">
   <bib>Makivchi, Masaru. "Morphophonemic Rules for English Stress." The Study of Sounds. Tokyo:
    Phonetic Society of Japan, 1966. Vol. 12, pp. 363–73. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D93">
   <bib>Martin, James G. "Rhythmic (Hierarchical) Versus Serial Structure in Speech and Other
    Behavior." Psychological Review 79 (1972): 487–509. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D94">
   <bib>-----. "Rhythm-Induced Judgments of Word-Stress in Sentences." Journal of Verbal Learning
    and Verbal Behavior 9 (1970): 627–33. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D95">
   <bib>Miller, C. B. "Accent: Classes and Variations." Proceedings of the Second International
    Congress of Phonetic Sciences. Ed. Daniel Jones and D. B. Fry. Cambridge: Cambridge University
    Press, 1936. pp. 235–39. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D96">
   <bib>Mol, H., and E. M. Uhlembeck. "The Linguistic Relevance of Intensity in Stress." Lingua 2
    (1956): 205–13. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D97">
   <bib>Morton, John, and Wiktor Jassem. "Acoustic Correlates of Stress." Language and Speech 8
    (1965): 159–81. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D98">
   <bib>Nanni, Debbie L. "Stressing Words in -Ative." Linguistic Inquiry 8 (1977): 752–62. </bib>
   <notes> Suggests a solution to the problem of words ending in this suffix, which has two
    alternative stress patterns. Based on Liberman and Prince (D83). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D99">
   <bib>Nessly, Larry. "Halle &amp; Keyser: English Stress." Language 53 (1977): 655–66. </bib>
   <notes> Reviews the first two sections of English Stress (stress rules; historical development)
    with no attention to the third section on metrics. See E777. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D100">
   <bib>Newman, Stanley. "On the Stress System of English." Word 2 (1946): 171–87. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D101">
   <bib>Ondráchková, Jana. "Stress and Duration in CVCV and CVCVCV Groups." Linguistics no. 83
    (1972): 56–63. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D102">
   <bib>Pike, Kenneth L., and Willard Kindberg. "A Problem in Multiple Stresses." Word 12 (1956):
    415–28. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D103">
   <bib>Prick van Wely, F. P. H. "Über den Rhythmus der and-Verbindungen im Englischen." Englische
    Studien 39 (1908): 468–69; 45 (1912): 467–69; 48 (1914–15): 477–79. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D104">
   <bib>Schane, Sanford A. "Non-Cyclic English Word Stress." Essays on the Sound Pattern of
    English. Ed. Didier L. Goyvaerts and Geoffrey K. Pullum. Ghent: Story-Scientia, 1975. pp.
    249–59. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D105">
   <bib>-----. "Rhythm, Accent, and Stress in English Words." Linguistic Inquiry 10 (1979):
    483–502. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D106">
   <bib>Schmerling, Susan F. Aspects of English Sentence Stress. Austin: University of Texas Press,
    1976. </bib>
   <notes> Criticism of Chomsky-Halle (D1). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D107">
   <bib>-----. "A Re-Examination of 'Normal Stress.'" Language 50 (1974): 66–73. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D108">
   <bib>Schramm, Wilber. "The Acoustic Nature of Accent of American Speech." American Speech 13
    (1937): 49–56. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D109">
   <bib>Scott, Fred Newton. "The Accentual Structure of Isolable English Phrases." PMLA 33 (1918):
    73–84. </bib>
   <notes> Examines stress-patterns in idioms and the titles of novels. The commonest English phrase
    is four syllables long and has a prevalently iambic rhythm. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D110">
   <bib>-----. "The Order of Words in Certain Rhythm-Groups." MLN 28 (1913): 237–39. </bib>
   <notes> Cites examples contradicting Jespersen's claim that in cases where phrases are formed by
    monosyllable + and + disyllable, the monosyllable comes first, partly because that order has a
    smoother rhythm. The proportion of the two types is in fact roughly 50–50. </notes>
  </item>

  <item id="D111">
   <bib>John Whyte, "The Order of Monosyllables and Disyllables in Alliteration" (MLN 30 [1915]:
    175–76) </bib>
   <notes> finds that 84% of the alliterative formulae in Willert (C126) place the monosyllable
    first. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="D112">
   <bib>Settera, George E. "English Stress." Glossa 8 (1974): 83–108. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D113">
   <bib>Severynse, Marion. "Irregular Stress Patterning in Lexical Compounds." Harvard Studies in
    Phonology, Vol. I. Ed. George N. Clements. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Department of
    Linguistics, 1977. pp. 369–89. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D114">
   <bib>Sharp, A. E. "The Analysis of Stress and Juncture in English." Transactions of the
    Philological Society, 1960, pp. 104–35. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D115">
   <bib>Sloat, Clarence. "Stress in English." Glossa 8 (1974): 121–39. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D116">
   <bib>Stampe, David. "On Chapter Nine" [of Chomsky-Halle (D1)]. Issues in Phonological Theory.
    Ed. Michael J. Kenstowicz and C. W. Kisseberth. The Hague: Mouton, 1973. pp. 44–52. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D117">
   <bib>Stutterheim, C. F. P. "Accentual Relationships as Viewed and Used in Language." Dutch
    Studies 1 (1974): 27–36. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D118">
   <bib>Tibbits, E. L. English Stress Patterns. Cambridge: Heffer, 1967. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D119">
   <bib>Tiffin, J., and M. D. Steer. "An Experimental Analysis of Emphasis." Speech Monographs 4
    (1937): 69–74. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D120">
   <bib>Trager, George L. "The Theory of Accentual Systems." Language, Culture, and Personality.
    Ed. Leslie Spier et al. Menasha, Wis.: Sapir Memorial Publication Fund, 1941. pp. 131–45. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D121">
   <bib>Vanderslice, Ralph. The Prosodic Component: Lacuna in Transformational Theory. Santa
    Monica, California: Rand Corporation, 1968; 57 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Complaining that the Chomsky-Halle generative phonology (D1) both ignores intonation and
    oversimplifies stress, Vanderslice offers an alternative, simplified model with four binary
    features: Accent, Emphasis, Cadence, and Endglide. He claims that his system will more
    adequately explain "accent deletion" and "stress shift" than either Trager-Smith or
    Chomsky-Halle. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D122">
   <bib>Vanvik, Arne. On Stress in Present-Day English. Oslo, 1961. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D123">
   <bib>Waldo, George S. "The Significance of Accentuation in English Words." Proceedings of the
    Ninth International Congress of Linguists. Ed. Horace G. Lunt. The Hague: Mouton, 1964. pp.
    204–10. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D124">
   <bib>Western, August. On Sentence-Rhythm and Word-Order in Modern English. Christiana, 1908. 51
    pp. </bib>
   <notes> PITCH </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D125">
   <bib>Bolinger, Dwight L. "Intonation and Analysis." Word 5 (1949): 248–54. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D126">
   <bib>-----. "Intonation and Grammar." Language Learning 8 (1958): 31–37. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D127">
   <bib>-----. "Intonation: Levels Versus Configuration." Word 7 (1951): 199–210. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D128">
   <bib>-----. Intonation: Selected Readings. London: Penguin, 1972. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D129">
   <bib>-----. "The Melody of Language." Modern Language Forum 40 (1955): 19–30. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="D130">
   <bib>-----. "A Theory of Pitch Accent in English." Word 14 (1958): 109–49. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D131">
   <bib>Glasgow, George M. "A Semantic Index of Vocal Pitch." Speech Monographs 19 (1952): 64–68. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D132">
   <bib>Jenkins, Robert A. "Perception of Pitch, Timbre, and Loudness." Journal of the Acoustical
    Society 33 (1961): 1550–57. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D133">
   <bib>Katwijk, A. F. W. van. "Implicit Knowledge of Pitch Patterns in the Perception of Accented
    Syllables." Löwen und Sprachtiger: Akten des VIII Linguistischen Kolloquiums Löwen. Ed. Rudolf
    Kern. Louvain: Peeters, 1976. pp. 385–94. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D134">
   <bib>Malone, Kemp. "Pitch Patterns in English." SP 23 (1926): 371–79. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D135">
   <bib>Siertsema, B. "Timbre, Pitch, and Intonation." Lingua 11 (1962): 388–98. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D136">
   <bib>Stevens, S. S. "Psychological Acoustics: Pitch and Loudness." Journal of the Acoustical
    Society 8 (1936): 1–13. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D137">
   <bib>Takefuta, Yukio, et al. "A Statistical Analysis of the Melody Curves in the Intonation of
    American English." Proceedings of the Seventh International Congress of Phonetic Sciences. Ed.
    André Rigault and René Charbonneau. The Hague: Mouton, 1972. pp. 1035–39. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D138">
   <bib>Wells, Rulon S. "The Pitch Phonemes of English. Language 21 (1945): 27–39. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D139">
   <bib>Woodrow, Herbert. "The Role of Pitch in Rhythm." Psychological Review 18 (1911): 54–77. </bib>
   <notes> TIMING, ISOCHRONY, PAUSE, LENGTH </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D140">
   <bib>Allen, George D. "Speech Rhythm: Its Relation to Performance Universals and Articulatory
    Timing." Journal of Phonetics 3 (1975): 75–86. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D141">
   <bib>-----. "Towards a Description of Stress-Timing in Spoken English." Proceedings of the
    Conference on Language and Language Behavior. Ed. Eric M. Zale. New York:
    Appleton-Century-Crofts, 1968. pp. 267–82. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D142">
   <bib>Bolinger, Dwight L. "Length, Vowel, Juncture." Linguistics no. 1 (1963): 5–29. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D143">
   <bib>Browne, Sandra C. "Phonological Aspects of Timing." The Fourth LACUS Forum, 1977. </bib>
   <notes> Ed. Michel Paradis. Columbia, S. C.: Hornbeam, 1978. pp. 444–50. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D144">
   <bib>Coleman, Colette L. "A Study of Acoustical and Perceptual Attributes of Isochrony in Spoken
    English." DAI 35 (1975): 4724A. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D145">
   <bib>Cowan, J. M., and B. Bloch. "An Experimental Study of Pause in English Grammar." American
    Speech 23 (1948): 89–99. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D146">
   <bib>DeBelaval, Domitila D. "An Investigation of Isochronism in the Rhythm of American English
    Speech." DA 27 (1966): 1355A (L.S.U.). </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D147">
   <bib>Duckworth, James E. "An Inquiry into the Validity of the Isochronic Hypothesis." DA 26
    (1966): 5424A (Connecticut). </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="D148">
   <bib>Eliason, N. "Two Notes on Vowel and Consonant Quantity." American Speech 17 (1942): 166–68. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D149">
   <bib>Goldhauber, Gerald M. "PAUSAL: A Computer Program to Identify and Measure Pauses." Western
    Speech 37 (1973): 23–26. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D150">
   <bib>Goldman-Eisler, Frieda. "The Distribution of Pause Durations in Speech." Language and
    Speech 4 (1961): 232–27. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D151">
   <bib>Haggard, Mark. "Correlations between Successive Segment Durations: Values in Clusters."
    Journal of Phonetics 1 (1973): 111–16. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D152">
   <bib>House, Arthur S. "On Vowel Duration in English." Journal of the Acoustical Society 33
    (1961): 1174–78. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D153">
   <bib>Kiatt, Dennis H. "Vowel Lengthening is Syntactically Determined in a Connected Discourse."
    Journal of Phonetics 3 (1975): 129–40. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D154">
   <bib>Kohler, Klaus J. "The Significance of Pauses." Proceedings of the Seventh International
    Congress of Phonetic Sciences. Ed. André Rigault and René Charbonneau. The Hague: Mouton, 1972.
    pp. 905–13. </bib>
   <notes> Pauses at regular intervals increase short-term memory. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D155">
   <bib>Lehiste, Ilse. "Isochrony Reconsidered." Journal of Phonetics 5 (1977): 253–63. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D156">
   <bib>-----. "The Temporal Realization of Morphological and Syntactic Boundaries." Working Papers
    in Linguistics 9 (1971): 114–30. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D157">
   <bib>-----. "The Timing of Utterances and Linguistic Boundaries." Journal of the Acoustical
    Society 51 (1972): 2018–24. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D158">
   <bib>Lieberman, Philip M. Sawashima, K. S. Harris, and T. Gay. "The Articulatory Implementation
    of the Breath-Group and Prominence: Crico-Thyroid Muscular Activity in Intonation." Language 46
    (1970): 312–27. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D159">
   <bib>Lisker, Leigh. "On 'Explaining' Vowel Duration Variations." Glossa 8 (1974): 233–45. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D160">
   <bib>-----. "On Time and Timing in Speech." Current Trends in Linguistics, XII: Linguistics and
    Adjacent Arts and Sciences. Ed. Thomas A. Sebeok. 4 vols. The Hague: Mouton, 1975. Part 4, pp.
    2387–2418. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D161">
   <bib>Martin, James G. "On Judging Pauses in Spontaneous Speech." Journal of Verbal Learning and
    Verbal Behavior 9 (1970): 75–78. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D162">
   <bib>Morgan, Bayard Q. "Some Functions of Time in Speech." American Speech 20 (1945): 28–33. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D163">
   <bib>Newcomb, William B. "Some Tempo Manifestations of the Terminals of English." DA 20 (1960):
    4103A (Wisconsin). </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D164">
   <bib>Nooteboom, S. G. "The Perceptual Reality of Some Prosodic Durations." Journal of Phonetics
    1 (1973): 25–45. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D165">
   <bib>Oliva, Joseph, and Judith Duchan. "Three Levels of Temporal Structuring in Spoken
    Language." The Fourth LACUS Forum, 1977. Ed. Michel Paradis. Columbia, S. C.: Hornbeam, 1978.
    pp. 460–68. </bib>
   <notes> Defines three levels: rhythmic (stress and length of syllables), metric (phrasal units
    equal in time from major juncture to major juncture), and beat-and-tempo (timing adjustments
    within the phrase). D165a Patch, Katharine. "Syllable Duration in Prose Read Aloud." Diss.,
    University of Edinburgh, 1962. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D166">
   <bib>Petersen, Niels R. "Identification and Discrimination of Vowel Duration." Annual Report of
    the Institute of Phonetics, University of Copenhagen 10 (1976): 57–83. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D167">
   <bib>Peterson, Gordon E., and Ilse Lehiste. "Duration of Syllable Nuclei in English." Journal of
    the Acoustical Society 32 (1960): 693–703. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D168">
   <bib>Port, Robert F. "The Influence of Speaking Tempo on the Duration of Stressed Vowel and
    Medial Stop in English Trochee Words." DAI 38 (1977): 233A. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D169">
   <bib>Rochester, S. R. "The Significance of Pauses in Spontaneous Speech." Journal of
    Psycholinguistic Research 2 (1973): 51–81. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D170">
   <bib>Rositzske, H. A. "Vowel Length in General American Speech." Language 15 (1939): 99–109. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D171">
   <bib>Shen, Yao, and G. G. Peterson. Isochronism in English. Studies in Linguistics Occasional
    Papers, no. 9. Buffalo: University of Buffalo Department of Anthropology and Linguistics, 1962.
    See also E417. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D172">
   <bib>Stene, Aasta. Hiatus in English: Problems of Catenation and Juncture. Anglistica, vol. 3.
    Copenhagen: Rosenkilde and Bagger, 1954. 102 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in Anglia 73 (1955): 257–68; in MLN 70 (1955): 458–59; in Études Anglaises 9 (1956):
    147; in Lingua 9 (1960): 110–12. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D173">
   <bib>Sumera, Magdalena. "The Concept of Isochrony: Some Problems of Analysis." Studies in
    Linguistics 25 (1975): 35–41. </bib>
   <notes> In speech, music, and verse. A noteworthy paper on general principles and problems with
    this concept. Bibliography. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D174">
   <bib>Uldall, Elizabeth T. "Isochronous Stresses in R[eceived] P[ronunciation]." Form &amp;
    Substance: Phonetic and Linguistic Papers. Ed. L. L. Hammerich et al. Copenhagen: Akademisk
    Forlag, 1971. pp. 205–10. </bib>
   <notes> Based on the work of Abercrombie (E102); the text of a prose parable, "The North Wind and
    the Sun," is divided into isochronous "feet," each foot beginning with the onset of a strong
    syllable. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D175">
   <bib>-----. "Relative Durations of Syllables in Two-Syllable Rhythmic Feet in R. P. in Connected
    Speech." Work in Progress, No. 5. Edinburgh: Department of Phonetics and Linguistics, University
    of Edinburgh, 1972. pp. 110–111. </bib>
   <notes> Experimental evidence generally confirms the three types of disyllabic configu- rations
    hypothesized by Abercrombie (E103), strong-weak being also long-short in a simple proportion of
    2:1, etc. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D176">
   <bib>-----. "Rhythm in Very Rapid R. P." Language and Speech 21 (1978): 397–402. </bib>
   <notes> Neither in a very rapid nor a normal reading of "The North Wind and the Sun" were the
    rhythmic "feet" isochronous. Longer feet took longer. D177 Umeda, Noriko. "Vowel Duration in
    American English." Journal of the Acoustical Society 58 (1975): 434–45. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D178">
   <bib>Weller, Herbert C. "Vegetative Rhythm Determinative of Speech Patterns." Journal of Speech
    Disorders 6 (1941): 161–71. </bib>
   <notes> Speculations on the relation of the rhythm of speech to the rhythm of breathing and
    related cardiac rhythms, bolstered by experimental evidence suggesting that "the normal speech
    phrase is a rhythmic unit within the rhythm of breathing." KINESTHETIC RHYTHM Experimental
    studies of the nature of rhythmic patterning in simple sounds (clicks or beats, which could be
    varied in intensity, duration, timing, and grouping), human motor responses, human
    speech-sounds, as well as other sensory stimuli, music, and dance, have generally drawn a
    fundamental distinction between objective rhythms (what is actually spoken or produced) and
    subjective rhythms (what the mind "hears" or constructs out of what it is given, based on expec-
    tation, projection, and an astonishing internal mechanism for the simplification and
    hierarchical ordering of complex recurrent stimuli). There have been many studies, and those
    which have examined sets of linguistic and prelinguistic sounds have frequently employed the
    terminology of versification, calling the groupings of features trochaic, anapestic, etc. Very
    often these studies have also applied their findings about clicks, taps, and nonsense syllables
    directly to verse, drawing conclusions about the nature of poetic meter or rhythm. In most of
    these studies the subjective aspect of rhythm is understandably given primary attention; hence
    the title above. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D179">
   <bib>Bolton, Thaddeus L. "Rhythm." American Journal of Psychology 6 (1894): 145–238; additions,
    pp. 310–11; corrections, p. 488. </bib>
   <notes> A sweeping study of subjective rhythmic phenomena in sound, with discussions of ritual,
    dance, and music, and an extensive discussion of rhythm in poetry (see pp. 167–78, 234–38) as
    well as the theories of Guest (E543), Lanier (E364), Corson (B40), and Poe (E315). Conclusions
    begin on p. 232. The auditors' responses to series of clicks which varied in intensity and
    duration showed that in the grouping of such stimuli an accented impulse is heard as falling
    first in the group, whereas a longer impulse is heard as falling last in the group. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D180">
   <bib>Garner, W. R. The Processing of Information and Structure. Potomac, Md.: Halstead Press,
    1974. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D181">
   <bib>Garner, W. R., and R. L. Gottwald. "The Perception and Learning of Temporal Patterns."
    Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology 20 (1968): 97–109. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D182">
   <bib>-----. "Some Perceptual Factors in the Learning of Sequential Patterns of Binary Events."
    Journal of Verbal Learning and Verbal Behavior 6 (1967): 582–89. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D183">
   <bib>MacDougall, Robert. "Rhythm, Time, and Number." American Journal of Psychology 13 (1902):
    88–97. </bib>
   <notes> Not an experimental study but a theoretical argument that draws skeptical conclusions
    about the interference of motor-responses and habituation with accurate time discrimination.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D184">
   <bib>-----. "The Structure of Simple Rhythm Forms." Harvard Psychological Studies, vol. 1.
    Psychological Review Monograph Supplement 4 (1903): 309–412. </bib>
   <notes> Difficult to assay; no conclusion is provided and the language is very dense. The author
    is interested in the hierarchical ordering of complex impressions (both objective and subjective
    (into simpler groupings (when the rate is fast, for example, a "dipodic" grouping principle
    usually appears). The three aspects of rhythm are Recurrence, Accentuation, and Rate. The
    results are applied to poetic meter on pp. 410–11; MacDougall suggests that a meter is not at
    all a simple repetition of identical elements: "both intensively and temporally [the rhythmic
    group] is moulded by its function in the whole sequence, the earlier iambic of a heroic measure
    being unlike the later, the dactyl which precedes a measure of finality different from that
    which introduces the series." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D185">
   <bib>Michon, J. A. Timing in Temporal Tracking. Assen: Van Gorcum, 1967. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D186">
   <bib>Miyake, Ishiro. "Researches on Rhythmic Action." Studies from the Yale Psychological
    Laboratory. Ed. E. W. Scripture. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1902. Vol. 10, pp. 1–48. </bib>
   <notes> Experiments in measurement of visual and aural stimuli, and especially of isochrony,
    intensity, and pitch in the rhythm of speech. Miyake was a student of Scripture's. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D187">
   <bib>Preusser, D. "The Effect of Structure and Rate on the Recognition and Description of
    Auditory Temporal Patterns." Perception and Psychophysics 11 (1972): 233–40. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D188">
   <bib>Preusser, D., W. R. Garner, and R. L. Gottwald. "Perceptual Organization of Two- Element
    Temporal Patterns as a Function of their Component One-Element Patterns." American Journal of
    Psychology 83 (1970): 151–70. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D189">
   <bib>Ross, Felix B. "The Measurement of Time-Sense as an Element in the Sense of Rhythm."
    University of Iowa Studies in Psychology, no. 6. Psychological Monographs 17, 3 (1914): 166–72. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D190">
   <bib>Royer, F. L., and W. R. Garner. "Perceptual Organization of Nine-Element Auditory Temporal
    Patterns." Perception and Psychophysics 7 (1970): 115–20. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D191">
   <bib>-----. "Response Uncertainty and Perceptual Difficulty of Auditory Temporal Patterns."
    Perception and Psychophysics 1 (1966): 41–47. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D192">
   <bib>Ruckmich, C. A. "A Bibliography of Rhythm." American Journal of Psychology 24 (1913):
    508–19; 26 (1915): 457–59; 29 (1918): 214–18; 35 (1924): 407–13. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D193">
   <bib>-----. "The Role of Kinaesthesis in the Perception of Rhythm." American Journal of
    Psychology 24 (1913): 305–59. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D194">
   <bib>Schick, H. F. "The Effect of Practice Upon the Bi-Manual Production of Rhythmic Patterns at
    Various Tempos." Diss., Ohio State University, 1930. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D195">
   <bib>Squire, C. R. "A Genetic Study of Rhythm." American Journal of Psychology 12 (1901):
    492–589. </bib>
   <notes> A study of rhythmic grouping in speech. Children were given lines of a repeated syllable
    and asked to read them aloud in varying configurations of stressing, pitches, and
    time-groupings. For involuntary rhythmical grouping, "primary rhythm" (equal pausing after every
    syllable) came most naturally, followed by time-grouping, wherein time preceded stress and pitch
    as the most important principle of grouping. Rather extensive conclusions (pp. 533–60) are drawn
    from all this, the most relevant of which is that the trochee seems to be the most natural
    grouping-form. The children found amphibrachs and anapests nearly impossible. D196 Stetson, R.
    H. "A Motor Theory of Rhythm and Discrete Succession." Psychological Review 12 (1905): 250–70,
    293–350. Inter alia, Stetson agrees with Squire that "judgments of temporal equality or
    inequality play no part in the rhythm experience." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D197">
   <bib>Vos, Peter G. "Temporal Duration Factors in the Perception of Auditory Rhythmic Patterns."
    Scientific Aesthetics 1 (1977): 183–99. </bib>
   <notes> Important bibliography. Given a unit of two tones, keeping intensity and frequency of the
    tones constant but varying the durations of both tones and silences, six configurations are
    possible. Which will be perceived as "iambic" and which "trochaic"? The hypothesis that longer
    tones will be perceived as accented and shorter as unaccented was confirmed, as was a second
    hypothesis that "in the absence of any objective cue for rhythmic perception . . . a trochaic
    rhythm [will be] induced." Twenty-one varieties of triadic units are possible, of which seven
    were tested here; results agreed with those for duple units. The methodologies of Stetson and
    Woodrow are criticized. Conclusion: variance in temporal structure alone "is a sufficient
    objective condition for the perception of order and accent and, hence, rhythm." Review of the
    literature at the end. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D198">
   <bib>Wallin, J. E. Wallace. "Experimental Studies of Rhythm and Time." Psychological Review 18
    (1911): 100–31, 202–22; 19 (1912): 271–98. </bib>
   <notes> Further inquiry into the degree of distortion in interval required to render a series of
    sounds unrhythmical. Variance of 7% in intervalic durations was accepted by auditors as
    rhythmical, but a 13% variation destroyed the rhythmicity. Lengthening of interval was
    invariably perceived but shortening was not. Subjects were able to discriminate between five
    degrees of deviation, which are termed rhythm limens. But they were able to apprehend deviations
    of time before they perceived deviations of rhythm; the former seem to be a series of discrete
    points, the latter a curve or field. The tempo of a rhythmic series has important effects on
    auditors, the most preferred rate being 120 clicks per minutes, or from .5 to .6 seconds per
    interval. Still, when intervals were irregular, the series was heard as trochaic rather than
    iambic. Also studied were auditors' abilities to estimate a mid-tempo halfway between two given
    tempos. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D199">
   <bib>Woodrow, Herbert. A Quantitative Study of Rhythm: The Effect of Variations in Intensity,
    Rate, and Duration. Archives of Psychology, vol. 2, no. 14. New York: The Science Press, 1909.
    66 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Experimental work showing that a trochiac rhythm can be changed to an iambic one "by
    increasing the interval immediately following the louder sound or by decreasing the interval
    immediately preceding it." When the intervals between sounds are equal but every other sound is
    raised in intensity, hearers perceive the sequence as trochaic: "a regularly recurring
    difference in intensity exerts a tendency towards rhythmical groups with the more intense sound
    at the beginning." This sort of work is important for any theory about the perception of poetic
    rhythm or meter. PROSE RHYTHM Over the course of the past century a number of metrists who
    studied English verse also turned their attention to stress-patterning and other forms of
    rhythmic organization in prose as well, partly because they recognized that verse is made up of
    the syntactic structures of prose and partly because they were interested in the tradition of
    consciously rhythmical prose which stretched back from Joyce, DeQuincey, and Sir Thomas Browne
    through the medieval Latin cursus to the highly stylized cadences of classical Latin prose.
    Efforts to show the presence of the cursus-patterns in the modern languages, however, have been
    thwarted by the fact that many of these patterns are identical to the stress-patterns of the
    naturally occurring phrases--a fact which has considerable significance in itself. The whole
    area is of peripheral interest to versification, so I cite sources without discussion. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D200">
   <bib>Baum, Paul F. The other harmony of prose: an Essay in English Prose Rhythm. Durham: Duke
    University Press, 1952. 230 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in Studies in Linguistics 11 (1953): 42–45; in Études Anglaises 6 (1953): 369–70.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D201">
   <bib>-----. "Prose Rhythm." Princeton (A18), pp. 666–67. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D202">
   <bib>Boulton, Marjorie. "Prose Rhythm." Anatomy of Prose. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul,
    1954. pp. 49–69. </bib>
   <notes> Scansions of passages; allows twenty-two types of feet. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D203">
   <bib>Brantner, Gunther. Prosaakzent und metrisches Schema in englischen Kompositen. Diss., Graz,
    1939. 43 pp. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D204">
   <bib>Byrne, M. St. Clare. "The Foundations of Elizabethan Language." Shakespeare Survey 17
    (1964): 223–39. </bib>
   <notes> See section 3. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D205">
   <bib>Chapman, John. "Clause-Length in English Prose." Dublin Review 158 (1916): 346–52. </bib>
   <notes> Note the reference here to an earlier essay of his in the same journal on sound in
    poetry. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D206">
   <bib>Clark, Albert C. Prose Rhythm in English. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1913; rpt Folcroft, Pa.:
    Folcroft Library Editions, 1974. 19 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A small tract reprinting one lecture. See also D226. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D207">
   <bib>Classé, André. The Rhythm of English Prose. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1939; rpt Norwood,
    Pa.: Norwood Editions, 1975. 138 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in MLR 35 (1938): 272; in Review of English Studies 16 (1940): 489–91. Includes
    Bibliography; based on Acoustics. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D208">
   <bib>Clough, Wilson O. "The Rhythm of Prose." University of Wyoming Publications 4 (1938): 1–19. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D209">
   <bib>Coard, M. L. "Huck Finn and Mr. Mark Twain Rhyme." Midwest Quarterly 10 (1969): 317–29. </bib>
   <notes> Close-range sound echoes in Twain's prose. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D210">
   <bib>Cooper, Lane. Certain Rhythms in the English Bible, with Illustrations from Psalms,
    Ecclesiastes, and the Lord's Prayer. Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell University Press, 1952. 16 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A tract. Anapests and dactyls in the Authorized Version. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D211">
   <bib>Cott, Jeremy. "Structures of Sound: The Last Sentence of Wuthering Heights." Texas Studies
    in Literature and Language 6 (1964): 280–89. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D212">
   <bib>Croll, Morris W. "The Cadence of English Oratorical Prose." SP 16 (1919): 1–55. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D213">
   <bib>Dahl, Torsten. "Alliteration in English Prose: Gleanings and Comments." English Studies 40
    (1959): 449–54. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D214">
   <bib>De La Mare, Walter. "Poetry in Prose." Proceedings of the British Academy 21 (1935): 239–
    321.</bib>
   <notes>Also published as an offprint. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D215">
   <bib>Deutschbein, Max. "Der rhythmische Charakter der neuenglischen Bibelübersetzung von 1611."
    Englische Studien 70 (1935): 132–37. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D216">
   <bib>Du Priest, Travis T. "The Liturgies of Jeremy Taylor and Richard Baxter: A Study of
    Structure, Language, and Rhythm." DAI 33 (1972): 2323A (Kentucky). </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D217">
   <bib>Eaton, Walter Prichard. "The Tapping Test for Immortality." Sewanee Review 27 (1919):
    129–38. </bib>
   <notes> On Patterson (D248). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D218">
   <bib>Elton, Oliver. "English Prose Numbers." Essays and Studies 4 (1913): 29–54; expanded and
    rpt in his A Sheaf of Papers. Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 1922. pp. 130–63. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D219">
   <bib>Emden, Cecil S. "Rhythmical Features in Dr. Johnson's Prose." Review of English Studies 25
    (1949): 38–54. </bib>
   <notes> Scansions. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D220">
   <bib>Fijn Van Draat, P. "The Place of an Adverb: A Study of Rhythm." Neophilologus 6 (1921):
    56–88. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D221">
   <bib>-----. "Rhythm in English Prose." Anglia 36 (1912): 1–58, 140, 492–538. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D222">
   <bib>-----. Rhythm in English Prose. Anglistische Forschungen, vol. 29. Heidelberg: Carl Winter,
    1910; rpt Amsterdam: Swets &amp; Zeitlinger, 1967. 145 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Close analysis of syntax. There is a memorial essay on this scholar which may be of
    interest: see Englische Studien 70 (1936): 381–88. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D223">
   <bib>-----. "Voluptas Aurium." Englische Studien 48 (1915): 394–428. </bib>
   <notes> The author's position, in brief, is that the cursus forms are found throughout English
    prose from Anglo-Saxon to the present day, but that these are not the result of any conscious
    effort but merely natural patterns of phrase-stressing, inherent in the structure of the
    language. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D224">
   <bib>Fitzgerald, Robert P. "The Style of Ossian." Studies in Romanticism 6 (1966): 22–33. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D225">
   <bib>Fleming, William S. "Formulaic Rhythms in Finnegan's Wake." Style 6 (1972): 19–37. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D226">
   <bib>Foster, Finley M. K. "Cadence in English Prose." JEGP 16 (1917): 456–62. </bib>
   <notes> Extends Clark (D206). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D227">
   <bib>Franz, W[ilhelm]. "Zum Prosarhythmus im Englischen." Zeitschrift für französischen und
    englischen Unterricht 10 (1911): 207–10. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D228">
   <bib>Gordon, Ian A. The Movement of English Prose. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1966. </bib>
   <notes> See chapter 2. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D229">
   <bib>Griffith, Helen. Time Patterns in Prose: A Study in Prose Rhythm Based on Voice Records.
    Psychological Monographs, vol. 39, no 3. Princeton: Psychological Review Company, 1929. 82 pp. </bib>
   <notes> D230 Hale, Edward E., Jr. "Poetic Rhythms in Prose." The Atlantic Monthly 78 (1896):
    227–32. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D231">
   <bib>Hayes, James J. "The Rhythm of Prose." English Journal (College Edition) 25 (1936): 868 ff. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D232">
   <bib>Hill, Geoffrey. "Redeeming the Time." Agenda 10, 4–11, 1 (1972–73): 87–111. </bib>
   <notes> For the author to conclude that "against all this Hopkins's poetry established a dogged
    resistance. Both ethically and rhythmically, his vocation was to redeem the time" is an
    impertinence: in fact, his subject is the social effects and speech-rhythms of
    nineteenth-century political pamphlets. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D233">
   <bib>Holthausen, F. "Rhythmische Prosa im Lillos The London Merchant." Archiv 113 (1903):
    307–14.</bib>
   <notes>See Ritter (D251). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D234">
   <bib>Honan, Park. "Metrical Prose in Dickens." Victorian Newsletter, no. 28 (1965), pp. 1–3. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D235">
   <bib>Hoover, Regina M. "Prose Rhythm: A Theory of Proportional Distribution." College
    Composition and Communication 24 (1973): 366–74. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D236">
   <bib>Kane, Thomas S. "'The Shape and Ring of Sentences': A Neglected Aspect of Composition."
    College Composition and Communication 28 (1977): 38–42. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D237">
   <bib>La Drière, J. Craig. "Prose Rhythm." Dictionary of World Literary Terms. Ed. Joseph T.
    Shipley. Boston: The Writer, 1970, pp. 252–53.</bib>
   <notes>This edition "completely revised and enlarged." Earlier editions are entitled Dictionary
    of World Literature. (New York: The Philosophical Library, 1943; 2nd ed. 1953.) </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D238">
   <bib>Lipsky, Abram. Rhythm as a Distinguishing Characteristic of Prose Style. Columbia
    University Contributions in Philosophy and Psychology, vol. 15, no. 4. New York: The Science
    Press, 1907. 44 pp. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D239">
   <bib>-----. "Rhythm in Prose." Sewanee Review 16 (1908): 277–89. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D240">
   <bib>MacDonald, Sister Mary L. "Poetic Speech in the Sermons of John Donne." DAI 30 (1969):
    2538A (Catholic University of America). </bib>
   <notes> Those "poetic" passages in the sermons that detach themselves from the other, more
    logically connected elements of thematic development may be identified by their more overt
    concern with the sound-stratum itself than with meaning: besides the patterning of qualitative
    aspects, the sounds also marshall themselves into more regular patterns of stresses, here termed
    general cadence and group cadence, which may be either coincident or counterpointed. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D241">
   <bib>Moloney, Michael F. "Metre and Cursus in Sir Thomas Browne's Prose." JEGP 58 (1959): 60–67. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D242">
   <bib>Monroe, Harriet. "Dr. Patterson on Rhythm." Poetry 12 (1918): 30–36</bib>
   <notes>; rpt in her Poets &amp; Their Art (E374) in slightly revised form as "Dr. Patterson's
    Researches." A perambulating review of Patterson (D248). Her view of his "true scientific
    spirit": "Long life to these researches!"Her prosodic view: "The rhythmic difference,
    scientifically speaking, between verse and prose is rather . . . in the grouping of bars, which
    is cadence, than in syncopation or coincidence within the bar itself." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D243">
   <bib>Njoku, Benedict C. "Cadence-Patterns in the Prose of Wordsworth and Related Figures of
    Cadence in his Verse." Diss., Catholic University of America, 1960. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="D244">
   <bib>Osgood, Charles G. "Verse in Spenser's Prose." ELH 1 (1934): 1–6. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D245">
   <bib>Parker, Edward L. "The Cursus in Sir Thomas Browne." PMLA 53 (1938): 1037–53. </bib>
   <notes> Extends Croll (D212). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D246">
   <bib>Parrish, W. M. "The Rhythm of Oratorical Prose." Studies in Rhetoric and Public Speaking in
    Honor of James Albert Winans. Ed. A. M. Drummond. New York: Century Co., 1925; rpt New York:
    Russell &amp; Russell, 1962. pp. 217–31. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D247">
   <bib/>
   <notes> Deleted. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D248">
   <bib>Patterson, William Morrison. The Rhythm of Prose: An experimental investigation of
    individual differences in the sense of rhythm. New York: Columbia University Press, 1916. Based
    on his dissertation at Columbia in 1916.</bib>
   <notes> Finger-tapping experiments which conclude that verse is distinguished by the coincidence
    of steady taps with normally accented syllables, whereas prose is syncopated. Critique of
    Sievers and Schipper, pp. 84–85. See also Monroe (D242). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D249">
   <bib>"Prose Rhythm." TLS, 13 September 1957, p. 547. </bib>
   <notes> A retrospective on the merits of Saintsbury (D254), fifty years after. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D250">
   <bib>Richards, G. C. "Coverdale and the Cursus." Church Quarterly Review 110 (1930): 34–39. </bib>
   <notes> Influence of the Latin prose rhythms on Coverdale; note also an earlier essay by Ernest
    Clapton, "Coverdale and the Psalter," in the issue for January 1929 (vol. 106?). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D251">
   <bib>Ritter, Otto. "Rhythmische Prosa im englischen Schauspiel." Archiv 117 (1906): 150. </bib>
   <notes> A note responding to Holthausen (D233). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D252">
   <bib>Robertson, Stuart. "Sir Thomas Browne and R. L. Stevenson." JEGP 20 (1921): 371–84. </bib>
   <notes> Generally indebted to Croll (D212). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D253">
   <bib>Routh, James E. "Prose Rhythms." PMLA 38 (1923): 685–97 </bib>
   <notes>; rpt in his The Theory of Verse (B187). Scansions. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D254">
   <bib>Saintsbury, George. A History of English Prose Rhythm. London: Macmillan, 1912, 1922; rpt
    Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1965. 482 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in The Spectator 109 (1912): 453–54; in Dublin Review 154 (1914): 297–313. The
    second edition adds a prefatory "Note on Quantity and Some Other Things." Three Appendices: (1)
    "Stave-Prose Poetry--Ossian, Blake, Whitman, etc."; (2) "Mason on Prosaic Numbers"; (3) "Table
    of Axioms, Inferences, and Suggestions." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D255">
   <bib>Sandbank, Shimon. "Euphuistic Symmetry and the Image." Studies in English Literature
    1500–1900 11 (1971): 1–13. </bib>
   <notes> Lyly's compulsion for rhythm controls even his imagery. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D256">
   <bib>Savage, Olive M. Rhythm in Prose Illustrated from Authors of the Nineteenth Century.
    London: University College, 1917. 54 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A pamphlet; follows Saintsbury (D254). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D257">
   <bib>Scott, Fred Newton. "The Scansion of Prose Rhythm." PMLA 20 (1905): 707–28. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D258">
   <bib>Scott, John H. Rhythmic Prose. University of Iowa Humanistic Studies, First Series, vol. 3,
    no. 1. Iowa City: The University, 1925 </bib>
   <notes>; rpt Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1970; rpt Norwood, Pa.: Norwood Editions,
    1975. 192 pp. See also his Rhythmic Verse (D331). Offers his own rhythmon theory. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D259">
   <bib>Scott, John H. and Zilpha E. Chandler. Phrasal Patterns in English Prose. New York: Ronald
    Press, 1932. 372 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A composition handbook for teaching writers to construct sentences by the rhythms of
    phrases. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D260">
   <bib>Shelly, John. "Rhythmical Prose in Latin and English." Church Quarterly Review 74 (1912):
    81–98. </bib>
   <notes> See response by M. W. Croll (D212). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D261">
   <bib>Sorrenson, Frederick S. "The Nature of the Cursus Pattern in English Oratorical Prose as
    Studied in Forty-Three Cadences of John Donne and the Collects." Diss., University of Michigan,
    1952. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D262">
   <bib>Tempest, Norton R. "Rhythm in the Prose of Sir Thomas Browne." Review of English Studies 3
    (1927): 308–18. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D263">
   <bib>-----. The Rhythm of English Prose: A Manual for Students. Cambridge: Cambridge University
    Press, 1930 </bib>
   <notes>; rpt Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1972. 138 pp. Rev: in Englische Studien 65
    (1931): 382–83; in London Mercury 23 (1931): 388; in TLS, 30 October 1930, p. 884. Scans by
    stresses alone; allows over twenty types of feet. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D264">
   <bib>Tolman, Albert H. "The Dactylic Hexameter in English Prose." MLN 6 (1891): 124. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D265">
   <bib>White, Mother Elizabeth S., R.S.C.J. "A Study of Symmetrical and Asymmetrical Tendencies in
    the Sentence Structure of Sir Thomas Browne's Urne Burial. DAI 24 (1963): 733A (Catholic
    University of America). </bib>
   <notes> See also: B149, B177, B217, D310, E217, E371, E545, E1444, E1501, J31, J76, J81–82, J87,
    J94–95, J100, J153, J176–77, J184, J237, J251, J279, J291, J330, K10, K26, K129, K214, K284,
    K323, K333–34, K359, L363, L479, L529, L772, L826, L1022, L1113, L1127–28, L1145, L1151, L1162,
    L1180–81, L1441, M21–22, M24, M82–83, M94, M143, M145, M149, M164, M189–90, M220, M247–48,
    M258–59, M263–65, M267, M291, M293, M298–99, M310. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D266">
   <bib>Abbott, Allan. "Rhythm in Poetry." Teachers College Record 28 (1927): 679–89. </bib>
   <notes> Broad review of the simpler metrical concepts; good points on the rhythm of children's
    rhymes and songs. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D267">
   <bib>Agenda: Special Issue on Rhythm 10, 4–11, 1 (1972–73): 3–67. </bib>
   <notes> See also the articles by Hill (D232) and Srawley (N126). The entire issue consists of an
    editorial, a questionnaire, twenty-two replies by modern poets, "Traditions Answer Back"--a
    group of quotations from famous poets as answers to the questions--a list of problems remaining
    to be solved ("Problems of Prosodists and Rhythm Rulers"), and the two articles cited above. The
    editorial is tendentious and irrelevant. The questionnaire contains twenty questions on General
    Points, Vers Libre, Syllabics, and Metrical Verse (sample: "Do you counterpoint your metre
    against the normal speech rhythm or do you attempt a coincidence?"). Replies: W. H. Auden, Anne
    Beresford, Keith Bosley, Basil Bunting, Peter Dale, Donald Davie, Peter Dent, Roy Fuller, Thom
    Gunn, Michael Hamburger, John Heath-Stubbs, Adrian Henri, Peter Levi, George Macbeth, John
    Montague, John Patchett, Omar Pound, Kathleen Raine, Tom Scott, Jon Stallworthy, Charles
    Tomlinson, and David Wright. For this reviewer's time, the best responses are by Davie,
    Tomlinson, and Wright. The quotations following are familiar; the list of problems unsolved is a
    list of real problems. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D268">
   <bib>Agenda: Supplement: On Rhythm from America 11, 2–3 (1973): 37–66. </bib>
   <notes> Questionnaire replies from Cameron, Davie, Eberhart, Hall, Hine, Lowell, Middleton,
    Oppen, Snodgrass, Stafford, and Zukofsky. Middleton's is the most erudite, and also mystical;
    Zukofsky bites off one-word answers; Donald Davie is irritated and irritable; Donald Hall makes
    the prize observation: "I think almost all of these questions are irrelevant to anybody's
    practice. Believe me, if you get neat and clean answers from anybody, disbelieve everything that
    is said." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D269">
   <bib>Bedetti, Gabriella. "On Understanding Poetic Rhythm." DAI 38 (1978): 4146A (Iowa). </bib>
   <notes> Understanding poetic rhythm differs from understanding other natural rhythms in that a
    process of "double perception" is required: the information gleaned about the rhythm must be
    integrated with thematic information as well. The theories of Shklovsky and Jakobson on the
    nature of poetic language are examined then applied to twenty poems by two American and two
    French poets. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D270">
   <bib>Byers, Prudence P. "A Formula for Poetic Intonation." Poetics n.s. 8 (1979): 367–80. </bib>
   <notes> A very cogent and informative synopsis of the author's dissertation, </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D271">
   <bib>Byers, Prudence P. "The Contribution of Intonation to the Rhythm and Melody of Non-Metrical
    English Poetry," dissertation at Wisconsin in 1977. </bib>
   <notes> In contrast to prose, poetry is spoken: (1) at a slower rate; (2) in shorter tone-units;
    (3) with more pauses; (4) in units relatively equal in length; (5) at a lower average pitch; (6)
    in a narrower pitch range; (7) in simple falling melodies; and (8) with simple falling nuclei.
    The conjunction of all these features, then, represents a de facto formula for intonation which
    identifies a text as "poetic." This fact suggests that the stress-group or metrical foot is not
    the basic rhythmic unit of verse but rather the "tone-group." Such groups "differ less in pitch,
    melody, and tone-type, and this makes them more nearly equal events than those in non-poetry.
    The sequence of units in poetry, therefore, is closer to being a regular recurrence of equal
    events. . . ." [italics added]. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D272">
   <bib>"The Decay of Rhythm." Saturday Review of Literature 5 (1928): 207–8. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D273">
   <bib>Dougherty, Adelyn. A Study of Rhythmic Structure in the Verse of William Butler Yeats. The
    Hague: Mouton, 1973. 135 pp. Based on her dissertation of the same title, DA 27 (1967): 3057A
    (Catholic University of America). </bib>
   <notes> That no full-scale study of the versification of the greatest poet of this century has
    yet been undertaken is a humiliation to our profession. Dougherty has given us a pilot study for
    such a work here: adopting the metrical system of La Drière (E570) she analyzes about 3000 lines
    of Yeats (25% of his canon) in an attempt to discover and define with some precision the
    features of his so-called Early, Middle, and Late styles of poetry. Her book consists of sixty
    pages of prose followed by scansions and charts. Conclusions: (1) "the poems in general are
    properly described as metrical, and the smallest constitutive unit of the metrical structure as
    an iamb"; (2) the most significant feature of Yeats's prosody is "the distinct character of the
    verse-line" as a unit; (3) Yeats's late style is most distinctive in its preference for highly
    nominal lines; and (4) a thorough study of his syntax is needed. Note that Dougherty uses the
    troublesome term "rhythm" quite deliberately, on the grounds that "it is the way in which a poet
    arranges his rhythms (in which meter may or may not inhere) that constitutes his rhythmic style,
    constitutes, therefore, what may be called in short his prosody. In a total analysis it is the
    'coincidence' . . . rather than the separateness of the domains of meter and rhythm that must
    concern the student of rhythmic structure in Yeats's verse." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D274">
   <bib>Draper, John W. The Tempo-Patterns of Shakespeare's Plays. Heidelberg: Carl Winter, 1957.
    161 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by Muir in MLR 53 (1958): 562–63; in Anglia 76 (1958): 306–7; in Études Anglaises 11
    (1958): 161–62; in Shakespeare Jahrbuch 94 (1958): 280–81; and see also the stinging criticism
    of method by Le Page (D316). Draper's book is the culmination of long study on the timing of the
    oral delivery of the lines in Shakespeare's plays, faster, slower, or even, as we can glean such
    knowledge from the evidence of spellings, metrical elisions, awkward clusters of consonants, and
    the like. We know that Shakespeare worked to vary the speech- tempos and registers and idioms of
    his various characters since, in part, the Galenic theory of the Humors widely accepted in the
    Renaissance entailed that various types of personalities would show distinctive celerity or
    lethargy in speech as well as in action. The book is densely written, with many statistics,
    tables, and charts covering all the major plays and most of the canon. One is aware, though,
    that evidence of elision or spelling is equivocal at best; it is nearly impossible to say for
    certain that at any given line Shakespeare was working for characterization rather than for
    regular (or irregular) meter (to uphold the latter is no denigration), or that the compositors
    have not taken liberties. Draper's command of the textual scholarship of Hinman, Greg, and the
    others also seems insufficient. But that timing-variation as a means to characterization was
    practiced (and valued) by Shakespeare, no one can deny. One also sees in Draper's work the best
    example of the debilitating, counterproductive expansion of modern scholarship: his useful book
    synthesizes the work of a score of now useless periodical publications, which I list below
    merely for the sake of completeness. This whole method of publication is vicious, swelling our
    libraries with redundant if not trivial (or worse, in some cases) information. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D275">
   <bib>-----. "Changes in the Tempo of Desdemona's Speech." Anglica [Revista di studi inglesi e
    americani] 1 (1946): 149–53. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D276">
   <bib>-----. "Contrast of Tempo in the Balcony Scene." Shakespeare Association Bulletin 22
    (1947): 130–35. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D277">
   <bib>-----. "Humor and Tempo in The Tempest." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 52 (1951): 205–17. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D278">
   <bib>-----. "Patterns of Humor and Tempo in King Lear." Bulletin of the History of Medicine 21
    (1947): 390–401. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D279">
   <bib>-----. "Patterns of Humor and Tempo in Macbeth." Neophilologus 31 (1947): 202–7. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D280">
   <bib>-----. "Patterns of Tempo and Humor in Othello." English Studies 28 (1947): 65–74. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D281">
   <bib>-----. "Patterns of Tempo in Measure for Measure." West Virginia University Bulletin 9
    (1953): 11–19. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D282">
   <bib>-----. "Patterns of Tempo in Richard III." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 50 (1949): 1–12. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D283">
   <bib>-----. "Patterns of Tempo in Shakespeare's Timon." Shakespeare Association Bulletin 23
    (1948): 188–94. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D284">
   <bib>-----. "Scene-Tempo in Macbeth." Festschrift für Heinrich Mutschmann. Marburg, 1951. pp.
    56–62. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D285">
   <bib>-----. "Speech-Tempo and Humor in Shakespeare's Antony." Bulletin of the History of
    Medicine 20 (1946): 426–32. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D286">
   <bib>-----. "Speech-Tempo in Act I of Othello." West Virginia University Bulletin, Philological
    Papers 5 (1947): 49–58. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D287">
   <bib>-----. "The Speech-Tempo of Brutus and Cassius." Neophilologus 30 (1946): 184–86. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D288">
   <bib>-----. "Tempo in Love's Labor's Lost." English Studies 29 (1948): 129–37. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D289">
   <bib>-----. "The Tempo of Hamlet's Role." Rivista di letterature moderne 2 (1947): 193–203. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D290">
   <bib>-----. "The Tempo of Richard II's Speech." Studia Neophilologica 20 (1948): 88–94. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D291">
   <bib>-----. "The Tempo of Shakespeare's Speech." English Studies 27 (1946): 116–20. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D292">
   <bib>-----. "The Tempo of Shylock's Speech." JEGP 44 (1945): 281–85. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D293">
   <bib>Farley, Odessa. "A Study of the Accentual Structure of Caesural Phrases in The Lady of the
    Lake." Thesis, University of Iowa, ca. 1920. </bib>
   <notes> Miss Farley was a student of John Hubert Scott's (D331); consequently, her thesis
    tabulates symmetra, metra, and non-rhythma. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D294">
   <bib>Faure, Georges. Les Élements du rythme poétique en anglaise moderne: Esquisse d'une
    nouvelle analyse et essai d'application au "Prometheus Unbound" de P. B. Shelley . The Hague:
    Mouton: 1970. 336 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by Beaver in Language 49 (1973): 188–90; in JAAC 30 (1972): 399–400. Faure's long
    Introduction takes account of nearly every conspicuous metrical work of this century up to about
    1960. His own theory though is not in the mainstream: he accepts stress as the principal feature
    of meter but believes that stress is primarily established not by intensity but by pitch; stress
    is rendered prominent "par les ruptures ou des inflexions MELODIQUES" and English verse-rhythm
    "est solidaire d'un puissant RYTHME DE TIMBRE." His pitch-accent theory marks five constant
    tones and seven "melodic" (rising, falling, or complex) tones in the melodic contour of the
    line, the tonal unit being the syllable not the single phoneme. The book is almost exactly
    divided between theory and application. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D295">
   <bib>Fisher, Hope. "A Study of Sentence-Stress in English Poetry and Prose." Diss., University
    of Michigan, 1922. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D296">
   <bib>Fogerty, Elsie. "Rhythm." Proceedings of the Second International Congress of Phonetic
    Sciences. Ed. Daniel Jones and D. B. Fry. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1936. pp.
    92–99. </bib>
   <notes> Argues that this vague term cannot be defined unless we distinguish "essential Rhythm"
    from "those patterns that are created by repetition out of Rhythm." "The fundamental conditions
    of Rhythm are time, force, and space. . . . the movements of speech are in their nature
    rhythmical." Her view of rhythm in verse is that "the isochonous interval between stress and
    stress . . . forms the basis of English prosody." Thereafter published as </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D297">
   <bib>-----. Rhythm. London: George Allen &amp; Unwin, 1937. 245 pp. </bib>
   <notes>See chapter 8, "Rhythm in Poetry," which is based on chapter 5, "Rhythm in Speech."
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D298">
   <bib>Frost, Robert. "The Constant Symbol" and "The Figure a Poem Makes." Rpt in Robert Frost on
    Writing. Ed. Elaine Barry. New Brunswick, N.J.: Rutgers University Press, 1973. pp. 125–28,
    128–33. </bib>
   <notes> See also the Interviews here (pp. 150–63) and Frost's letters (pp. 211–18 here as well as
    in Perkins [A25]) on meter (there are only two, "strict iambic and loose iambic") and "the sound
    of sense"--the intonation patterns of sentences. "But if one is to be a poet he must learn to
    get cadences by skillfully breaking the sounds of sense with all their irregularity of accent
    across the regular beat of the metre. . . . There are only two or three metres that are worth
    anything. We depend for variety on the infinite play of accents in the sound of sense." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D299">
   <bib>Funkhouser, Linda B. "Acoustical Rhythm in Performances of Three Twentieth Century American
    Poems." DAI 39 (1978): 1517A (St. Louis). </bib>
   <notes> Analyzes acoustic rate, pausing, and energy level in readings of Cummings's "Buffalo
    Bill's," Jarrell's "Death of the Ball Turret Gunner," and Frost's "Dust of Snow" by the poets,
    ten professors of literature, and ten random readers. The author has published the three parts
    of her dissertation as: </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D300">
   <bib>-----. "Acoustic Rhythm in Randall Jarrell's The Death of the Ball Turret Gunner." Poetics
    n.s. 8 (1979): 381–403. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D301">
   <bib>-----. "Acoustical Rhythms in 'Buffalo Bill's.'" Journal of Modern Literature 7 (1979):
    219–42. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D302">
   <bib>-----. "Acoustic Rhythm in Frost's 'Dust of Snow.'" Language and Style (forthcoming). </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D303">
   <bib>Gordon, Ralph. Verse and Prose Technique: A Study in Rhythm and Tone-Color. New York: City
    College Store, 1938. 144 pp. </bib>
   <notes> The material of his Technique of Verse (B81) is reworked here, but the emphasis turns
    from meter to rhythm, Gordon devising a system of bars and slashes to denote degrees of
    syntactic breaks between phrases, clauses, etc., both in prose and in verse. These syntactic
    patterns when set against the meter are striking; more work is needed here. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D304">
   <bib>Gray, James A. "The Form and Function of Rhythm in the Versification of Paradise Lost." DA
    28 (1967): 1785A (Washington at Seattle). </bib>
   <notes> Gray is interested not in the fact of the iambic meter of Milton's epic but in the
    rhythmic groups demarcated by the syntax; these syntactic-rhythmic groups are organized by
    stress, pitch, pause, and inflection, features which can be described by linguistic notation.
    Further, these rhythms correlate to distinct narrative styles in the poem: falling rhythms are
    associated with Satan and the postlapsarian humans; rising rhythms are associated with the
    prelapsarian pair; and stable rhythms are associated with the angelic orders, particularly such
    figures as Abdiel who are tempted but remain unshaken. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D305">
   <bib>Greiner, Donald J. "On Teaching Robert Frost's 'Sentence Sounds.'" English Record 21
    (1970): 11–14. </bib>
   <notes> Points up passages in the letters where Frost discusses his theory of the intoning of
    poetry and adds analysis of "Mending Wall." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D306">
   <bib>-----. "Robert Frost's Theory and Practice of Poetry." DA 28 (1968): 2684A (Virginia). </bib>
   <notes> Especially his theories of "form" and "sentence sounds": see chapters 2–4. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D307">
   <bib>Gummere, Francis B. The Beginnings of Poetry. New York: Macmillan, 1901, 1908. </bib>
   <notes> See Chapter II, "Rhythm as the Essential Fact of Poetry," pp. 30–115, for a compendious
    consultation of the authorities in defense of this thesis. See also E544. D308 Hammond, Marion.
    "A Note Concerning Rhythm Tests in Poetry and in Music." Journal of Applied Psychology 15
    (1931): 90–91. The psychological tests applied here are found to be unreliable, but they showed
    a low correlation between the subjects' sense of rhythm in music and that in poetry. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D309">
   <bib>Harding, D. W. "The Rhythmical Intention in Wyatt's Poetry." Scrutiny 14 (1946): 90–102. </bib>
   <notes> The mistake of Foxwell and all the other critics of Wyatt's prosody has been to assume
    that he intended to write regular meter. MS evidence shows that Wyatt deliberately roughened
    some lines. Therefore we should assume he did not intend to write in regular meters but rather
    in "rhythm units" the natural clitic groupings of syllables around a stress. Syntactically these
    groupings may be characterized as either "pausing rhythms" or "flowing rhythms." Wyatt stands on
    the edge of a great transition in English verse from the former to the latter; his work shows
    both. But Harding goes further to suggest the two types of rhythm as two fundamental modes of
    perception available in verse. Describing these, he thinks, will be more effectual than scanning
    meters. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D310">
   <bib>-----. Words Into Rhythm: English Speech Rhythm in Verse and Prose. New York: Cambridge
    University Press, 1976. 166 pp. </bib>
   <notes>Rev: in Style 12 (1978): 390–91; in PTL 4 (1979): 196–201. In his Clark Lectures for
    1971–72, Harding pursues the sensible thesis that rhythm in prose and poetry is based on--built
    up out of--the rhythm of speech. His method is non-technical, and in fact Harding is not
    especially interested in the kind of analyses of speech possible in acoustic phonetics or
    phonology. Rather, his method is simple and direct: he looks, repeatedly and steadily, at
    examples, asking how they work, how they are deployed, rhythmically, how they may be adapted to
    meter. Sometimes the natural rhythm (stress pattern) and the meter match so well that the meter
    seems nature not art; sometimes the meter will effect subtle alterations in a rhythm for
    semantic purposes; other times we can see how the meter will resolve for us a choice between two
    possible rhythms for a phrase, or, if several rhythms are congruent with the meter, how the
    sense will distinguish the right one. Now, in the account given by traditional prosody, when the
    speech rhythm varied within a strictly metered verse-line, one of two things happened: if the
    variation seemed acceptable or inoffensive it was called a permissible variation or
    substitution; if unacceptable, however, the line was judged unmetrical. This was accounted for
    by the primitive and questionable procedure of stipulating permissible combinations of "feet,"
    which is a mere mechanical description and by no means an explanation. A better answer would be
    that metrical lines establish a "metrical set," such that in aberrant lines, one part of the
    line establishes a clear "set" which the rest of the line does not then bear out. For Harding,
    when the rhythm and the meter clash, it is the rhythm which takes priority--as the reality--and
    "the notion that our reading should ever be some kind of 'compromise' between metre and natural
    speech is indefensible." Such suggestions are provocative, and warrant the full elaboration they
    could not receive in this context. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D311">
   <bib>Harris, M. A. "A Study of the Nature of Rhythm." PMLA 11 (1896): xxi–xxv (Proceedings). </bib>
   <notes> Discusses the grounding of poetic meter in the rhythms of mental processes and in the
    rhythms of the body and breath: "we hold rhythm to be an inseparable adjunct of poetry, and
    meter a separable adjunct." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D312">
   <bib>Herbert, T. Walter. "Tunes of Poetry: Experiments in Recognition." Emory University
    Quarterly 16 (1960): 164–73. </bib>
   <notes> This genteel, at times nearly fanciful, but unjustly forgotten essay contains a germinal
    idea that if pursued could bear fruit for a decade of scholarship: Herbert suggests, quite
    simply, that when the words--the meaning-bearing phonemes--are removed from a poem, a completely
    meaningful and quickly recognizable pattern-- "tune"--remains, the intonational contour of
    pitches, durations, and intensities. This contour varies considerably in its minutiae from one
    reader to the next, but some simple experiments will show that the general shape of the contour
    is astonishingly uniform. And if it is so for many of us, likely it was nearly so for
    Shakespeare himself. Not since Eduard Sievers has anyone suggested serious and comprehensive
    analysis of the pitch-patterns in poetry. Cf. Berry (C35), Newton (L518–21), and Turner (D339).
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D313">
   <bib>Kim, Myung W. "Dance and Rhythm: Their Meaning in Yeats and Noh." Modern Drama 15 (1972):
    195–208. </bib>
   <notes> Begin at p. 203: after his exposure to the Noh drama Yeats changed his conception of
    "rhythm" to include musical aspects alongside the verbal ones. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D314">
   <bib>Lenoski, Daniel. "The Symbolism of Rhythm in W. B. Yeats." Irish University Review 7
    (1977): 201–12. </bib>
   <notes> Not prosody, but offers a great many quotations from Yeats, and other Symbolistes, and
    Pater on rhythm. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D315">
   <bib>Lentricchia, Frank. "Robert Frost: The Aesthetics of Voice and the Theory of Poetry."
    Criticism 15 (1973): 28–42. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D316">
   <bib>Le Page, R. B. "The Dramatic Delivery of Shakespeare's Verse." English Studies 32 (1951):
    63–68. </bib>
   <notes> A full-scale criticism of the theory of John W. Draper (D274) that the stage-tempo of a
    passage or scene can often be determined from metrical evidence in the text. Specific
    objections: (1) the printed texts we have vary and are unreliable; (2) any computation of
    relative speech-rates can in no way be translated into an absolute span of minutes and seconds
    on stage--it is foolish to assume that each "normal" line took the same amount of time to be
    spoken; (3) rather than believing that hypermetrical lines were spoken more rapidly, we should
    consider that their unusual length is expressive--they were meant to take longer to say; (4)
    Draper rarely presents his full numerical data and makes an error in statistical method.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D317">
   <bib>Levý, Jirí. "Rhythmical Ambivalence in the Poetry of T. S. Eliot." Anglia 77 (1959): 54–64. </bib>
   <notes> On types of enjambment, which Levý sees as the most remarkable result of Eliot's aversion
    to the coincidence of rhythmic and syntactic periods. There are three types: regressive,
    continuous, and discontinuous. Also discussed: effects of absence of punctuation, and melody
    (rhyme). The syntactic period is the principle feature in Eliot's metric. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D318">
   <bib>Lord, Russell H., Jr. "A Study of Robert Frost's Theory of Sentence Tones and Some of Its
    Early Modifications." DAI 33 (1972): 1734A (Boston College). </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D319">
   <bib>Meerloo, Joost A. M. "The Universal Language of Rhythm." Poetic Therapy. Ed. Jack Leedy.
    Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott, 1969. pp. 52–66. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D320">
   <bib>Newdick, Robert S. "Robert Frost and the Sound of Sense." American Literature 9 (1937):
    289–300. </bib>
   <notes> Explication of Frost's poetics of tone, drawing heavily on the poet's own statements. The
    "sound of sense" is of course simply intonational contour. That is what separates the "Oh" of
    surprise from the "Oh" of scorn. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D321">
   <bib>Ogden, Robert M. "Eurhythmic." Sewanee Review 28 (1920): 520–43. </bib>
   <notes> Hortatory remarks in favor of general education in rhythm. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D322">
   <bib>Pakosz, Maciej. "Some Aspects of the Role of Intonation in English Versification." Studia
    Anglica Posnaniensia 5 (1973): 153–63. </bib>
   <notes> Pakosz identifies certain critical misdirections which have hindered study of the role of
    intonation (pitch, juncture, timing, tone) in English meter. For us "meter" has usually meant
    "stress," but pitch has been shown to be the single most important cue in the perception of
    stress, and clearly the very nature of the verse line alters syntactic and intonational contours
    from what they would otherwise be in prose. Therefore meter includes intonation as well as
    stress. Good review of the literature, but not a substantial original contribution, and
    articulated as if through a mouthful of sand. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D323">
   <bib>Philbrick, Charles H., II. "Theories of Rhythm in English and American Prosody from 1800 to
    1950." Diss., Brown University, 1953. 289 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A survey of experiments and theories of accent in the psychology of rhythm, distinguished
    by a notably elegant style, an immense breadth of reading, and a sharp ear for interesting
    biographical detail. The author himself suggests only the addition of metrical half-stress and
    rhetorical super-stress to the tools of scansion, through he doesn't credit scansion for much.
    His principal interests are isochronism and expectation. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D324">
   <bib>Pierce, L. Adeline. "Rhythm in Literature Parallels the Scale of Specificity in Speech
    Development." DA 2 (1940): 87 (Michigan). </bib>
   <notes> "Can literary rhythm be correlated with biolinguistic rhythm?" Kymograph measurements.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D325">
   <bib>Prince, F. T. "Voice and Verse: Some Problems of Modern Poetry." English 20 (1971): 77–83. </bib>
   <notes> Intriguing speculations on poetic contexts where "a tone of voice is intimately related
    to the rhythm," tone being taken both as pitch-inflection and as speaker's attitude. Prince
    knows--and says--that poetry leaves the matter of pitch indeterminate, whereas music does not,
    and his insistence falls only on the point that tone--voice--is crucial to poetry nonetheless.
    One other lure: "Would it be possible to define in poetry an element which corresponds to
    drawing in the visual arts? Would it be rhythm, syntax, composition--or simply 'meaning' in a
    very wide sense?" </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D326">
   <bib>Rhythm and Meter in Poetry (Filmstrip). Brunswick Production. Released by Educational
    Record Sales, 1973. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D327">
   <bib>Rhythm in Poetry (Filmstrip). New York: MacGraw-Hill, 1958. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D328">
   <bib>Roethke, Theodore. "Some Remarks on Rhythm." Poetry 97 (1960): 35–46; </bib>
   <notes>rpt in On the Poet and His Craft. Ed. Ralph J. Mills Jr. Seattle: University of Washington
    Press, 1965. pp. 71–84. Rpt as "What Do I Like?" in Conversations on the Craft of Poetry. Ed.
    Cleanth Brooks and Robert Penn Warren. New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1961; rpt in Gross
    (A23), pp. 218–32 under the same title. Enormously engaging: Roethke gives us here a great many
    short examples of rhythmical and prosodic effects with brief commentaries following. Fresh and
    lively. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D329">
   <bib>Rosenwald, John R. "A Theory of Prosody and Rhythm." DAI 30 (1969): 3435A (Duke). </bib>
   <notes> An argument that rhythm is the repetition of any element into recognizable patterns, and
    that restriction of the concept to its metrical sense prevents prosodists from adequately
    describing non-metrical poems. Then follow chapters on "purely visual and purely auditory"
    rhythms, combination rhythms, "rhythms imposed by the performer or audience", and line-length.
    Thesis: "The prosody of meter, however adequate in the past, must be modified so that it can
    deal with the poetry of the present and the future as well. By returning meter to its rhythmic
    origins and suggesting the rhythmic basis of all poetry, a prosody of rhythm can accomplish its
    goal." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D330">
   <bib>St. Clair, F. Y. "The Rhythm of Milton's Nativity Ode." College English 5 (1944): 448. </bib>
   <notes> The form of a Shapiro poem is a bitter parody of Milton. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D331">
   <bib>Scott, John Hubert. Rhythmic Verse. University of Iowa Humanistic Studies, vol. 3, no. 2.
    Iowa City: The University, 1925; rpt Norwood, Pa.: Norwood Editions, 1975; </bib>
   <notes> rpt Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1970. 216 pp. See also his Rhythmic Prose,
    no. 1 in the same series (D258). Underneath what I see as a wholesale confusion of both concepts
    and terms in this book (not to speak of the curious "gestural" scansions), there is a surprising
    bedrock of orthodox thinking. The single most unorthodox claim, and the central premise of the
    whole book, is that meter is subordinate to rhythm. The rhythmic phrase not the metrical foot is
    the ground unit of verse. Scott admits the existence of metering in feet (he is a Stresser; see
    his fine anatomy of the question-begging of temporalist theories on pp. 49–51, where he reminds
    us that "a perfectly arranged disposition of counted masses in a sequent order" (Ruskin) is a
    reality whereas timing is only a necessary fiction, so that "any attention to timing results
    almost inevitably in a warping of poetry"), but he argues that when all the metrical variations
    are admitted, what is left of regularity? The rhythmic "undercurrent" is more crucial than the
    metrical "current" (p. 63). So for Scott verse is to be measured by the rhythmic phrase not the
    foot, and it is precisely when the rhythmic phrases become ordered (regularized) that rhythmic
    prose rises into rhythmic verse. The units of rhythm he analyzes as either rhythma or quadrals,
    the rhythmon taking two forms, the symmetron and the metron. Symmetra are "isolable sentential
    phrases" having a scansion of "stressed and unstressed syllables to the right and left of a
    medial point"; metra, in contrast, are units "whose stress patterns show a duplication of some
    syllabic combination." Quadrals are sentences of four phrases having similar scansions. The
    reader can see that such idiosyncrasies make this a difficult book to penetrate and absorb, and
    though it reveals an extensive knowledge of previous scholarship, there is little here that one
    can take away as both new and valuable. Probably chapter 3 is the most important. See also
    Farley (D293). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D332">
   <bib>Sims, D. L. "Rhythm and Meaning." Essays in Criticism 6 (1956): 347–52. Reply by A. D. S.
    Fowler, pp. 352–57. </bib>
   <notes> A quarrel with F. W. Bateson's opinion that the reader of a poem must perceive in advance
    the meaning of a line so that he can know how to assign the line its proper rhythm--i.e., so he
    can read it aright. Sims notes that both processes occur nearly simultaneously, and to say that
    proper reading requires prior familiarity with the intonational patterns of the language is to
    say nothing new at all. Fowler, emphasizing the frequent deviance of poetic syntax, suggests
    that expectation is much less reliable in poetry than in prose, agreeing with Bateson on the
    logical precedence of meaning but agreeing with Sims that the process of apprehension is rarely
    sequential, mechanical, or fragmented. The issue, properly in the domain of psycholinguistics,
    is a crucial one in poetic theory. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D333">
   <bib>Snyder, Edward D. Hypnotic Poetry, A Study of Trance-Inducing Technique in Certain Poems
    and Its Literary Significance. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1930. </bib>
   <notes> A theory that certain poems are "actually and literally hypnotic," because their metered
    stresses fall at the regular half-second intervals which psychiatrists use to induce hypnosis.
    Includes a chapter on Free Verse. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D334">
   <bib>Sone, Tamotsn. "Rhythm in English Poetry." Youth's Companion (Japan), no. 1 (1947). </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D335">
   <bib>Sumera, Magdalena. "Aspects of Rhythm and Verse Structure in English." Diss., University of
    Edinburgh, 1971. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D336">
   <bib>-----. "Rhythm, Syntax and Verse Structure." Current Trends in Stylistics. Ed. B. B. Kachru
    and H. F. W. Stahlke. Edmonton (Canada): Linguistic Research, Inc., 1972. pp. 143–61. </bib>
   <notes> Demonstration (based on the system of David Abercrombie [E102–3]) that syntax is equally
    if not more determinative of rhythm than such conventions as rhyme or alliteration. Final
    versions of verse lines are compared to hypothetical alternatives, patterns of stress and
    quantity are examined, and types of rhythmical modification (between one line and the next) are
    identified. But it is chaos to call syntactic periods "feet," and the slightest familiarity with
    traditional prosodic terms would have reduced this essay by more than half. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D337">
   <bib>Taglicht, J. "The Function of Intonation in English Verse." Language and Style 4 (1971):
    116–22. </bib>
   <notes> A subject widely important yet widely ignored, but results here are slender: caesurae and
    line-ends seem to also mark ends of pitch-contours, and the even ictuses in dipodic verse have
    raised pitch. We need a thorough study of the conditions under which pitch (or juncture) can
    partially or solely signal Ictus in English verse. Cf. Crystal (E20). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D338">
   <bib>Tatsuma, Minoru. "Rhythm Patterns in English Poetry: Its Variety and Classification." The
    Study of Sounds: Papers Delivered at the Second World Congress of Phoneticians. Tokyo: Phonetic
    Society of Japan, 1966. Vol. 12, pp. 388–99. </bib>
   <notes> Identifies three: Phonic Rhythm (by Accent [Running Rhythm and Sprung Rhythm]; by
    Quantity; and by Combination of both); Thought Rhythm (varieties of Parallelism); and Emotional
    Rhythm (Tone-color, Syllable-count, and "Visionary Rhythm"). A summary outline; inexplicable
    statements and examples. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D339">
   <bib>Turner, W. J. "Tunes in Verse." The New Statesman and Nation n.s. 6 (1933): 844–45. </bib>
   <notes> The author asserts that in rhythm one may find tunes and tones (as in music), though in
    poetry the tuneless rhythm is the most highly developed. Still, one can sometimes hear
    "tune-rhythms" in verse; I take these to be stress-patterns, since all his examples are
    stress-verse and nursery rhymes and since he distinguishes "tune" from "melody." Rhythm is said
    to be based on meter as flesh on skeleton. Cf. Herbert (D312). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D340">
   <bib>Untermeyer, Louis. "Rhythm and Reason." The New Republic 32 (4 October 1922): 143–44. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D341">
   <bib>Van Caspel, P. P. J. "Acoustic Aspects of Poetry." Proceedings of the Sixth International
    Congress of Phonetic Sciences. Ed. B. Hala et al. Prague: Academia Publishing House of the Czech
    Academy of Sciences, 1970. pp. 243–44. </bib>
   <notes> The author urges on us his view that verse-structure depends on verse-recitation and that
    acoustic phenomena depend on indispensable psychic factors. Laboratory experiments disclose one
    other matter of interest, "the presence in the [verse] line of at least two rises in pitch,
    spaced at a certain distance," suggesting that it is "the melody rather than the sound
    intensity" which is crucial to the perception of rhythm. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="D342">
   <bib>Vander Ven, Thomas. "Robert Frost's Dramatic Principle of "Oversound.'" American Literature
    45 (1973): 238–51. </bib>
   <notes> Without being very helpfully precise, yet while rounding out the context, the author
    identifies Frost's "sentence-sounds" with a dramatic principle and with "the fundamental
    emotional energy of human nature." See also: B218, D179, E606, E1518. </notes>
  </item>
 </chapter>
</bibliography>
