<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
 <chapter title="">
  <item id="E1">
   <bib>Abercrombie, Lascelles. "The Function of Poetry in the Drama." Poetry Review 1 (1912):
    107-18 </bib>
   <notes>; rpt in English Critical Essays: Twentieth Century. Ed. Phyllis M. Jones. London: Oxford
    University Press, 1933; rpt 1947. pp. 252-72. "It is here that . . . metre gives to the poet's
    words a form which is itself a direct expression of the emotion which the words enclose."
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E2">
   <bib>Adams, Hazard, ed. Critical Theory Since Plato. New York: Harcourt, Brace, Jovanovitch,
    1971. </bib>
   <notes>For discussion of meter in the iconic texts of criticism, primarily English, s.v. "Meter"
    in the Index. Also s.v."Rhyme." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E3">
   <bib>Aiken, Conrad. "The Function of Rhythm." The Dial 65 (1918): 417-18. </bib>
   <notes>A review which digresses largely to Wordsworth's views on meter in poetry. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E4">
   <bib>Ammons, A. R. "A Note on Prosody." Poetry 102 (1963): 202-3. </bib>
   <notes>A suggestion that both ends of a verse line, being "weighted," tend to be counterbalanced
    by a medial caesura and other devices, so that the weight may shift from one end to the other,
    creating an effectual "pull" or motion down- ward--i.e., down the page. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E5">
   <bib>Barkas, Pallister. A Critique of Modern English Prosody (1880-1930). Studien zur englischen
    Philologie, vol. 82. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1934; rpt Walluf, Germany: Sandig, 1973. 100 pp. </bib>
   <notes>Rev: in TLS, 13 September 1934, p. 622; in JEGP 34 (1935): 461; in Anglia Beiblatt 46
    (1935): 263-65; in English Studies 18 (1936): 95-96. A correlate study to Fussell (E34), less
    urbane but more orderly and us- able and absolutely impartial. Barkas gives a history of what
    was surely the most contentious and confusing--and probably the most important--period in the
    history of versification by explicating separately the theory advanced by every major worker in
    the field from 1880-1930--i.e., Mayor, Bridges, Young, Aber- crombie, Hamer, Lanier, Alden,
    Omond, Saintsbury, Smith, Andersen, Stew- art, Sonnenschein, Bayfield, Thomson, Wilson, and
    Scott. Each short review, generally three to four pages, is succinct yet informative. Throughout
    the book, Barkas distinguishes carefully between Prosody [i.e. Meter] and Rhythmic [Rhythm],
    though the remainder of his terminology is still much too elaborate, imprecise, and cumbrous
    even after his best efforts to codify (see pp. 12-17). The same can be said for the more
    important typology of metrical theories sketched on pp. 7-11 and extended in the last chapter
    (pp. 86-100); it wants Occam's razor. Barkas distinguishes six types of theory, two of the them
    having subtypes (the non-Temporal, three, and the Temporal, five). He also distin- guishes,
    elaborately (see p. 90) between metrical pattern and actualization, which he calls respectively
    Rule Verse and Base Verse: "In Rule Verse what- ever the Metrical Rule prescribes is objectively
    present in the verse-pattern, but in Base Verse the elementary unit of the base need not always
    be objectively present." In sum, though his classifications multiply distinctions needlessly,
    Barkas's synopses of the theories of the eighteen metrists are full, fair, and use- ful.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E6">
   <bib>Bernard, Jules Eugene, Jr. The Prosody of the Tudor Interlude. Yale Studies in English,
    vol. 90. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1939; rpt Hamden, Conn.: Archon Books, 1969. 225 pp. </bib>
   <notes>Rev: in TLS, 24 June 1939, p. 378; in MLN 55 (1940): 455-62; in Review of English Studies
    16 (1940): 207-8. Not a synthetic study but nonetheless a highly useful reference work which
    analyzes separately 72 of the folk-drama interludes written between 1497 and 1593 (up to Nashe).
    Each analysis includes tabular information on meter and rhymes and two to three pages of
    discussion. Conclusions (pp. 193-211 and Preface): the various meters of the interludes were
    indigenous, not Continen- tally derived, not "doggerel" but in fact quite complex at times, and
    could dis- play variation for purposes of characterization and structure. Appendices of metrical
    information. Sound scholarship. Note that Bernard uses the terms "heavy" for iambic rhythm and
    "light" for anapestic. Cf. E73 and K307. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E7">
   <bib>Blackmur, R. P. "Lord Tennyson's Scissors: 1912-1950." Kenyon Review 14 (1952): 1-20; rpt
    in his Form &amp; Value in Modern Poetry. New York: Doubleday, 1957. pp. 369-88. </bib>
   <notes>The scissors symbolize the instrumentality of versification, which Blackmur ex- amines in
    the work of some twentieth-century poets, especially Eliot, Yeats, and Pound. Note also p. 211
    ff on prosaic syntax in poetry. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E8">
   <bib>Bradley, A. C. "Monosyllabic Lines and Words." In his A Miscellany. London: Macmillan,
    1929. pp. 245-67; rpt in Literary English Since Shakespeare. Ed. George Watson. London: Oxford
    University Press, 1970. pp. 50-64. </bib>
   <notes>Statistical tallies of lines containing only monosyllables in non-dramatic verse, the
    Shakespearean canon, and dramatic verse; percentages of monosyllabic words in selected prose
    passages also studied. Note that only five-stressed lines were tallied. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E9">
   <bib>Breen, A. T. "A Survey of the Development of Poetry Written in Trisyllic Metres to 1830,
    Approximately." Diss., National University of Ireland, 1965. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E10">
   <bib>Brown, Calvin S. "Monosyllables in English Verse." Studies in English Literature 1500-1900
    3 (1963): 473-91. </bib>
   <notes>Confutes the received opinion in English metrics that the great bane of English verse is
    its surfeit of monosyllables by showing (1) that English poets--even Pope--have successfully
    used sequences of monosyllables often, and (2) that the objections historically given to using
    monosyllables have no weight. In fact, the number of monosyllables in the language has not
    appreciably changed since Middle English, while the rise of science has added a great many
    polysyllabic words to the lexicon. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E11">
   <bib>Brown, Stephen J. "Versification: The Music of Speech." The Realm of Poetry: An
    Introduction. London: Harrap, 1921. pp. 26-45. </bib>
   <notes>Nontechnical and nonessential. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E12">
   <bib>Buchanan, Victor. "Versification." English Journal 22 (1933): 460-65. </bib>
   <notes>Should be useful in elementary schools. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E13">
   <bib>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor. Biographia Literaria. 2 vols. London, 1817. Rpt London: J. M.
    Dent (Everyman Editions) and New York: E. P Dutton, 1906; ed. George Watson, 1965, 1971. </bib>
   <notes>Coleridge's reply to Wordsworth's Preface (E100) begins at chapter 14, discussing the
    "superadded charm of metre" passim; chapter 18 is the crucial discussion, however. I hazard
    lengthy quotation, given the importance and breadth of the subjects Coleridge raises. Since "a
    poem contains the same elements as a prose composition, the difference therefore must consist in
    a different combination of them, in conse- quence of a different object proposed. . . . it is
    possible that the object may be merely to facilitate the recollection of any given facts or
    observations by artifi- cial arrangement, and the composition will be a poem, merely because it
    is dis- tinguished by metre, or by rhyme, or by both conjointly." But these constitute mere
    "superficial form," and of course many works achieve their objects of truth or pleasure which
    are not in meter, e.g. novels. "Would then the mere superaddition of metre, with or without
    rhyme, entitle these to the name of poems? The answer is that nothing can permanently please
    which does not contain in itself the reason why it is so, and not otherwise. If metre be super-
    added, all other parts must be made consonant with it. They must be such as to justify the
    perpetual and distinct attention to each part which an exact corre- spondent recurrence of
    accent and sound are calculated to excite." This is the familiar argument of "organic form." Yet
    Coleridge allows that "poetry of the highest kind can exist without metre" (the argument runs on
    a distinction be- tween verse and poetry that is operative without being consciously
    articulated). Denying absolutely that "between the language of prose and that of metrical
    composition there neither is, nor can be any essential difference," Coleridge ar- gues that
    things not controvertible are not identical. "The true question must be whether there are not
    modes of expression, a construction and an order of sentences, which are in their fit and
    natural place in a serious prose composition but would be disproportionate and heterogeneous in
    metrical poetry; and vice versa, whether in the language of a serious poem there may not be an
    arrange- ment both of words and of sentences and a use and selection of. . . figures of speech .
    . . which would be vicious and alien in correct and manly prose. I contend that in both cases
    the unfitness of each for the place of the other fre- quently will and ought to exist." Five
    arguments for this position are adduced. First, the psychological ba- sis of meter lies in "the
    balance in the mind effected by that spontaneous effort which strives to hold in check the
    workings of passion." That is, "the elements of metre owe their existence to a state of
    increased excitement," but these ele- ments are also "formed into metre artificially, by a
    voluntary act, with the de- sign and for the purpose of blending a delight with emotion, so the
    traces of present volition should throughout the metrical language be proportionally dis-
    cernible." The result is "an interpenetration of passion and of will." These emotions will
    naturally dictate forms not otherwise procurable. Second, the effect of meter is "to increase
    the vivacity and susceptibility both of the general feelings and of the attention. This effect
    it produces by the continued excitement of surprise, and by the quick reciprocations of
    curiosity still gratified and still re-excited." This is the same effect "as a medicated atmos-
    phere, or as wine during animated conversation," or, better yet, "as that of yeast, worthless or
    disagreeable by itself but giving vivacity and spirit to the liq- uor with which it is
    proportionately conbined." "Metre in itself is simply a stimulant to the attention, and
    therefore excites the question: Why is the atten- tion thus to be stimulated? . . . . Neither
    can I conceive any other answer that can be rationally given, short of this: I write in metre
    because I am about to use a language different from that of prose." Both these arguments amount
    to the same thing: meter is indicative, or adumbrative, of a special use of language in poetry,
    both lexically and syntactically (it is this latter especially which seems to be in the center
    of Coleridge's attention). Third, meter functions also as a catalyst or fixative. Meter having
    been associated, time out of mind, with poetry as its proper form, without which poetry will
    commonly be considered deficient, any other material which might be combined with meter "must,
    though it be not itself essentially poetic, have nevertheless some property in common with
    poetry as an intermedium of af- finity, a sort . . . of mordaunt between it and the superadded
    metre" (mordaunt being a chemical applied to fabrics to fix their color during dyeing). Fourth
    (obscure), there is a human instinct for "unity by harmonious adjustment." And fifth, the
    practice of all the best poets confirms: the excite- ment and passions aroused by poetry "demand
    a correspondent difference of language." It will be seen through all this that the problem is
    the insufficiently clari- fied term language. Later in the chapter Coleridge rejects the idea
    that rules could be given for analysis or differentiation of, say, the languages of rage and
    jealousy; necessarily it must all be a matter of intuition. (By this point his reac- tion to
    Wordsworth's claim that meter is the sole differentia of prose and poetry has reached the level
    of near-ferocity.) It is evident that in his remarks on me- ter he is concerned as much or more
    with syntax as with meter strictly speak- ing, but his position is important historically for
    its clear psychological basis (one thinks at once of I. A. Richards in the twentieth century):
    for Coleridge, meter both arouses and regulates passionate response. The reader may also wish to
    consult and E75, E262. </notes>
  </item>




  <item id="E14">
   <bib>C. M. Wallace. "Teaching the Preface-Biographia Dispute" in Wordsworth Circle 9 (1978):
    378-79 </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E15">
   <bib>D. H. Bialostosky's "Coleridge's Interpretation of Wordsworth's Preface to Lyrical Ballads"
    in PMLA 93 (1978): 912-24. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E16">
   <bib>Collins, Mortimer. "The Art and Accomplishment of Verse." London Society 20 (1871): 445-52. </bib>
   <notes>Exhorts gentlemen with leisure to cultivate versification "for pleasure and profit" but to
    eschew "trite meters." Critical of Sylvester (E402). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E17">
   <bib>Comfort. A. "It Goes Like This." Life and Letters To-day 31 (1941): 36-40. </bib>
   <notes>In praise of metered verse, in search of a compelling narrative poem. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E18">
   <bib>Creek, Herbert L. "Rising and Falling Rhythms in English Verse." PMLA 35 (1920): 76-90. </bib>
   <notes>Regardless of what we may choose to call the meter of a line, whether we view it as in
    either "rising" or "falling" rhythm seems to depend on seven factors: the reader's expectations,
    syllable-structure at the beginning of the line, and at the end, and around the caesura, weak
    endings, phrasal structure, and vocabulary. Creek is groping toward a recognition that the
    "rhythm" of a line is a function of its syntactic and, more importantly, morphological
    structure. Useful statistics here on the proportion of "imabic" to "trochaic" disyllables in
    iambic verse. Cf. Crapsey (E516), Stewart (E331), Atkins (E467), Hascall (E783), and Newton
    (E799). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E19">
   <bib>Croll, Morris W., et al. "Report of the Committee on Metrical Notation appointed at
    Philadelphia 1922." PMLA 39 (1924): lxxxvii-xciv. </bib>
   <notes>The Committee here furnishes the two schools of metrists--those favoring a "syllabic
    scansion" (meter based on accent) and those favoring "musical scan- sion" (rhythm based on
    time)--with a uniform set of symbols, the first denot- ing, in syllabic scansion, stress, and in
    musical scansion, quarter-note, the second denoting, in syllabic scansion, unstress, and in
    musical scansion, eighth-note, and so on. These symbols expedite printing and may eventually
    result in theoretical rapprochement, the Committee hopes. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E20">
   <bib>Crystal, David. "Intonation and Metrical Theory." Transactions of the Philological Society,
    1971, pp. 1-33. </bib>
   <notes> In this very salient reappraisal and prospectus Crystal shows how metrical the- ory over
    the past century moved from confusion (quantity or stress?) to doc- trine (stress) without
    inquiring much further. But "on what grounds, other than Tradition, has stress been singled out
    from the other phonological features of verse [i.e. intonation] and been identified with the
    metre? What experimental evidence is there to justify the priority of stress in this way? None
    has been provided." Yet the arguments supporting stress in meter apply equally well to
    intonation. The recent literature shows that many Continental metrists have already accepted an
    intonational metrics, while Anglo-American metrists seem content with stress metrics. Their
    contentedness is partially a reaction to the older confusions and skirmishes, which lasted far
    too long, but it is also a trib- ute to the enormous influence of the Trager-Smith phonology. An
    intonational metrics will have to reject this analysis, yet it would still retain the virtue of
    se- lectivity (not all intonational features are equally important), and it should give greater
    explanatory adequacy, as in describing free verse. In Crystal's view the "fundamental criterion"
    of such a metric is the line, "the identifying experience [of which] is non-segmental, a
    prosodic contour" [original italics]. Two experi- ments comparing a text set as verse and as
    prose showed that the line is coter- minous with the "tone-unit," that the prominences are
    contrastive by pitch not by loudness, and that more degrees of gradation are required in poetry
    than in prose. The synchronic view of English metrical theory ca. 1971 given here is valuable,
    but more valuable still is the glimpse provided of the course of the theory over the next
    several decades. Cf. D322, D337, E608, L1323, and L1341. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E21">
   <bib>Cunningham, J. V. "How Shall the Poem be Written?" University of Denver Quarterly 2 (1967):
    45-62. Rpt in the Collected Essays of J. V. Cunningham. Chicago: Swallow Press, 1976. pp.
    256-71. </bib>
   <notes>Answer: in meter. Cunningham examines the available "metrical languages" in English: free
    verse ("grammatical meter" or "parsing meter"), accentual verse, syllabic, quantitative, and
    "traditional and . . . parasitic meter." The tone is iconoclastic (e.g., "the basic English
    measure is the iambic octosyllable"), vig- orous, and pragmatic. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E22">
   <bib>-----. "The Problem of Form." In The Collected Essays of J. V. Cunningham. Chicago: Swallow
    Press, 1976. pp. 247-50. </bib>
   <notes>Form is "that which remains the same when everything else has changed. . . . form is
    discoverable by the act of substitution. It is what has alternative realiza- tions. And the
    generality or particularity of a form lies in the range or restric- tion of alternatives. It
    follows, also, that the form precedes its realization. . . ." It is "not that a literary work
    has form, but that it is a convergence of forms, and forms of disparate orders. It is
    coincidence of forms that locks in the poem. . . . For this is the poet's Poetics: prose is
    written in sentences; poetry in sen- tences and lines. It is encoded not only in grammar, but
    also simultaneously in meter, for meter is the principle or set of principles, whatever they may
    be, that determines the line. And as we perceive of each sentence that it is grammatical or not,
    so the repetitive perception that this line is metrical or that it is not, that it exemplifies
    the rules or that it does not, is the metrical experience. It is the ground bass of all poetry."
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E23">
   <bib>De La Mare, Walter. "Metrical Technique I, II." The National and English Review 146 (1956):
    89-97, 156-67. </bib>
   <notes>The first installment may be ignored altogether. The second represents an elaborate appeal
    to ignorance ("no precision of analysis, I think, is attainable"), though there is a long
    passage on sonal mimesis and a good point on "verbal melody." Emblematic: "units of English
    metre were better called boots than feet, since it is what they contain that is of any real
    importance, not them- selves." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E24">
   <bib>Eaton, Horace, A. "Irregularities in Verse." English Journal 1 (1912): 601-10. </bib>
   <notes>For its time, a very astute recognition of the implications of the dictum that "perfect
    regularity means monotony, and monotony destroys attention." Not only are the five theoretically
    equal feel unequal in timing or pacing, the stresses are unequal, as are the unstressed
    syllables, and the greater and lesser pauses. Variation is everything in verbal--as all
    other--art. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E25">
   <bib>Eaton, Richard B. Jr. "A History of American Prosody from Its Beginnings to 1880." DA 28
    (1968): 3669A (North Carolina). </bib>
   <notes>Traces the history of American prosodic theorizing from 1785 to 1880, dis- cerning therein
    two major modes: "auralism" and "visualism." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E26">
   <bib>Elze, Karl. "Metrik." Grundiss der englischen Philologie. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1887; 2nd
    ed., 1889. pp. 361-86. </bib>
   <notes>A general bibliographical review essay. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E27">
   <bib>Emerson, Ralph Waldo. "The Poet." In Essays: Second Series. Vol. 3 of The Complete Works of
    Ralph Waldo Emerson. 12 vols. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1903-4. pp. 9-10. </bib>
   <notes>"For it is not metres, but a metre-making argument that makes a poem,--a thought so
    passionate and alive that like the spirit of a plant or an animal it has an architecture of its
    own, and adorns nature with a new thing. The thought and the form are equal in the order of
    time, but in the order of genesis the thought is prior to the form." Two other dicta: "Art is
    the path of the creator to his work" and, better, "Language is fossil poetry." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E28">
   <bib>Erskine, John. "A Note on Whitman's Prosody," SP 20 (1923): 336-44. </bib>
   <notes>Insofar as this essay is about Whitman it is nothing other than utterly ludicrous. But in
    fact it is not about Whitman, it is about the nature of the line-end in verse. The line-end is
    the "one fixed mark" which enables the reader to distin- guish between verse and prose in
    audition. It can be denoted either by a rhyme-chime or by a pause. Lines having an odd number of
    stresses have an invariable pause, but lines with an even number have none and so naturally tend
    to be enjambed. Larger issue looming in the distance: poetry's two modes, visual and aural.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E29">
   <bib>Fairchild, Arthur H. R. "The Making of Poetry: Versifying." The Making of Poetry: A
    Critical Study of Its Nature and Value. New York: G. P. Ptunam's Sons, 1912. pp. 105-51. </bib>
   <notes>A curious but interesting fifth chapter eschews the process of verse-making for its
    (undeniably more interesting) effects: to mold language into a a kind of in- evitable, measured
    rhythm . . . is to bind the language more closely together, for these are really forms of
    word-association by sound. And to bind the lan- guage more closely together is to help knit
    together the images which that lan- guage represents." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E30">
   <bib>Fucks, William. "Possibilities of Exact Style Analysis." Patterns of Literary Style. Ed.
    Joseph Strelka. University Park, Pa.: Penn State University Press, 1971. pp. 51- 76. </bib>
   <notes>That is to say, quantitative analysis: charts and statistics of such features as
    word-length and sentence-length. See "Establishing the Strength and Effective Range of Metric
    Connection," pp. 65-68. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E31">
   <bib>Fussell, Edwin. Lucifer in Harness: American Meter, Metaphor, and Diction. Princeton:
    Princeton University Press, 1973. </bib>
   <notes>Chapter 1, "The Meter-Making Argument," is reprinted from Aspects of Ameri- can Poetry
    (Ed. Richard M. Ludwig. Columbus: Ohio State University Press, 1962. pp. 3-31); it is an arid
    region, full of airy remarks on the ambivalences and tensions of American poetry and its forms.
    "The history of American po- etry is the history of recurrent explosions, metrically centered,
    caused by the frustrations of the American poet, who is and is not an English poet, who has free
    verse but doesn't always want it, alternating with longer periods of con- ciliation and
    consolidation." Chapter 3, "What the Thunder Said," takes up diction. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E32">
   <bib>Fussell, Paul, Jr. "English [Versification]: I. Historical." Wimsatt (A20), pp. 191-203. </bib>
   <notes>Actually "typological and historical": the article surveys the four principal met- rical
    systems (accentual, syllabic, combined, quantitative) and traces the devel- opment (or at least
    change) of English metrics through six periods (OE to 20th c.) of extensive historical changes
    in the language and oscillations between con- vention and experimentation in poetic technique.
    The essay merely revises the material the author had used earlier in his handbook (E537) and in
    his Princeton Encyclopedia articles (</notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E33">
   <bib/>
   <notes> and E535). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E33">
   <bib>-----. "English Prosody." Princeton (A18), pp. 238-40. </bib>
   <notes>A valuable review, organized chronologically, reaching from Old English to the present.
    Fussell believes that no one metrical system can account for the entire gamut of English poetry,
    but that three things may at least be said: English verse is accentually based; it seems to flow
    "most pleasantly and naturally" in rising rhythm; and its natural line-length is one of "4 or 5
    isochronous units." The essay then proceeds by showing the drifts toward either pure
    Accentualism or Syllabism that have taken place at various times in the history of English
    verse, drifts from the central norm of a regulated number of both syllables and stresses. (The
    only faltering in this regard is the statement that Lanier's Musical prosody has a theoretical
    position emphasizing accentualism; obviously, it emphasized timing.) "Prosody" in the title is a
    solecism for "Metrics." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E34">
   <bib>-----. Theory of Prosody in Eighteenth-Century England. New London, Conn.: Con- necticut
    College Monographs, 1954; rpt Hamden, Conn.: Archon Books, 1966. 170 pp. </bib>
   <notes>Fussell's approach to the history writing is (a) thematic and (b) partitive. From the
    various prosodic issues and trends of the century he selects three for exami- nation: views on
    the metrical structure of the line; theory of elision (i.e. sylla- bism perserved thereby); and
    the increasing legitimacy of trisyllabic substitution (i.e. anti-syllabism, or the rise of
    accentualism as the dominant metrical princi- ple). He therefore ignores: the crucial question
    of the definitions and employ- ments of accent vs. quantity; rhyme; the complex relations of
    poetry and music, so important in the age; and the sundering of metrical theory between Timers
    and Stressers early in the century. In short compass, the history of versification in the period
    1660-1800 is as follows: heavy French influence on English letters after the Restoration
    resulted in the complete establishment of Syllabism (sylla- ble-counting) as the chief principle
    of meter; Bysshe is the central figure here (1702 etc.). At the same time, by a process that
    (pace Fussell) is still not well understood either theoretically or historically,
    counting-of-syllables led inevita- bly to regularity (regular alternation) of stresses. These
    principles dominate the- ory until about 1740 and remain visible up to about 1770; thereafter,
    the story is one of Accentualist insurgency, leading to (the French Revolution and) Ro-
    manticism. Over the century there is also a concomitant diremption in the view of prosodists as
    to whether Quantity, Time, or Accent is the basis of verse. This area is far more complex than
    Fussell allows. Altogether his study makes a series of compromises between a full history of
    versification theory in the century and a full account of the positions of the major theorists,
    who sometimes receive short shrift when their views are fragmented among Fussell's thematic
    divisions. Omond's method (A5) is less artful but more cogent: there we find a fuller assessment
    of the contribution of each theorist to the develop- ing understanding of the century. See also
    the criticisms in Kumbier (E1009). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E35">
   <bib>Gillis, Everett A. "American Prosody in the Eighteen-Nineties with Special Reference to
    Magazine Verse." Diss., University of Texas, 1948. </bib>
   <notes>Still a useful source of information, mainly on account of its scope. Gillis ex- amines
    the (a) prosodic theories or comments and (b) prosodic practices in the verse printed in the
    prominent American literary journals of the Nineties, placing both of these within the wider
    perspectives of both prosodic theory and practice in America, and also in England, in the
    nineteenth century. Out of the enormous mass of verse he examined (as cited), he scrutinizes
    more closely the work of eight prominent young poets (none of which ever rose into the first
    rank); nearly all of it is metrically very conventional. In the area of theory, the decade was
    still spinning out the ideas of Poe, Lanier, and perhaps Whitman; essays by the would-be
    literari were legion, of course, though Alden and others were pursuing the quiet ends of
    scholarship, while Bolton, for the scientists, looked into the mechanics of rhythm. Perhaps the
    principle issue of the day was the legitimacy of off-rhyme. Whoever writes the successor to
    Allen's American Prosody will find source-material here. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E36">
   <bib>Goodell, Thomas. "On English Versification." The Nation 93 (1911): 334-36. </bib>
   <notes>A review of Matthews (E588), Saintsbury (E636), and Kaluza (A4). See also R. M. Alden's
    following letter on "English Rhythm" (E269). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E37">
   <bib>Graves, Robert. "Harp, Anvil, Oar." In The Crowning Privilege. New York: Doubleday, 1955.
    Rpt in Gross (A23), pp. 52-71. </bib>
   <notes>Wonderful speculations on the origin of verse (harp), the nature of syllable- counting
    verse (anvil), and stress-verse (oar), followed by observations on the necessity of variations
    against the norm in meter, and on craftsmanship of verse in general; throughout, Graves
    emphasizes the seminal role of the Irish poets and verseforms on the development of the English
    meters. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E38">
   <bib>Gross Harvey. Sound and Form in Modern Poetry: A Study of Prosody from Thomas Hardy to
    Robert Lowell. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1964 </bib>
   <notes>; rpt 1968. An abridgement of chapter 7, "T.S. Eliot and the Music of Poetry," appears in
    Gross (A23), pp. 202-17. Rev: by Wimsatt in Michigan Quarterly Review (see E699); by G. W. Allen
    in American Literature 37 (1965): 350-52; by Hemphill in Kenyon Review 27 (1965): 777-79; in
    English Language Notes 3 (1966): 237-38. Excellent Prologue (on the four "beast of confusion" in
    the study of versifica- tion) followed by chapters on "Prosody as Rhythmic Cognition" (see B85)
    and "The Scansion of the English Meters" and separate studies of Pound, Crane and Stevens, and
    Eliot. Shorter sections treat Hardy, Yeats, Bridges, Robinson and Frost, Muir, Ransom, Browning,
    Whitman, Hopkins, the Imagists, Moore, Williams, Cummings, visual prosody, Auden, Spender and
    MacNeice, Thomas, Empson and Watkins and Reed, and Kunitz and Roethke and Lowell. An Epilogue
    reflects on the possibility of a "modern style." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E39">
   <bib>Haas, Robert. "One Body: Some Notes on Form." Antaeus 30/31 (1978): 329-42. </bib>
   <notes>"The pure iamb in fact can't be rendered; it only exists as a felt principle of or- der,
    beneath all possible embodiments, in the mind of the listener. It exists in silence, is
    invisible, unspeakable." "I don't think we are in a position yet to understand the reaction
    against metri- cal poetry that began in the middle of the nineteenth century. It's an astonish-
    ing psychological fact, as if a huge underpinning in the order of things had given way, and
    where men had heard the power of incantatory repetition be- fore, they now heard its monotony.
    Or worse." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E40">
   <bib>Hafner, Charles, Y. "Foundations of English Poetics: 1570-1575." DA 28 (1968): 3143A
    (Stanford). </bib>
   <notes>A study of Ascham (E109), Gascoigne (E538), John Rainolds' Oratorio in laudem artis
    poetica (1572), and Richard Wills' De re poetica disputatio (1573). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E41">
   <bib>Hamm, Victor M. "Meter and Meaning." PMLA 69 (1954): 695-710. </bib>
   <notes>In the relation of these two dimensions two factors may be discerned: "a prin- ciple of
    phonetic autonomy and a principle of semantic cooperation." Of the former, the level of
    background texture, Ransom is simply wrong to thing the meter a mere correlative or superadded
    external form; the meter is "part of the meaning," a kind of "emotional semantic," a statement
    of ambienceor, at the very least, order. Of the latter: meter can (1) serve as expository
    function, rein- forcing lexical sense; (2) "modulate and define emotion" in its emotive func-
    tion; or (3) reassure or else surprise the reader, in its affective function. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E42">
   <bib>Hamp, Eric P. "Phonetic and Semantic Metrics." Meaning: A Common Ground of Linguistics and
    Literature. Ed. Don L. F. Nilsen. Cedar Falls, Iowa: University of Northern Iowa, 1973. pp.
    146-52. </bib>
   <notes>"Some poetry is manifested heavily through phonetic recurrence in patterned
    configurations; other poetry is characterized by patterned configurations in rather abstract
    semantic features; and there is some poetry, a great deal in fact, that relies on a skillful
    blend of these two configurational mechanisms." More simply: a poem may be "metered" or
    organized not only by stresses or syntactic structures but by underlying semantic units also.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E43">
   <bib>Hannauer, Leo. "Das einsilbige Wort im engishchen Vers." Die Neueren Sprachen 33 (1925):
    348-51. </bib>
   <notes>Actually he gives statistics for monosyllables in French, German, and English prose
    fiction and poetry. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E44">
   <bib>Hart, James M. "The College Course in English Literature, How It May Be Improved." PMLA 1
    (1884-85): 84-95. </bib>
   <notes>A fascinating note on pp. 92-95 deplores the absence of any convenient metri- cal
    handbook, followed by a divagation on the history of blank verse. Was it this tiny crack which
    started the flood? </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E45">
   <bib>Hemphill, George. "Jonson's 'Fit of Rime Against Rime.'" Explicator 12 (1954): Item 50. </bib>
   <notes>Suggests defining rime as "modern conventions of verse." Cf. E74. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E46">
   <bib>Hollander, John. "The Metrical Emblem." Kenyon Review 21 (1959): 279-96. Abstracted in
    Sebeok (A19), pp. 191-92 </bib>
   <notes>; rpt in full in Chatman and Levin (A21), pp. 115-26; revised and expanded into chapter 7,
    "The Metrical Frame," of his Vision and Resonance (A13), pp. 135-64. Peregrine. Topics covered:
    linguistic treatments of metrics; the rhythmic structure of the mimetic lines in Pope's Essay on
    Criticism; alliteration, asso- nance, onomatopoeia, and echoic patterns in general; and
    musical-metrical modality. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E47">
   <bib>Ing, Catherine. Elizabethan Lyrics: A study of the development of English metrics and their
    relation to poetic effect. London: Chatto &amp; Windus, 1951. 252 pp. </bib>
   <notes>Based on her dissertation, "Metrical Theory and Practice in the Elizabethan Lyric," at
    Oxford in 1949. Rev: in TSL, 9 May 1952, p. 314; in Etudes Anglaises 5 (1952): 155-56; in
    Shakespeare Quarterly 4 (1953): 79-83; in Shakespeare Jahrbuch 89 (1953): 239-40. Though now
    supplemented by more recent, specialized studies, Ing's book re- mains a classic still to be
    consulted. The general plan is to anatomize Elizabe- than theories of meter and then compare
    these to the actual productions in verse--the lyrics--which were nearly always meant to be sung
    as madrigals and airs. Chapter 2 provides an extremely convenient synopsis of the theorists re-
    printed in Smith's Elizabethan Critical Essays (A26). Chapter 3 gives a similarly valuable
    Glossary of prosodic terms; the usage of such terms in the Renaissance was often ambiguous,
    inconsistent, and indiosyncratic, yet discriminations are crucial, and the terms are delicately
    unravelled. (Cf. these two chapters to E57 and E228.) Chapter 4 examines the "visual thing" of
    pattern poems and also the theories about quantitative verse (cf. Attridge, E112); chapter 5
    confronts the central metrical phenomonon of the age, verse set to music. Chapter 7 explores the
    role of the three prosodic aspects of speech-- pitch, stress, and duration--in Elizabethan
    lyrics in considerable detail; p. 200 ff discusses the role of stress in meter. Remaining
    chapters focus on the lyrics of Campion, Spenser, Shakespeare, and Donne. The book must be set
    alongside Thompson's (E91), since the latter stops with Sidney, while Ing, beginning with
    Tottel, surveys 1557-1633. More elegantly informed in its style and more synoptic in its
    erudition than Fussell (E34), Ing's work may be our best period study. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E48">
   <bib>Jacob, Cary F. "Some Phases of Recent Study in English Versification." Sewanee Review 19
    (1911): 498-503. </bib>
   <notes>A review of Schipper (All), Verrier (E454), and Matthews (E588), praising Verrier while
    denigratig the other two works. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E49">
   <bib>Justice, Donald. "Meters and Memory." Antaeus 30/31 (1978): 314-20. </bib>
   <notes>The question of "the mnemonic value of meters," intriguing in itself, yet leads to the
    even-deeper question of the effects of meter: Justice points to "the various combining and
    intersecting functions" of metering, remembering, control, and understanding in the poetic
    craft. In contrast to some others, his own view is that "the meters move along in their own
    domain, scarcely intersecting the domain of meaning, except in some illusory fashion or by
    virtue of conventions nearly private. The responsibility they bear to the sense, comic writing
    aside, is mostly not to interfere." That is, in themselves they are little, as Coleridge said,
    but their effect superimposedon powerful sense is more powerful still. "The twin illusions of
    control and understanding seem more valuable to me than this illu- sion of the real or the
    natural [i.e. mimetic meters]. Yet he can admit that "the meters seem always faintly
    teleological by im- plication. . . . they seem to propose that an emotion, however
    uncontrollable it may have appeared originally, was not, in fact, unmanageable." (Cf. Malof,
    E582.) And "the meters serve as a neutral and impersonal check on self-indul- gence and whimsy;
    a subjective event gets made over into something more like an object." Even memory is an "act
    not without craft," we know, and the me- tering of our verbalizing of our experience we want to
    know much more about. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E50">
   <bib>Kelley, Frank B. "The Rise and Development of English Metrification, with Special Reference
    to the Question of Quantity versus Accent as the Underlying Principle." Diss., New York
    University, 1894. 36 pp. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E51">
   <bib>Ker, W. P. The Art of Poetry: Seven Lectures 1920-1922. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1923; rpt
    Freeport, N. Y.: Books for Libraries Press, 1967. </bib>
   <notes>Rev: in TLS, 9 August 1923, p. 1; in South Atlantic Quarterly 23 (1924): 286- 87; in MLR
    19 (1924): 361-62. Remarks in the first lecture on the foreign and early influences on our
    versifi- cation. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E52">
   <bib>Koch, Walter A. Recurrence and a Three-Modal Approach to Poetry. The Hague: Mouton, 1966.
    55 pp. </bib>
   <notes>A general theory of poetic structure (expressed in very concise form) based on the key
    feature of recurrence; the three modes of analysis identified are Topical, Metrical, and
    Stylistic. In Metrics, recurrence may be either Phonetic, Syntac- tic, or Semantic (English
    verse has heavily exploited the first of these, but who has demonstrated a metering of
    "sememes"?) or a combination of them (i.e. phonetic + syntactic rather than phonetic +
    phonetic). Koch then examines the relationships of metrical constituents ("immediate
    juxtaposition, recurrent in- terval, non-recurrent interval"), patterns of such relationships
    ("contiguous overlapping, congruent, engrafted"), and the principles of metrical "piling,"
    "imposition," and "saturation." Altogether the merit of this brief monograph is to demonstrate
    afresh the possibiities for complexity in meter and (even further) in poetry. See also: Hans
    Gumbrecht's "Poetizitätsdefinition zwischen Funktion and Struktur: Ein Diskussions vorschlag an
    Walter A. Koch." Poetica 10 (1978): 342-61. E53 </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E54">
   <bib>Körting, Gustav. Encyklopaedie und Methodologie der englischen Philologie. Heilbronn:
    Henninger, 1888. </bib>
   <notes>An early philological handbook. Chapter 8, "Die Rhythmik des Englischen," pp. 368-90,
    gives a summary of the research to that date on Old through Mod- ern English meter. K. accepts
    the vierhebungstheoriefor OE and ME. Bibliogra- phy. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E55">
   <bib>Koziol, Herbert. Zahlen in englischen Versdichtungen. Sitzungsberichte der Österreichische
    Akademie der Wissenschaften, philosophisch-historishe Klasse, vol. 291, no. 5. Vienna, 1973. 47
    pp. </bib>
   <notes>In part Koziol is interested in how the names of numbers are used by poets to fill slots
    in the stress pattern of the verse-line. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E56">
   <bib>Kremer, Charles F. "Studies in Verse-Form in Non-Dramatic English Poetry from Wyatt to
    Sidney." Diss., Northwestern University, 1942. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E57">
   <bib>Kuhn, Ursula. "Prosody." English Literary Terms in Poetological Texts of the Sixteenth
    Century. 3 vols. Elizabethan &amp; Renaissance Studies, nos. 32, 33, 34. Salzburg: Salzburg
    Institut for englische Sprache and Literatur, 1974. Vol. 2. pp. 453-70. </bib>
   <notes>An extremely convenient and useful resource which cites brief extracts from the major
    Renaissance prosodists--Gascoigne, Puttenham, Sidney, Spenser, Harvey, Stanyhurst, and Webbe--on
    thirty-nine topics in prosody--e.g. rhyme, rhythm, meter, accent, quantitative verse. Prefixed
    by short topical Index. (Unfortunately the overprinted typescript is painful to read.) </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E58">
   <bib>La Drière, J. Craig. "Prosody." Princeton (A20), pp. 669-77. </bib>
   <notes>A remarkable general survey, sustained at a level very near the purely theoreti- cal.
    Prosody is defined as the study of "the elements and structures involved in the rhythmic or
    dynamic aspect of speech . . . as they occur in speech and lan- guage generally (linguistic
    prosody) or in the compositions of the literary arts (lit- erary prosody)" (italics original).
    This latter area has been more often termed ver- sification. Descriptive prosody may be either
    theoretical or historical, while evalua- tive work lies in the domain of criticism. The rhythm
    of verse is one manifesta- tion of rhythmic activity in general, and as a species is more
    closely related to the rhythms of dance--bodily movement--than to those of music, since the
    speech-mechanism itself is a motor behavior. Yet, "it is the sound as heard, the perceptual
    'phone' or 'allophone' rather than the phoneme as such, that is rele- vant for literary, as
    distinct from linguistic, structure of sound." All verse- rhythm is a patterning of the
    qualitative and quantitative features of sound, chiefly intensity or duration: La Dri|`ere gives
    a very extensive theoretical ac- count of the systematic possibilities of such patterning.
    Worthy of special note: "the datum of a prosodic analysis is ideally an oral performance (actual
    or con- ceived) rather than a written text." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E59">
   <bib>Legouis, Émile. A Short Parallel Between French and English Versification. Publications of
    the Modern Humanities Research Association, no. 9. Cambridge: Bowes &amp; Bowes, 1925. 18 pp. </bib>
   <notes> His Presidental Address to the Association published as a pamphlet. "The modern
    versification of England is the result of compromise, the trium- phant but painfully laborious
    ordering of chaos. It was only attained after years of groping efforts to fuse and reconcile
    antagonistic elements. . . . In fact, it took centuries to accomodate the language to the
    versification or the versifica- tion to the language. The verse which prevailed in the end was
    not primarily made for the language upon which it was imposed." The result? "English has emerged
    with two distinct kinds of verse, now no longer confusedly blended but kept separate for
    different uses and different effects." Nowhere is the whole history of our metric more
    succinctly or accurately expressed. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E60">
   <bib>Malof, Joseph. "The Artifice of Scansion." English Journal 54 (1965): 857-60, 71. </bib>
   <notes>The modern sensibility is so glaringly inept at recognizing and discussing poetic meter
    primarily because no adequate system of scansion is currently taught or understood. Scansion is
    not a theoretical construct but simply a "practical lan- guage of description," and the best
    notation is the one which provides the most accurate, concise, yet flexible description of the
    interplay between rhythm and meter. To deride scansion as "artificial" is to misunderstand its
    very nature. There is no one right scansion, all others being wrong; there are only better and
    worse scansions. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E61">
   <bib>Maxim, Hudson. The Science of Poetry and the Philosophy of Language. New York and London:
    Funk and Wagnalls, 1910. </bib>
   <notes>A true curiousity, this. The most dogged of prosodic historians will find rele- vant
    remarks following p. 152; all others will be intrigued by the illustrations more than anything
    else. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E62">
   <bib>"Metrical Technique." TLS, 6 April 1956, p. 207. </bib>
   <notes>Encourages the teaching of metrical form, not so much in the spirit of rigid rules and
    devices, but in such a way that the student can attend to the supple nuances of sullables.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E63">
   <bib>Moore, T. Sturge, D. S. MacColl, et all. "English Numbers." Correspondence in TLS, 9
    January-27 March 1919, pp. 20-21, 33, 45, 56-57, 69, 83-84, 97, 112, 125, 137, 151-52; 164-65. </bib>
   <notes>Interminable debate, each correspondent propounding his own theory of met- rics--Moore,
    the intuitivist; MacColl, the temporalist; Bayfield, the trochaic-- and the whole dreary
    exchange degenerating into bickering between Moore and MacColl. However, T. B. Rudmose-Brown's
    acknowledgment of signifi- cant shifts in his thinking (at p. 83) must not go unnoticed.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E64">
   <bib>Morse, Lewis K., ed. Melodies of English Verse. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1910. </bib>
   <notes>An anthology arranged by meters for training students to recognize and memo- rize metrical
    verse. Divided merely into Iambic, Trochaic, Anapestic, and Dactylic, but notice the Index of
    Metres. Cited in NUC, vol. 396, p. 362. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E65">
   <bib>Morton, Edward P. "Chronology and Metrical Tests." PMLA 25 (1910):xxxix (Proceedings).
    Abstract. </bib>
   <notes>Metrical evidence generally corroborates the accepted chronologies for Milton, Keats,
    Browning, and Tennyson. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E66">
   <bib>Murray, Gilbert. "Metre." The Classical Tradition in Poetry. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard
    University Press, 1927. pp. 80-121. </bib>
   <notes>An urbane, informed, detailed, non-technical explanation of the differences between
    Classical Greek and Modern English versification, with Hebrew and Chinese also discussed for
    contrast. Should be just the thing for undergraduates. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E67">
   <bib>Nakao, Toshio. [Poetic License and Three Models of Prosody.] Eigo Seinen (The Rising
    Generation) 118 (1972): 158-59. </bib>
   <notes> (In Japanese) Compares the Traditional, Trager-Smith, and Halle-Keyser systems. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E68">
   <bib>Newbolt, Henry. "A New Study of English Poetry, II: Poetry and Rhythm." The English Review
    10 (1911-12): 657-72; rpt in his A New Study of English Poetry. New York: E. P. Dutton, 1919.
    pp. 26-51. </bib>
   <notes>"Poetic rhythm is, in short, neither strict mechanical rhythm nor free speech- rhythm: it
    is speech limited by metric law, or Prosody. . . . A prosody, then, or metric law, there must
    be, to save the gesture from becoming invertebrate." Reviewing the course of meters over
    European history, the author makes an articulate plea for "the recognition of two principles":
    "That poetic rhythm is not an applied ornament" and that "the natural tendency of poetic rhythm
    will be toward perpetual change." Part I appears on pp. 285-300 of the same vol. 10. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E69">
   <bib>Ogden, C. K. "Sound, Sense, and Intelligibility." Psyche 15 (1935): 19-76. </bib>
   <notes>See the sections on "Verse Rhythm" (pp. 50-59) and "Prose Rhythm" (pp. 59- 74). Despite
    all the pedagogical platatudes about iambic meters, Ogden insists, the English language is
    deeply, irrefrangibly trochaic, and so therefore is its verse. Longfellow and the Hiawatha-meter
    merit a long digression in the "Verse" section, and indulgence which then widens to include the
    whole of the following section, a peregrination on the subjects of the relations of verse and
    prose, isochronism, prose rhythm, and stress. Surprisingly well informed. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E70">
   <bib>Owen, W. J. B. "The Theory of Metre." Wordsworth as Critic. Toronto: University of Toronto
    Press, 1969. pp. 27-36. See also pp. 125-27. </bib>
   <notes>Since one of the linchpins of Wordsworth's poetics in the 1800 and 1802 ver- sions of the
    Preface is his view of poetry as "the natural language of men," his simultaneous insistence on
    the preservation of meter in poetry would seem in- consistent. WW's defense rests on three
    conceptions of the function of meter: pleasure, regularity, and contrast. Meter per se gives
    pleasure as an ornament to language already efficacious. The regularity of meter tempers and
    restrains the excitement raised by the poetic fiction, as well as reminding the reader, implic-
    itly, that he is experiencing literature not life. And meter balances or contrasts the real
    language of men. Owen notes the evident discrepancy in WW's theo- ries and his practice, also
    admitting that "the prose parts of Wordsworth's blank verse, especially, appear to gain no
    advantage from being in metre." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E71">
   <bib>Parrish, Stephen M. Wordsworth and Coleridge on Meter." JEGP 59 (1960): 41-49. </bib>
   <notes>By close explication of the statements and arguments made by Wordsworth (in the Preface)
    and Coleridge (in BL) on meter, Parrish controverts the received critical opinion that
    Wordsworth denigrated meter as adventitious while Coleridge defended it as indispensable to the
    organic whole, the poem. That is the view Coleridge would have us believe. But in fact, though
    Wordsworth did argue that meter has no necessary connection with language,he held it to be
    essential for effecting the tranquility that is poetic pleasure, while for Coleridge meter was a
    stimulant and a matter of "superficial form," separable from the language that was central.
    Indeed to Coleridge meter was a symbol of a special- ized poetic language--precisely the view
    Wordsworth attacks in the "Preface." Wordsworth, focusing on the function of art, treats the
    role of meter in aesthetic response; Coleridge, focusing on the sources of art, treats the role
    of meter in the creative process. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E72">
   <bib>R, D. L. "On Versification." The Inspector, Literary Magazine and Review 2 (1826): 19-22. </bib>
   <notes>Short exposition of the metrical forms of blank verse, couplet, octosyllabic verse,
    quatrains, Spenserians, and the sonnet. Most interesting are the remarks on the structure of
    blank verse and citations of several obscure remarks on that form by Dr. Johnson; the rest is
    trite. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E73">
   <bib>Ramsay, Robert L. "Changes in Verse-Technic in the Sixteenth-Century English Drama."
    American Journal of Philology 31 (1910): 175-202. </bib>
   <notes>From 1480 to 1590 the verseform of English drama developed from the rhyme- royal and
    tail-rhyme stanzas (in four-stress lines) through the "septenary" cou- plet (the Fourteener) to
    the decasyllable (rhymed and blank) and prose. But "the attempt to find pentameters,
    alexandrines, or septenaries, even of an im- perfect kind, in [the dramas of the first half of
    the sixteenth century] reduces their versification to chaos." The old order was completely upset
    by "the most important innovation in versification of the century," the introduction of regu-
    lar meters (regular in syllable-count), the earliest example of which in the drama is Jasper
    Heywood's Senecan Troas of 1559. Blank verse, of course, first appeared in Gorboduc, 1562. See
    esp. p. 188 here, and see also K307. The final paragraph summarizes succinctly "the residuum of
    a hundred years of experimentation" in dramatic verseform, specifically the four metrical styles
    employed by the dramatists of the day to differentiate the Virtue and Vice characters and high
    social stations from low. Highly informative, Ramsay's essay is still authoritative, and its
    lucid map- ping of a bewildering terrain is augmented by frequent, detailed metrical analyses of
    plays. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E74">
   <bib>Rankin, J. W. "Rime and Reason." PMLA 44 (1929): 997-1004. </bib>
   <notes>Proposes an etymology for the idiom based on medieval Latin grammar: rhyth- mus denoted
    accentually based verse, while ratio meant quantitative, syllable- counting meter. (This was
    also the distinction between rhythmus and metrum.) The Renaissance classicists, then, used rime
    in the older sense of rythmus, to in- dicate meter based on stress. See also </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E45">
   <bib/>
   <notes> and C273. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E75">
   <bib>Renz, Merl F. "A Coleridge Unpublished Letter and Some Remarks Concerning the Poet's
    Interest in the Sound of Words." Notes &amp; Queries 198 (1953): 163- 65. </bib>
   <notes>Coleridge gives English accentual equivalents of the Greek quantitative feet in the first
    letter and exemplifies them in a Pindaric ode. In the second letter he muses on a stray couplet
    which he couldn't get out of his head on account of the intonation of the second line, "The
    pretty, pleasing playful, proley-prowley Pricket." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E76">
   <bib>Reyher, Paul. Essai sur le Doggerel. Diss., University of Paris. Bordeaux, 1909. 114 pp. </bib>
   <notes>Defining "doggerel" as "un mechant poeme depourvu d'originalite et sans pro- portions,
    mais il semble avoir surtout trait a sa versification d'une regularite ex- cessive," Reyher
    examines incompetently wooden and parodically incompe- tently wooden verses from Layamon to
    Swift, with heavier emphasis on the Middle English period. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E77">
   <bib>Richards, I. A. "Rhythm and Metre." Principles of Literary Criticism. New York: Harcourt,
    Brace, and World, 1925; rpt 1948. pp. 134-46. Rpt in Gross (A23), pp. 42-51. </bib>
   <notes>Richards takes what might be called a Gestalt (i.e., perceptional-field) approach to
    literature. Sound in poetry depends for its meaning entirely on context: its effect cannot be
    separated from the effects of other contextual elements; sound in itself has no meaning. The
    sound of a word cannot be considered apart from its meaning. The interaction of succession and
    simultaneity comprises rhythm. Meter, as "a specialized form of rhythm," is not a patterned
    stimulus but a pat- tered response, as well as being a "framing device" (cf. Hollander, E46).
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E78">
   <bib>Richardson, Leon J. "Repetition and Rhythm in Vergil and Shakespeare." University of
    California Chronicle 32 (1930): 177-82. </bib>
   <notes>A model of import and economy. The question raised is how repeated words in verse are
    fitted into the metrical pattern (or grid), or in other words, the ef- fect of repetition on
    word-meter alignment and, hence, the rhythm of the line. Given any word repeated (as a then b),
    there are four possibilities: (1) a and b have identical placements in the meter--such diaeresis
    tends to make the meter glare, and Richardson calls it "unmusical" in contrast to the other
    three types; (2) a and b may vary slightly in word-form (lover, loved, etc.) but be identically
    metrically treated; (3) a and b fall in different metrical positions (now arsis, now thesis)
    though identical in word-form; and (4) a and b differ both in metrical and in lexical
    treatment--the most "musical" type of all four. Convincing ex- amples from both poets (no
    influence is claimed). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E79">
   <bib>Sasaki, Tatsu. "Apocope in Modern English Verse." Studies in English Literature (Tokyo) 13
    (1933): 585-603. </bib>
   <notes>On words used in poetry which have dropped the final syllable: the most common are divided
    into seven catagories and discussed, with etymologies and very copious examples, Renaissance to
    Modern. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E80">
   <bib>Selden, R. "Roughness in Satire from Horace to Dryden." MLR 66 (1971): 264-72. </bib>
   <notes>The Elizabethan theory of the "roughness" of true sature understood the Ro- man view
    correctly in terms of roughness of tone (invective, vituperation), but not in terms of roughness
    of versification, since Horace believed that the num- bers should be polished even in the most
    virulent of lines. Jonson and Dryden, however, were the chief exponents of a return to the
    orthodox classical view demanding smoothness of metier despite sharpness of matter. A dense,
    discrimi- nation, yet extensive essay. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E81">
   <bib>Shapiro, Karl. "English Prosody and Modern Poetry." ELH 14 (1947): 77-92; published at
    Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1947; rpt Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions,
    1975. 16 pp. </bib>
   <notes>Rev. in Poetry 72 (1948): 332-35. Shapiro finds two historical trends to lament: one is
    that prosody, as an ostensible science, has seen little progressive development until the late
    nineteenth century; the other is that after the turn of the century and "one of the few great
    upheavals" in English poetry--free verse--prosody was thrown again into anarchy, from which it
    has not yet recovered. Shapiro then sketches in cameo the theoretical positions of the two chief
    schools of prosody, the Accentualists (Saintsbury and Bridges) and Temporalists (Lanier), with
    Omond in a medial position. These correspond roughly to the two broadest traditions in English
    verse, the stress-verse (Beowulf to Skelton to Hopkins) and the stress-verse (Chaucer to
    Housman). But the nineteenth-century prosodic synthesis was unable to cope with the new prosaic
    structures and rhythms in verse. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E82">
   <bib>-----. Essay on Rime. New York: Reyal &amp; Hitchcock, 1945. </bib>
   <notes>Rev: by Delmore Schwartz in The Nation 160 (1945): 498; reply by Shapiro, p. 690,
    rejoinder by Schwartz, pp. 691-92. In the first major section, "The Confusion of Prosody,"
    Shapiro attempts to map out the theorists and practitioners of his time in a prosaic verse, as
    if the Essay on Criticism were rewritten as The Prelude Of the theorists, Bridges on Milton,
    Lanier on verse, and Saintsbury on prose-rhythm are discussed; of the cloistered makers, Joyce
    and Eliot are assayed the great masters of our time (both indebted to Pound), as against the
    more ephemeral, weaker metrics of Donne, Browning, Hopkins, Whitman, Cummings, Lawrence,
    Williams, and the Imagist, Visual, and Objectivist prosodies. Strong stressing is hammering down
    the old "rising rhythm," and Shapiro ventures his hypothesis that "rhythm/Flows but in one
    direction, and that from Prose/To rime. The oppo- site is upstream, against/The grain of
    language and the course of change./ The measure of prosody is the current speech,/The cadences
    inherent in the voice/Of one particular generation." See also: </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E83">
   <bib>Williams, William C. "Shapiro is All Right." Kenyon Review 8 (1946): 123-26. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>



  <item id="E84">
   <bib>O'Conner, William Van. "Shapiro On Rime." Kenyon Review 8 (1946): 113- 22. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E85">
   <bib>Sharp, Robert L. "Some Light on Metaphysical Obscurity and Roughness." SP 31 (1934):
    497-518. </bib>
   <notes>(Begin at p. 510.) This is a clear statement of the older view that Donne and the
    metaphysicals deliberately wrote their meters rough, so as to suit the verse- form to the sense
    and mood of satire. This "harshness" lay not in syllable-count (here they are all relatively
    regular) but in preserving regularity of stresses. Roughness was also associated with
    "masculinity." The virtuosity of the meta- physicals in stanza-forms is also adduced as proof of
    the intentionality of their writing rough. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E86">
   <bib>Stanford, Donald E. "The Experimentalist Poet." In his In the Classic Mode: The Achievement
    of Robert Bridges. Newark: University of Delaware Press, 1978. pp. 80-125. </bib>
   <notes>Presently the authoritative survey of Bridges' theories and experiments in stress- ,
    quantitative-, and syllabic-verse. But cf. Gu|'erard (B86). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E87">
   <bib>-----. "Robert Bridges and the Free Verse Rebellion." Journal of Modern Literature 2
    (1971): 19-32. </bib>
   <notes>Summarizes Bridges' metrical experiments in non-conventional meters, i.e. ac- centual
    verse (cf. Milton's Prosody), quantitative verse (Now In Wintry Delights, etc.), "Neo-Miltonic
    syllabics" (The Tapestry), and "loose Alexandrines" (The Testament of Beauty). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E88">
   <bib>Stockley, W. F. P. "Uncertainty in English Prosody." Poet-Lore 41 (1930): 204-22. </bib>
   <notes>The author requires nineteen pages to tell us that metrists are confused about whether
    English verse is metered by time, accent, or syllables. Criticism of Bayfield (E336). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E89">
   <bib>Thiesmeyer, John E. "Problems in the Application of Linguistic System to the Study of
    Versification." Venture (University of Karachi) 6 (1970): 24-33. </bib>
   <notes>A critique of both Structuralist and Generative Metrists. Thiesmeyer notes that though the
    history of metrics has been muddled, the new linguistic efforts have been no improvement because
    they, like all the rest, have failed to be utterly explicit about defining terms. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E90">
   <bib>-----. "Prosodic Theory: A Critique and Some Proposals." DAI 35 (1974): 1064A (Cornell). </bib>
   <notes>Reviews and criticizes traditional, structural, and generative metrics. Metrical theory
    itself is said to be unsuccessful because it has not yet answered the fun- damental question of
    poetic ontology--what kind of object the poet is--and critical epistomology--how prosodic data
    is to be defined, gathered, and veri- fied. Thiesmeyer proposes a solution to the impasse in
    theory by redefining the subject of metrics as the poetic experience rather than the
    poem-object. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E91">
   <bib>Thompson, John. The Founding of English Metre. London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1961; 2nd
    ed. 1989, with Preface by John Hollander. </bib>
   <notes>Rev: in Sewanee Review 70 (1062): 688-91; in Criticism 5 (1963): 80-82; in Ar- chiv 200
    (1963): 219-21. See also Hawkes and Bateson (E719). Based on his dissertation, "The Iambic Line
    from Wyatt to Sidney," DA 18 (1958): 1040A (Columbia). Should become the locus classicus on
    Renaissance metrics and, indeed, on the more general subject of the nature of English
    accentual-syllabic meter in its sta- ple form, the iambic pentameter line. Beginning with a
    rigorous distinction between the natural (rhythmic) stresses of the language and the abstract
    metrical pattern, and adopting the two axioms entailed by this distinction--that verse can be
    read one way and scanned another, and that the effect of counterpoising rhythm against meter is
    to create tension [this is the hallmark of the structural approach]--Thompson traces out
    carefully the development of the pentameter line in early Renaissance verse, from the domination
    of natural speech rhythms in Wyatt through the other extreme of excessive metrical regularity in
    Surrey to the synthesis of both of these styles in the supple, finely modulated metrical
    instrument of Sidney, the meter which will be the standard of English poetry for three centuries
    thereafter. But equally remarkable is Thompson's argument that "the iambic metrical pattern has
    dominated English verse because it pro- vides the best symbolic model of our language"--that is,
    through meter "what poetry imitates is the structure of the language itself." Meter crystallizes
    (by se- lection, reduction, and abstraction) the deep structure of the language. Chapters: on
    Wyatt, Tottel, and Surrey; The Mirror for Magistrates; Googe, Turberville, and Gascoigne; The
    Shepheardes Calender; classical meters; and on Sidney. Two Appendices, Bibliography. Synopsis of
    the book will be found at E687. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E92">
   <bib>Tsur, Reuven. "Articulateness and Requiredness in Iambic Verse." Style 6 (1972): 123-48. </bib>
   <notes>The relationship of grammatical to prosodic features ("strings") in verse may be either
    convergent or divergent, states which differ markedly in "perceptual quality" or texture;
    divergence produces either soft focus (Milton, Shelley) where the two kinds of features
    gradually fade into each other, or split focus (Pope), where they are polarized. Articulateness
    and requiredness, antinomies, two sides of the same coin, are the two aspects of "breaking up a
    whole into segments." Ar- ticulateness implies segmentation of a whole into parts both
    "distinct" and "jointed" in order to simplify its perception. Requiredness implies the integrity
    of the whole through its parts: no part is superfluous. In general the more highly articulated a
    structure is, the more highly required are its parts, though not always. Split Focus: Clearly
    one of if not the chief function of verse-structure is to heighten the "visibility" of the
    segmentation, i.e. of the small-scale units. When grammatical and metrical units are not
    convergent, they "compete" with each other for our attention. The first of the two versions of
    the couplet below seems wittier to us--sharper in bite, stronger in pull--because "awake" (first
    version) is more highly required by the positioning of the syntactic break late in the line: Now
    Lapdogs give themselves the rowzing Shake, And sleepless Lovers, just at Twelve, awake. Now
    Lapdogs give themselves the rowzing Shake, And, just at Twelve, the sleepless Lovers awake. From
    this example and others we can see however that position is by no means the only factor in
    establishing tension--meter, narratorial voice, and many other factors pertain. Among the major
    English poets, Browning is by far the most vigorous at sustaining split focus; his verse has a
    very evident sharpness and a "conclusive" tone. Soft Focus: More extreme pressures and more
    complex structures pro- duce a melding of polarity into continuity and a "suspensive" tone, as
    in Wordsworth, Shelley, and Milton. A high frequency of syntactic breaks near the ends of the
    line normally produces split focus, but after sufficient reiteration will slide over into the
    blurred, multi-layered texture so common in Milton. Similarly the strong requiredness generated
    by enjambment produced fluidity by weakening the line-end. Stress-shifts and complex syntax may
    achieve the same effects. An important new approach to the description of verse-structure; see
    also Tsur's monography (E810), of which this article is anything but a mere redaction. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E93">
   <bib>"The Value of Meter in Verse." Current Literature (Later Current Opinion) 34 (10 Jan.
    1903): 10-11. </bib>
   <notes>Meter is as indispensable to poetry as the laws of perspective and color are to painting
    or the laws of scale and harmony are to music. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E94">
   <bib>Versification: A Monthly Magazine of Measure and Metre. Ed. Alfred Nutting. June 1891-June
    1892. London. </bib>
   <notes>Continued as Poetry and Prose until suspended in 1895; completely irrelevant to our
    concerns. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E95">
   <bib>Welch, Constance. "Some Experimental Work in Speech Rhythm." Quarterly Journal of Speech 11
    (1925): 247-52. </bib>
   <notes>The author believes that certain emotions are expressed in certain characteristic rhythms,
    and so her little experiments find what they were designed to find. She divides passages of
    prose into lines and feet of verse, mainly on the basis of logical breaks, then hunts for
    meters, producing such results as "Joy fell into two feet anapestic lines. The rhythm of love
    was very complex." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E96">
   <bib>Wells, Henry. W. "The Heritage of Form." In his New Poets From Old: A Study in Literary
    Genetics. New York: Columbia University Press, 1940; rpt London, 1964. pp. 129-71. </bib>
   <notes>A very broad yet informed survey of Poetic Influence, particularly metrical. The most
    interesting claim is that modern poetry is metrically more indebted to Medieval, Elizabethan,
    and Cavalier verse than to the Augustans, Romantics, and Victorians. Many examples. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E97">
   <bib>Williams, Miller. "The Line in Poetry." Antaeus 30/31 (1978): 309-13. </bib>
   <notes>Generalizations and observations on what is probably the most crucial area in all of
    poetics--the reader's perception of the line as a unit in the poem; why wasn't this essay
    written twenty years ago? </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E98">
   <bib>Williams, Ellis, Mrs. Annabel. "Uses and Abuses of Metre." An Anatomy of Poetry. Oxford:
    Basil Blackwell, 1922. pp. 68-81. </bib>
   <notes>Peregrine thoughts. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E99">
   <bib>Woods, Suzanne. "Aesthetic and Mimetic Rhythms in the Versification of Gascoigne, Sidney,
    and Spenser." Studies in the Literary Imaginination 11 (1978): 31-44. </bib>
   <notes>Woods tries to distinguish mimetic rhythms (metrical figures which imitate "the speaking
    voice the poem seeks to present or the statement the poem is mak- ing") from aesthetic ones ("in
    themselves somehow pleasurable"), but the first definition fails to explain how the actual
    presentation differs from a simulacrum of it, and the second amounts to nothing more than
    "non-mimetic," since no corollary class of "displeasurable" rhythms is identified. This
    distinction she claims did not obtain before the sixteenth century and cuts across the
    traditional separation of plain and aureate styles in Renaissance verse. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E100">
   <bib>Wordsworth, William. "Preface." Lyrical Ballads, With Pastorals and Other Poems. 3rd. ed.
    London: Thomas Longman, 1802; rpt in Literary Criticism of William Wordsworth. Ed. Paul M. Zall.
    Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1966. pp. 38-62. </bib>
   <notes>In the fifth paragraph Wordsworth commences upon the creation of his proper audience by
    warning his readers against any expectation of (what later came to be called) the "metrical
    contract"--reader presuppositions about the style and themes of poems set in a certain meter.
    His larger problem is to explain his paradoxical view that the "language" of poetry is identical
    to the language of prose, the "real language of men." Part of his strategy for a solution is to
    map out a rough theory of meter, defending meter as a source of "charm" and "pleasure" which may
    be beneficially superadded to the effects of prose, sense and order. The pleasure inhering in
    the regularity of meter will function as a mild narcotic, soothing the reader whenever the sheer
    excitement of good po- etry tends to overwhelm his emotions, and reminding him subliminally that
    what he is experiencing is art not reality. Thus the meter, emblem of "simili- tude in
    dissimilitude," produces "a complex feeling of delight." And what Wordsworth terms "the tendency
    of meter to divest language in a certain de- gree of its reality" will later be called
    "aesthetic distance." See Coleridge's reply at E13, and see E70 and E71. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E101">
   <bib>Yeats, William Butler. "A General Introduction for My Work" [1937]. In Essays and
    Introductions. New York: Macmillan, 1961, 1968. pp. 509-30. </bib>
   <notes>Especially section 3; Yeats's phrases speaking of the language and meters of po- etry,
    have come to be scarcely less memorable than Wordsworth's: "I discov- ered some twenty years ago
    that I must seek, not as Wordsworth thought, words in common use, but a powerful and passionate
    syntax, and a complete coincidence between period and stanza. Because I need a passionate syntax
    for passionate subject-matter I compel myself to accept those traditional meters that have
    developed with the language. . . . If I wrote of personal love or sor- row in free verse, or in
    any rhythm that left it unchanged, amid all its acci- dence, I would be full of self-contempt
    because of my egotism and indiscre- tion. . . . all that is personal soon rots; it must be
    packed in ice or salt. . . . I must choose a traditional stanza, even what I alter must seem
    traditional." See also section 5 of "The Symbolism of Poetry" [1900] in the same vol- ume. See
    also B36, B42, B85, B156, B158-59, B176, B193, B214, C58, D323, D332, E756-57, E764, E794,
    E1215, G15, G111, H17, H22, L42, L57, L100, L155, M181, N77. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E102">
   <bib>Abercrombie, David. "A Phonetician's View of Verse Structure." Linguistics, no. 6 (1964),
    pp. 5-13; rpt in his Studies in Phonetics and Linguistics. Language and Language Learning
    Series, no. 10. London: Oxford University Press, 1965. pp. 16-25 </bib>
   <notes>; rpt also in Phonetics in Linguistics: A Book of Readings. Ed. W. E. Jones and J. Laver.
    London: Longman Group, 1973. pp. 6-13. The study of verse-structure is a proper domain of
    phonetics "because verse is verse as a result of the way certain aspects of sound, or rather
    perhaps the sound-producing movements, of speech have been exploited or organized." The
    air-stream produced in speech is not continuous but pulsatory in two di- mensions: the regular
    muscular contractions creating pressure peaks, here termed chest-pulses (each of which
    corresponds to one syllable), and also the "less frequent, more powerful contractions of the
    breathing muscles which every now and then coincide with, and reinforce, a chest-pulse
    stress-pulses." Languages which organize the latter are stress-timed, those organizing the for-
    mer, syllable-timed. English verse, not different in kind from English speech, is stress-timed
    (stress-pulses may occur even in the absence of a sounded syllable), divided into isochronous
    stress-initiating units called feet, and "must be there- fore in some sense quantitative."
    Silent stresses are unexpectedly common, English verse has many more types of feet than Greek,
    and line-end is usually signaled by a silent stress, monosyllabic foot, or the rhyme. Notice the
    sample scansions, whch seem especially forced and unnatural. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E103">
   <bib>-----. "Syllable Quantity and Enclitics in English." In Honour of Daniel Jones. Ed. David
    Abercrombie et al. London: Longman's 1964. pp. 216-22 </bib>
   <notes>; rpt in his Studies in Phonetics and Linguistics. Language and Language Learning Series,
    no. 10. London: Oxford University Press, 1965. pp. 26-34. Appropriating the concepts (while
    oddly eschewing the terms) of classical ver- sification to the description of the rhythm of the
    English language (and verse), A. argues that there are consistent relations of quantity to be
    found between English syllables. Quantity in English syllables is relative to that in adjacent
    syl- lables and varies with context, in contrast to Greek, where syllabic quantity was absolute
    and constant. N.B.: syllable-quantity does not equal vowel quantity. A. postulates that English
    utterances are divided into isochronous stress-timed feet, such that "we cannot therefore sway
    anything about the quantity of a sylla- ble until we know its place in the foot." Three
    disyllabic feet are identi- fied(short-long, equal-equal, and long-short), all in triple time.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E104">
   <bib>Adams, Stephen J. "Pound's Quantities and 'Absolute Rhythm.'" Essays in Literature [Western
    Illinois University] 4 (1977): 95-109. </bib>
   <notes>Explicates those two principles in Pound's poetry. By the latter, he meant "melopoeia," or
    the absolute association of emotions with word-sounds--a complex but precise system of
    correspondences Pound held to be different for each language. Hence, Adams shows, he often
    subordinated lexical and seman- tic accuracy in his translations to melopoeic accuracy. By the
    former, Pound meant a rigorous system of verse-composition based on quantity, but lacking any
    consistency of principle: "Pound's syllable may be long either by nature, or by position, or by
    stress, but sometimes a stressed syllable is insisted on as short and counterpointed. Pound's
    principles are thus arbitrary and contradictory. . . . This is not to say that Pound's sapphics
    are failures, but that they are an illu- sion--a skillfully designed illusion." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E105">
   <bib>Allen, [Charles] Grant [Blairfindie]. "On the Galliambic Metre." The Attis of Caius
    Valerius Catullus Translated into English Verse, with Dissertations. . . . London: David Nutt,
    1892. pp. 126-54. </bib>
   <notes>Argues Catullus's meter to be highly regular (contrary to opinion) and of the form Ë Ë Ì Ë
    Ì Ë Ì Ì Ë Ë Ì Ë Ë Ë Ë Ì , the half-lines being derived from Greek iambic tetrameters. Tennyson's
    translation uses trochaic meter, George Meridith's iambic-anapestic. Tennyson's choice, Allen
    believes, arose from a mistaken accentual scansion of the classical verse. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E106">
   <bib>Applegate, James. "Sidney's Classical Meters." MLN 70 (1955): 254-55. </bib>
   <notes>Corrects a mistake by Theodore Spencer in ELH 12 (1945): 251-78. Sidney's fine little poem
    "When to my deadlie pleasure" is written in the Aristophanic not the Anacreonic meter. Wider
    discussion of Sidney's classical-imitative ex- periments follows. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E107">
   <bib>Arnold, Matthew. Three Lectures on Translating Homer. London: Longman's 1861. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E108">
   <bib>-----. Last Words on Translating Homer. London: Longman's, 1896. </bib>
   <notes>There is a noteworthy Introduction in the 1905 edition edited by W. H. D. Rouse, but the
    best modern text (with excellent notes) is On the Classical Tra- dition. Vol. 1 of The Complete
    Prose Works of Matthew Arnold. Ed. R. H. Super. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1960.
    See also Omond (E214), Spedding (E238), Munro (M140), Newman (E210), and Lord Redesdale (E220).
    On the criticial question of audience, Arnold considers the best reader and judge of a Homeric
    translation to be the scholar, both fluent in the original Greek and possessed of genuine taste
    in poetry. And though the lectures treat mainly of style and movement, the third of the original
    three turns to the ques- tion of meter, Arnold rejecting couplets (Chapman's and Pope's), blank
    verse (Cowper's Miltonic convolutions) and ballad meter (Francis W. Newman's), preferring
    instead the hexameter (Hawtrey's are approved, Clough's and Long- fellow's rejected) as being
    the closest to the original Homeric "movement" (a crucial term). The stiffness of the dactyls in
    the English hexameter may be avoided by frequent spondees; the only other requirement (also
    crucial) is that the lines must "read themselves"--i.e. the natural accent should not be
    wrenched unnaturally to fit the metrical pattern. The lines must read naturally to the Eng- lish
    ear, though at the same time the quantities must not be "utterly discarded." In the Last Words
    lecture (delivered November 30, 1861), Arnold makes a sincere effort to mollify Newman (whose
    Reply to Arnold's earlier criticisms in the second lecture showed him eager to avenge an
    inflated sense of injury) while at the same time defending his original judgments, then examines
    the views of Spedding (English hexameters should be quantitative) and Munro (quantity should be
    entirely ignored) with surprising energy, generally siding with Munro in favor of the accentual
    imitation as something "necessary and in- evitable" to the English ear. "We must work with the
    tools we have." The lecture concludes with the memorable soft eulogy for Clough. See also the
    untitled review by Noel Annan in The New Statesman n.s. 27 (1944): 191. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E109">
   <bib>Ascham, Roger. The Scholemaster [1563-69]. London: John Daye, 1570 </bib>
   <notes>; 2nd ed. 1571. Ed. Edward Arber. English Reprints series, no. 23. London, 1870, 1888. In
    Smith (A26), vol. 1, pp. 1-45. In the English Experience series, no. 15. New York: Da Capo
    Press, 1968. In facsimile, Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar Press, 1967. Ed. Lawrence W. Ryan. Ithaca:
    Cornell University Press, 1967. Ed. R. J. Schoeck. Ontario: J. M. Dent and Sons, 1966. Near the
    end of Book II, Ascham criticises his contemporary verse-writers, those "rash, ignorant heads,
    which now can easily reckon up fourteen syllables, and easily stumble on every rhyme" but are
    too idle and ignorant to labor for complete perfection of verse, "true quantity in every foot
    and syllable." Rhyme too earns his scorn: "our rude beggarly rhyming [was] brought first into
    Italy by Goths and Huns, when all good verses and all good learning too were de- stroyed by
    them. . . . to follow rather the Goths in rhyming, than the Greeks in true versifying, is even
    to eat acorns with swine, when we may freely eat wheat bread among men." Surrey and Periz are
    noticed as laudable poets who avoid rhyme and "observe just number and even feet" but their feet
    are unfortunately "feet without joints, that is to say not distinct by true quantities of
    syllables." Thus, the first important English commentator on verse-structure mis- understands
    the native accentual meter entirely, and so damns it for being too formless and easy, requiring
    neither labor nor learning. See also E40. As for the earliest English verse written in
    quantitative meters, there are some specimens in Ascham's Toxophilus (a popular treatise on
    archery) of 1545, and in Book I of The Scholemaster Ascham quotes verses by Thomas Watson
    (Bishop of Lincoln) from his unpublished translation of the Odyssey (ca. 1545). The interest in
    England in setting modern verse to classical meters seems to have been transmitted through
    Jacques de la Taille in France from Claudio Tolemei in Italy (1539). For further discussion of
    Ascham see: </notes>
  </item>

  <item id="E110">
   <bib>Strozier, Robert M. "Theory and Structure in Roger Ascham's The Scholemaster."
    Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 74 (1973): 144-62. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>



  <item id="E111">
   <bib>Ryan, Lawrence V. "The Scholemaster." In his Roger Ascham. Stanford: Stanford University
    Press, 1963. </bib>
   <notes> Especially pp. 272-76: a very sanguine perspective. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E112">
   <bib>Attridge, Derek. Well-Weighed Syllables: Elizabethan Verse in Classical Meters. London:
    Cambridge University Press, 1974; rpt 1979. 258 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Based on his dissertation, "The Elizabethan Experiments in English Quantitative Verse,"
    at Cambridge University in 1971. Rev.: in MP 76 (1978): 69-73; in English 24 (1975): 91-92.
    Attridge is now the standard reference on the subject of quantitative experi- ments in the
    Renaissance. The book contains three parts: parts 2 and 3 review the theorizing and the verses
    of poets, first synthetically (in 2), exam-ining the Renaissance attitudes toward both
    vernacular verse and classical imitators, the origin and extent of the vogue for quantitative
    verse, and the nature of the verse itself, then analytically by author (in 3), with separate
    examinations of each of the major theorists and poets. But more important is the more abstract-
    -but more crucial--analysis in part 1, not hitherto researched fully or directly, of the
    exceedingly complex question, "What is quantity?" This question resolves itself at once into
    three others, scarcely easier--"What is the modern under- standing of Latin verse?" "How did the
    Renaissance understand Latin verse?" and "How did the Romans understand Latin verse?" Everyone
    speaks glibly of longs and shorts, but as Attridge convincingly shows, the phonetic evidence is
    far too complex and ambiguous for the simplistic, text-book definition of quantity to be
    correct. It would seem, judging from Renais-sance primers for schoolboys, that the Renaissance
    approach, at least, was not to stress (in pro- nunciation of Latin verses) the ictuses (i.e. the
    "long" syllables" but rather the syllables which would be stressed according to normal English
    rules of accen- tuation. Such a "prosaic" stressing, rather than an ictic stressing, would
    effectu- ally polarize the normal accentual system from the more abstract and artificial
    "quantities," which were determined by a complex system of rules (not really very intelligible,
    even to them, but accepted on authority), among which was one which allowed determination of
    quantity by orthography (i.e. by varying the spelling of a word one could produce a desired
    quantity). Thus we can see how abstract and visual rather than aural was the whole Renaissance
    understanding of Latin verses, and also how sophisticated and antithetical it seemed in the face
    of vernacular poetry. It is this demonstration of the crucial role of phrase-stressing and
    orthography (taught to the Elizabethan schoolboy as he scanned his Latin verses) that Attridge
    is able to achieve an altogether remarkable synthesis of some very confusing evidence into that
    most difficult of all historicial results, a coherent, convincing, and "natural" account of what
    the problem looked like through the eyes of the men of the time. E113 Related: Percy Simpson,
    "The Elizabethan Pronunciation of Accented Greek Words." MLR 45 (1950): 509-10. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E114">
   <bib>Auden, W. H. Preface to Selected Songs of Thomas Campion. Boston: David Godine, 1973. pp.
    9-14. </bib>
   <notes>The poet setting verse to music must take vowel length into account, and surely Greek
    meters were originally derived from music. Scansions. Cf. E177. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E115">
   <bib>Aylward, Kevin J. "Milton's Latin Versification: The Hexameter." DA 27 (1966): 1331A
    (Columbia). </bib>
   <notes>How closely did Milton approximate the classical model? Aylward emphasizes the
    considerable inadequacies of the models-- contemporary grammars, school training, scholarship
    and informed opinion, and treatises on poetics--as partial justification for Milton's
    achievement, which he characterizes in various poems as "peculiar," "uncertain,"
    "indiscreet,""insensitive," "inept," and "arbitrary," the last of these being particularly apt.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E116">
   <bib>Baker, Sheridan. "English Meter Is Quantitative." College English 21 (1960): 309-15. </bib>
   <notes>A thesis Baker can uphold because he believes that stress "is the only cause of" quantity,
    or that quantity "more or less rides along with stress" nearly always. [This has yet to be
    proven.] "In Latin, syllables are long by intrinsic nature or position, and they stay in
    position. In English, stress alone makes quantity, and what one minute you think is stressed may
    not be the next time you look." [This is question-begging.]Baker identifies two types of short
    syllables in Eng- lish (time-values 1/4 and 1/2) and three types of longs (1, 3/4, and 1- 1/4).
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E117">
   <bib>Barnard, Mary. "A Communication on Greek Metric, Ezra Pound, and Sappho." Agenda 16, 3-4
    (1978-79): 62-68. </bib>
   <notes>Pound suggested a reference for study of Greek meters to this poet; she eventu- ally
    developed a short "balanced" line for translating the Sapphic fragments. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E118">
   <bib>Bayly, Anselm. An Introduction to Languages, Literary and Philosophical. London: John
    Rivington, 1758; rpt Ann Arbor: University Microfilms, 1953. See p. 173 ff. </bib>
   <notes>A comparative grammar. Bayly complains of the absence of fixed quantities for English
    words, then later remarks that "Accent is in English the same as Quan- tity, making that
    syllable long, on which it is laid, and the other syllable short." Accent (acute, grave, or
    circumflex) is taken as the rising or falling of the voice; "quantity then may be considered as
    the time, and accent, the tune [of lan- guage]." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E119">
   <bib>-----. "Poetry." The Alliance of Musick, Poetry, and Oratory. London: John Stockdale, 1789.
    pp. 79-122; rpt Ann Arbor: University Microfilms, 1953. </bib>
   <notes>The scope of Prosody encompasses Accent, Quantity, Feet, and Rhythm. Ac- cent, the
    elevation or depression of the voice, "answers to tones in musick." Musical notes are
    occasionally used in scansions, and though Bayly traces accent back to Greek versification,
    still he thinks that "certain syllables of a certain quantity constitute feet" in English verse.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E120">
   <bib>[Bayne, Thomas?] "English Hexameters and Elegaics." Macmillan's Magazine 86 (1901): 430-37. </bib>
   <notes> Cf. Thomas Bayne's note on "English Hexameters and </notes>
  </item>

  <item id="E121">
   <bib>Elegaics" in Notes and Queries, 9th series, vol. 7 (1901): 321-22. </bib>
   <notes>Correcting an ill-informed critic, the author mentions the hexameters of Coleridge,
    Clough, Longfellow, and Kingsley, discusses Harvey and Spenser at greater length, then notes the
    elegiac verses of Arthur Munby and Sir Lewis Morris, discussing Browning's "Ixion" at length.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E122">
   <bib>Benson, Carl. "Short Chapters on Novel and Exotic Metres." American Review: A Whig Journal
    4 (1846): 482-85; 5 (1847): 72-73, 174-75, 502-4. </bib>
   <notes>On the possibilities for English versions of the classical Hexameters, Pentame- ters,
    Iambic Trimeters (our Alexandrines), Sapphics, Alcaics, Hendecasyllabics, and irregular meters.
    Mentions the poverty of English spondees. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E123">
   <bib>[Benson, William.] Letters concerning Poetrical Translations, and Virgil's and Milton's
    Arts of Verse &amp;. London: J.Roberts, 1739; rpt New York: Garland, 1970. 83 pp. </bib>
   <notes>A rather detailed comparison of the versification of Virgil and Milton in eleven features
    of their verse; Benson scans by duration (Letter 8). Milton is taken up in letter 5. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E124">
   <bib>Blackie, J. S. "Homer and His Translators." Macmillan's Magazine 4 (1861): 268-80. </bib>
   <notes>Professor Blackie takes a more philosophical view of the question than most of the
    reviewers did; he also gives a lengthy defense of rhyme, concluding there- from that the
    ballad-meters (long- line couplets of Common Measure, that is) would be best. Penultimate
    paragraphs takes up (and promptly flings down) the hexameter. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E125">
   <bib>-----. "Remarks on English Hexameters." In his Horae Hellenicae. London: Macmillan, 1874.
    pp. 278-96. </bib>
   <notes>"The beau ideal of a translation as a work of art unquestionably is, that it shall be . .
    . a FACIMILE, as far as may be. . . . a translator is bound to transfer every measure of his
    original into that measure of his own language, which in its style, character, associations, and
    effects, corresponds to his model." The prin- ciple to be followed, then, is not literal
    reproduction but correspondence of effect, whatever the means. Blackie favors the old
    fourteeners of Chapman and the fifteen- syllabled trochaic lines of Locksley Hall to any other
    measure in English--quantitative or accentual hexameter, couplet, or blank verse--for ren-
    dering Homer. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E126">
   <bib>[Blundell, James, tr.] Hexametrical Experiments, or A Version of four of Virgils Pastorals
    . . . done in a structure of verse similar to that of the original Latin, with hints to explain
    the method of reading and a slight essay on the laws of the metre. London: William Pickering,
    1838. </bib>
   <notes>The two "slight" introductory essays on the hexameter (pp. 1-25) take up a fourth of the
    book. Though the "longs" and "shorts" of Blundell's metric thwart accent only rarely, he bases
    his system of quantitative hexameters on time: "in relation to the time which their utterance
    requires, the syllables of our language may be divided into four kinds, the long, the short, the
    double short, and the common." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E127">
   <bib>Bridges, Robert. "Epistle to a Socialist in London." The Monthly Review 12 (1903): 150-64. </bib>
   <notes>Hexameter verse, with a "Summary of Stone's Prosody," pp. 165-67. Said to be the second of
    two Epistles, the first being Now in Wintry Delights. See also "A Peace Ode" (alcaics?) in the
    same periodical, 11 (June 1903): 141-43. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E128">
   <bib>-----. The Feast of Bacchus. Oxford: Privately printed by H. Daniel, 1889. </bib>
   <notes>Brief note at the end, dated 1885. The meter of his version of Terence, Bridges says, is a
    six-stress line, with certain additional provisions for "distribution" of stress among several
    short syllables, and any other similarity to the iambic tri- meter of Latin comedy is
    accidental. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E129">
   <bib>-----. Ibant Obscuri: An Experiment in the Classical Hexamater. Oxford: Clarendon Press,
    1916. </bib>
   <notes>The Introduction, "Virgil's Rhythms," pp. 1-18, originally appeared in the New Quarterly
    for January 1909. "A Note on Stone's Prosody," at the end, pp. 154- 58, reprints Bridges' 1903
    "Summary of Stone's Prosody" (E130) with new 1916 "Observations" in parallel columns. Throughout
    the Introduction Bridges reiterates that a poet can achieve great effects only in those forms
    that are coge- nial to the language, so that any attempts to reproduce a form successful in an-
    other language but graceless in one's own, simply for the sake ofcopying, is ut- ter folly.
    Bridges' own "undertaking was not to copy the Latin imitation of the Greek but to make an
    analogous attempt in [his] own language." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E130">
   <bib>-----. Now in Wintry Delights. Oxford: Daniel Press, 1903. </bib>
   <notes>See the six-page note at the end, where Bridges confirms that this verse is written in a
    classical-imitative meter based on the system of Stone. (E251), which Bridges sketches briefly
    for readers unfamiliar with it, adding remarks and observations. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E131">
   <bib>[Brightland, John?] "The Art of Poetry." A Grammar of the English Tongue, With Notes,
    Giving the Grounds and Reason of Grammar in General </bib>
   <notes>, To which are now added, The Arts of Poetry, Rhetoric, Logic, &amp;c. . . . London, 1711;
    2nd rev. ed. 1712. pp. 131- 68. The Prosodia affixed to the grammar mainly treats the principal
    genres of po- etry, but chapter 1 gives a quantitative account of meter. I have seen only the
    second edition, but Culler reported that the first edition titled its section on verse "New
    Prosodia; or the Art of English Numbers." Three degrees of quan- tity are stipulated (long,
    short, and variable) as well as three of accent; "Accent is the raising and falling of the
    Voice, above or under its usual Tone, but an Art of which we have little Use, and know less, in
    the English Tongue." Bysshe is criticized in a note for the "erroneous use of Accent for
    Quantity." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E132">
   <bib>Calverley, C. S. "On Metrical Translation" </bib>
   <notes> and the two following essays in Literary Remains of Charles Stuart Calverley. London:
    George Bell, 1885. pp. 172-85. (The first originally appeared in the London Student for October
    1868.) Calverley intends to correct a modern misconception by insisting that the an- cients read
    (pronounced) their verse one way but scanned it another, i.e. "by an accent which was so far
    arbitrary that it was wholly independent of the scan- sion, and was intended partially to
    conceal the scansion," in contrast to modern imitations of classical meters. In these latter he
    finds their monotony and ca- cophony most offensive. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E133">
   <bib>Campbell, T. M. "Longfellow and the Hexameter." MLN 23 (1908): 96. </bib>
   <notes>Addendum by Charles Eliot Norton, p. 231. Longfellow's early dislike of the accentual
    hexameter (1841) was apparently re- versed by an approving review in a German periodical,
    resulting in his use of the meter in 1845. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E134">
   <bib>Campion, Thomas. Observations in the Art of English Poesie. London: Richard Field for
    Andrew Wise, 1602; rpt in the Works of Thomas Campion. Ed. Walter R. Davis. London: Faber &amp;
    Faber, 1969; in Smith (A26), vol. 2, pp. 327-55; in facsimile: Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar Press,
    1969. </bib>
   <notes>Written perhaps as early as 1591, by its publication date Campion's treatise had become
    simply an index of what concessions the faltering theory of classical- imitative verse in
    English was driven to in order to have any credence at all. In the First Book of Ayres in 1601
    Campion had declined the use of quantitative meters in favor of "ear-pleasing rimes," and when
    he came to a full-scale de- fense of the classical forms the following year, his position was
    mixed at best: he bases quantity directly on accent ("above all the accent of our words is
    dilli- gently to be observed, for chiefly by the accent in any language the true value of the
    syllables is to be measured"), though "accent," being described as rising, falling, grave, or
    flat, seems to be not only stress but pitch. Yet at the same time he allows length by position,
    which does in fact wrench accent. Fortunately, though, he scans by ear (phonetically) rather
    than by eye, allowing no clumsy machinery of orthography. The bulk of the Observations presents
    the eight measures (iambic, dimeter, trochaic, elegaic, three types of lyric, and ana- creonic)
    which English could improve itself by adoption. But the most interest- ing matter is that
    Campion's close training in music leads him to treat verse- structure (quantity) in terms of
    Time. Anyone who can "time a song" can see that Latin and English pentameters "are in nature all
    of the same length of sound . . . for either of them being timed with the hand, quinque
    perficiunt tem- pora, they fill up the quantity (as it were) of five semibreves." Metrical rests
    are allowed in verse as in music, and the failing of pyrrhic substitutions in iambic lines lies
    in their "curtailing their verse." Number in poetry, too, refers not only to the number of
    syllables but also to "the length or shortness of their sound" as is the case when verse is set
    to music. Omond (A5) misses this crucial matter entirely, as well as one other: in his chapter 4
    Campion reveals what is demon- strably a clear understanding of trochaic and trisyllabic
    substitutions. But none of these keen perceptions did any good: the whole quantitative
    controversy had been moribund for a decade when the Observations was published, and Daniel's
    reply (E521) was irrefragable. And Campion's defense, by revealing the severe weaknesses of his
    position, served only to advance the case of the Accentualists. See N75. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E135">
   <bib>Carne-Ross, D. S. "New Metres for Old: A Note on Pound's Metric." Arion 6 (1967): 216-32. </bib>
   <notes>Lucid technical analysis of The Cantos and some Greek verse to show that Pound's metric is
    based on a "rhythmic constant"(recurring phrases equal in syllable count) and, indeed, quantity
    (taking quantity in English verse as pitch is in Greek, i.e. variable not central). The
    impressively marshalled evidence in- cludes a little book which Pound read, Duhamel and
    Vildrac's 1912 Notes sur la technique poétique. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E136">
   <bib>Carpenter, Edward. "On English Hexameter Verse." Cambridge Review, 22 February and 1 March
    1900, pp. 219-21, 235-36. </bib>
   <notes>Very skeptical of the practicability or range of the quantitative hexameter in our
    stress-marked language. Discusses Clough (E140), Arnold (E108), and Stone (E251). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E137">
   <bib>Cayley, C[harles] B[agot]. The "Prometheus Bound" of Aeschylus, translated in the original
    metres. London: John Camden Hotten, 1867. </bib>
   <notes>Seven page Preface: "I have endeavoured to realize the metres of my original by the
    strictest consideration of the quantities of the words I have employed," and further, "I have
    taken pains to combine the accents of my lines in modes partially regular and familiar to the
    English ear." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E138">
   <bib>-----. "Remarks and Experiments on English Hexameters." Transactions of the Philological
    Society, 1862-63. pp. 67- 85. Later published separately at Berlin, 1863. 21 pp. </bib>
   <notes>A series of divagations ending in an outright evasion, but one gathers that, for Cayley,
    paying attention to the accentual structure of classical verse is of even greater importance
    than attending to the quantities of English syllables. But he denies that accent lengthens
    syllables in English and that "accent in the modern languages is the same thing as quantity in
    the ancient"; indeed, an accentual hexameter is "diametrically opposed to classical usage and
    principle." Yet mod- ern translators of classical verse can never succeed until "they can become
    in posse, if not in esse, exact imitators of both the accentual and quantitative com- binations
    of the ancients." Time and pauses in English verse also mentioned (first page). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E139">
   <bib>Chasles, Philarète, et al. Letters to The Athenaum, April-June 1849, pp. 411, 487, 517,
    597-98, 644-45. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E140">
   <bib>Clough, Arthur Hugh. The Bothie of Toper-na-Fuosich. London, 1848; </bib>
   <notes> rpt as The Bothie of Tober-na-Vuolich in The Poems and Prose Remains. Ed. Blanche Clough.
    2 vols. London: Macmillan, 1869. Vol. 2, pp. 201-87. Also rpt in the Oxford Standard Authors
    edition of A. L. P. Norrington (Oxford University Press, 1951, 1967) with a valuable
    Introduction (section IV of which discusses the quantitative verse). Accentual hexameters
    written in imitation of the classical quantitative meter. Also in accentual hexameters are
    Amours de Voyage and the six "Essays in Classi- cal Metres" (two passages from the Iliad, two
    Elegiacs, on Alcaic, and "Ac- taeon"). Add to these an essay, "Illustrations of Latin Lyrical
    Meters," and the "Letters of Parepidemius, Number Two: On Translating Homer" which may be
    located conveniently in the Selected Prose Works edited by Buckner B. Trawick (University of
    Alabama Press, 1964, pp. 66-84,180-86). The latter es- say first appeared in the 1888 edition of
    the Prose Remains. Clough's view is that both accent and quantity are important to both
    classical and modern verse; in classical verse, however, the metrical accent was based on pitch,
    and independent of the ordinary accentuations based on stress-- i.e., "The accent of speech was
    lost in the accent of song." Thus, "with the an- cients the accent of words in metre was . . .
    independent of their colloquial ac- cent: while with us the two are kept simply identical. The
    accent of words with us is fixed, with them was in metre arbitrary. So on the other hand, with
    them, the quantity was fixed and carefully observed;with us it is variable, and greatly
    neglected. Still there can be no question but that discrimination of quantity enters largely
    into the modern art of versifying." To modernize a clas- sical meter, then, two rules are
    necessary: "the Metrical Accent must remain the same" and "Quantity should be preserved." Clough
    cleaves strictly to the first but not the second. In short, he uses the modern English
    stress-accent as ana- logue of the classical Greek pitch-accent to mark the metrical ictus. The
    British reader has no patience, he observes (second letter of Parepidemius), for so so-
    phisticated a treatment as one which might counterpoint or oppose the stress and the ictus.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E141">
   <bib>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor. "Hexameters," "Translation of a Passage in Ottfried," "Catullian
    Hendecasyllables," "Homeric Hexameters," "The Ovidian Elegaic Metre," "Hexameters (Paraphrase of
    Psalm XLVI)," "Hymn to the Earth," "Mahomet," and "Ad Vilnum Axiologum." In Poetical Works. Ed.
    Ernest Hartley Coleridge. London: Oxford University Press, 1912, 1967. pp. 304-8, 326-30,
    391-92. </bib>
   <notes>Accentual hexameters, mainly, written about 1799 in most cases. The Elegaic Metre" couplet
    is the only that has become well-known, but the note to "Hymn to the Earth" proffers some
    instruction for "intelligent female readers of poetry": "in the attempt to adapt the Greek
    metres to the English language, we must begin by substituting quality of sound for
    quantity--that is, accentuated or comparatively emphasized syllables, for what in the Greek and
    Latin verse, are named long. . . ." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E142">
   <bib>Crowe, William. A Treatise on English Versification. London: John Murray, 1827. 334 pp. </bib>
   <notes>The book had been earlier serialized under the title "On English Versification" in the
    London Magazine 7 (1823): 29-37, 173- 80, 273-82, 429-36, 661-68; 10 (1824): 29-35. Public
    Orator of long standing at Oxford, Crowe's theoretical position dates from the 1760's: he
    accepts quantity as the basis of verse almost as if it were axiomatic. More curious still, "the
    simplest elements of verse are letters-- of letters are formed syllables--of syllables feet--of
    feet a verse." Yet having been faithful to the letter, he turns to the spirit--sounds. The
    Introduction gives an interesting historical review of the prosodists--Webbe, Gascoigne, Putten-
    ham, Campion, Daniel, Cowley, Woodford, Poole, Bysshe, Pemberton, Fos- ter, Mitford, and several
    other lesser mortals. Of the several "experiments" in metric undertaken in English poetry
    (alliterative, classical-imitative, and four- teener, e.g.), only that of "ten syllables, free
    from rhyme" has succeeded. From this we can see that Crowe takes decasyllabism as an absolute.
    In its time, his book was the voice of things past. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E143">
   <bib>Cuddy, Lois S. "The Influence of Latin Poetics on Emily Dickenson's Style." Comparative
    Literature Studies 13 (1976): 214-29. </bib>
   <notes>Proposes a new explanation for Dickinson's verseform: the meter is meant to be
    quantitative. What E. D. learned in the Stoddard and Andrews Latin grammar text she read at the
    Amherst Academy she later tried to replicate in her own work, using dashes to denote caesurae
    and foot boundaries and using capitali- zation and italics to insure that certain words within
    the lines would receive unusual stress and hence lengthening of syllables. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E144">
   <bib>Cummings, Prentiss. Hexameter Verse and its requirements in order that it may "read
    itself." Cambridge, Mass.: Riverside Press, 1900. 68 pp. </bib>
   <notes>The requirements for meeting Arnold's dictum about the smoothness of English hexameters
    are that "accent should not be sacrificed for the sake of quantity" and that "every ictus
    syllable should be an accented syllable." Cummings distin- guishes ictus, accent, and emphasis,
    and constructs a schema of nine line-types, based on the number and position of "emphasized
    feet"; "emphasis may be ef- fected by stress or by lengthening the vowel." But after the
    Introduction of the English forms, the book turns exclusively to Greek and Latin examples.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E145">
   <bib>Davis, Walter R. "A Note on Accent and Quantity in A Booke of Ayres." MLQ 22 (1961): 32-36. </bib>
   <notes>Campion repeats vowel sounds to insure identical quantity and thereby en- riches the
    traditional accentual meters with superimposed quantitative effects in "Come let us
    sound,""Turne backe you wanton flyer," and "Harke al you la- dies." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E146">
   <bib>Duckworth, George E. "Milton's Hexameter Patterns--Vergillian or Ovidian?" American Journal
    of Philology 93 (1972): 52-60. </bib>
   <notes>In the hexameter poem, Milton's metrical style is mixed, resembling the Ver- gilian
    Eclogues rather more than the Aeneid or Ovid; in the elegies, he resembles Ovid more closely
    than the classical Roman poets did themselves. Extensive statistical analysis. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E147">
   <bib>Dunn, Catherine M. "A Survey of the Experiments in Quantitative Verse in the English
    Renaissance." DA 28 (1967): 193A (U.C.L.A.) </bib>
   <notes>A broad study of the movement through its vicissitudes in England, touching also on its
    Italian origin and French transmission. Poets examined: Ascham, Spenser, Harvey, Sidney, Abraham
    Fraunce, John Dickinson, "Anomos," Richard Barnfield, Stanyhurst, Webbe, Abraham Fleming, Robert
    Greene, Francis Sabie, and author of Henry VII, Campion, and Daniel. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E148">
   <bib>Ellis, Robinson. The Poem and Fragments of Catallus Translated in the Metres of the
    Original. London: John Murray, 1871. </bib>
   <notes>The fourteen page Preface praises Tennyson's work and sets forth explicitly the "rules"
    for quantitative verse on "the true positional principle": (1) "accented syllables, as a general
    rule, are long, though some syllables which count as long need not be accented"; (2) the laws of
    position are to be observed according to the general rules of classical prosody. Problems of
    application are discussed di- rectly. General principle: "Quantity," in English revivals of
    ancient metre, de- pends not only on position, but on accent." (The ambiguity is evident; see
    Munro (E203).) </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E149">
   <bib>Elze, Karl. Der englische Hexameter. Einladung zu den öffentlichen Prüfungen im
    Herzoglichen Gymnasium zu Dessau . . . 8-9 April 1867. Dessau: H. Neubürger, 1867. </bib>
   <notes>Formerly the best available source on English quantitative verse, Elze has not been
    entirely superseded by Attridge (E112); his treatment of second- and third-rate writers is more
    detailed, and he covers both the Renaissance and the nineteenth century and also the classical
    imitations in general and the transla- tions of Homer in particular. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E150">
   <bib>English Hexameters Translations, from Schiller, Göthe, Homer, Callinus, and Meleager.
    London: John Murray, 1847. </bib>
   <notes>Contributions by Hare, Hawtrey, Herschel, Lockhart, and Whewell; "all the pieces are
    executed with the intention that the lines, being read according to the natural and ordinary
    pronunciation, shall run into accentual hexameters or pentameters." Fifty pieces in a small
    oblong volume, bound in beautiful Ori- ental boards. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E151">
   <bib>"The English Translators of Homer." National Review (London) 11 (1860): 283-314. </bib>
   <notes>An historical survey of the various English translators, arising from a review of Newman's
    and Wright's efforts; the reviewer approves ballad-meter as most ap- propriate. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E152">
   <bib>Ernle, George. The Wrath of Achilleus, translated from the Iliad into quantitative
    hexameters. London: Oxford University Press, 1922. 135 pp. </bib>
   <notes>Preface, pp. 1-17. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E153">
   <bib>Evans, Robert O. "Spenser's Role in the Controversy over Quantitative Verse."
    Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 57 (1956): 246-56. </bib>
   <notes>Evans believes that (1) the whole controversy has been "exaggerated," that (2) Spenser's
    skill at writing q. verse has been underrated, that (3) the Harvey cor- respondence should not
    be taken seriously, and that (4) though "there is no reason to assume that quantitative verse
    cannot be written with some success in English," the whole phenomenon is simply a sophisticated
    literary game. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E154">
   <bib>Fairclough, H. R. "The Influence of Virgil upon the Forms of English Verse." Classical
    Journal 26 (1930): 74-94. </bib>
   <notes>Taking Bridges' Ibant Obscuri for a point of departure, Fairclough surveys the English
    attempts at hexameters from Stanyhurst through Tennyson, especially the flurry in the nineteenth
    century, finding that none "has ever been really successful." The review then turns to the
    metiers of couplet and blank verse-- the couplet in Douglas, Dryden and Pope, blank verse in
    Chaucer, Shake- speare, Dryden, many lesser poets, and most importantly, Milton. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E155">
   <bib>Fenyo, Jane K. "Grammar and Music in Thomas Campion's Observations in the Art of English
    Poesie." Studies in the Renaissance 17 (1970): 46-72. </bib>
   <notes>Commentators on Campion have always been unable to reconcile his evident skill and
    subtlety at versecraft with the seeming obtuseness of many statements in the Observations. But
    in fact, Campion's prosodic treatise simply follows the order of Lyly's grammar (the standard
    Renaissance authority) rather closely. Fenyo gives a section-by-section comparison, then argues
    that Campion in ef- fect saw, heard, and spoke English verses quantitatively. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E156">
   <bib>The First Booke of the Preservation of King Henry the VII. London: 1599. </bib>
   <notes>Written in quantitative hexameters and containing a noteworthy short preface. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E157">
   <bib>Fraunce, Abraham. The Lamentations of Amyntas for the death of Phillis, paraphrastically
    translated out of Latine into English Hexameters. London: 1587, 1588, 1589, 1596. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E158">
   <bib>-----. The Countesse of Pembroke's Yvychurch. London: 1591. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E159">
   <bib>-----. The Countess of Pembroke's Emanuell. London: 1591. </bib>
   <notes> Also ed. by Grosart for the Miscellanies of the fuller Worthies' Library, 1871. Next to
    Stanyhurst's Aeneis the most substantial body of quantitative hexame- ters written in the
    Renaissance. The title of the first section of Emanuell de- clares the verse to be in "ryming
    hexameters." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E160">
   <bib>Fuller, Roy. "Boos of Different Durations." Southern Review 11 (1975): 825-37. </bib>
   <notes>Leisurely speculations, acute and intelligent observations, and errant reasoning on
    duration of syllables (Quantity) in poetry. From a reading of Sonnenschein and Scripture's work
    on acoustic metrics, Fuller derives "the 'myth' of stress" as the basis for English verse.
    Duration is the thing. Noteworthy digression: "diffi- culties or irregularities of scansion may
    be minimized or explained if the ques- tionable passage is read for sense." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E161">
   <bib>Fulton, Edward. "Sidney, Spenser, and the Areopagus." MLN 31 (1916): 372-74. </bib>
   <notes>Though there is no evidence definitely establishing the existence of the Are- opagus as a
    club, it is indisputable that Spenser and Sidney were intimate friends and that Spenser was
    seriously concerned to obtain agreement among the poets practicing quantitative verse on the
    rules they were to follow. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E162">
   <bib>Garnett, Richard. "On Translating Homer." Universal Review, 1889; rpt in his Essays of an
    Ex-Librarian. New York: Dodd, Mead, 1901. pp. 3-27. </bib>
   <notes>Approves of the couplet as the superior meter to blank verse, the ballad Alex- andrine,
    and the English hexameter for purposes of translation. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E163">
   <bib>"German Epics and English Hexameters." Dublin University Magazine 44 (1854): 55- 72. </bib>
   <notes>Reviews translations by James Cochrane of German poems by Voss and others into English
    accentual hexameters; the reviewer complains that though accent is principle in English,
    quantity should be attended to also. Technical notes on meter in translation, pp. 63-64, 66-68.
    Omond was disappointed by this. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E164">
   <bib>Gildon, Charles. The Complete Art of Poetry. 2 vols. London: Charles Rivington, 1718. Vol.
    1, pp. 293-303. </bib>
   <notes>Gildon, arch-enemy of Bysshe (E505), represents the reactionary forces in
    eighteenth-century English metrics still attempting to apply the Classical system to English
    verse. In this fictitious dialogue, Laudon defends the quantities of classical Greek as being
    the basis of English versification, accent being a matter pertaining only to performance, not to
    meter. The classical "feet," in fact, are represented by notes on a musical staff, since the
    "quantities" were thought to be derived originally from actual time-values. Dryden's
    "Alexander's Feast" is so scanned as example. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E165">
   <bib>-----. The Laws of Poetry As laid down by the Duke of Buckinghamshire in his Essay on
    Poetry, By the Earl of Roscommon in his Essay on Translated Verse, and by the Lord Lansdowne on
    Unnatural Flights in Poetry, Explain'd and Illustrated. London: 1721. See pp. 62-72, 315-16. </bib>
   <notes>Gildon defends blank verse against "rhyme" and discusses the nature of "accent" in
    classical verse as well as modern. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E166">
   <bib>[Goldsmith, Oliver?] "Versification." The British Magazine, 1763 </bib>
   <notes>; rpt as no 18. in The Complete Works of Oliver Goldsmith. London: Charles Griffen, 1862.
    See also essays 14 ("Origin of Poetry") and 15 (Poetry Distinguished from Other Writing"). The
    attribution has recently been questioned (see PMLA 39 (1924): 310 ff). The author of the essay,
    rather ill-informed, seems to have been reading the Renaissance theorists. He claims that number
    in modern verse pertains only to syllables rather than to feet as in the classical, and that
    quantitative verse could be written in English if only a little effort were bestowed, since "it
    is impossible that the same measure, composed of the same times, should have a good effect upon
    the ear in one language, and a bad effect in another." This is thoughtless. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E167">
   <bib>Goodell, Thomas D. "Quantity in English Verse." Transactions of the American Philological
    Association 16 (1885-87): 78-103. </bib>
   <notes>Though recognizing the differing prosodic bases of classical and modern verse, Goodell
    agrees with Lanier that time-values are the basis of English verse, which is therefore somewhat
    like Greek. The similarities between the two prosodies are thereafter emphasized throughout,
    musical notation is correlated to the classical scansion marks, and two modes are indentified:
    "feet of three times and feet of four times." Rules are given on pp. 100-2. The essay explicitly
    conjoins the Tempo- ralist scansion with the classical Greek system. Notice M77. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E168">
   <bib>Hampton, Barnabas. Prosodia Construed, and the meaning of the most difficult words therein
    contained plainly illustrated;Being an addition to the construction of Lilie's Rules, and of
    like necessary use. London, 1639; rpt 1704. 29 pp. </bib>
   <notes>A pocket-sized standard handbook of the time giving metrical rules based on quantity. The
    text is in Latin and English, alternating after every term or phrase. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E169">
   <bib>Hanssen, Selby. "An Analysis of Sir Philip Sidney's Metrical Experiments in 'The Arcadia.'"
    Diss., Yale University, 1942. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E170">
   <bib>Hardy, Douglas. "Influence of Finnish Kalevala in the Composition of the Longfellow's 'Song
    of Hiawatha.'" Brigham Young University Studies 4 (1962): 140-47. </bib>
   <notes>Accentual hexameters. Cf. Moyne and Mustanoja (E205), Larrabee (E193), Kunze (E189), and
    Holman (E180). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E171">
   <bib>Harrison, Frederic. "The Old Books in War-Time." English Review 19 (1915): 389- 404; 20
    (1916): 13-24. </bib>
   <notes>The only possible verseform for translating the classics (Homer, Virgil) into English is
    blank verse. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E172">
   <bib>Harvey, Gabriel, and Edmund Spenser. Three Proper and wittie familiar Letters: lately
    passed betweene two Vniuersitie men: touching the Earthquake in Aprill last, and our English
    refourmed versifying. London: H. Bynneman, 1580. </bib>
   <notes> And later in the same year, by the same printer: </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E173">
   <bib>Harvey, Gabriel, and Edmund Spenser. Two other very commendable Letters of the same mens
    writing: both touching the foresaid Artificiall Versifying, and certain other Particulars More
    lately deliuered unto the Printer. </bib>
   <notes>The second letter of the Three concerns the earthquake and may be ignored; the other four
    are reprinted in Smith (A26), vol. 1, pp. 87-122, and see also pp. 123-24 (note that Smith
    prints the later two letters first, followed by the earlier two, deleting the one on the
    earthquake). Harvey's other Foure Letters and his Letter-Book are available in A. B.Grosart's
    edition of the Works of Harvey (Lon- don, 1884-85), and there is also an extract from the Foure
    Letters in Smith, vol. 2, pp. 229- 38. On the Letter-Book as a first draft of a literary hoax,
    see </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E174">
   <bib>J. W. Bennett, "Spenser and Harvey's Letter-Book." MP 29 (1931): 163-86. </bib>
   <notes>The double exchange between "Immerito" (Spenser) and Harvey is perhaps the central
    surviving text of the whole quantitative movement, since it is our source for the differing
    opinions of Drant, Spenser, and especially Harvey, who seems to have been the prime mover behind
    it all. Spencer was himself mainly unmoved. It used to be thought that these three writers
    formed a literary coterie, the Areopagus (see p. 89 in Smith and accompanying Notes), but the
    evidence is tenuous and the opinion is not much promoted anymore. I follow Smith's ordering of
    the letters below. In the first letter, Spenser acknowledges that Sidney and Dyer have
    "prescribed certaine Laws and rules of Quantities of English sillables for English verse" and
    "drawen mee to their faction"; indeed, "I am, of late, more in loue wyth my Englishe Versifying
    than with Ryming." He chides Harvey for "a breache in Maister Drant's Rules" and provides a
    sample of quantitative lines, the "Iambicum Trimetrum," which Harvey then chides in return, in
    the second letter, with wit and energy turning serious, as not being precisely perfect (though
    he admits knowing nothing of Drant's rules). Spenser in the short third letter asks for a copy
    of Harvey's rules and offers to send Drant's as annotated by both Sidney and himself; he also
    opines that the English Hexameter "will easily and fairly yeelde it selfe to oure Mother tongue.
    For the onely or chiefest hard- nesse, whych seemeth, is in the Accente; whych sometime gapeth,
    and as it were yawneth illfauouredly, comming shorte of that it should, and sometime exceeding
    the measure of the Number, as in Carpenter the middle sillable, be- ing vsed shorte in speache,
    when it shall be read long in Verse, seemeth like a lame Gosling that draweth one legge after
    hir. . . ." His following question is significant for implying a sharp distinction between
    (accentual) reading and (quantitative) scansion of the orthographic line: "for why, a Gods name,
    may not we, as else the Greekes, haue the kingdome of oure owne Language, and measure our
    Accentes by the sounde, reseruing the Quantitie to the Verse?" It is in the fourth letter then
    that Harvey comes to give examples of his own practice and to quarrel about theory. His view in
    a nutshell: "the Latine is no rule for us. . . .Position neither maketh shorte nor long in oure
    Tongue."English orthograpyy is far too fickle to serve as the basis of a visual versification:
    only pronunciation will serve: "it is not either Position, or Diph- thong, or Diastole, or anye
    like Grammer Schoole Deuice that doeth or can indeede either makelong or short, or encrease, or
    diminish the number of Silla- bles, but onely the common allowed or receiued PROSODYE. . . . you
    shall neuer haue my subscription or consent (though you should charge me wyth the authoritie of
    fiue hundreth Maister DRANTS) to make your Carpenter, our Carpenter, an inch longer or bigger
    than God and his Englishe people haue made him." All this may amount to no more than saying that
    the quantity of an English syllable does not entail an accent, or vice versa; if so, Drant and
    Sidney thought precisely the same. Harvey does not dispel Spenser's confusion on this point. And
    his purpose throughout is to secure the right basis for determining quantity, not to substitute
    accent for it. Webbe observed that Harvey's whole approach was not entirely serious, and clearly
    the statements near the end of the fourth letter are more rhetoric than anything else: they
    certainly are not a clear or careful synopsis of his views. In practice, Harvey scans by
    quantities, and he even admits length by position except for doubled consonants, which he rec-
    ognizes are not sounded so. His verses are more or less passable by accent, but Hendrickson
    attributes this to the arbitrary monosyllabic structure of the lan- guage not to any conscious
    choice. See also E224, E227, and E268. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E175">
   <bib>Hendrickson, G. L. "Elizabethan Quantitative Hexameters." PQ 28 (1949): 237-60. </bib>
   <notes>The criticism of Elizabethan classical-imitative verse commonly raised by prosodists--that
    its pronunciation is aberrant beyond redemption--is a simple catagory mistake: the quantivists
    never intended to write accentual-analogue hexameters, where the natural word-stresses
    correspond to the quantities and the ictuses. When they read their (English quantitative)
    verses, they read fol- lowing the accents, even as Latin verses themselves were read during the
    Ren- aissance. When they scanned their verses, however, they scanned the metrical quantities
    without regard to accent. This is not a case of "double audition" but rather of two separate
    activities altogether. It is true that the quantities and the accents do correspond perfectly in
    some lines, but this is due not to design but to the structure of the language itself; all such
    lines will be found to be entirely monosyllabic. Critics have also misunderstood Harvey. His
    theoretical statements are confused, and he does recognize the impossibility of length by
    doubled conso- nants in English, but his verses show that like the others he accepted length by
    position. Like them too he scans by quantity but pronounces by accent. Stany- hurst even went a
    little further toward Latin polysyllabicity in his verses, but he too conforms. See E240.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E176">
   <bib>"Hexameters in English." TLS, 8 March 1917, p. 114. Correspondence follows on 22 March-31
    May 1917, pp. 141, 153, 165, 177, 189- 90, 261-62. </bib>
   <notes>The initial article reviewing Ibant Obscuri is sympathetic and appreciative, tak- ing the
    trouble to explain very carefully both the general phonetic aspects of English hexameters
    (accent must be entirely disregarded) and also Bridges' modifications of his Latin prosodic
    models. The correspondents are of mixed opinions, several of them thinking "the metre is really
    hopeless in English," but the last two adduce modern parallels in Indian and Arabic, where the
    quantita- tive meter is successfully preserved apart from any accentual articulation. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E177">
   <bib>Hollander, John. Introduction to Selected Songs of Thomas Campion. Boston: David R. Godine,
    1973. pp. 15-27; revised and expanded into chapter 4 of his Vision and Resonance (A13), pp.
    71-90. Cf. E114. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E178">
   <bib>-----. "Observations in the Art of English Quantity." In his Vision and Resonance (A13),
    pp. 59-70. </bib>
   <notes>A lucid short account of the nature of quantitative verse in classical Greek and Latin and
    "the two different ways that 'quantity' could be used, both metaphori- cally, in English verse,"
    i.e. in a stress-analogue meter (the stress pattern identi- cal to what the quantitative pattern
    would have been in Latin, the quantities being ignored in the English) and in the Renaissance
    experiments, a kind of "written code" meter (where the quantities of the English syllables are
    deter- mined by applying the Latin rules to the English orthography, the sounds and stressing of
    the line being ignored altogether). Hollander thinks Tennyson's re- mark about "scissors" a joke
    and some of his verses a "burlesque" revealing his "contempt" for the whole business. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E179">
   <bib>Holowell, B. M. "The Elizabethan Hexametrists." PQ 3 (1924): 51- 57. </bib>
   <notes>We do tend to forget how very easy it is to demonstrate (as H.does here) the
    contemporanious legitimacy, respectablity, and rationality of the Elizabethan quantitative
    experiments. The paltry vernacular poetry looked trivial in com- parison with the great
    monuments of the classics, and since the metrical schemes of the two verse-systems were so
    obviously different, perhaps that was the problem! The schoolmen took the Latin system,
    "transplanted it bodily to English verse and proceeded to cultivate it." How else find out?
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E180">
   <bib>Holman, C. Hugh. "The 'Hiawatha' Meter in The Yenassee.” MLN 67 (1952): 418- 19. </bib>
   <notes>The lyrics in Simms's novel are in Longfellow's hexameters. Cf. Larrabee (E193), Hardy
    (E170), Moyne and Mustanoja (E205), and Kunze (E189). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E181">
   <bib>"Homeric Translators and Critics." Saturday Review 12 (1861): 95-96. </bib>
   <notes>A review of the dispute between Arnold and Francis Newman, partial to the latter. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E182">
   <bib>Humphries, Rolfe. "Latin and English Verse--Some Practical Considerations." On Translation.
    Ed. Reuben Brower. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1959. pp. 57-66. </bib>
   <notes>"The difficulty of converting quantitative to accentual meters. . . . is greatly ex-
    aggerated." The Latin shows accentual effects, and quantitative effects cannot be avoided in
    English (examples). The real problems in translation are the great variety of feet in classical
    meters, the dissimilarity of conventional line-lengths, the immense resources of word-order
    denied to English, and the preservation of some modicum of the sound-structure of Latin.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E183">
   <bib>Inge, W. R. "Classical Metres in English Poetry." Essays by Divers Hands (Transactions of
    the Royal Society of Literature) n.s. 2 (1922): 131-51. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E184">
   <bib>An Introduction of the ancient Greek and Latin measures into British poetry. London: T.
    Cooper, 1737. </bib>
   <notes>The Preface, pp. xiii-xvii, gives rules for quantitative verse. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E185">
   <bib>Jury, Charles R. Well-Measur'd Song: Quantitative and Quasi-quantitative Verse in English.
    Ed. Barbara Wall and D. C.Muecke. Melbourne: F. W. Cheshire, 1968. 67 pp. </bib>
   <notes>The posthumous treatise of an Australian poet on the possibilities for metering syllabic
    duration in English poetry. Jury observes, sensibly, that stress is the dominant characteristic
    of our language, but that quantity exists as well, and that major English poets (e.g. Pope in
    the Essay on Criticism) have sometimes employed syllable-length very successfully in English
    verse. The poet who wishes to imitate classical verse in English may do so in one of five ways:
    (1) substitution of stress in the (quantitative) metrical patterns, ignoring quantity altogether
    (Clough, Longfellow); (2) occasional foregrounding of quantity in accentual verse for sharp
    effects (Pope); (3) a serious attempt to order quantities in the English syllables on the
    classical model, which yet is willing to yield to the native stress-patterns wherever the verse
    becomes strained (Swinburne)-- Jury terms this verse quasi-quantitative; (4) rigorous
    quantitative meter regardless of stress (Bridges); and (5) both a correct quantitative pattern
    and a natural, correct, and corresponding stress pattern (Tennyson). Rules are given for the
    quantity of English syllables. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E186">
   <bib>Kenner, Hugh. "The Muse in Tatters." Agenda 6 (1968): 43-61. </bib>
   <notes>On Pound's translations--and transformations--of the Sapphic fragments. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E187">
   <bib>Khanna, Ravindra. "Sri Aurobindo's Contribution to English Prosody" Cultural Forum (New
    Delhi) 14, 3-4 (1972): 88-92. </bib>
   <notes>This Indian poet has written English poems in both stress verse and quantitative verse.
    Rules for the latter, summarized here, are said to be taken from Auro- bindo's long essay on the
    subject in vol. 30 of the Complete Works. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E188">
   <bib>Koschat, Erna. Versuche in antiken Metren bei R. S. Bridges. Diss., Vienna, 1929. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E189">
   <bib>Kunze, Erich. "Zur Metrik des 'Kalevala-Verses' bei Freiligrath und Longfellow."
    Wissenschaftliche Zeitschrift der Ernst Mortiz Arndt-Universität Griefswald 11 (1962): 249-53. </bib>
   <notes>Cf. Hardy (E170), Larrabee (E193), Moyne and Mustanoja (E205), and Hol- man (E180).
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E190">
   <bib>Lancaster, H. Carrington. "Classical Versification in English Poetry of the Sixteenth
    Century." Sewannee Review 11 (1903): 467- 73. </bib>
   <notes>"Had there been an English Ennuis to express the theories of Harvey and other pedants of
    his kind in some great poem, the verse of the Elizabethan Age, if not of succeeding periods,
    would be very different from what it really is." Short views of the major metrists and their
    opinions on the subject. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E191">
   <bib>Landor, Walter Savage. "English Hexameters" and "German Hexameters." The Last Fruit off an
    Old Tree. London, 1853; </bib>
   <notes>the first of these is rpt in The Poems of Walter Savage Landor. Ed. Geoffrey Grigson.
    London: Centaur Press, 1964. pp. 178-79. See also "On English Hexameters" on pp. 308-9 there,
    rpt from the 1863 Heroic Idylls. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E192">
   <bib>Larminie, William. "The Development of English Metres."Contemporary Review 66 (1894):
    717-36. </bib>
   <notes> May also have been reprinted separately. English meter, Larmine opines, is based on not
    two but four quantities, though stress "greatly helps out the quantitative deficiencies." Rhyme
    is and "unneces- sary burden" to be got rid of (in English; L. admits in a long digression its
    im- portance in the other languages). Assonance, however, can be valuable support to English
    verse. Swinburne is praised for the wide use of feet of three or more syllables, and the rhythms
    of the Authorized Version are upheld as exemplary. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E193">
   <bib>Larrabee, Stephen A. "Brougham, Longfellow, and Kalevala." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 56
    (1955): 258-59. </bib>
   <notes>The original charge of plagiarism (of meter) was levelled by W.C. Porter in the
    Mercersbury Review for November 1855. Cf. Moyne and Mustanoja (E205) and Hardy (E170), Kunze
    (E189), also Holman (E180). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E194">
   <bib>Lefevere, André. Translating Poetry: Seven Strategies and a Blueprint. Assen, The
    Netherlands: Van Gorcum, 1975. See section 1.2.3, "Metrical Translation," pp. 57-76. </bib>
   <notes> The book discusses English translations of the 64th poem in Catullus from 1870-1970.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E195">
   <bib>Lindsay, Alexander William Crawford, Lord. Earl of Crawford and Balcarres. On the Theory of
    the English Hexameter, and its applicability to the Translation of Homer. A Letter to William
    John Hamilton. London: John Murray, 1862. 31 pp. </bib>
   <notes>A tract. His explanation of the deliquescence of the hexameter line in English poetry is
    that modern poets have ignored the rules, while adopting the metrical form, of classical Greek
    versification. Thereafter follow Rules (they are accen- tually based), long exemplary
    translations from Homer and Schiller, and notes. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E196">
   <bib>Loane, George G. "The Fourteener in Translation." Notes and Queries 188 (1945): 200-2. </bib>
   <notes>The critics have generally panned this meter as a medium for translation of classical
    hexameter; the translators themselves have been more receptive. Sam- ples. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E197">
   <bib>Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth. Evangeline [1847]. In The Writings of Henry Wadsworth
    Longfellow. 11 vols. Cambridge, Mass.: Riverside Press, 1886. Vol. 4, pp. 19-106. </bib>
   <notes>Written in accentual (dactylic) hexameters, though the rhythm is much more supple than
    many people think. Longfellow had tried this meter earlier in his "The Children of the Lord's
    Supper" and "To a Driving Cloud," but it was the discovery of a translation of Homer of
    Blackwood's Magazine that fixed him upon it. The poem is also famous for inspiring Clough to
    write his Bothie (E140). See Sieper (K350) for more details. See also p. 240 of the review in
    North American Review 66 (1848). See also E235 and E242. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E198">
   <bib>Mackay, H. W. Boyd. "English Hexameter." Poet-Lore 23 (1912): 139- 44. </bib>
   <notes>Eschewing accentual hexameters, Mackay sets forth the metrical form for the hexameter line
    in any language, the rules for quantity in English (the ear must be the absolute judge; no
    length by rule or position is to be allowed), and the special difficulties of writing the true
    quantitative line in our language. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E199">
   <bib>McKerrow, R. B. "The Use of So-Called Classical Metres in Elizabethan Verse." MLQ 4 (1901):
    172-80;5 (1902): 5-13,148-49. </bib>
   <notes>Cogently, McKerrow classes "practically all verse that has ever been called clas- sical"
    as (1) verse called quantitative but in fact accentual and nothing else; (2) verse adopting the
    abstract pattern of classical verse but substituting accent for quantity; (3) "quantitative"
    verse in which the quantities are determined by natural English pronunciation; or (4)
    "quantitative verse which adopts, at least in part, the true classical rules, such as length by
    position. In general the devel- opment was from the fourth type to the second. McKerrow observes
    quite correctly that, as for judgments on the whole enterprise, "to accuse such men of simple
    folly were surely a still more simple presumption in ourselves." Given the authoritative status
    of the classics and the wretchedness of vernacular poetry at the time, it would be surprising if
    no classical-imitative verses had been at- tempted. As for quantity, the determination of the
    length of the syllable had- nothing to do with (1) whether or not the length of the vowel was
    noted, (2) pronunciation, or (3) actual duration of time.It was entirely conventional; scansion
    was divorced from pronunciation. Nothing else explains the theorists' concern with orthography.
    McKerrow assays separately the contribution of each of the known figures of the movement--Drant,
    Dyer, Sidney, Harvey (the disparity between his theory and practice is noted), Stanyhurst,
    Webbe, Fraunce, Puttenham, Sabie, Dickinson, the anonymous author of The First Booke of the
    Preservation of King Henry VII, Campion, and Sandford [in the sup- plementary note;
    chronologically he comes first]. A wellspring essay: McKer- row's immense bibiographical
    knowledge enabled him to make many sugges- tions here that had never been made previously and
    even now have not been pursued. See also: </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E200">
   <bib>Dibelius, Wilhelm. "Über die Verwendung klassischer Versmassee in der englishen
    Renaissance." Shakespeare Jahrbuch 39 (1903): 325-26. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E201">
   <bib>Maynadier, Howard. "The Areopagus of Sidney and Spenser."MLR 4 (1909): 289- 301 </bib>
   <notes>Discusses, inter alia, the Harvey-Spenser correspondence (E172-3). The first known
    reference to the Areopagus per se is in the late nineteenth century, hardly early enough to be
    reliable evidence. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E202">
   <bib>Milham, Mary-Ella. "Arcady on the Atlantic." Humanities Association Bulletin 19 (1968):
    42-51. </bib>
   <notes>Close analysis of quantitative poetry by Longfellow, Bliss Carman, and C. G. D. Roberts,
    with some wider remarks on the Victorian penchant for classical meters in English verse.Carman's
    translations of Sappho evidence particular metrical variety. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E203">
   <bib>Monro, C[harles] J[ames]. "Latin Metres in English, After Sidney, Tennyson, and Mr. Ellis."
    Journal of Philology 4 (1872): 223-30. </bib>
   <notes>A skeptical assessment of Ellis's (E148) two rules for quantitative verse in Eng- lish,
    namely, that (1) syllables otherwise short may count for metrical purposes as long if accented,
    and (2) the syllable under the ictus must be accented. Hence Monro concludes that by not
    allowing long by unstressed syllables in ictic position Ellis is writing only "a metre and a
    half"--a fully accentual meter but only partly a true quantitative meter. Praises Sidney's
    quantitative work. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E204">
   <bib>Montgomery, Robert L., Jr. Symmetry and Sense: The Poetry of Sir Philip Sidney. Austin:
    University of Texas Press, 1961. </bib>
   <notes>The first chapter examines Sidney's technical development; see esp. the section of his
    classical meters on pp. 13-19. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E205">
   <bib>Moyne, Ernest J., and Tauno F. Mustanoja. "Longfellow's 'Song of Hiawatha' and Kalevala."
    American Literature 25 (1953):87-89 </bib>
   <notes>Longfellow adopted the hexameter meter he found in Anton Schiefer's transla- tion. Cf.
    Hardy (E170), Larrabee (E193), Kunze (E189), and Holman (E180). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E206">
   <bib>Murray, Gilbert. "What English Poetry May Still Learn from Greek." Essays and Studies 3
    (1912): 7-31. </bib>
   <notes>It may learn three things: religion, architecture, and texture.The third of these occupies
    most of the article, beginning on p. 15. Murray gives detailed atten- tion to the English meters
    appropriate for translation as well as the nature and strengths of the Greek meters in epic,
    dramatic, and lyric poetry. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E207">
   <bib>Murray, L[indley]. English Grammar, adapted to the different classes of learners. York:
    Wilson, Spence, and Mawman, 1795.The fourth part, "Prosody," (pp. 146-59) </bib>
   <notes>discusses versification only on pp. 155-59, since in this author's view, "prosody"
    consists of both the rules for pronunciation in English and also the laws of versification.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E208">
   <bib>Nares, Robert. Elements of Orthoepy, containing a distinct view of the whole analogy of the
    English Language, so far as it relates to Pronunciation, Accent, and Quantity. London: T. Tayne
    and Son, 1784; facsimile reprint: Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar Press, 1968. </bib>
   <notes>Founder of the Royal Society of Literature, Nares produced a book on pro- nunciation that
    was authoritative in its time and influential on Walker's Dic- tionary. Part 2 treats accent,
    Part 3 quantity. Accent he calls "a species of em- phasis," distinguishing it from the Greek
    pitch-accent. Quantity he admits is variable in English, though the gradations can all be
    grouped as simply short or long. Rules for quantity, pp. 216- 18. Nares refuses to let accent
    determine syllables as long, yet he also insists that modern meters are deficient in com-
    parison with classical ones (pp. 211, 219-21). Chapter 10 of Part 3 sanctions elision and
    diaeresis in verse. For a fuller account of the laws of versification the reader is referred to
    Mitford (p. 142). There is a full-scale study of Nares' treatise by Claus-dirk Pollner E209
    (Bern: Herbert Lang, 1976). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E210">
   <bib>Newman, Francis W[illiam]. Homeric Translation in Theory and Practice. A Reply to Matthew
    Arnold, Esq. London: Francis and Norgate, 1861. 104 pp. </bib>
   <notes>A wincing response to Arnold's severe censures of Newman's translation of Homer; Newman
    replies by condemning the hexameter translation by Arnold as unfit for the common, unscholarly
    reader. Written while its author still felt the sting of the wound, the book is a close
    rejoinder to both accusations and phrases, and so has little of independent value. Arnold
    replied the following year in his Last Words lecture (E108). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E211">
   <bib>Nowell-Smith, Simon. "Bridges' Classical Prosody: New Versions and Variants." TLS, 28
    August 1943, p. 420. </bib>
   <notes> See also the earlier essay on p. 415, and a confirmatory addendum on p. 444. Nowell-Smith
    catalogues and analyzes the manscripts of the poems in Bridges' quantitative period, here dated
    1901-3, in disagreement with Gu|'erard. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E212">
   <bib>Omond. T. S. "Accent and Quantity." The Academy 76 (1909): 798-800. </bib>
   <notes>A response to Bridges' hexameters in the 1909 New Quarterly, attacking the Laureate's
    complete rejection of accent (in favor of quantity) as the basis for English meter. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E213">
   <bib>-----. "Arnold and Homer." Essays and Studies 3 (1912): 71-91. </bib>
   <notes>All discussions of translating Homer eventually come to the question of an ap- propriate
    meter. This one does, too, in the midst of a helpful review of the en- tire subject.
    Illuminating comparisons of translations. Arnold himself, it hap- pens, preferred the Hexameter
    above Blank Verse and all other English meters as the best form for rendering Homer. Omond
    sketches the history of hex- ameters beginning on p. 84; This essay might be read most
    profitably just after reading Arnold's lectures directly; no study of English quantitative verse
    is needed. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E214">
   <bib>-----. English Hexameter Verse: with a Specimen. Edinburgh: David Douglas, 1897. 48 pp. </bib>
   <notes>Omond's earliest work on the classical meters; his continued research allowed him to
    expand this essay in both scope and detail into the 1903 English Metrists, all of this work
    being finally superceded by the 1921 edition (A5). See also E310. Here Omond rough-sketches the
    Elizabethan efforts to reproduce quan- tity in English verse, the nineteenth-century German and
    English efforts to imitate the quantitative pattern in accent, and Omond's own approach, the
    view that "the true unit of English verse is not the foot, nor even the accent, but simply a
    period of time," so that the hexameter becomes "simply a verse of six periods" (italics
    original). The essay concludes with a free translation of Book 5 of the Odyssey. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E215">
   <bib>Omond, T. S., and John Sargeaunt. "These Lame Hexameters."Letters to TLS, 1920, pp. 456,
    472, 488, 504, 520, 536, 552. </bib>
   <notes>Bickering over Tennyson's hexameters, whether accentual or quantitative. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E216">
   <bib>Oxenford, John. "The Practice of Writing English in Classical Metres." Classical Museum 3
    (1846): 279-83. </bib>
   <notes>Urges the use of authentic "classical metres" in translating Greek verse: Oxen- ford is
    emphatic that the position of the ictus must be preserved (by accent, in English), and he seems
    to think that the classical pattern of quantities can be preserved as well, albeit with "much
    greater latitude," given the nature of our language. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E217">
   <bib>Palmer, George Herbert. "Hexameters and Rhythmic Prose." The Atlantic Monthly 66 (1890):
    526-34. </bib>
   <notes>Palmer finds the former of these unsuited for translation of Homer (on the grounds that
    English is weak in dactylic words) and recommends instead the latter, or an "iambic
    recitative,"subjoining his translation of Book 23 of The Odyssey as example. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E218">
   <bib>Park, B. A. "Milton and Classical Meters." Milton Quarterly 6 (1972): 75-77. </bib>
   <notes>Milton's imitation of the classical meter (the fourth Asclepiadean) of Horace's Carm. I.5
    in his translation of it ("What slender Youth bedew'd") is intelligible only if we postulate
    that he took for the final syllable in the English line what was the final accented syllable in
    the Latin line (thereby shortening the syllable count for all the lines in the translation). In
    other words, Milton took over the accentual pattern which is formed as a by-product of the
    quantitative meter in the Latin. The same stanza-form is used by Collins for the "Ode to
    Evening," by Southey for "To Hymen" and "Written on the First of January," and (with rhyme
    added) by Marvell for the "Horatian Ode." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E219">
   <bib>Poirier, Michel. Sir Philip Sidney and English Quantitative Verse. Diss., Paris, 1944. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E220">
   <bib>Redesdale, John Thomas Freeman Mitford, Lord. Thoughts on English Prosody and Translations
    from Horace. </bib>
   <notes> And </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E221">
   <bib>Redesdale, John Thomas Freeman Mitford, Lord. Further Thoughts on English Prosody. Oxford
    and London: J.H. and James Parker, 1859. 16 pp and 15 pp. (Tracts). </bib>
   <notes>The author is the nephew of William Mitford (E599). Established quantitative rules based
    on his earlier translation of several Horatian Odes. "When quantity is governed by fixed rule,
    the strongest emphasis may be placed on a short syllable without injury to the metre, and
    reading is carried on without regard to anything but the sense of the passage." The second
    essay, written a month later, defends this position against some intervening criticisms.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E222">
   <bib>Review of Longfellow's Ballads and Other Poems. North American Review 55 (1842): 114-44. </bib>
   <notes>The review turns into a history of the hexameters in Greek, Latin, Spanish, German, and
    English. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E223">
   <bib>"Rhymed Hexameters and Pentameters." Blackwood's Magazine 59 (1846): 496. </bib>
   <notes>Four poems in the mixed meter, with a headnote. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E224">
   <bib>Ringler, William. "Master Drant's Rules." PQ 29 (1950): 70-74. </bib>
   <notes>Prints three corrected texts containing all of Sidney's known statements on the rules for
    making quantitative verses. No explication, however. See Sidney (E234). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E225">
   <bib>Sandford, James. Houres of Recreation . . . done first out of Italian into English. 2nd ed.
    London: Henry Binneman, 1576. </bib>
   <notes>It was McKerrow who first noticed that one of the poems appended to this lit- tle book is
    in five languages--Greek, Latin, Italian, French, and English--and in the Classical "elegaic
    couplet" metre, thus representing the second known in- stance of quantitative verse printed in
    English (after Ascham's). The verses do not appear in the first edition (1573), which was
    entitled The Garden of Pleasure. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E226">
   <bib>Sayers, F[rank]. "Of English Metres." In his Disquisitions Metaphysical and Literary.
    London: J. Crouse and W.Stevenson, 1793; rpt in his Works. London, 1830; rpt New York: Garland,
    1971. pp. 129-37. </bib>
   <notes>Since English syllables may be denominated long or short, as in every other language, "it
    is difficult to assign a cause why the same arrangement of English syllables [as that in
    classical verse] should not be pleasing also." Notes instances in the Renaissance and by Milton;
    is hopeful of more to come. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E227">
   <bib>Schelling, Felix E. "The Inventor of the English Hexameter."MLN 5 (1890): 212- 14. </bib>
   <notes>Those scholars who have impugned Harvey's character for his having said that he wished to
    be remembered as The Inventor of the English Hexameter have taken the sentence out of a
    sensitive context and thereby misconstrued it. It would seem that Greene had taunted Harvey with
    that epithet and worse, and Harvey, replying in his Fowre Letters, naturally would prefer the
    best of them. For references see the citation data at E173 and also E174. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E228">
   <bib>-----. Poetic and Verse Criticism of the Reign of Elizabeth. University of Pennsylvania
    Publications in Philology, Literature, and Archaeology, series 9, vol. 1, no.1. Philadelphia:
    University of Pennsylvania Press, 1891. 97 pp. </bib>
   <notes>Unjustly neglected: this dissertation provides commentary on all the major Renaissance
    prosodists embroiled in the quantitative controversy--Ascham, Gascoigne, James VI, Blenerhasset,
    Harvey and Spenser, Stanyhurst, Nashe, Webbe, Puttenham, Sidney (Gosson and Lodge), Harington,
    Campion, and Daniel--commentary more extensive than most available elsewhere. Non- technical
    literary history. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E229">
   <bib>Schuman, Sharon. "Sixteenth Century English Quantitative Verse: Its Ends, Means, and
    Products." MP 74 (1977): 335-49. </bib>
   <notes>Attempting to ferret out the elusive definition of "quantity"used by the Eliza- bethans
    and also a legitimate rationale they could have held for their poetic practice, Schuman examines
    (1) the "aesthetic assumptions" made by the Eliza- bethan poets, (2) their conception of Latin
    versification, and (3) the principles which they seem to have used in constructing their
    quantitative verses. Her conclusion is that the Elizabethan poets scanned a syllable as long or
    short by two rules, operating sequentially, the first mandatory and the second optional: if a
    syllable was not long by (positional) definition in the Latin system, then it might be by
    accentuation in the English one.That is, the English poets wrote quantitative verse which was to
    be scanned according to the Latin rules but read (stressed) according to the regular English
    pronunciation. The first system was visual, the second aural. Astoundingly, the author seems
    totally unaware of the work of Attridge (E112), but nevertheless the article is closely argued
    and offers a useful com- parison of the work of Willcock and Hendrickson (</notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E265">
   <bib/>
   <notes> and E175). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E230">
   <bib>Shadwell, Lancelot. The Iliad of Homer, Faithfully Rendered in Homeric Verse from the
    Original Greek. London: William Pickering, 1844. </bib>
   <notes>Pure text; no Preface or notes. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E231">
   <bib>Shawcross, John T. "The Prosody of Milton's Translation of Horace's Fifth Ode." Tennesee
    Studies in Literature 13 (1968): 81-89. </bib>
   <notes>Noticing that Sprott's accentual-syllabic scansion of the Ode left numerous ir-
    regularities, Shawcross scans it by quantities, but the numerous irregularities then left force
    him to conclude that Milton freqently reduced (1) two short syl- lables to one long and (2) a
    trochee to a stressed monosyllable.Choruses from Samson Agonistes are likewise scanned. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E232">
   <bib>Shipley, Joseph. "The Problems of the Elizabethan Poets."Poet-Lore 38 (1927): 358- 72. </bib>
   <notes>Surveys the opinions of all the major Elizabethan metrists on the issues of (1) the use of
    rime and (2) accent vs. quantity.The general problem for the poets of course was to discover and
    legitimize a model for the new poetry. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E233">
   <bib>Short, R. W. "The Metrical Theory and Practice of Thomas Campion." PMLA 59 (1944): 1003-18. </bib>
   <notes>Campion's theory of English meter can be properly appraised only by setting aside
    altogether his interest in music (and musical settings) and by understand- ing his beliefs about
    accent and quantity. Short, claiming [without any further explanation] that English has "four
    classes of syllables" differentiated by stress, pitch, and length, argues (1) that Campion was
    interested not in classical met- rics but in the quantities (and accents) properly a part of
    English meter, when the classical rules are reconciled to the vagaries of English pronunciation,
    and also (2) that Campion sought to write verse having lines comprising equal peri- ods of time
    regardless of their syllabic filling. Such a theory with such a practice Short has
    understandable difficulty reconciling; he therefore argues that the proper illustrations of
    Campion's position in the Observations are not the exam- ples given therein but Campion's own
    poems published the year before in A Book of Ayres. These latter are then compared to verses by
    Greene and Dekker. A patchwork explanation, of thin and motley material erratically stiched.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E234">
   <bib>Sidney, Sir Philip. The Countess of Pembrokes Arcadia. London, 1590, 1593, etc. </bib>
   <notes>A number of the verses in the Arcadia are frankly experimental, including imi- tations of
    quantitative meters.There is no full- scale essay on this matter, so the reader will have to
    consult: (1) The Index, s.v. "Versification," in Jean Rob- ertson's edition of the Old Arcadia
    (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973), p. 513, though the references lead only to her Commentary,
    which is heavily reliant upon (2) The Poems of Sir Philip Sidney. Ed. William A. Ringler, Jr.
    Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1962. Ringler's invaluable edition offers both Commentary (see pp.
    385-86, 390-93 (above all), and 402-3) and a Table of Verse Forms (pp. 569-72). See also
    Maynadier (E201), Underdown (E259), Applegate (E106), Hanssen (E169), Poirier (E219), and
    Ringler (E224). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E235">
   <bib>Smith, Albert. "Syringaline: A Myth, by Professor Long- and-short-fellow." The Month, 1851,
    pp. 192-96. </bib>
   <notes>A parody of Longfellow's hexameters. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E236">
   <bib>Sonnenschein, E. A. What is Rhythm? Accompanied by an Appendix on Experimental Syllable
    Measurement. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1925. 228 pp. </bib>
   <notes>Rev: in TLS, 10 September 1925, pp. 573-74 (leading article) with reply by S. on 17
    September, p. 600; in The Dial 80 (1926): 316-22; in MLR 23 (1928): 483-85; in American Journal
    of Philology 47 (1926): 187-91. See the critique by MacColl at E369. Sonnenschein's treatise on
    rhythm contains three general chapters-- "Rhythm Defined," "Rhythm and Music," "Music and
    Verse,"--three chapters on Rhythm in Isosyllabic [Vedic], Greek, and Latin Verse, and four
    chapters on quantity--"Rhythm in English Verse: The Ratio of Foot to Foot," "Syllable
    Measurement in English," "Quantity in English Verse: The Ratio of Rise to Fall," and "English
    Experiments in Classical Metres." His definition: "Rhythm is that property of a sequence of
    events in time which produces on the mind of the observer the impression of proportion be- tween
    the durations of the several events or groups of events of which the se- quence is composed."
    "My own proposed system of scansion may be described as an attempt to reinstate the foot (in the
    ancient sense of the term) as a unit of measurement." That is, he believes that English is
    exactly like Greek and Latin in that two "short"syllables may stand for one "long" and so
    receive metrical ictus, and also in that accent and quantity are inseparable.Chapter 8 gives
    Rules for the Quantity of every English syllable, based on the kymography measurements in the
    Appendix. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E237">
   <bib>Southey, Robert. Preface to A Vision of Judgment [1821]. In The Poetical Works of Robert
    Southey. 10 vols. London:Longman, Orme, Brown, Greer, &amp; Longmans, 1838. Vol. 10, pp.
    195-212. For the collected edition Southey added an additional Preface (pp. vii-xxi) in response
    to Tillbrook (E257). Rev: in the Edinburgh Review 35 (1821): 422-36. </bib>
   <notes> With this poem Southey initiated the vogue of accentual hexameters in English in the
    nineteenth-century--a classical-imitative meter substituting stress for length. Southey's
    hexameter line contains six feet, the first four of which may be either dactyls or trochees, the
    fifth being always a dactyl and the sixth a tro- chee. In this practice he follows the Germans,
    substituting trochees in the mod- ern verse for spondees in the classical, since he agrees that
    the true spondee is so rare a species in modern speech as to be scarcely ever seen. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E238">
   <bib>Spedding, James. "Arnold on Translating Homer." Fraser's Magazine 63 (1861): 703- 14; </bib>
   <notes> rpt as "On English Hexameters" in his Reviews and Discussions: Literary, Political, and
    Historical, not relating to Bacon. London: Kegan Paul, 1879.pp. 316- 43. Reviews Arnold (E107),
    squarely objecting to his argument that the hexameter is the best meter for rendering Homer in
    English;in a closely reasoned and technical counterargument, Spedding examines the nature of
    accent and quan- tity in both Greek and English, and the rules for the hexameter in each, in or-
    der to show that the effect of the English hexameter line on the Englishman who knows no Greek
    is not the same as the effect of Homer's lines on a Greek; it is that man whom Spedding claims
    is the proper judge of a translation, not the scholar fluent in both languages. The 1879 volume
    adds "corrections and explanations." Munro (M140) disagrees sharply. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E239">
   <bib>Spingarn, J. E. "Classical Metres." A History of Literary Criticism in the Renais-sance.
    New York: Columbia University Press, 1899; 2nd rev. ed. 1908. pp. 298-304. </bib>
   <notes>A short account of the theories of the major Renaissance prosodists. Not en- tirely
    reliable, as subsequent scholarship has shown. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E240">
   <bib>Standop, Ewald. "Zur Beurteilung der Elisabethanischen Hexameter." Studien zur englischen
    und amerikanischen Sprache und Literatur: Festschrift für Helmut Papajewski. Ed. Paul G. Buchloh
    et al. Neumünster: Wacholtz, 1974. pp. 350- 62. </bib>
   <notes>A long, close review of Hendrickson (E175), generally approbatory. Standop reminds us that
    the classical-imitative phenomenon is not restricted to the Renaissance, and that we still
    cannot judge very well the aesthetic (metrical) value of the experiments. The Renaissance read
    such verse with normal prose accents, not with a melodic accent, though perhaps both systems
    were heard simultaneously (Standop). Thus our reading or quantitative verse by accent may not be
    so unrealistic; the Renaissance poets generally avoid congruence of ac- cent and ictus, and it
    may be that counterpointing of stress and ictus is the best compromise solution, as we see in
    the "thin"spondees of Voss with their "free- floating' stress. The ultimate question in these
    matters is whether English sylla- bles are long and short; the answer must be No. Conclusion:
    the nature of quantitative verse arises not from the hypothetical pattern but from the real ac-
    centual pattern, whether intended or not. A balanced theory will pay attention to both. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E241">
   <bib>Stanyhurst, Richard. Preface "Too thee Learned Reader." In The first foure books of Virgil
    his Aeneis translated intoo English verse by Richard Stanyhurst, with other Poetical Devises
    theretoo annexed. London. 1582. Rpt in Smith (A26), vol. 1, pp. 135-47. </bib>
   <notes>Praised by Harvey but treated cooly by some others (who were put off both by his language
    and by his uncompromising classicism, probably), Stanyhurst seems to have the strongest effort
    of any of the Renaissance quantivists to ad- here to the Latin metrical system. Not only does he
    follow the quantitative structure of the Latin line strictly, he also adheres to the accentual
    structure of its last two feet, and he even conforms to the morphological structure of the meter
    as well. Observing that the stress-rules for English are radically different from those for
    Latin, Stanyhurst concludes that the strictest application of the Latin rules to English will be
    disastrous, so that he is willing to scan sometimes strictly by syllabic quantity (as for words
    of Latin etymology) and sometimes by letting the accent qualify the syllable as long. He speaks
    much of sounds, but it is clearly the orthography that is the actual determinant in practice, as
    can be seen in his selection between variant spellings of a word so as to fit the quanti- tative
    rules for length by position (which were visual rules anyway). But since the Preface to his
    Aeneis is very short and sketchy, and since his verse is in- tended to be read as anything but
    accentual-syllabic English meter, it is very difficult to have a clear grasp of his entire
    position.Attridge is helpful here; he devotes a short chapter to Stanyhurst. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E242">
   <bib>Steele, R. B. "The Meter of Evangeline. MLN 9 (1894):cols. 413- 16. </bib>
   <notes>Cf. E197. The accentual hexameter may be compared to the classical quantita- tive
    hexameter by examining the three main characteristics of the latter in the former--the
    proportion of dactyls to spondees, monosyllables at line-end, and caesura- placement. The same
    features are also treated in the subsequent </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E243">
   <bib>-----. "The Meter of Miles Standish." MLN 9 (1894): cols.476- 79. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E244">
   <bib>Stephens, W. H. Elements of English Verse as a Science and an Art. London: Macmillan, 1933.
    118 pp. </bib>
   <notes>An extravagant system of new terminology and convoluted scansion operations based on
    Quantity. Every syllable in English is said to have a quantity fixed by usage, and which depends
    on "texture," "metrical stress" (?), and "incidental emphasis." A numerical score for each of
    these three factors is tallied, giving the "scansion feet of sound." This metrical tally may
    then be set against the "spans of thought or emotion"(the line divided syntactically and marked
    for natural speech-stresses). Conflict between these two systems is called a "cross- draw"; the
    classical longs and shorts are renamed "strokes" and "flicks," and any monosyllable which can be
    either is called a "rover." Arf. The rules for assigning quantity, besides being garbled, vague,
    and ludi- crous, are actually based on accent, as is this entire misconceived system. Sub-
    sequent essays written by this author: </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E245">
   <bib>-----. "The Stroke-Flick Structure of English Verse." Poetry Review 26 (1935): 23-28. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E246">
   <bib>-----. "The Stroke-Flick Rhythm in Canadian Verse." Poetry Review 26 (1935): 471-75. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E247">
   <bib>-----. "Stroke-Flick Tendencies in Australian Verse." Poetry Review 26 (1935): 383-86. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E248">
   <bib>-----. "Discipline in Pattern for English Verse." Poetry Review 26 (1935): 139-42. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E249">
   <bib>-----. "New Measures in English Verse." Poetry Review 26 (1935): 213-17. </bib>
   <notes/>
  </item>


  <item id="E250">
   <bib>-----. "Four-Time in English Verse." Poetry Review 28 (1937): 297- 99, 381-84. </bib>
   <notes>Doubtless Stephens would have both been and not been, had he had his prefer- ence. He
    speaks here of strokes as "the stressed syllable in the word," yet "the Metrical Quantity" of
    both monosyllables and polysyllables is "invariable," even though the influence of Classical
    Prosody on English has been pernicious; worse, there are "Seven Dominant Rhythms or Measures (or
    Metres)" such as "Two-Time," etc. This is lunatic. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E251">
   <bib>Stone, William Johnson. On the Use of Classical Metres in English. London: Henry Frowde,
    1898. 59 pp. </bib>
   <notes>[Omond and Bridges cite this date; BMC cites 1899.] Posthumously published (with some
    revisions (by Bridges?)) as Classical Metres in English Verse, the second part of Bridges' 1901
    edition of Milton's Prosody (E495). Omond thought that had Stone lived longer (he died at 26)
    his judgments, par- ticularly phonetic, would have been sounder. In any event the substance of
    his theory--and it is a significant statement--would not have changed. Part I of his treatise
    give a short history of previous attempts at quantitative verse and theory in the Renaissance
    and Nineteenth Century; Part II presents his argument. Stone believes that classical verse was
    just the reverse of the modern: Greek meter was quantitative but "combated" by speech-accents,
    while English meter is accentual but opposed by quantities. Hence a truly quantitative verse
    must be metered by quantities with combative(counterpoised) accents. Such a verse must be
    written with strict attention to quantity ("any compromise is fa- tal");accent and quantity are
    not to coincide, as in Tennyson, and accentual imitation of quantitative structure is
    deplorable.Accent in English does not lengthen the syllable, Stone thinks, nor do double
    consonants lengthen the vowel--there is no length by position for us. Accent in the modern
    languages is precisely the same as it was in Greek--a rise in pitch. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E252">
   <bib>Swanson, Roy A. "Classical Meters in Modern Languages." Princeton (A18), pp. 126-28. </bib>
   <notes>See also s.v. "Hexameter." Not as systematic as it might be, but cogent and reasonably
    accurate. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E253">
   <bib>Swinburne, Algernon Charles. "Choriambics," "Hendecasyllabics,"and "Sapphics." Poems and
    Ballads. First Series and Second Series. London, 1866, 1878; </bib>
   <notes> rpt in The Bonchurch Edition of The Complete Works of Algernon Charles Swinburne. Ed.
    Edmund Gosse and T. J. Wise. 20 vols. London: William Heinemann, 1925.Vol. 3, pp. 88-89; vol. 1,
    pp. 331-35. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E254">
   <bib>[Taylor, William.] "English Hexameter Exemplified." The Monthly Magazine 1 (1796): 404-5. </bib>
   <notes>Omond (A5) identifies this "transversion" of 19 lines from Macpherson's Ossian as the
    first specimen of accentual hexameters in English on the German model; after this first
    dislodgement, the avalanche soon followed. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E255">
   <bib>Tennyson, Alfred Lord. "Attempts at Classical Metres in Quantity." Cornhill Magazine, 1863,
    pp. 707-9. </bib>
   <notes> Four samples of classical-imitative verse: "Hexameters and Pentameters,""Alcaics,"
    "Endecasyllabics," and "Specimen of a Translation of the Iliad in Blank Verse." The latter
    three, along with "Boadicea," were reprinted under the heading "Experiments in Quantity" in
    Enoch Arden and other poems (1864), and thereafter, with the first sample restored, in The
    Eversley edition of The Works of Alfred, Lord Tennyson. Ed Hallam Tennyson. 9 vols. London:
    Macmillan, 1907-8. Vol. 2, pp. 295- 306. The most authoritative edition is The Poems of
    Tennyson, ed. Christopher Ricks, London: Longmans, 1969, where the five poems appear as nos. 325
    and 332-35, pp. 1118- 23, 1153-57. Lord Tennyson's attitude toward writing quantitative verse in
    English was commensurate with his attitudes toward other technical matters: he chose the high
    and rocky way. He wrote to satisfy both the classical and the modern systems simultaneously;
    accent and quantity are meant to coincide throughout. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E256">
   <bib>Tennyson, Hallam, Lord. Jack and the Beanstalk: English Hexameters. London: Macmillan,
    1886; </bib>
   <notes> rpt in The Eversley edition of The Works of Alfred, Lord Tennyson. Ed. Hallam Tennyson. 9
    vols. London: Macmillan, 1907-8. Vol. 2, pp. 329-31; rpt in The Poems of Tennyson. Ed.
    Christopher Ricks.London: Longmans 1969. pp. 1799-81. Two fragments of experiments in
    quantitative-imitation written by Hallam with some assistance by his father; accent and quantity
    are intended to coincide. The "Bluebeard" first appeared in 1874. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E257">
   <bib>Tillbrook, S[amuel]. Historical and Critical Remarks Upon the Modern Hexametrists, and Upon
    Mr. Southey's "Vision of Judgment." Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1822. 84 pp. </bib>
   <notes> + fold-out comparative charts. A valuable study for its particular subject: Tillbrook
    gives a very widely in- formed historical survey of hexameter verse both in other languages and
    (espe- cially and preponderantly) in English Renaissance verse. His view of the Ger- man
    accentual hexameters is deprecatory, apparently assuming that all proper classical- imitative
    verse must be essentially quantitative;indeed there is very lit- tle discussion of theory, but
    see pp.62-63. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E258">
   <bib>Trevelyan, R. C. "Classical and English Verse Structure." Essays and Studies 16 (1930):
    7-25. </bib>
   <notes>Trevelyan essays to explain why the English meters never could (and never can) equal the
    mellifluousness, grace, and complexity of the Classical meters of Vir- gil, Horace, Pindar,
    Sappho, etc. His view of our prosody is a Temporalist one: English has only "duple time" and
    "triple time" meters of isochronous bars al- ways beginning on a stress. And the fact, in his
    view, is the explanation: In English the bars must always be equal in duration, but the
    constituent syllables may vary greatly in number or length in order that the bar-lengths come
    out equal. In Classical verse, on the other hand, each syllable has a fixed proportion relative
    to the others, and the lengths of the bars do not matter. The result is regularity for our verse
    but variety for ancient verse. He reviews the various English efforts at imitation, especially
    those of Bridges, and offers his own translation, thinking that any successful modern imitation
    of the classical pat- terns "would have to be mainly indicated and expressed by accent."
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E259">
   <bib>Underdown, Mary E. I. "Sir Philip Sidney's 'Arcadian' Eclogues: A Study of His Quantitative
    Verse." DA 25 (1964): 1222A (Yale, 1961). </bib>
   <notes>The nature of Sidney's early education in Latin enabled him to apply the rules for Latin
    verse, including the all-important "position" rule, to English verse while still preserving the
    distinction between accent and quantity. Underdown explicates the mechanism whereby "the
    quantitative structure of [Sidney's] verse regulates its phrasing, which in turn forms the basis
    of rhythmical organi- zation," the word-group replacing the Latin polysyllable for purposes of
    avoid- ing metrical diaeresis. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E260">
   <bib>Van De Vender, George W. "The Prosody of Milton's Sampson Agonistes." DAI 34 (1974): 5209A
    (Mississippi). </bib>
   <notes>Milton uses accentual equivalents to the classical quantitative meters in the play,
    dividing them into stichic meters (dialogue) and lyric meters (choral odes). Mil- ton's meters
    in general parallel the Greek dramatic verseforms very closely. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E261">
   <bib>Webbe, William. A Discourse of English Poetrie, Together with the Author's judgment
    touching the reformation of out English Verse. London: John Charlewood for Robert Walley, 1586.
    Ed.Edward Arber. English Reprints series, no. 26. London, 1869.Rpt in Smith (A26), vol. 1, pp.
    226-302. </bib>
   <notes>The student may begin at p. 266 in Smith. The first twenty or so pages (up to p. 247)
    trace the history of poetry from classical times through Middle English (Webbe notices Gower,
    Chaucer, and the author of Pierce Ploghman, who he says was the first to observe quantity
    without rhyme in English) up to his con- temporaries, Webbe dispensing praise for many but
    condemning the "uncount- able rabble of ryming Ballet makers."The next twenty pages discuss the
    genres, subjects, and moral ends of poetry. The common English verse Webbe observes is based
    upon counting of syllables and rhyme and has three requirements: equivalence of line-lengths
    (the lines must be "answerable" to each other in syllables or feet), observance of natural
    stressing (i.e. an ordering of words such that none are "wrested contrary to the natural
    inclination or affection of the same"), and rhymes which do not wrench violently syntax or
    sense. Diversity of line and stanza is illustrated from the Shepheardes Calendar. Webbe notes
    that the "naturall course"of English verse seems to be iambic, and if the "right quantitie" of
    the words be followed the line will turn out properly as an iamb. But the scansions show that
    this "quantitie" means stress and nothing else. Rhymes and various sorts of acrostics are
    noticed; Webbe then turns (p. 278) to classical-imitative verses, arguing (a little opaquely but
    shrewdly) that even if the languages are dissimilar English should be able to adjust its rules
    to Latin even as Latin did to Greek. He admits that length by position will have to be
    abandoned, he cites twelve types of metrical feet, and he complains that monosyllables naturally
    long in English he was forced to treat as short in his own quantitative verses so as to supply
    the serious deficiency of short syllables in English, under the Latin rules. His actual
    statements about quantity in English are confused and his practice is inconsis- tent: his
    scansions ignore accent altogether yet length by position is admitted at points. Examples of
    Hexameters, Sapphics, and other meters conclude the trea- tise. In large part derivative and on
    the whole unexceptional, Webbe's prosodia is something of an anomaly: it seems scarcely to have
    been noticed by his con- temporaries. Its chief characteristic is conservatism. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E262">
   <bib>Whalley, George. "Coleridge on Classical Prosody: An Unidentified Review of 1797." Review
    of English Studies n.s. 2 (1951): 238-47. </bib>
   <notes>Reprints the text of a review of Bishop Horsley's On the Prosodies of the Greek and Latin
    Languages which Coleridge wrote for the February 1797 number of the Critical Review, at a time
    which his views of versification were being formed. Horsley is cited at M104; see also Patterson
    at E845. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E263">
   <bib>W[helpley], J. D. "The Art of Measuring Verses." American Review. A Whig Journal 7 (1848):
    484-92. </bib>
   <notes>Ostensibly a review of Everett (E531), but the reviewer repudiates those prin- ciples in
    preference to his own--scanning English verse literally by syllabic quantity--which he promotes
    here. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E264">
   <bib>[Whewell, W.] "Dialogue on English Hexameters." Frazer's Magazine 36 (1845): 665-70. </bib>
   <notes>Attribution given by Omond (A5). Defends accentually based hexameters on the grounds that
    even recitation of Latin verses uses stress as a marker. Trochees will be allowed to substitute
    for dactyls (the time being equal), though spondees in English verse are claimed. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E265">
   <bib>Willcock, G[ladys] D. "'Passing Pitefull Hexameters': A Study of Quantity and Accent in
    English Renaissance Verse." MLR 29 (1934): 1-19. </bib>
   <notes>A general review of the whole Elizabethan quantitative movement which is constrained, by
    the very scope and difficulty of its subject-matter, into a terse, generalizing style. A number
    of the author's judgments have been subsequently refined or reversed, but it is to her credit
    that she recognizes the absolutely central position of orthography (so seemingly superficial) in
    the whole problem of writing and reading quantitative verses correctly: "the conclusion is
    forced upon one that when Elizabethans . . . talk about quantity and so on, they are speaking of
    something visible rather than audible."Otherwise not entirely reli- able. Cf. Hendrickson
    (E175). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E266">
   <bib>Wilson, John. "Homer and His Translators." Blackwood's Magazine, April 1831- February 1834. </bib>
   <notes>Rpt in his Essays Critical and Imaginative. Ed. J. F. Ferrier. Edinburgh and London: W.
    Blackwood and Sons, 1856-57. Vol. 4, pp. 1-389. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E267">
   <bib>Wölk, Konrad. Geschichte und Kritik des englischen Hexameters. Normannia:
    Germanisch-Romanische Bücherei, vol.3. Berlin: Emil Felber, 1909. 146 pp. </bib>
   <notes>This is the most extensive review of the subject available, even though it rep- resents
    little advance upon the studies of Elze (E149) and the bibliographic spadework of Omond
    (E214).Usefully, Wölk devides his attention between the quantitative hexameters of the
    Renaissance and after (50 pages) and the accen- tual-imitative hexameters mainly of the
    nineteenth century, up to Stone and Bridges (60 pages). This distinction, along with the
    diachronic organization, makes for great clarity, and there are frequent long extracts, though
    unfortu- nately without scansions (who will ever be as assiduous as Omond?). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E268">
   <bib>Young, G. M. "A Word for Gabriel Harvey." Life and Letters, 1930; rpt in English Critical
    Essays: Twentieth Century. Ed. Phyllis M. Jones. London: Oxford University Press, 1933;rpt 1947.
    pp. 284-90. </bib>
   <notes>Defends Harvey's good judgment on the classical hexameter in talking Spenser out of using
    the meter for The Faerie Queene. (Cf. E172-73). See also: C227, C322, E7, E280, E373, E376,
    E471, E574, E632, E692, E758- 59, E977, E1192, E1227, E1241, E1456, E1518, G77, L115, L176-78,
    L295, L521, L807, L1112, L1596-1600, L1692, M106, M140, N50, N72, N125. </notes>
  </item>
 </chapter>
</bibliography>
