<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
 <chapter title="">

  <item id="E269">
   <bib>Alden, Raymond Macdonald. "English Rhythm." The Nation 93 (1911): 442-43. </bib>
   <notes> A response to Goodell's review essay (E36); Alden discusses the problems of metrical
    pause (he accepts it) and lengthening of the syllable, and he emphasizes the necessity of the
    abstract concept of the (disyllabic) metrical foot. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E270">
   <bib>-----. An Introduction to Poetry for Students of English Literature. New York: Henry Holt
    and Company, 1909; 2nd ed. 1937. </bib>
   <notes> In contrast to Alden's earlier English Verse (A1), a collection of examples and extracts,
    the Introduction sets forth his theoretical views on the nature of poetry; the salient chapters
    are 4 and 5 (on metrics) and 6 (on rhyme and stanza forms). His central position is that "two
    elements are equally necessary to the forming of rhythm: the equal time-intervals and the
    stresses which mark them." Meter, then, simply fixes the number of syllables regularly repeated
    in the rhythmic frame. Secondary accent on syllables is allowed, which may be either a stress or
    a slack for metrical purposes, and whever metrical ictus conflicts with normal word-stress,
    "hovering accent" will resolve the clash into compromise. And "in general, stress is relative
    rather than positive." (All of Alden's stress-rules (p. 172) are ahead of his time.) Quantity,
    though more variable, is relevant too: when the quantity of a syllable is too short for its
    time-interval, either lengthening or a compensatory pause will fill the deficiency; "pauses may
    also fill the place of wholly missing syllables, in order to complete the approximate equality
    of the time-intervals between stresses." The function of meter and the apparent
    interconvertibility of iambic and trochaic meters are explored in detail. Alden reviews several
    scansion systems, evasively, finally settling on the old macron-and breve. Four meters are
    considered basic, and metrical variation is discussed at length, one such device being
    infrequent substitution of pyrrhics and spondees. Far from being a mere student's manual,
    Alden's treatise tackles nearly every major issue in versification head-on, in a sensible yet
    astute approach, with frequent long digressions to review the scholarship on a subject, as well
    as summaries of his own developing arguments. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E271">
   <bib>-----. "The Mental Side of Metrical Form." MLR 9 (1914): 298-308. </bib>
   <notes> "To pronounce in one way and scan in another" is not at all unreasonable, because meter
    is a pure abstraction, assumed by the knowledgeable reader, even though it may be "wholly
    discarded or only partially represented in actual utterance." This axiom will account for
    "metrical rests" and explain how stresses outside of ictus are demoted in utterance while slacks
    under ictus may be promoted. Isochronism is only a subjective reality, even though the metrical
    foot has both a temporal and syllabic character, Alden admits. He agrees with Omond that "rising
    and falling rhythms" are essentially the same meter, and he deplores the whole conception of
    acoustics research as a legitimate method in metrics. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E272">
   <bib>-----. "The Time-Element in English Verse." MLN 14 (1899): cols. 478-94. </bib>
   <notes> Reprinted as Part Three of his English Verse: Specimens (A1). Summary, cols. 491-92.
    Criticizes J. M. Robertson (E320). Though Alden would "certainly not try to name feet or
    describe lines on any basis other than that of accent," he takes up here the matter of time in
    verse-- that is, rhythm--and examines specifically the Musical Analogy and Quantity. He argues
    that Lanier carried the analogy too far and gives a detailed account of the contrasts between
    verse and music. Variable quantities in English syllables are granted, even though they are not
    metrically ordered, yet Alden argues (this is the crux) that just as speech-accents are adjusted
    in the reading of verse under the pressure of the meter, so too the natural, various syllabic
    quantities may often be adjusted (we know that stressed syllables are commonly prolonged, for
    example), in order that the time-periods between accents will be held equal. Even if it were not
    so cogently prepared for, that conclusion seems reasonable beyond much cavil. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E273">
   <bib>Anderson, Johannes C. "Classification of Verse." Transations of the New Zealand Institute
    42 (1909): 481-533. </bib>
   <notes> In the exceedingly complex (and convoluted) metrical system presented here, Anderson
    identifies and elaborates on nineteen different types of "stress units" (the term chosen to
    supplant the traditional "foot"), the prototypical unit being a fixed period of time demarked by
    stresses and containing from one to four syllables. The very term itself entails a broader
    premise, which Anderson argues directly: English verse is metered with a basic unit of quadruple
    members. Such a premise naturally forces some unusual scansions, as for example when feminine
    endings are considered the first half of a stress-unit completed at the beginning of the
    following line. Very much attention is given to metrical pauses, and the nineteen types of units
    are eventually reduced to only seven for practical purposes. Section 1 of the treatise argues
    that no real distinction can be drawn between "iambic" and "trochaic," and after the subsequent
    section essays the same for anapest, dactyl, and amphibrach, Anderson concludes in the third
    that "absolutely no line of demarcation can be made between duple and triple" meters. No other
    metrists has ever been willing to go that far. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E274">
   <bib>-----. "The Development of the Four-syllabled Metrical Unit in the Australian Modification
    of the English Ballad." Transations of the New Zealand Institute 41 (1908): 418-21. </bib>
   <notes> Anderson's metrical system admits only feet of either two or three syllables, with the
    stress always falling on the last (iamb or anapest). But he considers that a unit of three
    initial slacks is possible, though very rare, and here he cites examples from ballads. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E275">
   <bib>-----. The Laws of Verse. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1928. 227 pp. Rev: in TLS,
    17 May 1928, p. 375; by Sonnenschein in the Oxford Magazine, 14 June 1928, p. 641; in English
    Review 47 (1928): 371; by Tempest in Review of English Studies 6 (1930): 116-20. </bib>
   <notes> Anderson, a New Zealander, was a correspondent with T. S. Omond both in letters and in
    metrical theory. That theory distinguishes poetry from prose by a "temporal metre"--"a rhythm of
    time underlies the words, and once this rhythm has been perceived, syllables can be omitted or
    inserted, accents suppressed . . . without the perception of that rhythm being lost. It is this
    rhythm of time that is metrical. . . . the words and accents float upon the metre." Critical of
    the methods of Guest (E543), Bridges (E491), and Saintsbury (E636), Anderson identifies the
    eight-crested "Romance verse" [i.e., Long Meter] as the stable lyric measure in English. The
    foot is here termed a "stress-unit," and though it seems to him irrelevant whether a stress
    begins or ends the unit, Anderson takes it to end, for the sake of convenience. His scansions
    place a grave accent above the line for "syntactical accents" and a short vertical mark below
    the line for "metrical wavecrests," the coincidence of two marks above and below a syllable
    denoting, then, the "metrical stress." Three basic rhythms of verse are identified--those
    consisting of disyllabic, trisyllabic, and quantrisyllabic units--yet strangely enough, Andersen
    argues that the effects of the disyllabic [duple time] and trisyllabic [triple time] rhythms are
    the same; indeed, he thinks that iambic rhythms can become trochaic almost insensibly, based on
    "a variable sonant hover" on every stressed vowel not ending a word: the accented syllable is
    shorted, he thinks, while the following syllable is lengthened (or another syllable inserted in
    the same duration). The four-syllable rhythm is also discussed at length, it being a compound
    form of the disyllabic rhythm. Line and stanza forms occupy the remainder of the book. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E276">
   <bib>-----. "Metre." Transactions of the New Zealand Institute 40 (1907): 466-85. </bib>
   <notes> Defining rhythm as "an uninterrupted succession of equal divisions of time, each more or
    less filled with sound," Anderson devotes considerable attention to ballad meter, which he
    persists in (mistakenly) analyzing by the apparatus for foot-verse (rather than stress-verse),
    the foot. To analyze stress-verse in feet is a category mistake, of course, but what is more
    surprising here is that Anderson makes very little of his Temporalist assumptions, instead
    emphasizing that "all blank verse, all ballad verse . . . is essentially iambic" and arguing
    that all the other meters are secondarily derived from the iambic, which itself is modelled on
    our internal cardiac rhythms. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E277">
   <bib>-----. "A Natural Classification of English Poetry." Transactions of the New Zealand
    Institute 41 (1908): 410-18. </bib>
   <notes> The scheme does seem natural enough; it has three categories--the eight- stressed
    (sixteen syllables) Ballad line, which by variations of initial and final syllables can be
    transformed as far as the six-stressed (twelve-syllabled) line; the five-stressed Heroic line,
    including Couplet and Blank Verse forms; and Irregularly lined forms, e.g. Odes and
    pattern-poems. Both the Ballad and Heroic verse may be found in continuous and Stanzaic
    arrangement. Table of forms and subforms appears on p. 412; many examples with scansions follow.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E278">
   <bib>-----. "The Verse-Unit." Transactions of the New Zealand Institute 43 (1910): 606- 55. </bib>
   <notes> Follows E273. The next higher level of metrical organization, above that of "stress
    units," is the "verse unit," consisting (in the full form) of eight stresses and often printed
    in two halves, each half more commonly known as a "line." The native British meter was of course
    the Ballad verse (seven stresses), but it was joined after the Conquest by the Romance verse
    (eight stresses), which had two offspring, the Nibelungen verse and the Alexandrine (each of six
    stresses). Anderson works out all the rhythmical and typographic (i.e. stanzaic) variations of
    these verses, but really, unless one wants examples, the whole genealogy is summarized (rather
    technically) in the dense concluding section (pp. 642-55). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E279">
   <bib>Anderson, Johannes C., and T. S. Omond. "The Limits of Verse-Length" and "The Reversed
    Foot." Letters to The Academy 75 (1908): 284-85, 306; 76 (1909): 856-58, 903-6, 927. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E280">
   <bib>Barham, Thomas Foster. "On Metrical Time, Or, the Rhythm of Verse, Ancient and Modern."
    Transactions of the Philological Society, 1860-61, pp. 45-62. </bib>
   <notes> Omond (A5) thought this "a remarkable paper," primarily I think on account of its scope.
    Barham accepts that modern meter is based on "tone, or accent," though he ushers in the old
    quantities as well by noting the "obvious" fact that "the syllable which contains most
    articulate utterance will occupy the longest time in pronunciation." But he also defines "the
    due observation of time in the recitation of metre" as Rhythm [this indeed is very exact], he
    admits metrical rests, he recognizes isochrony, and he thinks scansion by dipodies simpler. Yet
    the treatment of ancient meter in the last half of the essay surely colors heavily that of
    modern in the first, and we can hear not far behind all this the schoolboy doctrines of a
    classical prosody applied to English verse. Here is the best instance of the conflation and
    confusion of Temporalist and quantitative theories. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E281">
   <bib>Boomsliter, Paul C., and Warren Creel. "The Secret Springs: Housman's Outline on Metrical
    Rhythm and Language." Language and Style 10 (1977): 296-323. </bib>
   <notes> Ostensibly an attempt to explain the eight items in Housman's famous footnote (E297), the
    article actually ranges very far afield from direct answers to Housman's questions to a more
    general account of the processing of temporal events in human perception, which is the real
    subject here. Several of Housman's questions remain effectively unanswered. But the account
    given here of the precedence effect is simply fascinating. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E282">
   <bib>Boomsliter, Paul C., Warren Creel, and George S. Hastings, Jr. "Perception and English
    Poetic Meter." PMLA 88 (1973): 200-8. Reply by Elias Schwartz, pp. 1193; rejoinder by the
    authors, pp. 1194-95. </bib>
   <notes> Opposed to all objective theories or measurements of verse, the authors hold that
    metrical pattern inheres "in the perception not in the signal," wherein the mind engages in an
    active perceptual patterning, a pattern of expectation (of stressing recurring at equal
    intervals) projected. As support for this temporal theory of meter the authors record
    schematically some "unled choral reading" of verse by a group [consider the socio-dynamics and
    assumptions behind this method]. The verse is "Pease Porridge Hot," Dickenson, Tennyson, all of
    it close to if not actually stress-verse, so we are not surprised when they "discover" the
    metrical pause. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E283">
   <bib>Bracher, Frederick. "The Silent Foot in Pentameter Verse." PMLA 62 (1947): 1100-7. </bib>
   <notes> An attempt to answer three of Housman's provocative questions (E297), and with due notice
    of Prall (E318) and Schramm (E428), Bracher argues that every pentameter line is followed by a
    test of one foot (he will not allow metrical rests shorter than a full foot); indeed, all lines
    having an odd number of feet are followed by such a rest, though even-footed ones are not, on
    the grounds that humans naturally tend to compound simple rhythmic impulses, but odd-numbered
    rhythms cannot be resolved into simple groups. Thus blank verse is six-footed in actuality. As
    for the paradox of line-combinations: lines having the same number of feet should combine easily
    whether entirely filled with sound or ending in a rest; verses of different feet will combine
    well if both end in rests but not otherwise. Thus tetrameters and trimeters, and pentameters and
    trimeters, but not tetrameters and pentameters. Finally, tetramemeter verse, being entirely
    filled with sound, requires a rhyme to mark the line-end for the ear. Beguiling sense or
    nonsense? </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E284">
   <bib>Cobb, Charles W. "A Further Study of the Heroic Tetramemeter." MP 14 (1917): 559-67. </bib>
   <notes> An unsatisfying argument that there exists a type of line we may call the "heroic
    tetrameter," consisting of ten syllables but having only four equal time- measures (and hence
    only four strong stresses, the medial syllables in the line all being weak). Cf. E1122. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E285">
   <bib>-----. "A Scientific Basis for Metrics." MLN 28 (1913): 142-45. </bib>
   <notes> Demonstrates weaknesses in definition of metrical terms in Saintsbury (E636), Bright and
    Miller (E500), and Lanier (E364), in order to stipulate some definitions himself (scansions by
    equal time). Proposes a theorem: "Some readers read heroic [iambic pentameter] lines tetrameter
    (i.e., four major stresses marking time-periods instead of five). Then reports results of
    "objective " time-analysis of a passage read aloud by several subjects, supporting Cobb's
    argument that decasyllabic lines often have four parts not five. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E286">
   <bib>Creel, Warren. "How to Hear Time Values in Verse." English Journal 22 (1933): 810-16. </bib>
   <notes> Presents charts divided into blocks into which lines of verse are set so that the reader
    can learn to tap out beats, hear rests, syncopation, and so on. Conveniently, most of the verse
    chosen is dipodic (which as stress-verse, is meant to be heard aloud), and so the snake bites
    its tail. Creel can still have a go of it forty years later; see E281. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E287">
   <bib>-----. Rhythm and Meaning. Albany, N. Y.: Mimeographed by the author, 1957. 120 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in Quarterly Journal of Speech 44 (1958): 203. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E288">
   <bib>Dallas, E. S. "Verse." Poetics: an Essay on Poetry. London: Smith, Elder, 1852. pp. 158-88. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by Masson (rpt in his Essays on English Poets, 1856); see also the leading article
    on Dallas in TLS, 18 January 1936, pp. 41-2. "A verse depends on the order and nature of its
    accents. There is no good ground for withstanding the common doctrine, that accent depends on
    the relative sharpness of tones. Their sharpness depends upon time; upon the number of their
    vibrations in a given time. . . . Such, then, is metre in its simplest form--time heard." To the
    units of meter Dallas applies the term "bars," and he associates the three principal types of
    poetry--Dramatic, Epic, and Lyric--with three modes of metrical organization--(respectively) the
    foot, the bar, and the stanza. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E289">
   <bib>Edwards, Richard. Treatise on English Prosody. London, 1813. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E290">
   <bib>-----. Specimens of English Accentuated Verse, wherein the Intensity of Pronunciation only
    is measured and the Length of the Syllables is unnoticed. London, 1813. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E291">
   <bib>-----. Specimens of English Non-Accentuated Verse, or Verse measured with a Regard solely
    to the Length of Time required in the Pronunciation of Syllables, the Accent and Emphasis being
    entirely unnoticed. London, 1813. </bib>
   <notes> Omond believed that these must have been small tracts and that none of them was extant,
    but John Prudhoe reported in TLS, 7 April 1950, p. 215, that the first and third had been found.
    Edwin Guest (see E543; 1838 edition, vol. 1, p. 111) simply repeated that Edwards measured verse
    "with a regard solely to the length of time required in the pronunciation of syllables, the
    accent and emphasis being entirely unnoticed." Edwards also held the preposterous view that
    since correct verse required rules, and since no one before himself had written the rules
    correctly, that therefore he himself was the first English poet. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E292">
   <bib>Eyres, Grace E. "Principles and Technique of the Modern English Dipodic Line." M. A.
    Thesis, University of Texas, 1938. </bib>
   <notes> Follows Stewart (E333); includes an analysis of Christabel. Directed by Whitehall.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E293">
   <bib>Gurney, Edmund. "The Sound-Element in Verse." The Power of Sound. London: Smith, Elder,
    1880. pp. 423-50. </bib>
   <notes> Saintsbury (History of English Criticism, p. 512) approved of Gurney's work because it
    recognized that the "music" of poetry is quite different from music itself, that metrical rhythm
    is imposed upon, not latent in, speech," and that the sound-stratum of a poem can augment its
    meaning--"the setting includes a new substance." His book is a study of musical form and the
    psychology of acoustical perception, and in chapter 19 he sets forth a theory of meter based on
    his studies in music. Stresses occur at equal intervals of time, feet may contain from one to
    five syllables, and rests may fill up deficient measures. But the distinction (which Saintsbury
    noted) that Gurney draws between verse- music and tonal-music proper is sharply made: the ictus
    in music normally falls first in the bar, whereas in verse it often falls last; "there is no
    significance in this difference, which in no way affects the common feature of regular accents."
    If iambic verse were set to music, the accented syllables would fall first in the musical bars
    but still last in the meter. "The difference. . .is a mere matter of the eye. See also the essay
    on </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E294">
   <bib>Gurney, Edmund. "The Appreciation of Poetry" in his Tertium Quid. 2 vols. London: Kegan,
    Paul, Trench, &amp; Co., 1887. Vol. 2, pp. 191-250; the subject in general is "the position of
    [a reader's] native language in respect of his appreciation of verse." On the "musicality" and
    meter of verse, see pp. 203-16. </bib>
   <notes> For critical discussion, see: </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E295">
   <bib>Myers, Rollo. "Edmund Gurney's The Power of Sound. Music &amp; Letters 53 (1972): 36-43. </bib>

   <notes/>
  </item>




  <item id="E296">
   <bib>MacKerness, E. D. "Edmund Gurney's The Power of Sound." Music &amp; Letters 37 (1956):
    356-67. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E297">
   <bib>Housman, A. E. The Name and Nature of Poetry. Cambridge University Press, 1933. 51 pp. Rpt
    1961. Rpt in The Name and Nature of Poetry and Other Selected Prose. Ed. John Carter. New York:
    New Amsterdam, 1989. </bib>
   <notes> The reputation of the famous footnote (p. 8) to Housman's 1933 Leslie Stephen lecture at
    Cambridge is justly deserved; even Pound in his glowering review in The Criterion was forced to
    admit its value. There Housman enumerates eight particular metrical phenomena which still remain
    unaccounted for by theorists, the "latent base, comprising natural laws by which all
    versification is conditioned, and the secret springs of the pleasure which good versification
    can give. . . ." See Boomsliter and Creel (E281), and note E956 and E991. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E298">
   <bib>Hunt, (James Henry) Leigh. An Answer to the Question "What is Poetry?" including Remarks on
    Versification. Ed. Albert S. Cook. Boston, 1893; rpt New York: G. E. Stechert, 1926. 98 pp. </bib>
   <notes> The essay is the opening one of Hunt's Imagination and Fancy of 1844. Much of the piece
    upholds the distinction between Imagination and Fancy, but versification is discussed on pp.
    37-63: verse is held essential to poetry as "that finishing, and rounding, and 'tuneful
    planeting' of the poet's creations, which is produced of necessity by the smooth tendencies of
    their energy or inward working, and the harmonous dance into which they are attracted round the
    orb of the beautiful." Its virtues are "strength, sweetness, straightforwardness,
    unsuperfluousness, variety, and oneness." "Strength is the muscle of verse, and shows itself in
    the number and force of the marked syllables. . . . Unexpected locations of the accent double
    this force, and render it characteristic of passion and abruptness. . . . Weakness of
    versification is want of accent and emphasis." Hunt detests inverted syntax but praises
    Coleridge for "dividing [verses] by time, instead of syllables. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E299">
   <bib>Jenkin, Fleeming. "Dr. Guest on Rhythm" and two other essays in Saturday Review 55
    (February-March 1883): 248-49, 270-71; </bib>
   <notes> rpt in condensed form as "On Rhythm in English Verse" in Papers Literary, Scientific,
    &amp; by the late Fleeming Jenkin. Ed. Sidney Colvin and J. A. Ewing. 2 vols. London: Longmans,
    Green, 1887. pp. 149-70. Jenkin's judgment of Guest: "under a new name we meet with the old
    false law, classifying verse by the mere number of accents; and in place of scansion we are
    offered new and far more complex rules which, notwithstanding their great laxity, are
    inapplicable to much good verse. We conclude that the new theory is of small value." Jenkin
    himself is a Timer, though he speaks most often of stress, yet he also wishes to preserve the
    old terms of long and short [it is not clear if he means these as simply ictic and non-ictic],
    allowing "a pause followed by a weak syllable" to count as a long. But he will allow spondees
    and pyrrhics to be stronger and weaker varieties of the iamb, and he shows an astute recognition
    that two systems operate simultaneously in the metrical line- -"grouping by section"
    (syntactic-semantic units) and "grouping by feet" (meter). Within his catch-all theory that
    recognition (see pp. 159-60) is an island of surprising clarity and cogency. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E300">
   <bib>Kent, Charles W. Introductory Notes to the Study of Poetry. Charlottesville: Anderson
    Bros., 1895. 86 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A primer of sonal, metrical, and stanzaic forms. Meter is said to rest on bars of equal
    times, and Kent calls iambic and trochaic meters 3-time rhythm, but he does not go so far as to
    scan with notes, and he admits that English verse, unlike music, is essentially iambic. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E301">
   <bib>Lecky, James. "On the Phonetic Theory of English Prosody." Transactions of the Philological
    Society, 1885-87, Monthly Abstract of Proceeedings, pp. ii-vi (December 19, 1884). </bib>
   <notes> A scansion system is proposed: the foot will begin on the stressed syllable (following
    Ellis), and five degrees of stress as well as three degrees of length will be marked. "Thus
    metre, rhythm, and verse [are] all dependent on proportions of quantity or time, marked off by
    pauses or by variations of stress." Lecky speaks frequently of quantity, which he eventually
    defines as temporal. See Sumera (E401). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E302">
   <bib>MacDonagh, Thomas. Thomas Campion and the Art of English Poetry. Dublin: Hodges, Figgis,
    1913; rpt New York: Russell &amp; Russell, 1973. His thesis at University College, Dublin, in
    1911. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by Rudmose-Brown in the Irish Review 3 (1913): 52-54. The book represents a theory
    of meter which was derived from M's original study of Campion's Observations but subsequently
    assumed larger proportions, so that the final result is bivalent in character but essentially
    theoretical. M. draws heavily on Omond, but surpasses him in drawing, as the axiom of his whole
    approach, an explicit distinction between Song-Verse and Speech-Verse. Both are comprised of
    accent and quantity, in isochronous periods, but in speech-verse the units are additionally
    regulated by "weight" (undefined). Song-verse originated in music, whereas speech-verse arose
    from discourse even though it may become oratorical. The present volume treats only song- verse.
    Also discussed: music and meter; quantitative and accentual verse. MacDonagh, a well-known Irish
    poet, was executed by court-martial for activities in the Sinn Fein revolution before the
    subsequent volume could be written. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E303">
   <bib>Morton, William C. The Harmony of Verse. Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1967. 232
    pp. </bib>
   <notes> An idiosyncratic notation system and nomenclature is introduced here for a worn and
    familiar theory of meter: equal timing between stresses. We have astericks or "basic syllables"
    (stressed syllables) preceded or followed by dots ("sub-basic syllables," i.e. unstressed), to
    wit: .*., compounded by colons as bar lines, double colons, heavy dots, dashes, and such like,
    all to denote Basic, Major, and Minor Metre in this homespun account of the "physio-
    psychological basis of verse." This work has been tactfully ignored by metrists since its
    publication. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E304">
   <bib>Northcroft, George J. H. How to Write Verse: being Studies in the Principles and Practice
    of the Art of English Verse-structure. London: Smith's Publishing Co., 1904; 3rd ed. 1915; 4th
    ed. revised and enlarged, 1929. 158 pp. </bib>
   <notes> "It is not syllables that recur, nor accents, but the time-spaces or periods occupied
    partly by syllables, partly by pause. . . . [these] periods I hold to be the basis of English
    verse-structure." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E305">
   <bib>Omond, T. S. "'Dactylic' Verse in English." The Spectator 129 (1922): 635. </bib>
   <notes> Cites examples of dactylic and anapestic lines, arguing that between them there is no
    essential difference whatsoever. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E306">
   <bib>-----. English Verse-Structure (A Prefatory Study). Edinburgh: David Douglas, 1897; rpt
    Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1969, 1974. 59 pp. </bib>
   <notes> In his first monograph Omond posits his axiom that the "period" not the "foot" is the
    unit of English meter. Our verse exhibits quantity (metrical quantity is not to be confused with
    natural linguistic quantity), accent (too fickle to serve as a basis for meter), and pause [here
    Omond fails to distinguish stress-verse from syllable-counting verse], but its crucial feature
    is time not accent. There is no real distinction between iambic and trochaic, or anapestic and
    dactylic, meters; the only true meters in English are "common time" and "triple time." But in
    any event all that the prosodist can hope to elucidate are the Principles of verse, not any
    fixed Rules. Omond surveys briefly the theories of Symonds, Bridges, Guest, Poe, Jenkin,
    Sylvester, Steele, and Ellis. Note his rather over-emphatic denial (on p. 54) of any character
    that he is confusing meter with rhythm; that tone of defensiveness is indeed justified. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E307">
   <bib>-----. "A Hint on the Reading of Verse." Journal of Education, June 1908. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E308">
   <bib>-----. Metrical Rhythm. Tunbridge Wells: R. Pelton, 1905; rpt Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft
    Library Editions, 1973; rpt Norwood, Pa.: Norwood Editions, 1976. 27 pp. </bib>
   <notes> The first half of this essay reviews Thomson's The Basis of English Rhythm (E405), which
    presents a system of temporal metrics even more extensive than Lanier's (E364) or Steele's
    (E394). Omond himself accepts Time as the key to verse-structure but rejects the Musical
    analogy, so he allows himself the latter half of this essay to succinctly propound his own
    theory of meter. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E309">
   <bib>-----. Some Thoughts About Verse. English Association Pamphlet no. 55. Oxford: Oxford
    University Press, 1923. 20 pp. </bib>
   <notes> In an elegant and engaging prose style, stripped of tendentiousness and technicalities,
    Omond proffers, succinctly, his views in favor of "time-structure as the basis of metre,"
    isochrony, "Common" and "Triple Time," pyrrhic feet, line-length [he believes the tetrameter to
    be our most native form], free verse [opposes], terminology [awkward], "metrical pause,"
    alliteration, and "inversion." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E310">
   <bib>-----. A Study of Metre. London: Grant Richards, 1903; rpt London: Alexander Moring, 1920;
    rpt New York: Lemma Publications, 1972. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by J. W. Bright in MLN 37 (1922): 59-62, with reply by Omond, pp. 181-83; in The New
    Republic 31 (1922): 224-25; by E. P. Morton (appreciatively) in The Dial 40-41 (1906): 381; in
    The Nation 77 (1903): 118- 20; in The Academy 64 (1903): 363-64 (see also the letters by Verrier
    and Omond on "Metre," pp. 517-18, 542). The Temporalist theory of verse-structure, deriving from
    Sir Joshua Steele in 1775 (E393), has been most forcefully promoted in our own century by Omond,
    who is very likely also the most articulate spokesman in the entire tradition, This monograph is
    the formal statement of his theory, as opposed to his other works of a
    historical/bibliographical nature. "All meter is essentially rhythmical. That is to say, it
    consists of equal units ["periods"], uniform as regards duration. . . . If periods constitute
    rhythm, they must do so by uniform succession. Syllables do not supply this absolute recurrence;
    their order of succession is changeful, capricious. They need to be contrasted with underlying
    uniformity. That substratum seems afforded by time. Isochronous periods form the units of metre"
    (italics original). The axiom of the theory, then, is that the verse-line is a temporal
    phenomenon constituted of equidurational segments. Accents are mainly "signaling elements" used
    simply to mark or signal periodicities. Accent cannot be the constituent or base of meter, Omond
    argues, because stress rules in English are too fickle to regulate verse: word-accent is too
    easily disfigured by sentence-accent (but see p. 24). Omond cautiously accepts Blake's theory of
    monopressures (E484) to explain the physiology of accent. Quantity is acknowledged a fact of our
    language and our verse, though ornamental rather than constitutive; poets who write verse "based
    solely on quantity may be said to sin against the genius of their language." Metrical pause is a
    crucial component of meter as well, this to be distinguished from the various pauses for effect
    in performance. Of metrical types Omond allows four: two measures, duple and triple, in two
    modes, rising and falling. (Blake's theory allows a maximum of three syllables per
    monopressure.) Readers with keen noses may detect here the bouquet of old wine in new bottles.
    Short Appendix on "Pseudo-Classical Measures." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E311">
   <bib>Omond, T. S., et al. "'Inverted Feet' in Verse." The Academy 75 (1908): 329-30, 351-52,
    401, 429, 451-52, 475-76, 498-99, 524, 548-49, 571. </bib>
   <notes> A vigorous demonstration that at least two common fallacies in metrics--first, that
    inverted feet are not to be explained as inversions but as trisyllabic + monosyllabic feet, and
    second, that only speech-accents are required for scansion--may be entirely dissipated by
    clearly distinguishing between speech stress and metrical ictus. Inversions are to be explained
    by (1) ignoring the natural accent in favor of the meter, or (2) actual substitution in the
    meter. Excellently useful examples. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E312">
   <bib>Omond, T. S., et al. Letters to TLS, 23 September–23 December, 1920, pp. 619, 702, 858,
    877; 6 January–30 June 1921, pp. 11, 28, 76, 126, 179, 259, 276, 308, 355-56, 388, 404, 420. </bib>
   <notes> There is little exchange; Omond takes the occasion to promote theories of his own on the
    necessity of measured language to express emotion, the temporal basis of meter, isochrony,
    metrical disregard of speech accents, the difference of prose and verse ("purely a matter of our
    mental relation to the words"), the mischief of using classical terminology, and the irrelevance
    of quantitative verse in English ("piquant . . . scholars' toys"). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E313">
   <bib>Parsons, Rev. James C. English Versification for the Use of Students. Boston: Leach,
    Shewell &amp; Sanborn, 1891; rpt Boston and New York: 1891, 1920. 155 pp. Rev: by Tolman in MLN
    8 (1893): 219-22. </bib>
   <notes> A student's handbook with chapters covering all the conventional subjects, but marred by
    confusion of terms: what most prosodists would call the domain of meter is here termed rhythm,
    which is defined as the recurrence of accents at regular intervals of time, the accented
    syllable being either followed or preceded by as many as two unaccented ones. Meter then becomes
    merely the building-up of lines from such "rhythmic" "feet." He allows nine such "feet," finding
    the pyrrhic "very frequent." Worse still, it seems to matter little whether the accent is marked
    at the end of the foor or at the beginning. Parsons reinterates his concern for equal-timing but
    in practice only marks stresses. Such ambivalences are the seeds and sprouts of anarchy.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E314">
   <bib>Perry, John O. "The Temporal Analysis of Poems." British Journal of Aesthetics 5 (1965):
    227-45. </bib>
   <notes> This is unquestionably the best available discussion of the general nature of temporality
    in the form of the poem, with its implications for our understanding of the ontological status
    of "the poem," and hence the modes of respose which are available for criticism. Critics as a
    rule have been more than reluctant to even admit that a poem might have a temporal dimension,
    formally (some metrists have argued quite the reverse, of course), even though they recognize
    obvious temporal structuring in narration or plotting. But such a reluctance constitutes a
    confession of ignorance, and the perpetuation of it an appeal to ignorance. Some recent
    codifications in metrical theory offer hope of a solution, and the key to the whole problem
    might well be "abstract metre apprehended as a temporal construct." But in fact there are a
    number of "clocks" simultaneously regulating the timing of poetry (though note: the notion of
    isochonous lines in verse is false). Too, timing effects may arise from lexical and semantic
    levels as well as formal, if not all of these together. A proper temporal analytic should be
    operable at both the macro- and the micro-levels of the art-work. An extraordinarily dense yet
    cogent essay. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E315">
   <bib>Poe, Edgar Allan. "The Rationale of Verse." The Southern Literary Messenger 14
    (October-November 1848): 577-85, 673-82; </bib>
   <notes> rpt in The Complete Works of Edgar Allan Poe. Ed. James A. Harrison. 17 vols. New York:
    Thomas Y. Crowell, 1902; rpt New York: AMS Press, 1965. Vol. 14, pp. 209-65. Rpt in The
    Rationale of Verse: A Preliminary Edition, Incorporating Cognate Documents by Goold Brown,
    William Cullen Bryant, and James Davenport Whelpley. Ed. J. Arthur Greenwood. Princeton, N. J.:
    Wolfhart Book Co., 1968. This last edition is reviewed in a very perceptive article by Richard
    B. Eaton, </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E316">
   <bib>Eaton, Richard B. "Poet's Prosody in Perspective." Poe Studies 5 (1972): 61-62. </bib>
   <notes> Eaton takes issue with Greenwood's opinion of Poe's prosody by showing in detail the
    difficulty--and necessity--of an accurate historical understanding of prosodic thought in Poe's
    time, or any time. Poe "marked stresses, he confused them with quantities, and he counted
    syllables." Thus the temporalist theory of one age overlaps the stress theory of another age,
    and both are only partly or vaguely understood by poets as well as grammarians of the time. Is
    it any wonder prosody is so hard to read aright? The "Rationale" essay is an amplification of an
    earlier study, "Notes on English Verse," published in The Pioneer for March 1843. With his
    accustomed vigor of tendentious rhetorical argumentation, Poe takes up the standard of the old
    longs and shorts, insisting on the quantitative terminology for English as well as Latin. Accent
    determines length, but Poe's system of prosody really rests on time. Admitting that quantity is
    infinite in gradation yet clutching the dogma of one-long-equals-two-shorts, Poe is driven, by
    the fact of extrametrical syllables in lines, to devise a cumbersome--nearly ludicrous-- system
    of halves, thirds, and sixths, indicating syllabic duration in scansion with numbers and
    fractions, and allowing, besides the only feet he recognizes-- iamb, trochee, anapest, dactyl,
    spondee, and "caesura" (a single long syllable)-- a host of other misbegotten siblings: "bastard
    iamb," bastard dactyl," etc., and the "quick trochee." His refusal to admit pyrrhics into the
    system is transparently casuistical. And Poe differentiates rhythm from meter only in that the
    former identifies the feet while the latter denotes the number of feet per line, which is
    scarcely any cutting distinction. Altogether, the conservatism and the confusion in Poe's
    thinking produce an extravagently indefensible system. Yet against this one must say that the
    "Rationale" essay has been fertile ground for subsequent work: we find here the notion that a
    poetic line must "read itself" (be incapable of misarticulation), and concept of the "variable
    foot," and the abstract principle of "equality" (also termed "proportionality" and "equivalence"
    developed so importantly a century later by a distinguished Slavist and linguist. The
    "Philosophy of Composition" and "Poetic Principle" essays contain some remarks on versification
    that are too familiar to require notice. The "Marginalia" (vol. 16, pp. 111-12 in the Complete
    Works) reiterate Poe's fascination with strict laws of mathematics, and he reminds us that laws
    deduced from observable effects are by no means identical to those controlling composition. The
    salutary effect of rhyme is said to depend on recurrence at "unanticipated intervals." Finally,
    Poe's 1843 review of The Poets and Poetry of America contains a short synopsis of his views of
    versification (vol. 11 of the Works, pp. 225-36). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E317">
   <bib>Prall, D. W. "Rhythm as Temporal Structure." In his Aesthetic Judgment. New York: Thomas Y.
    Crowell, 1929; rpt 1967. pp. 138-77. </bib>
   <notes> Section 6 is on verse. The ideas presented here are developed more amply and closely in
    Prall's later work (next entry). Suzanne Langer's analysis is heavily indebted to Prall.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E318">
   <bib>-----. "Temporal Patterns: Verse Rhythm." Aesthetic Analysis. New York: Thomas Y. Crowell,
    1936; rpt. 1967. pp. 93-134. </bib>
   <notes> A discursive yet meticulous analysis of temporal ordering by an eminent but now-neglected
    American philosopher. We give form to time by measure. Nothing can be gained for scansion by
    "misapplied classical terms or loose musical analogies"; verse is ordered by measures and
    "counts" (beats). Iambic pentameter is nothing of the sort, but rather "three measures to the
    line, each measure divided into halves, and each half further divided into three counts.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E319">
   <bib>Robertson, John M. Essays Towards a Critical Method. London: T. F. Unwin, 1889. </bib>
   <notes> Expanded as: </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E320">
   <bib>Robertson, John M. New Essays Toward a Critical Method. London and New York: J. Lane, 1897. </bib>
   <notes> 378 pp. In this latter see "Appendix: Accent, Quantity, and Feet." Omond (A5) observed
    drily that Robertson simply "perpetuated Poe's confusion of Quantity and Accent in The Rationale
    of Verse." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E321">
   <bib>Roe, Richard. The Elements of English Metre, both in prose and verse, illustrated under a
    variety of examples. . . . London: The Author, 1801, 94 pp. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E322">
   <bib>-----. The Principles of Rhythm both in Speech and Music, especially as exhibited in the
    mechanism of English verse. Dublin, 1823. </bib>
   <notes> "Metre consists of a succession of parts, in subordinated proportions . . . which parts,
    abstractly considered, are those solely of time or duration. Hence metre . . . is the same
    wherever found; and all that is adventitious, or extrinsic, is to be sought for in the nature of
    its vehicle." "A foot . . . takes up about two-thirds of a second, and may therefore contain as
    many syllables as can conveniently be uttered in that time." All feet are equal in time, no
    matter how comprised; notation consists of a linear graph under the verse, marked off with short
    vertical lines, so as to denote the greater or lesser duration of the words in the feet by
    greater or lesser extension along the line. Finally, to confound clarity altogether, "feet are
    distinguished by accent and quantity. But, as feet distinguished by accent and quantity do not
    constitute different species of metre, but only give by their mixture an agreeable variety to
    the cadence; and as accent is the more general mark of distinction, and also commonly
    accompanies quantity; so, for the greater ease of expression, I shall mostly speak of the former
    indiscriminately for both." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E323">
   <bib>Routh, James. "English Iambic Meter." PMLA 40 (1925): 921-32; </bib>
   <notes> rpt in B187. Expanding on Scripture's work in phonetics, Routh distinguishes "word
    stress," "verse stress," and "sense stress"; he accepts isochrony (subject to pauses) and
    concludes that "English iambic verse is rhythmically nothing but English prose so readjusted
    that, on an average, four ordinary prose accents, with the addition of a fifth accent made for
    the occasion by the heightening of an ordinarily less-heavily stressed syllable, supply the
    singing accents." Statistics. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E324">
   <bib>Rudmose-Brown, Thomas B. Étude comparée de la versification francaise et de la
    versification anglaise: L'alexandrin et le blank verse. Grenoble: Allier Brothers, 1905. 216 pp. </bib>
   <notes> His dissertation at Grenoble. Holding that "there is no essential difference between the
    Latin and Greek system and the modern system" of verse, the author proffers his thesis that both
    English and French meters are founded on a single common principle, "the measure of isochronous
    intervals of time." Along the way he gives considerable attention to most of the major English
    and French metrical theorists. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E325">
   <bib>-----. "The Principles of English Versification." Dublin Magazine 5 (1930): 5-18. </bib>
   <notes> Initially a hostile review of Katherine Wilson (E411) and acoustic/musical metrics in
    general, but the article soon expands to a wide compass of foreign meters and metrists in order
    to substantiate the author's thesis that syllabic verse and stress verse are two distinct
    species of animal, producing a very curious hybrid type when crossed (as in English). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E326">
   <bib>Schwartz, Elias. "Rhythm and Meaning in English Verse." Criticism 6 (1964): 246- 55. </bib>
   <notes> Reply by </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E327">
   <bib>John Oliver Perry, "The Relationship Between Rhythm and Meaning." Criticism 7 (1965):
    373-78; rejoinder by Schwartz, pp. 379-81. </bib>
   <notes> Schwartz's essay is revised and expanded as chapter 5 ("Rhythm and Meaning") of his The
    Forms of Feeling. Port Washington, N. Y.: Kennikat Press, 1972. pp. 59-71. Imitative and
    expressive effects acheived by stress-patterns in lines of verse are not rhythmical because both
    rhythm and meter are "essentially temporal structures." Schwartz gives an Aristotelian account
    of rhythm: whereas the drama can only reproduce the external signs of inner emotion in others,
    rhythm "corresponds in its movement with the movement of the soul" directly. For Schwartz,
    whatever is abstracted is meter; the rhythm is inseparable from performance. Meters he thinks
    may correspond to "general classes of feelings." All this is wooly, which Perry has little
    trouble showing in his reply. Imitative and expressive metrical effects are not to be denied,
    and Schwartz's whole account of the treatment of emotions in poetry is superficial, as is his
    conception of the semantic structure of verse. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E328">
   <bib>Schwartz, Elias K., W. K. Wimsatt, Jr., and Monroe C. Beardsley. "Rhythm and 'Exercises in
    Abstraction.'" PMLA 77 (1962): 668-74. </bib>
   <notes> Schwartz's side of the exchange (pp. 668-69, 671-74) is expanded as "Rhythm and Meter,"
    chapter 4 of his The Forms of Feeling. Port Washington, N. Y.: Kennikat Press, 1972. pp. 43-58.
    Schwartz's reply to Wimsatt and Beardsley (E700) perceives clearly that unless they "recognize
    the psychological status of rhythm, they cannot be made to see its temporal basis." W &amp; B
    amplify Leonard Meyer's distinction between pulse, rhythm, and meter, then clarify their own
    position: "meter. . . is what we actually hear in the poem when it is read aloud; rhythm is
    something which is aroused in the mind by means of the poem's meter, something which is felt by
    the listener and which in turn stirs his further feelings." (Thus, for them meter is objective,
    rhythm subjective, while for Schwartz meter is subjective and rhythm objective.) S. responds
    with his counterassertion "that meter is real, that it is distinct from rhythm, and that both
    meter and rhythm are temporally measured." Being perfectly abstract, meter is never actually
    heard, but rather is inferred: It "exists in the mind of the reader" as a "normative pattern" of
    expectation. What we actually perceive are the strong stresses and the temporal intervals
    between them, intervals roughly but not precisely equivalent. It is neither necessary nor
    possible to show that syllabic durations are physically equal. "Meter is an ideal temporal
    norm." The meter and rhythm are correlated by the reader simultanously, via "double audition."
    Schwartz argues that inverted feet are preceded by pauses, so that "trochaic substitutions" are
    actually a pause + a monosyllable + an anapest. W &amp; B's final response expresses skepticism
    as to this last and reasserts their belief that Schwartz actually proves their own case.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E329">
   <bib>Schweinitz, George W., de. "Dipodism in English Verse in the Nineteenth and Twentieth
    Centuries: A Study in the Relations Between Thematics and Metrics." University of Iowa Abstracts
    of Dissertations 9 (1949-52): 394-96. </bib>
   <notes> Chapters 1-3 trace the development of dipodic meter from Burns to Auden (its use seems
    mainly confined to the oral tradition); chapter 4 surveys its treatment by prosodists (Patmore,
    Lanier); chapter 5 attempts to correlate some genres and themes with the use of this meter.
    Indebted to Stewart (E333) for scansion symbols. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E330">
   <bib>Smith, Egerton. The Principles of English Metre. London: Oxford University Press, 1923; rpt
    Westport, Conn.: Greenwood Press, 1970. 326 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in London Mercury 8 (1923): 441; in The New Statesman 21 (1923): 650- 52; in TLS, 20
    March 1924. p. 171 (also correspondence on May 22 and 29); in English Studies 8 (1926): 56-58.
    The most authoritative statement of the Temporal theory of metrics: Smith's scholarly and
    synoptic work should be consulted in precedence to Omond (E310), Lanier (E3654), or Patmore
    (E384). Here one will find full chapters on metrical pause, metrical equivalence (trisyllabic,
    monosyllabic, and combined substitutions), nature of the ictus (weight and accent), quantity,
    hypercatalectic verse, metrical variation, syllabic theories of verse, song-verse, English
    meters, imitations of Classical meters, rime, stanza, free verse, blank verse, sonnets, and
    fixed forms. Long Glossary of terms. Smith himself offers little that is new to the theory, but
    his treatise easily outdistances all its peers in tone, treatment, and scholarship: the
    explanation of the theory is remarkably balanced and thorough, leaving nothing slighted or
    ignored on any side, pursuing the argument with civility, and offering frequent, minute
    digressions on definitions of terms, Classical antecedents or etymologies, and treatment of
    various problems by other metrists. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E331">
   <bib>Stewart, George R., Jr. "The Iambic-Trochaic Theory in Relation to Musical Notation." JEGP
    24 (1925): 61-71. </bib>
   <notes> Musical metrists have a problem with the metrical terms "iambic/trochaic" and
    "rising/falling," since these distinctions do not exist in music. One or the other--analogy or
    terminology--must go. Stewart, assuming that trochaic meter equals falling rhythm, counts the
    number of falling, rising, and neutral stress-patterns in the phrases of several "trochaic" and
    "iambic" poems, discovering thereby that the proportions of all three are in each case quite
    mixed, with many neutrals, and that the falling phrases are only slightly more frequent in
    "trochaic" verse than in "iambic," and not at all predominant even within the "trochaic." All
    that one can say is that the mixes are pretty thorough and that we discriminate some extremely
    subtle shifts quite markedly. But the distinctions "iambic/trochaic" and "rising/falling"
    Stewart finds unwarranted. Cf. Newton (E799), Hascall (E783), Creek (E18), Crapsey (E516), and
    Atkins (E467). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E332">
   <bib>-----. "A Method Toward the Study of Dipodic Verse." PMLA 39 (1924): 979-89. </bib>
   <notes> Extending his earlier work on the ballad meters, Stewart shows that the pattern x - | x -
    | x - | x - | x - | x - | x - is a septenary in Pope but a dipodic line in Kipling, based on the
    proportional frequency of occurrence of each of the parts of speech in each position. But a more
    simplified analysis a Dipodic Index can be derived for a given poem, and Stewart finds that
    dipodism begins to be clearly perceived at about index 35. But the most intriguing question of
    all is that of the tendency toward dipodic structure in the stress system of the language
    itself. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E333">
   <bib>-----. The Technique of English Verse. New York: Holt, Rinehart, &amp; Winston, 1930; rpt
    Port Washington, N. Y.: Kennikat Press, 1966. 235 pp. </bib>
   <notes> One of the most substantial studies published in the first half of this century; Stewart
    is perhaps the least temporal (certainly the least dognatically so) of Timers, and his book can
    make that theory more attractive to confirmed Stressers than any of the rest. His approach
    offers two distinctive and significant features: Phrasing, and Dipodism. For scansion the
    following siglia are employed: S O o p l P = = = = = = stressed syllable heavy unstress
    unstressed syllable pause for an unstress light stress pause for a stress; these Stewart deploys
    in groups in scansions so as to indicate not only the stress- pattern of the line (note he has
    four levels available rather than two) but also the syntactic structure, the phrasal boundaries.
    The system is simple, efficient, and doubly informative. Notice that Stewart's simple and
    compound phrasing corresponds precisely to constituent analysis in structural linguistics, and
    that by including phrase-structure he is able to account for "rising" and "falling" rhythms more
    adequately than anyone else. On the temporal aspect he is modest but firm: the "time-structures"
    of verse are "practically identical," and so Stewart begins the first foot of the line with the
    first stress. Unfortunately this forces him to call a 5-foot line a 4-foot line with "a little
    left over at beginning and end" which is neither elegant nor efficient, and Stewart wisely
    chooses not to pursue this course. He allows four feet--the monosyllabic, iambic, trochaic, and
    amphibrachic--and of course he makes much of the metrical pause. When he comes to quadruple
    meters, i.e. Dipodic verse, his analysis again merits praise for charting new terrain. His
    scansion notation allows much further progress than Patmore (E384) was able to make. But notice:
    nearly all his examples are ballads, and the import of his analysis is to rewrite stress-verse
    as a highly regular meter bordering on foot-verse by the liberal insertion of metrical pauses;
    the ultimate result of this tack will be to eliminate entirely the concept of stress-verse,
    where the slack syllables are unconstrained. Much food for thought here. See Stewart's article
    at K379 and his earlier monograph at E892, and see also Stevenson (E400). Note E292. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E334">
   <bib>Taig, Thomas. Rhythm and Metre. Cardiff: University of Wales Press, 1929. 140 pp. Rev: in
    TLS, 20 June 1929, p. 491; in Review of English Studies 6 (1930): 116- 20. </bib>
   <notes> Not strictly a "timer," Taig is cognizant of the complexity of these matters, and also of
    the natural limitations of assertion: the result is a refreshingly restrained, yet sophisticated
    discourse. He considers both "timers" and "stressers" to be mistaken in believing that any
    single dimension of speech- rhythm is supreme for metrical purposes or solely worthy of
    notation; as an alternative, he employs (with conscious dissatisfaction) two systems, a wave-
    graph and musical notation, to indicate both duration and intensity. Three basic metrical
    patterns or systems are identified: Variable, Doubtful, and Fixed. In the Variable pattern
    (example: Old English alliterative), the constraints are relatively weak. In the Doubtful
    pattern, the numbering of syllables is rigidly controlled but their timing is generally
    uncontrolled, causing metrists to be "doubtful" of the nature of the prosodic base. But as the
    constraints increase, the timing too is Fixed, creating that sort of stress-verse where the
    reader can scarcely miss the intended timing of the line. A long fifth chapter takes up the
    "Spoken Line," a subject, current opinion notwithstanding, which is indispensable to metrics.
    Taig's analysis of the double-stranded rope of performance--the metrical expectation perceived
    simultaneously with the rhythmic/syntactic ordering--raises the tantalizing prospect that "the
    forms employed in the utterance can be reduced to a few well-defined types, that the
    speech-variations of blank verse can be classified at least as easily as those of the
    alliterative line in Old English." This analogy is pursued through a short analysis, and three
    Groups of line-patterns are also identified which seem to operate in the metrical orchestration
    of long passages of verse (5 waves, 4, and 3). A short final chapter traces the parallel
    historical development of rhythmical counterpoint in music and in verse. Replacing Taig's term
    "wave" by the more familiar "bar" or "foot," one might claim that this book is merely old
    familiar tea in an unfamiliar package, yet the seeming glibness of the term belies the broad
    learning and deep thinking consistently evidenced here. Any reader who believes that deep
    thinking can come to a trivial and conventional conclusion does not understand deep thinking.
    This is a difficult book, in both the negative and positive sense of the word. See also: B122,
    E845, N53, N60. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E335">
   <bib>Andrews, C[larence] E[dward]. The Writing and Reading of Verse. New York: D. Appleton,
    1918. 327 pp. </bib>
   <notes> An introductory handbook of versification; Part 1 sets forth the Principles and Part 2
    the metrical and stanzaic forms. The metrical theory followed is Lanier's Musical approach
    (E364). Nothing bears notice except this definition of terms: "Stress is metrical emphasis;
    Accent is sense emphasis. When these do not coincide throughout a line we have: Light Stress,
    emphasis required by the meter but not by sense, or Extra Accent, emphasis required by sense but
    not by meter." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E336">
   <bib>Bayfield, M. A. The Measures of the Poets: A New System of English Prosody. Cambridge:
    Cambridge University Press, 1919; rpt Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1970; rpt
    Norwood, Pa,: Norwood Editions, 1975. 107 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by Hulbert in MP 17 (1920): 727-29; in MLN 35 (1920): 122-26. See also Stockley
    (E88). Bayfield pushes the musical analogy to verse to its ultimate logical end, that is, into
    absurdity: since the stress begins the bar in music, therefore all English verse has always been
    written in a trochaic meter; indeed, by definition, the iambic foot cannot exist. Stress is
    acknowledged central to English verse, but stressed syllables are said to last twice as long as
    unstressed in utterance, and recur at equal intervals, i.e. in "triple-time." Bayfield seems to
    have read none of his contemporaries. Now, Omond's view of this whole business was that the
    whole uproar raised by the appearance of Bayfield's books was pointless and unnecessary, the
    argument itself being tautology and calling for no response. In other words, if everyone is
    agreed on the stressing of a line, it makes no difference where the bar-marks for foot-division
    are drawn: it makes no difference whether we call the line iambic or trochaic. Possibly this
    logic is too radically simple to strike me as correct, but I cannot believe that (1) there is no
    syntactic or metrical difference between what are commonly called "rising rhythms" and "falling
    rhythms," or that (2) the long history of what poets thought they were doing, in writing in the
    iambic pentameter tradition, counts for nothing at all. Cf. his E1093 and E1094. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E337">
   <bib>Beardsley, Monroe C. "Verse and Music." Wimsatt (A20), pp. 238-52. </bib>
   <notes> Essential reading--as much for what is not said as what is. Beardsley turns directly to
    the most important available (and widely ignored) source currently on rhythm in music, Cooper
    and Meyer (N30), summarizing its premises: "in music, meter is pulse plus accent, rhythm is
    accent plus grouping," and "a 'rhythmic pattern' in music is what prosodists are wont to call a
    'metrical pattern' in verse." (Note the implication that rhythm is a higher-order concept than
    meter.) He does not, however, adequately explain their hierarchical scansions, as he does not
    adequately explain his own--his second subject. Proposed is a scansion-system I have not seen
    elsewhere, which appears to account for both metrical pattern and syntactic (i.e. rhythmical)
    grouping, and can explain the complex, unified, double sense of movement in lines of verse that
    we are commonly aware of. Beardsley then reviews, disinterestedly, the arguments for and against
    a musical scansion of verse, as well as the problems in setting verse to music. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E338">
   <bib>Brown, Calvin, S. "Can Musical Notation Help English Scansion?" JAAC 23 (1965): 329-34. </bib>
   <notes> Literally or systematically, no. It "indicates a regularity that [we] do not hear,
    creates more problems than it solves, and is in general more of a nuisance than a help." No one
    learns musical notation in order to apply it to verse, and any systematic application of the
    analogy becomes strained at once. Isochronous time-periods also seem unnatural contrivances, the
    span between stresses often varying widely. "Individual syllables have no simple relations in
    objective fact." Hence musical scansion is legitimized neither theoretically, practically, nor
    objectively. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E339">
   <bib>Browne, William Hand. "Certain Considerations Touching the Structure of English Verse." MLN
    4 (1889): 193-202. </bib>
   <notes> Approves of the methods of Lanier and T. R. Price; believes that the poetic line is
    composed of "staves" (originally, hemistichs), which "may be of any length, from a single
    syllable carrying one accent, to a whole line less one such syllable." Objects to all borrowed
    Greek terminology for prosody. A curio. Had he been reading Guest (E543)? </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E340">
   <bib>Chandler, Albert R. "Rhythms of Speech." Beauty and Human Nature. New York: D.
    Appleton-Century Company, 1934. pp. 238-76. </bib>
   <notes> See also the following chapter. Chandler reviews in detail the approaches of Scripture,
    Wallin, Patterson, and Griffith, finally settling on a musical scansion of the verse-line as his
    own preference. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E341">
   <bib>Chapman, James. The Music, or Melody and Rhythmus of Language. Edinburgh: Michael Anderson,
    1818; rpt Hildesheim, Germany, and New York: Georg Olms, 1972. </bib>
   <notes> Followed by a second volume soon after: </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E342">
   <bib>-----. The Original Rhythmical Grammar of the English Language. Edinburgh: James Robertson,
    1821. </bib>
   <notes> The two volumes may be treated together, since despite some variance of terminology and
    scansion notation between them they both seem to be virtual reprints of the system in Steele's
    Prosodia Rationalis (E394). One might naturally expect that the diligent student would wish to
    see his master's teachings carried on a generation or two after him, but such a characterization
    would be insufficient here: whole sections of Steele are reproduced verbatim by Chapman. Of the
    whole second work, the last section of chapter 13, "Errors of Prosodians," bears the most
    interest to us now: Chapman criticizes Pemberton, Mitford, Walker, Murray, and Carey. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E343">
   <bib>Croll, Morris W. "Music and Metrics: A Reconsideration." SP 20 (1923): 388-94; </bib>
   <notes> rpt in Style, Rhetoric, and Rhythm: Essays by Morris W. Croll. Ed. J. Max Patrick and
    Robert O. Evans. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1966. pp. 430- 36. Lamenting the lapses
    of contemporary metrical theory from Lanier's system of musical scansion (E364), Croll reasserts
    that "the musical interpretation of our verse form is the correct statement of its rhythmical
    law." Syllable-counting, the concepts of iambic, trochaic, etc., and the notions of rising and
    falling rhythms "are real facts, of course, but they are not facts of rhythm"; they are "merely
    optional modes of procedure, customs that may be observed or not at pleasure." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E344">
   <bib>-----. "The Rhythm of English Verse." In Style, Rhetoric, and Rhythm: Essays by Morris W.
    Croll. Ed. J. Max Patrick and Robert O. Evans. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1966. pp.
    365-429. </bib>
   <notes> Introduction to the essay and its historical context by Evans, pp. 361-64. The essay was
    first printed in mimeograph by the English Dept. of Princeton in 1929, though it may have
    existed as early as 1923-24. See s.v. Croll in NUC. Rev: in Anglia 85 (1967): 184-85; in
    Seventeenth Century News 25 (1967): 45- 46; in Modern Language Journal 51 (1967): 112-13; in
    Thought 42 (1967): 295- 97. This short monograph outlines Croll's system of musical metrics,
    which is derived from Lanier (E364) and closely parallel to Thomson (E404), whose work Croll
    apparently did not see until its publication in 1923, the date of the first version of his own
    essay. For scansion notation Croll employs a system of superlinear horizontal bar-lines with
    flags to denote time-values. He considers iambic/trochaic verse to be in triple time,
    anapestic/dactylic in duple, so stressed syllables are tacitly granted double the duration of
    unstressed. Following illustration of these two, a long section treats the "double or compound
    measure," i.e. dipodic meter. Here Croll treats the ballad meters, though his attempt to scan
    every ballad as if it were dipodic is very obviously unreasonable. A final section postulates
    the existence of yet one higher level, the "double-compound" (double-dipodic) measure, in effect
    in double- quadruple time, one measure would therefore contain four degrees of stress, i.e.
    This, too, seems an improbable complication, and examples are scarce. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E345">
   <bib>Dabney, Julia Parker. The Musical Basis of Verse: A Scientific Study of the Principles of
    Poetic Composition. London: Longmans, Green, 1901; rpt New York: AMS Press, 1970; </bib>
   <notes>rpt Westport, Conn.: Greenwood Press, 1968. 269 pp. See also her subsequent article in
    E345a The Athenaeum, 18 April 1903, pp. 506-7, on "The Musical Basis of Verse," and a very late
    précis, E346 "The Relations Between Music and Poetry." Music Quarterly 13 (1927): 377- 83.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E347">
   <bib>Douady, Jules. La Prosodie Anglaise. Paris, Didier, 1928. 322 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in Revue Belge de Philologie et d'Histoire 9 (1930): 606-7. An introduction to the
    forms: his scansions are Musical. Chaucer is said to be the founder of our poetry, and many of
    the quotations are taken from rather obscure poets. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E348">
   <bib>Eliot, T. S. The Music of Poetry. Glasgow: Jackson and Sons, 1942; rpt in Partisan Review 9
    (1942): 450-65. </bib>
   <notes> Rpt in his On Poetry and Poets. London: Faber &amp; Faber, and New York: Farrar, Straus,
    &amp; Giroux, 1957; rpt Noonday Press, 1961, pp. 17-33. There is too much ore here to mine in
    one extract: Eliot reminds us that the study of metrics is a useful and necessary occupation but
    only at an early stage, for "a study of anatomy will not teach you how to make a hen lay eggs":
    assimilation and imitation create good poetry, not scansion or analysis. English verse has
    received influence from many foreign verse-forms, and Eliot suggests that there may be two
    systems operant at once in our meter even as accent and quantity both were attended to in late
    Latin verse. But he insists that meter cannot be studied apart from meaning. There is no such
    thing as appreciating the melody of verse without understanding its sense. "Melody" is not mere
    mellifluousness, and the mimetic or semantic range of pure sound is quite limited. Altogether,
    poetry is close kin to conversation, and cannot afford to stray far or long from the common
    speech. Blank verse and free verse are discussed. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E349">
   <bib>Ellis, Oliver C. de C. "Stream and Structure in English Poetry." In Poetic Technique.
    Altrincham: John Sherratt &amp; Son, 1949. pp. 11-64. </bib>
   <notes> The three gentlemen who jointly wrote and published this book comprise the Poetry Lover's
    Fellowship; that may be taken as some indication of its quality. Mr. Ellis believes that
    "English Prosody, then, is a science of music." In his system every foot begins with a stress.
    He opines that the decasyllabic line is the progeny of two of the older octosyllables, so that
    the normal pentameter is to be thought of as followed by six metrical rests. An original
    scansion-system is included. (The following essay by Geoffrey Johnson, however, on composing
    verse, contains some very sensible suggestions.) Cf. I10. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E350">
   <bib>-----. "Suggestions for a System of Scansion of English." In the Manchester Quarterly and
    Poetry Review for Nov. 1923; rpt in his Poetry and Science. Manchester: Sharratt &amp; Hughes,
    1924. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E351">
   <bib>Frye, Northrop. "Music in Poetry." University of Toronto Quarterly 11 (1942): 167- 79. </bib>
   <notes> Subsequent alternative versions of this essay appear as: </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E352">
   <bib>-----. "The Rhythm of Recurrence: Epos." In his Anatomy of Criticism. Princeton: Princeton
    University Press, 1957; rpt New York: Atheneum, 1965. pp. 251-62. Rpt in Gross (A23), pp.
    168-80. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E353">
   <bib>-----. "Lexis and Melos." Introduction to Frye (A15), pp. ix-xxvii. </bib>
   <notes> Interested in "what affinities to music may be discerned in the features that poetry
    shares with music--sound and rhythm," Frye elucidates some of the manifold "confusion between
    the musical and the euphonious" in poetry. "Music" of course is not "beauty of sound" but
    "organization of sound." Hence, "when we find a careful balancing of vowels and consonants and a
    dreamy sensuous flow of sound, we are probably dealing with an unmusical poet. Pope, Keats, and
    Tennyson are all unmusical. . . . When we find sharp barking accents, crabbed and obscure
    language, mouthfuls of consonants, and long, lumbering polysyllables, we are probably dealing
    with melos, or poetry which shows an analogy to music, if not an actual influence from it."
    Metrically, "when in poetry we have a predominating stress accent and a variable number of
    syllables between two stresses . . . we have musical poetry, that is, poetry which resembles in
    its structure the music contemporary with it." Frye believes that behind the iambic pentameter
    lies a four-stress line which "seems to be inherent in the structure of the English language,"
    adducing as proof some musical scansions of lines from Lydgate and Skelton. (This I think is a
    confusion of meter for rhythm.) Imitative effects are also discussed. In sum, Frye posits that
    the two varieties of poetic melos arise "the one from the external influence of music, the
    other, internal, from the language itself." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E354">
   <bib>Gardiner, William. The Music of Nature. . . . London: Longman, Brown, Green and Longmans,
    1832; 2nd ed. 1843. </bib>
   <notes> See chapters 50 and 51 on "Rhythm in Language" and "Quantity" (pp. 476- 98). Gardiner
    scans verse by musical scoring, the stress after the bar, iambic lines usually being set as
    Common (duple) Time. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E355">
   <bib>Hallock-Greenewalt, Mary. "Pulse in Verbal Rhythm." Poet-Lore 16 (1905): 79-85. </bib>
   <notes> Wherever the pied piper Lanier should lead. . . . Her only new verse to the song is to
    propose anew the old cardiac systole-and diastole as the basis of double meters. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E356">
   <bib>Hendren, Joseph W. Time and Stress in English Verse with Special Reference to Lanier's
    Theory of Rhythm. Rice Institute Pamphlets, vol. 46, no. 2. Houston, Texas: The Rice Institute,
    1959. 72 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Intended as an apologia for and simplified exposition of Lanier's system of temporal
    metrics (E364). Hendren considers the verse measure "the exact counterpart of that used in
    music," he considers the binary meters to be in triple rhythm, and he scans alternately with
    musical notation and with numerals indicating syllabic duration (he believes that the auditor
    can discriminate syllable-lengths of 3⁄4, 1, 11⁄2, and 2). And though Hendren recognizes four
    degrees of stress, his scansions strongly suggest a belief that stressed syllables are doubled
    in length--a ghost we had thought long since buried. Hendren has no evidence for that claim
    other than an appeal to authority, and he recognizes rightly that objective studies of rhythm
    are less relevant than subjective (perceptual) ones. But any thorough study of Lanier will find
    some salient observations and sensible adjustments of his theory herein. See Hendren's earlier
    monograph at E871. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E357">
   <bib>Hendren, Joseph W., W. K. Wimsatt, Jr., and Monroe C. Beardsley. "A Word for Rhythm and a
    Word for Meter." PMLA 76 (1961): 300-8. </bib>
   <notes> [Hendren has the first six pages, W &amp; B the last three.] Hendren begins his reply to
    Wimsatt and Beardsley by collapsing several crucial distinctions ("to reject measured time as an
    integral character of metrical structure is to deny the existence of verse rhythm"; "we cannot.
    . . separate meter from the performance"; and tapping out the beats of a blank- verse line "will
    show its triple rhythm and its plain arrangement of long and short syllables"), then argues that
    the isochronism which may be demonstrated in tapping out lines is not mathematically precise;
    the durations are but "sensibly equal." He recites the obligatory temporalist litany of
    Poetry-and- Music, approves the work of Snell, Schramm, and Thomson, then returns finally to a
    methodical countering of the points raised by Wimsatt and Beardsley, especially the picket-fence
    analogy. Wimsatt and Beardsley in their reply expand their scope to Hendren's monograph (E356),
    attacking his assumptions ("measures when recited will often differ enormously") as well as the
    experimental evidence for isochrony. They respond to Hendren's crucial query "If the stresses
    are not measuring time in the recitation of the verse, what are we to suppose they are measuring
    instead?" with a trenchant answer, "Syllables, number of syllables, are measured--syllables
    grouped according to stress and slack, so many slacks between each stress." And they summarize
    their traditional position concisely: "Syllabic quantitative meters are not possible in English
    because syllabic quantity is not an objective feature of English. Isochronism (of intervals
    between primary stresses, as urged by the linguists) is not a principle of English meter,
    because if it is an actual feature of the language, it is a constant feature and is hence not
    susceptible of the manipulation by which the poet distinguishes metrical from non-metrical."
    They even go so far as to disparage Hendren for "the irrelevance of his theory to actual
    problems of English meter." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E358">
   <bib>Hollander, John. "The Music of Poetry." JAAC 15 (1956): 232-44. </bib>
   <notes> With a supple grasp of the whole warp of western melos and with some deft analytical
    fingering, Hollander ravels out the knotted-up skeins of music's relation to verse, vis |`a vis
    meter, from classical Greece to Sidney Lanier. That is, he traces out the divergence of verse
    meter from its origin in music, the later forced conflations of dissimilar metrical systems in
    verse (Latin with Greek, Romance with Old English), and the resultant confounding of prosodic
    terminology. Finally, his remarks on the convenient imprecisions and the category mistakes of
    musical theories of meter are trenchant, and his insistence on a recognition of the distinction
    between performative and descriptive systems of scansion amounts to something like a sine qua
    non for all future theories of English meter. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E359">
   <bib>Jacob, Cary F. "On Tonality in English Verse." Sewanee Review 17 (1909): 448-57. </bib>
   <notes> A surprisingly detailed immersion in the fundamentals of acoustic phonetics yields a
    surprising conclusion: strictly speaking, none of the three musical terms key, pitch, or harmony
    may be properly used to describe verse-structure-- verse has only tone-color (the difference
    between two instruments playing the same note). Musical terminology really ought not be used at
    all for verse. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E360">
   <bib>Jones, Llewellyn. "The Mechanics of Poetry." Bookman 56 (1922): 503-5. </bib>
   <notes> Reviewing a primer of versification, Jones rebukes its authors for basing their metrical
    theory on accent alone, rather than on time, which he himself supports. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E361">
   <bib>-----. "A Principle of Prosody." The Freeman 5 (1922): 162. Reply by C. E. Russell, p. 402;
    rejoinder by Jones, p. 593. </bib>
   <notes> Jones disagrees with Lanier (E364) in claiming that lines are filled with both syllables
    and pauses, so that the timing is duple (2/4) not triple (3/8), each bar consisting of two
    quarter-notes rather than an eighth-note and a quarter-note. Russell defends Lanier. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E362">
   <bib>Kafalenos, Emma M. "Possibililties of Isochrony: A Study of Rhythm in Modern Poetry." DAI
    35 (1974): 2273A (Washington). </bib>
   <notes> Approves of musical notation of the temporal dimension of poetry but notes that Hopkins
    wrote isochronous feet without resorting to musical notation and that William Carlos Williams
    wrote what amounts to short isochronous lines. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E363">
   <bib>Kroeger, A. E. "Rhythm." Southern Magazine 11 (1872): 220-24. </bib>
   <notes> We are told that "reasoning has nothing whatever to do with the matter of rhythm," a
    statement this article indeed bears out. Kroeger scans by length, one long equalling two shorts,
    but marks meter (calling it rhythm) with musical notation, a procedure which results in the
    incredible blunder of calling iambic-trochaic patterns triple time and dactylic-anapestic
    patterns duple (common) time. Even so, he complains that the macron-breve notation of poetry
    cannot indicate more subtle variations of tempo, and he admits that quantities in speech vary
    enormously. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E364">
   <bib>Lanier, Sidney. The Science of English Verse. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1880, rpt
    1898, 1901, 1927. </bib>
   <notes> "Imprint dates on copies vary." Rpt in The Centennial Edition of the Works of Sidney
    Lanier. Vol. II. The Science of English Verse and Essays on Music. Ed. P. F. Baum. Baltimore:
    Johns Hopkins University Press, 1945. (Baum's Introduction should not be overlooked). A seminal
    text in metrical theory, less interesting in itself perhaps than for the sake of the enormous
    influence it exerted on critical conceptions of poetic form for more than forty years after its
    publication. The axiom of all of Lanier's thought is that human speech (and, by extension,
    spoken verse-- poetry) is a sound-phenomenon, produced by a reed instrument (the vocal
    apparatus), and organized in duration , pitch, and intensity (principally the first), making it
    theoretically indistinguishable from music. That is, he conceives of verse and music not merely
    as analogous phenomena but as coincident in origin and correpondent in ordering-principles--"the
    two species of the genus art of sound." From this one axiom of the identity of all patterning of
    Sound, three propositions may be derived which apply equally to music and verse and produce
    differing effects merely due to the qualitative differences in "musical sounds" and "spoken
    words": these propositions express the co-ordinations of the ear in terms of duration, pitch,
    and quality as (respectively) Rhythm, Tune, and Tone-Color. Rhythm, the subject which occupies
    Part I of the treatise, may be classed as primary or secondary and occurs in 3-rhythm and
    4-rhythm modes, as we learn in music. Lanier thinks "no circumstance in the history of
    aesthetics so curious as the overpowering passion of the English [poetic] ear for 3-rhythm as
    opposed to 4-rhythm." For scansion, of course, the line of verse is denoted by a time-signature
    and musical notes expressing the durations of the syllables. Metrical (musical) rests are
    therefore permissible and valuable features of verse-structure. Part II, entirely ignored by
    subsequent scholars, treats Tune; Part III, rhyme (at length), alliteration (short notes), and
    Sylvester's "phonetic syzygy" (E402). Metrical analysis of Shakespeare's verse receives
    considerable attention; see pp. 185-224. Lanier's achievement in the history of metrical theory
    was to systematize the verse-music analogy and to popularize the musical scansion-sigla
    suggested by Sir Joshua Steele (E394) a century earlier. A century later he is not followed at
    all, his musical scansions actually being thought unduly precise and therefore denoting features
    of performance rather than paradigms. And there is the added twist that Lanier's scansions
    depart from all established musical convention in not placing the accented note first in the
    bar--this seems a flagrant inconsistency in the sort of theory where consistency is only less
    crucial a criterion than clarity. Omond (A5) appreciated the book (see pp. 195-202) but
    Saintsbury rattled his armor (A8, vol. 3, pp. 493-97). See also J214. For two modern
    applications of Lanier's theory to Old and Middle English verse, see Pope (J241, J242) and
    Schiller (K329). See also Hendren (E356) and Niessner (E382). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E365">
   <bib>Lightfoot, Marjorie J. "Accent and Time in Descriptive Prosody." Word 26 (1970): 47-64. </bib>
   <notes> Discussion of linguistic research on and conceptions of syllable, word-stress,
    sentence-stress, and isochronism. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E366">
   <bib>-----. "Description and Transcription of Temporal Patterns of Rhythm in English Verse."
    Language and Style 7 (1974): 192-204. </bib>
   <notes> Adducing all the familiar authorities, the author inquires as to which type of musical
    notation would be most accurate for English verse--the divisive (regular measure), the additive
    (changes in time-signature between measures), or the free temporal (no fixed time-signatures at
    all). She concludes that the first of these notations, the one we have known all along, is the
    best. Cf Mussulman (E380). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E367">
   <bib>-----. "Numerical, Sequential, and Temporal Patterns in English Verse." Quarterly Journal
    of Speech 57 (1971): 193-203. </bib>
   <notes> Observes, simply, that numbering (e.g. of syllables and/or of stresses), sequence (e.g.
    alternation of stress and slack), and timing (isochronous intervals between stresses) are three
    principles that conjointly organize verbal sequences into verse. She considers all three to be
    constitutive of meter. Both musical and acoustic approaches are embraced: scansions are in
    musical notation, and iambic verse is said to be in Triple time based on Snell's conclusion
    (E452) that stressed syllables are twice as long as unstressed. Meter we can only identify
    through Performance. Verse-types: syllabic, accentual-syllabic, measured accentual, and
    unmeasured accentual (free). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E368">
   <bib>-----. "Temporal Prosody: Verse Feet, Measures, Time, Syllabic Distribution, and
    Isochronous Accent." Language and Style 7 (1974): 245-60. </bib>
   <notes> An effort at clarifying some of the key terms in temporal metrics. "Verse feet" specify
    the numerical and sequential constraints on the verse, whereas "measures" reveal the durations
    of syllables and pauses "in verse rhythm." Lightfoot does not explicitly differentiate meter
    from rhythm, though she does hold that "verse feet and measures identify different phenomena,
    both of which are valuable to descriptive prosody." The same meter may have various
    time-signatures (though iambic verse is usually in triple time, stressed syllables being double
    the length of unstressed), though transpositions occur in performance. "Rhetorical accents" are
    preserved as "isochronous accents" in the line even when they do not match the ideal pattern of
    "metrical stresses." The formulations here are new, but the concepts underneath them are not.
    Occam's Razor is wanted badly. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E369">
   <bib>MacColl, D. S. "Metre." Saturday Review 141 (1926): 153-54, 186-87; rpt in his Confessions
    of a Keeper, and Other Papers. London: Alexander Macklehose, 1931. pp. 313-22. </bib>
   <notes> A critique of E. A. Sonnenschein (E236), particularly his rejection of isochronism;
    MacColl believes the stress-intervals to be perceptually equal if not absolutely so, and he
    argues for the metrical pause. Sonnenschein replies amicably (in Saturday Review) on pp. 293-94;
    final exchange of letters, p. 336 (MacColl) and pp. 367-68 (Sonnenschein). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E370">
   <bib>-----. "Patmore and Hopkins: Sense and Nonsense in English Prosody." London Mercury 38
    (1938): 217-24. </bib>
   <notes> Sometime after delivering his English Association lecture (E371), MacColl discovered
    Patmore's essay on the musical theory of meter (E384) which he here Elevates, with all due
    pieties, at the same time Excommunicating Hopkins for his "mistaken views on prosody," pausing
    only to enumerate the latter's metrical Sins. He believes that Hopkins recanted late in his life
    in favor of Patmore's views, and that no one has noticed this fact. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E371">
   <bib>-----. "Rhythm in English Verse, Prose, and Speech." Essays and Studies 5 (1914): 7-50. </bib>
   <notes> "My contentions will be (1) that the distinction between 'quantitative' and 'accentual'
    verse is a false one; that the current theory of English prosody [Saintsbury's] is
    unintelligible save by reference to the classical, and that the classical itself is a musical
    theory; (2) that the musical law of rhythm alone can explain the structure of English verse
    [Lanier]; (3) that it also underlies the structure not only of 'numerous' prose, but of all
    prose and speech." The essay is a long critique of Saintsbury's position from the perspective of
    Lanier and Thomson. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E372">
   <bib>Malden, Henry. "On Greek and English Versification." Proceedings of the Philological
    Society [retitled Transactions after 1854] 3 (1847): 95-110. </bib>
   <notes> A very good example of the confusions fostered in British studies of versification in the
    middle of the last century by undue allegiance to classical philology. Malden, distinguishing
    between syllabic duration, pitch, and stress, reaffirms the commonplaces that quantity in
    English is simply more variable than in Classical Greek, and that while Greek accent was by
    pitch English is by stress, but he considers the guiding principle of versification in both
    languages to be Time, i.e. Music. "Indeed it is the peculiar characteristic of verse in all
    languages . . . that it is speech arranged in musical time." "Time, as essential to music, must
    be essential to verse." In English versification the feet are isochronous measures of time
    "beginning or ending" with a stress, preferably the former, Malden thinks, exactly as in music.
    The influence of Steele's disciples is still strong ca. 1850. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E373">
   <bib>Manwaring, Edward. Of Harmony in Numbers in Latin and English Prose and in English Poetry.
    London: M. Cooper, 1744; rpt New York: Garland, 1970. 53 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A treatise on rhythm--the clausulae of rhythmical prose and the regularized metrical feet
    of poetry. The whole discourse must have seemed pedantic even in the eighteenth century; it is
    saturated with classical prosodic and musical terminology and is therefore quite convoluted.
    "Numbers" seems to mean "feet" (pp. 10-11), these being the aggregates of "Rhythms" (12-14),
    both irregular and regular. Of verse (Chapter 4), Manwaring holds that English Versification is
    "made according to the diatonic scale," i.e., the "half and whole Times" of the iambic or
    trochaic feet are analogous to the half and whole steps or Tones in music. Iambic verse on this
    account would be in triple time, and in fact it is barred so that the "first syllable in every
    full foot" is "acuted" (accent is based on pitch here). English verse, we are told near the end,
    must attend to accent, quantity, and "Concord" (caesure-placement); the pentameter "is a seventh
    in music." Fussell's remarks on this work (E34) show only that he failed to read it closely, or
    altogether. Cf. M130. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E374">
   <bib>Monroe, Harriet. Poets &amp; Their Art. New York: Macmillan, 1926. </bib>
   <notes> The concluding Section on "Poetic Rhythms" reprints four essays, three from Poetry--"A
    Word About Prosody" (E377), "Rhythms of English Verse" (E376), "Dr. Patterson's Researches"
    (E242)--and one from the English Journal, "The Free Verse Movement," (E1511). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E375">
   <bib>-----. "Prosody." Poetry 20 (1922): 148-52. </bib>
   <notes> Vigorous applause for the recent "scientific" approach to metrics, with particular
    approval of the musical notation-system for exactitude. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E376">
   <bib>-----. "Rhythms of English Verse." Poetry 3 (1913-14): 61-68, 100-11; </bib>
   <notes>rpt in slightly revised form in her Poets &amp; Their Art (E374), pp. 268-84. Praises
    Lanier as the sole Authority under the heavens, and triumphantly exclaims that "English verse is
    as quantitative as Greek verse." Musical scansions. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E377">
   <bib>-----. "A Word about Prosody." Poetry 27 (1925): 149-53; </bib>
   <notes> rpt in her Poets &amp; Their Art (E374), pp. 263-67. The essay is--in her words--"a
    repetition of the obvious." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E378">
   <bib>More, Paul Elmer. "Rhythm and the Science of Poetry." Sewanee Review 10 (1902): 406-17; </bib>
   <notes> rpt as "The Science of English Verse." in his Shelburne Essays, First Series. 2 vols.
    Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1904. Vol. 1, pp. 103-21. A review of Liddell (E424), whom More
    redresses for an offensive messianic tone. Along the way, More himself postulates Three Laws of
    Rhythm ("Rhythm . . . is a branch of acoustics, is a measurement of time marked off by the
    regular recurrence of similar events, in verse is . . . much less absolute and regular than
    rhythm in music. . . ."). He argues that quantity is inseparable from stress (and also pitch) in
    both the Classical languages and Modern English, but that the laws of quantity in Modern English
    are not the same as those for the classical languages; he notes a "rhythmizing instinct" in our
    reading aloud of nursery rhymes, as opposed to our "normal unrhythmical enunciation" of speech.
    Approves of Lanier, Goodell, and Schipper. E379 Readers interested in More's reputation may
    consult R. Shafer's Paul Elmer More and American Criticism (1935). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E380">
   <bib>Mussulman, Joseph A. "A Descriptive System of Musical Prosody." Centennial Review of Arts
    and Sciences 9 (1965): 332-47. </bib>
   <notes> No writer who has wanted to describe verse rhythm with musical notation has displayed
    greater depth of comprehension about musical structure than this one. The concepts of divisive,
    additive, free, and numerical meter in music provide a more sophisticated and flexible prosodic
    instrument, each type of meter having relative advantages and defects for describing various
    situations in verse-lines. Do not neglect the final footnote on pitch. See also Lightfoot
    (E366). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E381">
   <bib>Newman, Ernest. "The Rationale of English Verse-Rhythm." The Weekly Critical Review
    (Paris), 3, 10, 17, 24 September 1903. </bib>
   <notes> Not seen; very obscure. Discussed in Omond (A5), p. 245, however. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E382">
   <bib>Neissner, Gertrude. Sidney Lanier als Lyriker und seine metrischen Theorien. Diss., Vienna,
    1939. 112 pp. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E383">
   <bib>Odell, J. An Essay on the Elements, Accents, and Prosody of the English Language. London:
    Lackington, Allen, 1806; rpt Hildescheim, Germany, and New York: Georg Olms, 1969. </bib>
   <notes> Quantity is as distinct from accent in classical Greek as it is in modern English; our
    verse is based on "emphasis," the term "accent" being used for pitch or musical tone, as in
    classical speech. Thereafter, Odell follows Steele (E394) on "cadence": "Rhythmus is a general
    term, comprising two distinct modes, which are called common time and triple time, or common and
    triple metre. . . . rhythmus has its essence in arsis and thesis, but metre in syllables and in
    their difference." Syllable length by position is rejected, and since emphasis is said to have
    controlled quantity even in Greek, "metre is always subordinate to rhythmus." The metrical
    cadence is "equivalent to a musical bar," and so begins an emphatic syllable; it may contain a
    metrical rest, so that all the cadences will have equal duration. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E384">
   <bib>Patmore, Coventry. "English Metrical Critics." North British Review 27 (1857): 127-61. </bib>
   <notes> Revised and reprinted as "Prefatory Study on English Metrical Law" in his Amelia,
    Tamerton Church-Tower, Etc., London: G. Bell and Sons, 1878; this text changed its title but
    otherwise remained virtually unchanged through many subsequent reprintings. There is an
    excellent twentieth-century edition: </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E385">
   <bib>Roth, Sister Mary Augustine. Coventry Patmore's "Essay on English Metrical Law": A Critical
    Edition with a Commentary. Washington, D. C.: Catholic University of America Press, 1961. </bib>
   <notes> (Her dissertation.) Roth takes her text of the Essay from the 5th Collective Edition of
    Patmore's Poems, 1894. Her bibliography contains 281 entries. The "critics" Patmore has in mind
    are mainly Guest (E543) and O'Brian (M151). Though most of Patmore's ideas were not new at the
    time, still his essay has been very influential, and it stands as one of the three or four major
    documents in the evolution of the Temporal theory of verse. In the essay he pursues vigorously
    the case for verse being divided into "isochronous intervals," though he holds these to be
    perceptually (mentally) equal rather than physically. These intervals are to be demarcated by
    "an 'ictus' or 'beat,' actual or mental. . . . it has no material and external existence at
    all." (One notes the conflation or confusion of metrical ictus and speech stress here.) Mitford
    (E600) and Steele (E394) are praised, and Hegel's Aesthetics provides some further foundation.
    But Patmore's most important and original contribution is his argument that English verse is all
    dipodic: "the elementary measure, or integer, of English verse is double the measure of ordinary
    prose,--that is to say, it is the space which is bounded by alternate accents; that every verse
    proper contains two, three, or four of these 'metres,' or as with a little allowance they may be
    called, 'dipodes.'" He also argues the importance of medial and final metrical pauses. O'Brian's
    work prompts an argument that alliteration in Anglo-Saxon was no mere ornament but a metrical
    device needed to mark the accents; by extension, the, rhyme in modern verse serves a metrical
    function also. See also Stobie (E944) chapter 4 of Holloway (E914), and Patmore (E937). For
    further information on Patmore, see </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E386">
   <bib>Baum, P. F. "Coventry Patmore's Literary Criticism" in University of California Chronicle
    25 (1923): 244-60. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E387">
   <bib>[Ramsay Allan, Jr.] An Enquiry into the principles of English versification, with some
    analogical remarks upon the versification of the Ancients. Manuscript in the British Library. </bib>
   <notes> n.p., n.d. Omond owned the MS before bequeathing it; see his discussion in A5, pp. 95-
    97. Ramsay generally follows Steele (E394). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E388">
   <bib>Riley, Alice C. D. The Elements of English Verse Correlated to Music: A Manual for
    Teachers. Chicago: C. F. Summy Co., 1906. 148 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Intended for the teaching of rhythm--in verse as in music, and vice versa--to children in
    the elementary grades. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E389">
   <bib>Ruskin, John. Elements of English Prosody for Use in St. George's Schools. Orpington
    (Kent): George Allen, 1880. 62 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A pamphlet tract for students. Saintsbury (A8) noted the "eccentricities of
    nomenclature," and concluded that "Mr. Ruskin was himself very imperfectly trained in these
    matters" (vol.3, p. 450). If Ruskin in fact was trained, this would be fair, but he seems mainly
    interested in setting verse lines to music, and he hardly troubles himself about precision of
    either thought or terms (he believes that "the stress-accent on English words will be found
    always to involve delay as well as energy or loudness of pronunciation, and that, at all events
    in verse, it may be considered as identical with quantity"; if the examples he gives prove
    false, we are told to substitute other correct ones), so I suspect that he taught himself such
    as he knows. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E390">
   <bib>Sapir, Edward. "The Musical Foundations of Verse." JEGP 20 (1921): 213-28. </bib>
   <notes> Perhaps a misleading title: Sapir approves of Amy Lowell's idea that the lineation of
    free verse corresponds to demarcations of time, yet though free verse is timed, S. admits that
    standard English verse is stressed verse, and that in fact the feature used to mark the
    "sectioning" or "periodic structure" of verse can be any of a number of things. He also thinks
    "the same rhythmic contour" will be verse or prose depending on how deeply it strikes our
    attention--it is not an objective phenomenon. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E391">
   <bib>Scholl, Evelyn H. "English Metre Once More." PMLA 63 (1948): 293-326. </bib>
   <notes> An effort to show that the meter of the songs written by the school of English lutenists
    (1597-1632) is in fact the meter of all modern English verse--that is, a temporal meter, barred
    in measures beginning with a stress, in duple and triple time, with metrical rests. The chief
    feature of the lute-songs is that the musical rhythm is completely subordinate to the words; in
    fact, they are "like speech with a definite pitch." In general Scholl rejects the notion that
    syllable- counting is one axiom of English meter. She also discusses, in the course of her
    exposition, the views of virtually all the major modern metrists. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E392">
   <bib>Sibbald, James, ed. Chronicle of Scottish Poetry; from the thirteenth century to the union
    of the crowns. 4 vols. Edinburgh; C. Stewart, 1802. </bib>
   <notes> See the preface to vol. 4, esp. pp. xlvi-lxiii: "in many of the antient Scottish, as well
    as English poems. . . . the measure seems rather to be regulated by the division of the time
    required for recitation of the line, into portions like musical phrases; not necessarily equal
    in the number of syllables, but requiring an equal period of time for their pronunciation. . . .
    which in music is called common time." "The mechanism and scheme of Anglo-Saxon versification
    seem to depend entirely upon quantity . . . without any other regard to the number of syllables
    than that the longest line shall not contain more than twice the number of the shortest
    corresponding line." Musical scoring is used for scansion of examples. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E393">
   <bib>Steele, Sir Joshua. An Essay Towards Establishing the Melody and Measure of Speech, to be
    Expressed and Perpetrated by Peculiar Symbols. London: J. Almon, 1775; </bib>
   <notes> facsimile rpt: English Linguistics 1500-1880, no. 172. Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar Press,
    1969; rpt Ann Arbor: University Microfilms, 1953. Expanded in the second edition as: </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E394">
   <bib>-----. Prosodia Rationalis: or an Essay Towards Establishing [etc.]. London: T. Payne &amp;
    Son, 1779. </bib>
   <notes> Bysshe's influence on the eighteenth century is greater (simply by precedence), but
    Steele is among the two or three most influential figures in the entire history of English
    versification, as well as a major figure in the history of phonetics. He is responsible for
    charting an entirely new course in verse- theory, despite the fact that his magnum opus,
    Prosodia Rationalis, is a treatise on suprasegmental phonology, not metrics. Steele's theory of
    verse influenced Thelwall, Odell, Chapman, and Roe, and after them Coventry Patmore, A. J.
    Ellis, Sidney Lanier, T. S. Omond, and John C. Pope. He devoted his career to devising a set of
    orthographic symbols to transcribe the inflectional features of English speech (stress, pitch,
    and duration) and, by extension, the structure of English verse; these were quasi-musical. Hence
    Steele transfers the structure of music, vis |`a vis verse, from the level of analogy to the
    level of identity. In adapting music to describe verse he was preceded by Gildon (E164), but
    Gildon never applied the idea beyond a mere example. Steele deserves the credit for elaborating
    the system formally; he shrugs off the half-hearted efforts of the earlier prosodists and
    reaches out to grasp the wider theoretical implications of the ideas he is pursuing. Prosodia
    Rationalis, however, is more a book to be read about than read. It began as a reply to Lord
    Monboddo and his doctrine that "the music of our language. . . [is] nothing better than the
    music of a drum, in which we perceive no difference except that of louder or softer." But as
    each section of Steele's argument was completed, he sent it off for Lord Monboddo's comments,
    which were then incorporated along with Steele's replies in subsequent sections of the book:
    "consequently, Prosodia Rationalis is, in effect, an extended dialogue between the two men, to
    which is appended, in the second edition, an additional series of questions from other hands,
    together with the author's replies." (Omond). Steele obviously went far out of his way to
    present his system as even-handedly as possible. His system distinguishes five features: •
    accent: by which Steele means pitch, or tone, and which he is perceptive enough to recognize
    changes in even slides, not in discrete or abrupt shifts; • quantity: meaning relative duration
    of syllables or pauses. Steele uses quasi- musical symbols to denote "accent" and quantity
    simultaneously, the heads denoting the direction of pitch-change, the tails (tails above heads
    in his system), duration: • emphasis: a term Steele uses ambivalently and confusedly to denote
    both the absolute duration between stresses (cadence, bar), and also the stresses themselves,
    based on the analogy of the systolic circulatory system of the human body, the heartbeat of
    which is both regular and intensified. Hence Steele considers syllables either "heavy" or
    "light" (poise is the general term for this phenomenon), and he distinguishes three degrees,
    heavy, light, and lightest; "the rhythmus or measure of speech is the number of cadences in a
    line or stanza"; • pause: in four durations: semibreve, minim, crotchet, and quaver; and •
    force: or loudness, also in four gradations: louder, loud, soft, softer. In versification, time
    not syllables is to be the basis of meter; the concept of the metrical pause originates with
    Steele. But he recognizes also that even if the structure of verse is actually that of music the
    pentameter line cannot be scanned with bar-lines before the stresses, i.e. with a final
    monosyllabic foot and an initial anacrusis; instead, Steele scans it with a stressed rest
    beginning the line and an unstressed rest at the end: (/p) I do not think that you will ever
    know (p). The five-foot line thus becomes a six- or even as much as an eight- in some cases;
    Steele does not seem to mind the extremities of this position. Mixing of common and triple time
    is therefore no problem at all, nor is trisyllabic substitution, since everything depends soley
    on time. Altogether, one may say that Steele's ideas were, with some slight qualifications,
    essentially sound. The notion of emphasis is the chief weakness of his analysis. Some of his
    transcriptions are unreliable, but since he had no technology to support him, no recorders or
    oscilloscopes for playback, he had to rely on his ear alone for the one and only hearing of the
    line. In the history of phonetics he position is very firm. In the history of versification he
    represents the first, perhaps the foremost, proponent of a view that has not been widely
    accepted as the correct account of meter but which has been widely recognized as legitimate,
    even indispensable, as an account of rhythm. After Lanier even several of the prominent Temporal
    metrists shied away from the concept of music as anything more than analogy to verse, yet these
    judgments could be comfortably made from the distance of a century and a half from Steele's
    pioneering work. Reference: Omond (A5), pp. 87-95, Fussell (E34), pp. 139-43. See also the
    following very informative essays: </notes>
  </item>




  <item id="E395">
   <bib>Abercrombie, David. "Steele, Mondboddo, and Garrick." In his Studies in Phonetics and
    Linguistics. London: Oxford University Press, 1965. pp. 35-44. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>




  <item id="E396">
   <bib>Alkon, Paul K. "Joshua Steele and the Melody of Speech." Language and Speech 2 (1959):
    154-74. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>




  <item id="E397">
   <bib>Barker, Marie L. "Joshua Steele on Speech-Melody (1779)." MLR 19 (1924): 169-74. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>




  <item id="E398">
   <bib>Neuman, John B. "The Phonetic Aspect of Joshua Steele's System of Prosody." Speech
    Monographs 18 (1951): 279-87. </bib>
   <notes> See also D. Crystal, Prosodic Systems and Intonation in English (1969), 22-25. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E399">
   <bib>Stetson, R. H., and T. E. Tuthill. "Measurement of Rhythmic Unit-Groups at Different
    Tempos." Studies From the Psychological Laboratory of Oberlin College. In Psychological
    Monographs, vol. 32, no. 3 (1923), pp. 41-51. </bib>
   <notes> This happens to be a study of whether or not the actual performances of rhythmic groups
    in music (e.g. "iambs," sixteenth-notes followed by accented dotted-eights) correspond to the
    theoretical values (they do not, the authors conclude), but it has relevance for Temporalist
    metrics, since its conclusion is that "the sense of rhythm cannot be explained in terms of
    judgment of time intervals." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E400">
   <bib>Stevenson, Charles L. "The Rhythm of English Verse." JAAC 28 (1970): 327-44. </bib>
   <notes> Drawing upon concepts from the earlier work of Steele (E394), Andrews (E335), and Stewart
    (E333), Stevenson deploys a full-fledged theory of English meter that rests on both stressing
    and timing, distinguishes metrical ictus from speech stress, adopts some of the features of the
    analogy of verse to music while recognizing sensibly and explicitly the weaknesses and
    limitations of that analogy, and derives a "foot-free prosody" based on the whole line. With a
    very striking illustration, Stevenson demonstrates the difference between "metrical stress"
    (ictus) and "accent" (speech stress) and the functions of the former: as conspicuously regular
    markers of the metrical paradigm, metrical stresses "have a partitioning effect: they help us to
    see the pattern as composed of sub-patterns. . . . [they] provide consecutive 'frames' that
    divide the total 'picture' into smaller 'pictures.' The frames, moreover, are similar frames. So
    they invite us to compare the pictures within them, noticing when they are alike and when they
    are different. . . . The frames help us to make the visual comparisons on which our sense of
    organization depends." The two features which establish ictus are approximately equal timing and
    limited variability of syllables (i.e. the number of syllables must be relatively small and
    relatively uniform). Stevenson sees that timing is only "a part of the explanation."
    Alliteration, stanza-pattern, and pitch can also occasionally help mark ictus. "Metrical
    stresses are as if ornamental frames, of aesthetic interest in their own right." Music is indeed
    analogous to verse in that the stresses in verse begin "stress-intervals" equivalent to musical
    bars (Stevenson claims that "to call a stress-interval by the name foot" is "entirely
    misleading," but what's in a name? The concept of sub-linear metrical unit is retained.), and
    metrical pauses are admissible, as is syncopation. Yet pauses in verse may be ambivalent, though
    not so in music, and verse-pauses cannot be "held" over several beats as in music, even besides
    the obviously greater syllabic variation possible in music, so the analogy has decided
    limitations and is "always a little misleading" anyway. But syllabic length and syntactic
    phrase-structure, though both quite variable in English verse, are susceptible to marking in
    scansion and should be noticed. Finally, in a long and important penultimate section, Stevenson
    argues that the stubborn retention of the "foot" by prosodists has been a result of a
    fundamental misconception: they have been sidetracked by undue emphasis on the beginning of the
    line and have believed that the metering of the rest of the line must operate on a principle of
    the "best echo" of the onset. But the phrase-structure usually belies any clear echoes, and the
    "foot" therefore appears very artificial. This misconception may have arisen from the general
    nature of poetic composition, which Stevenson hypothosizes operates mainly on the principle of
    limited syllabic variability between ictus, extended also to the line-beginning. Such a general
    principle produces "facts" capable of varying interpretation. Stevenson's interpretation, on the
    whole, is provocative and extensive; his approach is remarkably sensible. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E401">
   <bib>Sumera, Magdalena. "The Temporal Tradition in the Study of Verse Structure." Linguistics,
    no. 62 (1970), pp. 44-65. </bib>
   <notes> A useful, if partisan, capsule history of the Temporal theory of meter, written by a
    resolute rhythmist and active admirer of Thomson. The essay synopsizes the theories of Sir
    Joshua Steele, Walter Young, James Chapman, Coventry Patmore, James Lecky, William Thomson, and
    Morris Croll. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E402">
   <bib>Sylvester, J[ames] J[oseph]. The Laws of Verse or Principles of Versification Exemplified
    in Metrical Translations. . . . London: Longmans, Green, 1870. 152 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by Ingleby in The Fortnightly Review 14 (1870): 488. Sylvester was a professional
    mathematician, and the bulk of this book prints his verse translations and an inaugural address
    in mathematics. But the Preface and pp. 64-71 discuss metrics. Sylvester agrees completely with
    the theory of Poe (E315), adding only Musical notation for scansion. Rhythm, we are told,
    consists of Metric, Chromatick, and Synectic, meter itself comprising Accent, Quantity, and
    Suspensions. The Synectic, again, consists of Anastomosis, Symptosis, and Phonetic Syzygy; it is
    this last that especially interests him. He may have found this idea in Mason (E584-86) though
    the sense is not the same and the transmission seems tenuous. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E403">
   <bib>Thelwall, John. Selections for the Illustration of a Course of Instructions on the Rhythmus
    and Utterance of the English Language. . . . London: J. McGreery, 1812. </bib>
   <notes> The section on "Principles of Metrical Proportion, and of Rhythmus," pp. xliv-lviii, is
    the one of interest to us in this elocution and rhetoric manual; Thelwall adopts Steele's (E394)
    principles and notation entirely. For reasons I cannot fathom, Omond (A5) devotes three pages to
    this work. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E404">
   <bib>Thomson, William. The Rhythm of Speech. Glasgow: Maclehose, Jackson, 1923. 559 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Many adherents of musical metrics consider Thomson the authoritative treatment of the
    subject in this century; at the very least it can be said that the massive volume was ahead of
    its time. The last third of the book concerns Greek and Latin verse. Chapters 1-5 treat the
    general nature of temporal grouping or Rhythm ("a series of blows" is the crux of the
    definition). Chapter 6 gives the formal statement of his 24 Laws of Speech Rhythm, followed by
    exemplary analyses in Chapter 7. Chapter 8 redresses Lanier and Goodell for accepting only
    quantity (Thomson is commonly very contentious without naming names at all), chapters 11 and 12,
    Mayor, Latham, and Bridges for accepting only accent. Chapter 9 discusses "unsuspected meters"
    and chapter 10 provides analyses. See the longer discussion of Thomson in Sumera (E401).
    Thomson's magnum opus was based on the following earlier publications: </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E405">
   <bib>-----. The Basis of English Rhythm. Glasgow: W. &amp; R. Holmes, 1904; 2nd ed. 1906. 63 pp. </bib>
   <notes> The pamphlet promulgates Lanier's (E364) system of musical scansion. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E406">
   <bib>-----. Laws of Speech-Rhythm. Glasgow: James Maclehose and Sons, 1916. 16 pp. + chart. </bib>
   <notes> The 24 Laws which constitute chapter 6 of his later, principle work (E404). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E407">
   <bib>-----. Notes to accompany a paper on 'The Role of Numbers in the Rhythm of Ancient and
    Modern Languages.' Edinburgh, 1907. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E408">
   <bib>-----. Rhythm and Scansion. Edinburgh: H. &amp; J. Pillans &amp; Wilson, [1911]. 28 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A small tract; reprinted from The Secondary School Journal. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E409">
   <bib>Tolman, Albert H. "Lanier's Science of English Verse." In The 46th Birthday of Sidney
    Lanier. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1888. pp. 37-45; </bib>
   <notes> rpt in his The Views about Hamlet and Other Essays. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1904; pp.
    105-13. A highly appreciative, non-technical review. Prosodic work before Lanier is said to have
    been "a scientific ignorance." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E410">
   <bib>Webb, Richard, and E. R. Coulson. Sidney Lanier: Poet and Prosodist. Athens: University of
    Georga Press, 1941. 108 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in MLN 57 (1942): 214-15. Two dissapointingly elementary and unhelpful essays by men
    who scarcely accepted Lanier's views. The Science of English Verse is taken up on pp. 39-53 and
    its reviews (generally hostile) are reprinted on pp. 82-97. But one may be amused to read that
    "the trouble began early in life in an inability to choose between music and poetry." Amused or
    not, one should not trouble to look up this puerile book. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E411">
   <bib>Wilson, Katherine M. The Real Rhythm in English Poetry. Aberdeen: Aberdeen University
    Press, 1929; </bib>
   <notes> rpt Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1972; rpt Norwood, Pa.: Norwood Editions,
    1975, 1977; rpt Philadelphia: R. West, 1978. 171 pp. Rev: in TLS, 5 December 1929, p. 1024.
    Following an opening review (and rejection) of the Pychological approach to poetic rhythm
    (Attention Span and Kinesthesis theories), the author comes to her point and method. "We are
    going to collate the prosody of poetry with that of music." This thesis she will pursue even
    beyond the shortcomings of Lanier and others. "We may define [the foot] in accents, in
    quantities, as an isochronous interval, a monopressure, a centroid. . . . We disagree in almost
    every conceivable way about the composition of the foot, delimiting and refining, but here let
    us take our motto--Prosody, beware of exclusion. There is not one thing, metrical form." This is
    fair, but worse follows: "Consequently we shall not narrow the meaning of foot, but follow
    Saintsbury's lead in shirking a farther definition." But her scansions show not only notes and
    bars but also "feet" which seem to be basically syntactic and word boundaries. She accepts a
    system from Prout's Musical Form providing "Fore Phrase" and "After Phrase," each of these
    having an A and B section, each section having a and b "feet" (exemplified in the hemistichic
    octosyllabic couplet). This system allows her to describe (for fifty pages) complex phrasing
    patterns in verse. See also her essay </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E412">
   <bib>Wilson, Katherine M. "Meaning in Poetry and Music." Music &amp; Letters 9 (1928): 211-25. </bib>
   <notes>See also N136. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E413">
   <bib>Young, Walter. "An Essay on Rhythmical Measures." Transactions of the Royal Society of
    Edinburgh 2, part 2 (1786): 55-110. </bib>
   <notes> Remarks on rhythm both in music and in poetry, the latter beginning on p. 72; Young's
    view of poetic measure is derived entirely from his larger conception of rhythm in music, so
    that for example iambic feet in verse are simply trochaic feet with anacrusis. Part 2 of the
    essay considers the pleasing forms of variation on "regular and perfect rhythm." See also: C40,
    C48, E164-65, E167, E419-20, E871, E994, E1009, E1474, E1499, E1511, I22, I36, N34. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E414">
   <bib>Brown, Warner. "Temporal and Accentual Rhythm." Psychological Review 18 (1911): 336-48. </bib>
   <notes> Concludes that the temporal rather than the accentual aspect of rhythm is fundamental.
    Experiments in finger-tapping and the reading of both iambic pentameters and nursery-rhyme
    verses show greater irregularities in force than in timing. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E415">
   <bib>-----. Time in English Verse Rhythm: An Empirical Study of Typical Verses by the Graphic
    Method. Archives of Psychology, no. 10; Columbia Contributions to Psychology, 17, no. 2. New
    York: The Science Press, 1908. 77 pp. </bib>
   <notes> An important study, unjustly neglected, which draws some radical conclusions from
    kymograph recordings of speech (Brown makes some trenchant criticisms of the assumptions behind
    all finger-tapping and motor-response methodologies) and applies them to theories of meter and
    rhythm. "There is nothing in the temporal regularity of simpler rhythmic processes which
    contradicts the assumption of a non-temporal theory of rhythm. And the lack of temporal
    regularity in verse makes such an assumption inoperative." There is no equality of durations in
    verse-rhythm. "Is it not natural, then, to conclude that time equality is an inference derived
    from the apparent equality of two impressions or expressions and confirmed by actual equalities
    in many rhythms, but not really a constitutive factor in the rhythm at all? . . . In the end it
    will be much simpler to talk of a rhythm which is actually present . . . the beats of which are
    not fixed in time, while its effect upon us is that of a series of equal time intervals." And
    none of the six theories of meter hitherto advanced (quantitative, accentual, musical,
    stress-verse, centroid, temporal- syllabic) can account for the facts by itself. An adequate
    theory of meter will have to account for everything--duration, intensity, pitch, etc. "The
    empirical facts leave no room for a theory of verse rhythm based merely on time." Cf.
    Boomsliter, Creel, and Hastings (E282). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E416">
   <bib>Dillon, George L. "Clause, Pause, and Punctuation in Poetry." Linguistics, no. 169 (1976),
    pp. 5-20. </bib>
   <notes> Repeats some of Snell's (E452) experiments, confirming her conclusion that line-end does
    not itself desiderate a pause unless the syntax at line-end does, and adding the discovery that
    readers tend to place pauses either by clause boundaries or by punctuation, with about one pause
    per line. Discusses (skeptically) the "silent stress" or "metrical pause" pp. 10-11. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E417">
   <bib>Hedges, James S. "Towards a Case for Isochronous Verse." 1975 Mid-America Linguistics
    Conference Papers. Ed. Francis Inglemann. Lawrence: University of Kansas Department of
    Linguistics, 1976. pp. 202-11. </bib>
   <notes> Criticizes the Shen-Peterson study of isochronism (D171) for mistaken methods based on
    misconstrued sources. "The boundaries of the isochronous units are not primary stresses, but are
    junctures instead." Oscilloscope analysis of recordings of Hopkin's "Pied Beauty" shows
    isochrony between junctures in the lines. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E418">
   <bib>Hurst, Albert. S., and John McKay. "Experiments in Time Relations of Poetic Metres."
    University of Toronto Studies, Psychological Series 1 (1900): 155-75. </bib>
   <notes> From experiments in which subjects read verse lines aloud with attention to the rhythm
    and simultanously tapped their fingers on a recording device, the authors conclude that
    isochrony does exist in poetic meter. Yet while agreeing that feet are temporally equal, they
    deny that the syllables of the feet have any simple and fixed ratios, such as two to one.
    Dactylic feet are shorter than anapests, trochees shorter than iambs. But a real difference can
    be found between dactylic and anapestic feet, and to a lesser extent between trochaic and
    iambic, in terms of the temporal durations of the constituents of the foot: where a is the
    shortest syllable and c the longest, the dactylic pattern in bac, the anapestic abc. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E419">
   <bib>Jacob, Cary F. "Concerning Scansion." Sewanee Review 19 (1911): 352-62. </bib>
   <notes> Defends the musical conception of verse with an appeal to scientific authority
    (acoustics) and a capsule history of ancient music. But Jacob thinks Lanier made three
    significant errors in method: (1) he believed all English verse to be in triple time (much of it
    is commonly double); (2) he believed the meters (e.g. iambic and trochaic) to be rhythmically
    distinct from each other (Jacob denies it); (3) he believed meter a crucial element of verse
    ("the one essential of verse is rhythm. . . . the phrase and not the line is the thing to be
    considered"). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E420">
   <bib>-----. The Foundations and Nature of Verse. New York: Columbia University Press, 1918. </bib>
   <notes>Based on his dissertation at Columbia. Rev: in MP 17 (1920): 727-29; in JEGP 19 (1920):
    430-33. A temporal theory of verse-structure based on the work in Acoustics by Scripture (E431)
    (Jacob accepts his "centroids") and in Psychology by Wood- row (D199), Wallin, (D198), and
    others. Thus, although Jacob advocates Musical notation for scansion, the experiments here
    recorded durations for words, silences, and phrases. Cf. Snell (E452). Jacob believes, by the
    way, the differences between iambic and trochaic meters to be a subjective impression-- a
    perceptual grouping of phenomena which may occur either way without any objective difference.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E421">
   <bib>-----. "Rhythm in Prose and Poetry." Quarterly Journal of Speech Education 13 (1927):
    357-75. </bib>
   <notes> A maundering essay upholding distinct rhythm as the differentia of poetry. Of interest as
    curiosities are the very elaborate scansions of prose (North, Malory, Conrad) compared to poetry
    (Shakespeare, Tennyson, Pound); these mark syntactic groups, time, stress, and quantity. Such
    gardens need weeding. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E422">
   <bib>Kaplan, Robert B. "An Analysis of Contemporary Poetic Structure, 1930-1955." DA 24 (1963):
    3749A (Southern California). </bib>
   <notes> English and American poets writing between these dates are classified as "New Puritans"
    or "New Pagans." Oscilloscope analysis of oral interpretations of poems, providing subtler
    gradations of stress, pause, and duration, reveals that both traditional metrics and linguistic
    metrics have deficiencies in terminology. Of metrics: "the field is choked by a great clutter of
    unscientific thinking, prejudice, and ignorance." At 315 pages, a very ambitious thesis both
    thematically and methodologically. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E423">
   <bib>Liddell, Mark H. A Brief Abstract of a New English Prosody Based Upon the Laws of English
    Rhythm. Lafayette, Ind.: Murphey-Bivens, 1914. 47 pp. </bib>
   <notes> The bulk of this little book gives rules for assigning degrees of stress to the various
    parts of speech, though late chapters indicate how "verse-stress" may modify the
    speech-stresses. His unit of verse is the "rhythm-wave," which "corresponds to the 'foot' in
    metrical prosody, to the 'bar' in music." A stress metric, no matter what he calls it. Six
    degrees of stress are distinguished. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E424">
   <bib>-----. An Introduction to the Scientific Study of English Poetry: Being Prolegomena to a
    Science of English Prosody. New York: Doubleday, Page, 1902. 312 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Resolute for a scientific prosody, Liddell eschews all talk of "feet" or any suggestion
    that English verse follows quantity; he resolutely upholds Stress as the key, but unfortunately
    then confounds this clarity with talk of "thought- moments" and graphs of "rhythm-waves." The
    book may be said to begin on p. 166; the most accessible synopsis is chapter 16, but there is a
    pr|'ecis on p. 251. See Morris (next entry), and see More's criticisms in E378. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E425">
   <bib>Morris, Amos R. "Liddell's Law of English Rhythm." Papers of the Michigan Academy of
    Sciences, Arts, and Letters 22 (1936): 485-91. </bib>
   <notes> Calling for a review of the methodological utility and perceptual validity of Liddell's
    six-level stress system and his 86 laws of speech rhythm, Morris formulates three questions as
    criteria for evaluation: "the question of how accurate is his notation of the relative stress. .
    . . the question of the relation of stress to the other four component physical factors, pitch,
    time, tempo, and tone color. . . . and a third question of the relation of normal word-stress to
    sense-stress." Criticizing Liddell's treatment of the third problem and setting aside the
    second, Morris examines the first: four men read then scanned passages of verse; phonetic
    analyses of the readings, along with the scansions, were then compared with Liddell's own
    scansions. All three were very similar, and so the six-level notation is tentatively confirmed
    as perceptually valid. Table of Results. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E426">
   <bib>-----. The Orchestration of the Metrical Line: An Analytical Study of Rhythmic Form.
    Boston: Richard G. Badger/Bruce Humphries, 1925. 162 pp. </bib>
   <notes>2nd ed. 1936. 155 pp. Based on his dissertation at Michigan in 1923. Readings of twelve
    short passages of blank verse, lyrics, prose, and free verse are phonetically analyzed on
    instruments to produce graphs and tables of duration, pitch, and stress. Time seems to be given
    the first position, but the interaction (conflicts and correspondences) shown between the three
    features is the more complex, more interesting matter. Morris finds seven temporal patterns in
    the ballad but only three in blank verse; also, "pitch, stress, and quantity coincide less
    exactly as we get further away from the song lyric and the scanned reading of verse."
    Conclusions on pp. 159-62. N. B.: the prose is terribly elliptical. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E427">
   <bib>Patterson, William Morrison. "New Verse and New Prose." North American Review 207 (1918):
    257-67. </bib>
   <notes> See D248. Restatement of Patterson's theory of rhythm (accents mark perceptually
    isochronous intervals) and verse-typology ("unitary verse," "metrical verse," "spaced prose,"
    "normal prose," "mosaics," and "blends"). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E428">
   <bib>Schramm, Wilber Lang. Approaches to a Science of English Verse. University of Iowa Studies,
    Series on Aims and Progress of Research, no. 46. Iowa City: The University, 1935. 82 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Along with Snell (E452), Schramm is the principle researcher in Acoustical metrics using
    the kymograph for "objective" measurement of verse. He pays his respects to Lanier and
    Scripture; he notes that accent normally comprises intensity, duration, and pitch increases
    together; he constrasts "speech melody" to musical melody. Chapters on Rime, Rhythm, and the
    Metrical Foot. Though this methodology has not been much admired or followed by later
    prosodists, nevertheless the calm reasonableness of tone here is refreshing and admirable. Short
    annotated bibliography at the end. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E429">
   <bib>-----. "Time and Intensity in English Tetrameter Verse." PQ 13 (1934): 65-71. </bib>
   <notes> Stress marks the meter in English verse, stress which comprises pitch, duration, and
    intensity. Which of these is the most important? Experiments show pitch to be largely
    irrelevant, while duration correlates 50% more often with metrical ictus than intensity does.
    And on the average, stressed syllables are exactly twice as long as unstressed. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E430">
   <bib>Scripture, E[dward] W[heeler]. Grundzüge der englischen Verswissenschaft. Marburg: N. G.
    Elwert, 1919. 98 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in MLR 25 (1930): 358-59; in Archiv 164 (1933): 75-77; in Anglia Beiblatt 41 (1930):
    357-62; in LGRP 51 (1930): 195-97. See also Chatman (E713), pp. 82-86. E. W. Scripture was one
    of the world's leading phoneticians in his day, a pioneer in the recording of speech on a
    mechanical apparatus, the kymograph, for analysis. His magnum opus in acoustic phonetics, and a
    sort of capstone to his career at the University of Vienna, is: </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E431">
   <bib>-----. The Elements of Experimental Phonetics. London: Edward Arnold, and New York: Charles
    Scribner's Sons, 1902. 627 pp. + graphs. </bib>
   <notes> In his later years, however, Scripture turned from phonetics to versification, studying a
    variety of verseforms in both English and German and publishing a considerable number of
    articles on meter and "the melody of speech" (pitch) in verse as he codified and applied his
    theory of versification, which is summarized in the last major work of his life, the
    Grundz|"uge. All of the articles on verse that Scripture published both before and after that
    book are based on its theory, so I cite them below with little commentary. The core of that
    theory is the postulate that the poetic line, based on observed recordings of speech, is a
    continuous soundstream, not segmented into any discrete units called "feet," but rather
    organized by major internal peaks of "energy" (convergences of intensity, loudness, pitch,
    articulation) which group their proclitic and enclitic syllables around themselves to form
    wave-like forms in the soundstream. Scripture refused to admit that syllable- boundaries could
    be identified (though inconsistently he admitted the existence of syllabicity), so no
    segmentation was possible. The result was that he was forced to search for line-types, given his
    view of the line as unit, and though a great many were identified, they could never be reduced
    to a satisfyingly small number of basic types, as in Sievers. But Scripture's work was a
    stimulus to Schramm (E428), whose method seems much more sensible. Other studies by Scripture:
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E432">
   <bib>-----. "Analyses of Verse from Herrick, Scott, and Hood." Archives néerlandaises de
    phonetique expérimentale 5 (1930): 64-76. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E433">
   <bib>-----. "Besondere Betonungen im englischen Vers." Anglia 53 (1929): 219-22. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E434">
   <bib>-----. "Die Betonung im englischen Satz." Archiv 142 (1921): 203-8. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E435">
   <bib>-----. "The Biology of Verse." Nature 114 (1924): 825-26. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E436">
   <bib>-----. "The Choriambus in English Verse." PMLA 43 (1928): 316-22. </bib>
   <notes> Abandoning in part his earlier rejection of the "foot," Scripture finds many choriambi
    (denoted :..: where : represents a strong vowel and . a weak one; alternatively, / x x / ) in
    English verse. But he does so only by terming the running sequence : . . : . . : . . : . . :
    choriambic as well, which seems dubious; traditionally such a sequence would be called dactylic
    or anapestic. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E437">
   <bib>-----. "English Speech Molecules and Analogues in Greek Metrics." Archives néerlandaises de
    phonetique expérimentale 6 (1931): 46-60. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E438">
   <bib>-----. "Experimentalphonetische Studien über die englische Verszeile." Archiv für die
    gesamte Psychologie 65 (1928): 61-90. </bib>
   <notes> Graphic analyses of Milton and Kipling; responses to a questionnaire on meter and rhythm;
    general characterization of English metrical types, with examples, according to his system.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E439">
   <bib>-----. "Experiments in the Phonetics of Shakespeare's Verse." TLS, 29 March 1923, p. 216.
    Responses: April 5, p. 232 (Sturge-Moore and Sonnenschein); April 12, p. 247 (Abercrombie);
    April 19, p. 269 (Rudmose-Brown); </bib>
   <notes> rejoinders by Scripture on April 19, p. 269, and April 26, p. 287. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E440">
   <bib>-----. "Investigations on the Nature of Verse." Vox 32 (1922): 4-14. </bib>
   <notes> Recordings of "Who Killed Cock Robin." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E441">
   <bib>-----. "Der Lears-Vers oder der englische Dochimus." Anglia 51 (1927): 136-38. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E442">
   <bib>-----. "Die Metrik in Masefield's 'Sea Fever.'" Die Neueren Sprachen 37 (1929): 145-47. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E443">
   <bib>-----. "The Nature of Verse." British Journal of Psychology 11 (1921): 225-35. </bib>
   <notes> Translated into German in Neusprachliche Studien: Festgabe Karl Luick. (Die Neuren
    Sprachen, Supplement no. 6.) Marburg, 1925. pp. 82-89. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E444">
   <bib>-----. "The Physical Nature of Verse." Nature 114 (1924): 534-35. Discussion, pp. 682-83,
    825-26; 115 (1925): 15. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E445">
   <bib>-----. "Studies in the Melody of Speech." Vox 32 (1922): 26-32. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E446">
   <bib>-----. "The Study of English Speech by New Methods of Phonetic Investigation." Proceedings
    of the British Academy 11 (1921-23): 270-99. </bib>
   <notes> Published as an offprint by Oxford University Press in 1923. Studies in pitch-patterns
    ("the melody of speech") in speech and verse. Section 5 returns to "Cock Robin" and Mother
    Goose. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E447">
   <bib>-----. "Die Versformen in Mother Goose." Anglia 54 (1930): 199-208. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E448">
   <bib>-----. "Die Versformen und Betonungspringzipien bei Hardy und Kipling." Die Neueren
    Sprachen 38 (1930): 122-26. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E449">
   <bib>-----. "Whence Does the Poet Get the Form of his Verse?" Modern Languages 5 (1923-24):
    163-72. </bib>
   <notes> Responses to a questionnaire sent to a number of lesser-known poets on the subject of
    where they derive and how they handle verse-forms. See also J273-74, K343, L326, L442, L591-97,
    M187. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E450">
   <bib>Snell, Ada, L. F. "An Objective Study of Syllabic Quantity in English Verse: Blank Verse."
    PMLA 33 (1918): 396-408. </bib>
   <notes> Kymograph experiments on twenty five lines of Paradise Lost show that 84% of the stressed
    syllables are longer than the unstressed, by an average of .2 sec. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E451">
   <bib>-----. "An Objective Study of Syllabic Quantity in English Verse: Lyric Verse." PMLA 34
    (1919): 416-35. </bib>
   <notes> In iambic, trochaic, anapestic, and dactylic meters 90% of the syllables under ictus were
    longer than the unstressed syllables outside of ictus in the same foot. Conclusion: "it is
    evident that Saintsbury's theory that the rhythm of English verse may be interpreted in terms of
    quantity, and that the foot is the unit, has justification in fact. That stress marks off the
    time-unit, or the foot, and produces length, is undoubtedly true." </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E452">
   <bib>-----. Pause: A Study of Its Nature and Its Rhythmical Function in Verse, Especially in
    Blank Verse. Contributions to Rhetorical Theory, no. 8. Ann Arbor: The Ann Arbor Press, 1918;
    rpt Norwood, Pa.: Norwood Editions, 1975. 85 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Based on her dissertation at Michigan in 1916. Acoustic-phonetics analysis, via kymograph
    measurement, of the position and length of pauses (N. B.: rhetorical, syntactic, and logical,
    not metrical pauses) in the reading of Paradise Lost by eleven subjects, as compared to their
    readings of lyric verse. Then, measurement of the phrasal units or syntactic groups demarcated
    by the pauses (these average 6.3 syllables and 1.9 sec. in length). Chapter 4 treats the
    questions of "metrical rests" and equal-timed feet, concluding that "when it is possible for a
    foot in a given poem to be five times as long as another in the same poem, and when one foot may
    frequently be twice as long as another, it is obvious that the theory of equality of time cannot
    be maintained, and that the omission of light syllables is not compensated for by pauses."
    Summary of Results at the end. Readers by and large agree on the placement of pauses, of which a
    third more appear within the line than at its end. Interestingly, the word preceding a pause is
    significantly lengthened. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E453">
   <bib>Triplette, Norman, and E. C. Sanford. "Studies of Rhythm and Meter." American Journal of
    Psychology 12 (1901): 361-87. </bib>
   <notes> A study of the meter and stanza forms of Stress Verse--specifically, nursery rhymes,
    collegiate cheers, and military tunes and chants. Fingertapping and timing experiments on both
    adults and children show roughly isochronous intervals between beats, with some variations.
   </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E454">
   <bib>Verrier, Paul. Essai sur les principes de la métrique anglaise. 3 vols. Paris: Libraire
    Universitaire, 1909-10. His dissertation at the University of Paris. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by Rudmose-Brown in MLR 6 (1911): 230-40; Verrier replies, indignant at "gross
    misrepresentation," in 7 (1912): 522-35, to which Rudmose-Brown responds in "English and French
    Metric," 8 (1913): 104-8; Verrier concludes the exchange in 9 (1914): 385-88. Volume 1 presents
    the theory of Acoustic Metrics, volume 2 the more general theory of rhythm (in prose, song, and
    verse) including a valuable chapter (5) on comparative versification, and volume 3 the kymograph
    experiments on Isochrony. Verrier is the most substantial study of English metrics ever
    undertaken which attempts to apply the assumptions and methods of acoustic phonetics. (It is
    not, however, necessarily the most authoritative; Verrier has been criticized sharply for using
    too few subjects in his tests to guarantee valid results.) He also uses musical notation as
    well, though not systematically. Meter is considered a species of rhythm, and metrical feet,
    which begin with the stressed vowel, are perceptually equal if not objectively so. (In practice
    Verrier takes as equal feet that are unequal by as much as 40%.) In fact, though the whole third
    volume concerns the acoustic experiments, Verrier is finally not committed to objective
    versification; the psychological theories discussed in volume 2 are much closer to his central
    conception of the subjectivity of the perpection of rhythm. Synopsis: "le rythme n'y est
    constitué que par la coincidence de l'accent avec le temps marqué. . . . il est constitué, comme
    celui de la musique, par le retour de temps marqué à intervalles sensiblement égaux." Verrier's
    researches generated the following studies, though see also L988-96. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E455">
   <bib>-----. Notions simplifées de versification anglaise. Paris: Libraire Charles Delagrave,
    1891. 38 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A small manual setting forth the metrical types. Rising and falling rhythms are
    emphasized. Short appendices on Accentuation, Terminology, and an interesting table of Lagaoedic
    Meters. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E456">
   <bib>-----. Questions de métrique anglaise. Paris, 1912. </bib>
   <notes>Cited in the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature, col. 42, but not listed in
    either NUC or BMC. R. M. Alden saw it sometime between 1912 and 1914 and described it as a
    useful synopsis of the argument of the Essai in pamphlet form. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E457">
   <bib>-----. "Une variation métrique ('Inversion of Accent')." Revue de phon|'etique 2 (1912):
    133-38. </bib>
   <notes> Argues that the so-called trisyllabic substitution in the first foot of the iambic
    pentameter is actually a catalexis followed by a trisyllabic foot; the scansion of the line
    should not be | / x | x / | x / | x / | x / | but rather | (x) /| x x / | x / | x / | x / |. See
    also C178, D242, D248, D323, E236, L1072. </notes>
  </item>
 </chapter>
</bibliography>
