<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
 <chapter title="">
  <item id="E458">
   <bib>Abbott, Edwin A., and J. R. Seeley. English Lessons for English People. London: Seeley,
    Jackson, and Halliday, 1871; </bib>
   <notes> rpt almost annually thereafter for over two decades. A grammar for the newly created
    English courses in schools. Part 3 treats "Metre," giving a simplified, conventional account of
    meters (accent is the basis in English), rhyme, quantity, caesura, and alliteration. Metrical
    Rules: (1) no succession of three syllables without metrical accent; (2) no two consecutive
    syllables in the same word may be metrically accented; (3) metrical accent in polysyllables must
    fall on lternate syllables. See the critique of Abbott's metrical system (both here and in his
    Shakespearean Grammar) in Chapter 3 of Mayor's Chapters on English Metre (E592) and the
    predecessor of that chapter, E594. E459 Abercrombie, Lascelles. Poetry: Its Music and Meaning.
    London: Oxford University Press, 1932. 64 pp. A small primer in paper covers. Meter is discussed
    on pp. 16-36. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E460">
   <bib>-----. Principles of English Prosody. London: Martin Secker, 1923. 155 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in The Saturday Review of Literature 136 (1923): 111; in The New Statesman 21
    (1923): 650-52; and in The Nation Athenaeum 33 (1923): 307-8; in TLS, 1 May 1924, p. 1; in MLR
    19 (1924): 364-67; in English Studies 8 (1926): 56-58. An introduction to meter on accentual
    principles which was influential in its time. Meter is defined as "rhythm varying over a
    constancy . . . the modulated repetition of a rhythmical pattern." This principle--"rhythmical
    constancy persisting through rhythmical variation," or the variation and the norm--has become a
    central axiom of stress metrics. Yet beyond that point Abercrombie is on a shaky ledge in
    defending the old principles of "equivalence" and "substitution." He can ably distinguish
    metrical base from rhythmic norm, yet he claims that any type of foot may be substituted in the
    rhythm of a blank- verse line for an iamb in the meter because "whatever foot occurs [in the
    rhythm] represents _ _ / standing in place of it when the verse is spaced out in the hearing
    against the ideal pattern," so that any rhythm is perfectly "equivalent" to its metrical base.
    But that is nonsense--no trochaic line fits an iambic base; rhythm is not "equivalent" to meter,
    it corresponds to meter if the rules for correspondence are satisfied. Altogether, the book is
    marred by the lingering influence of Saintsbury, yet it has great fixity of purpose in riveting
    its attention on the theoretical bases of scansion. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E461">
   <bib>-----. The Theory of Poetry. London: Martin Secker, 1924; New York: Harcourt, Brace, 1926; </bib>
   <notes> rpt New York: Biblo &amp; Tannen, 1968. Rev: in TLS, 1 May 1924, p. 1 (leading article);
    in The Nation-Athenaeum 34 (1924): 24, 844; in Sewanee Review 36 (1928): 383-84; in South
    Atlantic Quarterly 27 (1928): 440-41; in Poetry 28 (1926): 169-73, 227-32. There is also a
    review article by Theodore Stenberg on "Abercrombie's View of Poetry" (i.e. his ideas and
    achievement) in Sewanee Review 37 (1929): 108-14. Abercrombie exerted a modest influence on the
    thinking of the literari in the early decades of the century, and his critical opus shows the
    style of the times-- elegance and generality. See chapters 3 and 5 on rhythm, sound, and meter.
    Stenberg neatly summarizies Abercrombie's view of the emergent vers libre: "Free verse loses
    rather than gains by freeing itself from metrical patterns, for metrical rhythms are continuous,
    whereas free rhythms are not. Metrical rhythm, then, lends a certain unity, as well as a certain
    heightening of emotion, that free verse and prose are not likely to have. Poetry can, however,
    exist without metre." E462 There is a retrospective by Oliver Elton, "Lascelles Abercrombie,
    1881-1938," in Proceedings of the British Academy 25 (1939): 394-421. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E463">
   <bib>Anderson, J. Redwood. "The Principle of Uniformity in English Metre." Durham University
    Journal n.s. 2 (June 1941): 188-200; 3 (December 1941): 33-49. </bib>
   <notes> In search of a mathemetically absolute Constant through all syllabic Variations, Anderson
    compares the Virgillian hexameter, the French Alexandrine, and the Old English alliterative
    line, finding in them Bases of (respectively) quantity, number, and stress. Each of these three
    qualities is then considered as the possible Constant for modern English verse, but all are
    rejected, as is time. Instead, the Base which underlies all realizations is recognized as a
    "subjective," abstract pattern of repetition of abstract elements [some others would call these
    non-ictus, ictus], such that the pattern for the heroic line is | xa | xa | xa | xa | xa | .
    Verse itself, as a system of abstractions and concretions, may be divided into: (1) "the fixed
    element as predictable, or expected"----the Base (2) "the fixed element as heard" (3) "the
    variable element"----the Modulation </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E464">
   <bib>Anderson, Wallace L. "Metrical Deviations and the Teaching of Poetry." College English 19
    (1958): 259-63. </bib>
   <notes> The best pedagogy is to define meter in terms of its expressive variation, not in terms
    of Regularity. The variations are central not incidental. Scans Shakespeare's Sonnet 73.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E465">
   <bib>Arnell, Charles John. The Art and Practice of Versification. Exeter: Sydney Lee, 1925. 54
    pp. </bib>
   <notes> An elementary manual, primarily on stanza-forms, appallingly cavalier in definitions.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E466">
   <bib>Arnold, Thomas. "Appendix; On English Meters." In his A Manual of English Literature,
    Historical and Critical. London: Longmans, Green, 1862; 2nd ed. 1869. Boston: Ginn, Heath, 1873.
    pp. 521-35. </bib>
   <notes> "Metre is the arrangement into verse of definite measures of sounds, definitely accented.
    Thus the hexameter is the arrangement in lines of six equivalent quantities of sound, called
    feet, each of which consists, or has the value, of two long syllables, and is accented on the
    first syllable. . . . In English poetry, length or quantity depends almost entirely upon accent.
    Accented syllables are long, unaccented syllables short." Feet recognized are the iambic,
    trochaic, anapestic, dactylic, spondaic, and amphibrachic. Metrical and stanzaic forms are
    illustrated. Written before Schipper, Arnold's short essay is aware only of Guest (E543); his
    principles are clearly accentual, and we can see here his deliberate (struggling) effort to
    preserve the old classical terminology for the modern verse. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E467">
   <bib>Atkins, H. G. "Holding Down the Trochees." MLR 37 (1942): 356-58. </bib>
   <notes> In English "there is no natural trochaic verse, but only trochiac lines in which the
    falling rhythm is maintained deliberately by the use of a very definite and conspicuously
    employed linguistic material, failing which the natural iambic rhythm inevitably reasserts
    itself." Cf. Creek (E18), Stewart (E331), Crapsey (E516), Hascall (E783), and Newton (E799).
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E468">
   <bib>Bailey, James. "Linguistic Givens and Their Metrical Realization in a Poem by Yeats."
    Language and Style 8 (1975): 21-33. </bib>
   <notes> A synopsis of the theory and "linguistical-statistical" methods of Russian metrics,
    followed by an application of the principles of dol'nik verse (a mixed stress-meter) to Yeats's
    "Cap and Bells." Concludes with a defense of statistics in metrical studies. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E469">
   <bib>-----. Toward a Statistical Analysis of English Verse: The Iambic Tetrameter of Ten Poets.
    Lisse [Netherlands]: Peter de Ridder Press, 1975. 79 pp. Rev: in Anglia 97 (1979): 218-32. </bib>
   <notes> A study narrower in scope and therefore more accessible to most students as an
    introduction to the Russian (i.e. inductive) method in metrics than the monograph by Tarlinskaja
    (E673). Bailey compiles statistics and displays his results in graphic form for stress placement
    and variation, syllabic variation, enjambement and rhyme, lexical selection, and stanza form in
    the iambic tetrameter verse of Jonson, Milton, Pope, Cowper, Blake, Wordsworth, Tennyson, Eliot,
    Auden, and Graves. In respect to rhythm the iambic tetrameter has undergone the greatest changes
    in the twentieth century; it has remained constant in the basic syllabic- and stress-structure
    of the stem of the line, in use of anacrusis, avoidance of contiguous unstressed ictuses, and
    nonmetrical stressing, but substantial changes have occurred in rhythmical variety and average
    stressing, frequency of hiatus and polysyllabic words (higher), and use of elision (lower).
    Bailey has an acute awareness of the uses and abuses of statistical information, and his study
    takes a well-modulated and effective stance between the rocks and the whirlpool, generalization
    and detail. An important direction for metrics in the future. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E470">
   <bib>Barnes, William. "Prosody" and "Rhyme." In his A Philological Grammar. London: John Russell
    Smith, 1854. pp. 261-76, 277-308. </bib>
   <notes> The chapter on "Prosody" gives a rather full comparison of classical Greek and modern
    English meters. The following chapter on "Rhyme" gives an even fuller comparative view of
    Occidental and Oriental varieties of rhyme. Barnes was a poet and (prodigious) philologists, a
    close friend of Hardy, and influental on the early work of Hopkins. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E471">
   <bib>Bateson, Harold D. The Battle of the English Metrists. Liverpool: D. Marple, 1919. 45 pp. </bib>
   <notes> An edition of twelve copies. Four branches of metrical theory are identified: the
    accentualist (Guest, etc.), the quantivist (Saintsbury having one view, Bridges and Stone
    another), the sectionalist (Guest again), and the musical (Lanier). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E472">
   <bib>-----. An Introduction to the Study of English Rhythms, With an Essay on the Meter of
    Coleridge's "Christabel." Manchester, 1896 (24 pp.); rpt Liverpool, 1904 (26 pp.). </bib>
   <notes> Taken from the Manchester Quarterly for 1894. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E473">
   <bib>Baum, Paull F. The Principles of English Versification. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard
    University Press, 1922; rpt New Hamden, Conn.: Archon Books, 1969. 215 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in JEGP 22 (1923): 445-49; in Poetry 22 (1923): 218-21; by Bright in MLN 38 (1923):
    125-28; in Saturday Review of Literature 134 (1922): 888-90. Baum's handbook is leisurely and
    urbane: it will be found useful for undergraduates, though at advanced levels students will see
    that his refinements of taste interdict any refinement of distinctions. He asserts quite clearly
    that "the basis of English metre is dual: time and stress are inextricable," but in practice he
    works by stresses, though musical notes are used for illustration. The chapters on Rhythm in
    Prose and Verse and on Modulation are the best, with excellent examples of prose recast as verse
    and vice versa. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E474">
   <bib>Beattie, James. "An Essay on Poetry and Music, as they affect the mind." In his Essays.
    Edinburgh: Printed for William Creech, 1776. pp. 348-580. </bib>
   <notes> Actually written ca. 1762. There are apparently two editions in 1776, a quarto of four
    essays and an octavo of three. See the final chapter in the essay, especially the last ten
    pages, though also p. 158 ff; see also the next entry. Beattie accepts the Latin terminology and
    scansion sigla but bases meter on "emphasis" (i.e. stress, the term "accent" denoting pitch),
    though some musical notation is used. The pentameter consists of five feet, with thirty types of
    variation. He declares himself adverse to strict syllabism, holding that contractions are never
    made in recitation and hence should not be made in print. Further reading: </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E475">
   <bib>Land, Stephen K. "James Beattie on Language." PQ 51 (1972): 887-904; </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E476">
   <bib>Flood, W. H. G. "An Eighteeth Century Essayist on Poetry and Music." Musical Quarterly 2
    (1916): 191-98. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E477">
   <bib>-----. The Theory of Language. Originally part of his Dissertations Moral and Critical.
    London, 1783; </bib>
   <notes> republished separately in 1788 in two Parts. Rpt Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar Press, 1968;
    rpt New York: AMS Press, 1974. Chapters 4 and 5 or Part I are for us. Beattie scans by
    "emphasis," reserving the term "accent" for elevation of tone, i.e. pitch. Though ordering of
    long and short syllables "may sometimes form the rhythm of English verse, yet that which
    invariably and essentially forms it" is the ordering of stresses. Beattie admits only the four
    commonest feet, taking the old terms without quibble, but he balks altogether at eliding extra
    syllables in a line in pronunciation. Indebted to Sheridan (E651-52). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E478">
   <bib>Beaumont, Sir John. "To His Late Majesty [James I], Concerning the True Forme of English
    Poetry" [1629?]. </bib>
   <notes> Rpt in The Works of the English Poets. . . . Ed. Alexander Chalmers. 21 vols. London: J.
    Johnson, 1810. Vol. 6, pp. 30-31. Poem in couplets praising rime, contemptuous that "on halting
    feet the ragged poem goes." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E479">
   <bib>Beauties of poetry displayed, containing observations on the different species of poetry
    and the rules of English versification. 2 vols. London: J. Hinton, 1757. </bib>
   <notes> See Preface, xxiv-xxxiv. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E480">
   <bib>Belsham, William. "On Stile and Versification." Essay 33 in his Essays Philosophical and
    Moral, Historical, and Literary. London: C. Dilly, 1789; 2nd ed. 1799. pp. 481-99. </bib>
   <notes> Begin at p. 486; Belsham's genteel essay defers to the critics in fashion (mainly Kames
    (E566)), notes the principal forms (blank verse, couplets, and elegaic quatrains), and touches
    on the foremost poets (Pope, Cowley, Waller, Thomson, Young). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E481">
   <bib>Bernhart, A. Walter. "Complexity and Metricality." Poetics 12 (1974): 113-42. </bib>
   <notes> A look into Jespersen (E562) which concludes that "the criterion for determining the
    metricality of the line is the predominance of pattern- affirming parts over
    pattern-contradicting parts within the line." A new scansion system is then presented (cf.
    Jespersen's) which is concerned not with Position but with Changes in Position. Cf. also
    Chatman's "meter-fixing" feet (E713). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E482">
   <bib>Blackstone, Bernard. Practical English Prosody: A Handbook for Students. London: Longmans
    1965. 164 pp. </bib>
   <notes> I have only one quarrel with this student's manual--it allows spondees and pyrrhics;
    otherwise, the first word of its title is amply justified: The book is clear, compressed,
    thorough, and not unduly elementary. Perhaps chapter 2 on metrical style--shifts and
    vacillations--is the most useful. Long final chapter on the Lyric. Exercises. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E483">
   <bib>Blair, Hugh. Lectures on Rhetoric and Belles-Lettres. 2 vols. London, 1783. </bib>
   <notes> Blair's Rhetoric, which had gone through over 130 editions by the turn of this century,
    offers us an excellent view of the contemporaneous conception of versification on the "lower"
    levels of pedagogy. See Lecture 38 on "Nature on Poetry--Its Origin and
    Progress--Versification," specifically pp. 324-34. Blair recognizes the difference in
    versification between the ancient and the modern languages, so that "mere quantity is of very
    little effect in English versification," and he allows "some liberty for the sake of variety" in
    the placement of accents. The general rule is for five accents and ten syllables in the heroic
    line. A long discussion of caesura-placement shows the influence of Bysshe, and remarks on Blank
    Verse and Couplet Verse conclude the lecture. Lecture 41 (vol. 2) on "The Poetry of the Hebrews"
    is also of interest, as is lecture 13 (vol. 1), "Structure of Sentences--Harmony," esp. p. 259
    ff. The date of the work is not exactly indicative of the true period of influence of these
    ideas since the Lectures were published at the conclusion of Blair's career as Professor of
    Rhetoric at Edinburgh. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E484">
   <bib>[Blake, J. W.] Accent and Rhythm Explained by the Law of Monopressures. Edinburgh:
    Blackwood, 1888. </bib>
   <notes> The principles of this work were adopted and later expanded by W. W. Skeat in his
    prefaces to Chaucer and in his Philological Society paper (E656). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E485">
   <bib>[Blenerhasset, Thomas] "The Induction" to "The Complaint of Sigebert." In The Seconde Part
    of the Mirrour for Magistrates. London, 1578. </bib>
   <notes> Rpt in Parts Added to "The Mirror for Magistrates" by John Higgins &amp; Thomas
    Blenerhasset. Ed. Lily B. Campbell. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1946. pp. 450-51. In
    this Introduction is found the first known reference to our staple English line as iambic. Note
    also that the tragedy which precedes it, "The Complaynt of Cadwallader," is written in accentual
    hexameters, iambic and unrhymed. The salient passage: "But fyrst tell me Inquisition, wyll you
    penne this mans meterless Tragedy as he hat pronounst it? good Memory geue me your aduise, for
    it agreeth very wel with the Roman verse called Iambus, which consisteth on sixe feete, euery
    foote on two syllables, one short and an other long, so proper for the English toung, that it is
    great maruaile that these ripewitted Gentlemen of England haue not left of their Gotish kinde of
    ryming, (for the rude Gothes brought that kind of writing fyrst, &amp; imitated the learned
    Latines &amp; greekes)." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E486">
   <bib>Brenton, Thaddeus R. T. An Essay on Poetics. London: Oxford University Press, 1932. 58 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Distinguishes meter from rhythm: "if, in general, rhythm aside from metre is a poetical
    tenet, it is only secondary to, and superimposed upon, metre." Criticism of free verse. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E487">
   <bib>Brewer, R[obert] F. A Manual of English Prosody: being an Introduction to the Study of
    Poetry. London, 1869. </bib>
   <notes> Enlarged as E488 Orthometry: A Treatise on the Art of Versification and the
    Technicalities of Poetry. London, 1893. Rev. ed: E489 Orthometry: The Art of Versification and
    the Technicalities of Poetry. Edinburgh: John Grant, 1912; rpt 1950. 376 pp. For all its
    enormous length and pretentious title, the book is a mere handbook of forms. Chapters on meters,
    stanzas, forms, imitative sounds, and classical meters in English; Rhyming Dictionary at the
    end. Philbrick (D323), pp. 274- 76) accuses Brewer of plagiarisms "too numerous to mention" from
    Crowe (E142). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E490">
   <bib>Bridges, Robert. "A Letter to a Musician on English Prosody." Musical Antiquary 1 (1909). </bib>
   <notes> Revised and rpt as no. 15 of his Collected Essays, Papers, &amp;. London: Oxford
    University Press, 1927-36. Vol. 2, pp. 53-85. Rpt in Gross (A23), pp. 86-101. Actually of wider
    scope than its title suggests. Bridges' short account of versification is both readable and
    informative. He distinguishes between Speech-Rhythm (as determined by Quantity, Pitch, and/or
    Loudness) and Metrical Rhythm and isolates three basic types of metrical systems—Quantita- tive,
    Syllabic [i.e. Accentual-Syllabic; Bridges' term is misleading], and Stress Verse. Bridges
    believes that the English accentual-syllabic meter is a descendant of the Medieval Latin system,
    arising out of inattention to the quantities; he identifies the four principles of English verse
    as syllable- counting, alternation of stress, reduction of extra syllables by elision, and
    ignoring of syllabic quantity. Bridges also returns to classical versification throughout the
    letter. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E491">
   <bib>-----. Milton's Prosody: With a Chapter on Accentual Verse &amp; Notes. Revised final
    edition. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1921; rpt 1965, 1967. 119 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in TLS, 14 April 1921, p. 240; by Omond in MLR 17 (1922): 90-96; by Bright in MLN 37
    (1922): 316-20; by Masson in the Literary Review, 25 June 1921, p. 2; in The New Republic 31
    (1922): 224-25. This definitive version of Bridges' magnum opus concludes the work he began in
    1887 with the publication of his essay, </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E492">
   <bib>-----. "On the Elements of Milton's Blank Verse in Paradise Lost." In Paradise Lost, Book
    I. Ed. H. C. Beeching. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1887. 153 pp. </bib>
   <notes> (Listed in the standard bibiography of Milton by David H. Stephens.) This essay was
    followed by a second, published anonymously in 1889 as </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E493">
   <bib>-----. On the Prosody of Paradise Regained and Samson Agonistes: Being a Supplement to the
    paper "On the Elements of Milton's Blank Verse in Paradise Lost," which is reprinted in the Rev.
    H. C. Beeching's edition of Paradise Lost, Book I, Clarendon Press, Oxford. Oxford: Basil
    Blackwell, 1889. 12 pp. </bib>
   <notes> This is a small tract in paper covers. Thereafter, the two essays were revised and
    published together as </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E494">
   <bib>-----. Milton's Prosody: An Examination of the Rules of the Blank Verse in Milton's Later
    Poems, with an Account of the Versification of Samson Agonistes and General Notes. Oxford:
    Clarendon Press, 1893. 80 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in The Nation 60 (1895): 166; in School Review 4 (1896): 553-54; in The Athenaeum,
    24 March 1894, p. 372; and in Chapter 7 of Mayor's Chapters on English Metre (E592). In the
    decade following, Bridges began experimenting with quantitative meters and also discovered the
    work of W. J. Stone on classical metrics (E251), which he combined with his own work on Milton
    as a memorial to Stone's untimely death and reissued as </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E495">
   <bib>-----. Milton's Prosody, &amp; Classical Meters in English Verse, by William Johnson Stone.
    Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1901. 174 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Each part has separate title page. Rev: in Nation 74 (1902): 370-71, and (more fully) by
    B. A. P. Van Dam in Englische Studien 32 (1903): 98-110. From this, Bridges then published three
    papers collectively titled </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E496">
   <bib>-----. "Miltonic Elision." The Athenaeum, January 1904, pp. 83-84, 113-14, 147- 48. </bib>
   <notes> Here he argues that Milton's extra syllables are to be elided for purposes of the meter
    but are to be spoken aloud without reduction, thereby enriching the complication of the verse.
    Even though Bridges' work on the versification of Milton may soon be superceded by Weismiller
    (E1342), his final edition of Milton's Prosody will nonetheless remain a classic. In fact, it
    may be said that the descriptive- analytical approach to metrics so extensively pursued in the
    twentieth century received its impetus chiefly from Bridges. His principles throughout Milton's
    Prosody are three: (1) his method is Inductive; (2) he conceives of the verse- line as
    consisting of a Norm and its Variations; and (3) he considers the verse of Milton to be
    essentially syllabic, and only secondarily accentual. Bridges repeatedly evidences his firm
    grasp of historical phonology, his keen attention to Milton's technic, and his wide reading in
    the history of classical versification. Part I, "On the Prosody of Paradise Lost," treats the
    counting of syllables and accents as the fundamental principles of Miltonic meter; Bridges' view
    of Miltonic elision is that syllables are to be fully realized in pronunciation but elided in
    scansion. The number and placement of accents belongs to the rhythm but not to the meter, since
    for Bridges the accentual structure of Milton's verse is only accessory, "like the flesh on a
    skeleton." He cites lines with three, four, and five accents, with inverted feet in each of the
    five positions, and with line-breaks (he eschews the term "caesura") in each of the nine
    possible positions. Part II, on PR and SA, cites instances of Milton's steady relaxation of the
    rules he followed for PL Part III, "Obsolete Mannerisms," discusses the old conventions for
    "recession of accent," spelling, and pronunciation. The newly-added Part IV, "On the Prosody of
    Accentual Verse," offers remarks on Christabel and seven rules for the prosody of stress verse,
    the joint effect of both of which is that the metrical units or measures in the scansion are to
    be "sometimes determined" by grammar (remember that stress for Bridges is an element of rhythm
    and that sentence-stress in normal speech- rhythm is partially determined by syntax). His
    scansion system marks (in accent) single and double stress and (in quantity) heavy, light, and
    short syllables in combinations producing sixteen varieties of feet. This account will suggest
    that Bridges' mind always remained a little swayed by classical versification, and his typology
    sometimes looks a bit eccentric to us. Yet he insisted on accurate phonetics, his ear was good,
    and his conception of Rules and Norms has had illustrious adherents later in this century. And
    at least one part of Milton's Prosody is entirely beyond cavil--the Preface: delightful wit.
    Discussion of Bridges' work may be found in Prince (E1279), Kellog (E567), Stanford (E86, E87),
    Diekhoff (E1141), and Stall (E664). Note also E689 and E938. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E497">
   <bib>Bright, James W. "Concerning English Rhythms." The Athenaeum, 8 July 1899, p.70. </bib>
   <notes> Abstract of a paper read before the Philological Society on June 30: Bright censures the
    notions of "inversion of accent" and "substitution," which "must be corrected by a consideration
    of the secondary word-accents of the language, which are capable of ictus, and of the rhetoric
    of verse, which permits a new emphasis on words of subordinate force. . . . a verse must be
    read, or scanned, with a strict observance of the regular recurrence of the ictus; when the
    ictus is 'in conflict' with the chief word-stress, it will be marked for the ear by a slight
    increase of pitch. . . ." More imaginatively, Bright suggests that Sievers' Five Types may be
    found in modern verse, and also that "the rhythmic employment of the secondary word-stress as
    possible ictus furnishes the means for passing from an 'accentual' to a 'quantitative' system of
    versification," as in early and late Latin. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E498">
   <bib>-----. "Concerning Grammatical Ictus in English Verse." An English Miscellany Presented to
    Dr. Furnivall in Honour of his 75th Birthday. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1901. pp. 22-33. </bib>
   <notes> Metrical ictus can be filled not only by primary word-accents but also promoted secondary
    accents, and readings of verse should reflect this fact. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E499">
   <bib>-----. "Rhythmic Elements in English, with Illustrations from Shakespeare." University of
    Texas Bulletin, no. 1701 (1917), pp. 68-88. </bib>
   <notes> For its location this essay seems unusually opaque (stylistically) and defensive
    (tonally); its purpose is a formal statement of the method of "routine scansion" ("the artistic
    effects of scansion according to rhythm-signature"), which is simply the notion that word-stress
    and sentence-stress are both controlled by ictus when words are arrayed in verse. To this end
    Bright must show how "versification in a language is intimately bound up with the special system
    of accentuation of that language," which he performs for English by showing that "secondary
    word-accent is available for verse-stress (ictus)." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E500">
   <bib>Bright, James W., and R. D. Miller. The Elements of English Versification. Boston: Ginn and
    Company, 1910, 1913; rpt Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1973. 157 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A student handbook: Part One gives definitions of terms and examples of meters (the four
    commonest, in line-lengths up to octameter) and sound- effects, including a chapter (4) on
    Scansion; Part Two illustrates stanza forms from couplet to sestina. Bright, Professor of
    English at Johns Hopkins and President of MLA, exerted considerable influence on the study of
    both versification and Old English early in this century, both himself (see J34, J35) and
    through the studies of his graduate students Huguenin (J133), Melton (E1018), Miller (E596), and
    Brown (E1112), though he himself curiously never undertook a work on the order of Mayor's. The
    crux of Bright's metrical theory is the secondary accent posited between the levels of stressed
    and unstressed in phonology (most conspicuous in compound nouns and other polysyllables) which
    is available in meter as either (promoted to) ictus or (demoted to) non-ictus depending on the
    contiguous stresses. Such a tripartite system was by no means new, but Bright augmented it with
    something that was, his correlate theory of "pitch-accent," a proposal that when the syllable
    under ictus is not marked by stress-prominence (as in "trochaic substitution") a compensating
    prominence by pitch or length is adduced. A further refinement was added by his students, called
    "arsis-thesis variation" (a poet's use of the same word twice, fairly close together, but with
    the stress-pattern of the word reversed the second time for semantic and aesthetic effect). Yet
    Bright's theory is not entirely free from ambivalences: Omond is unquestionably right to declare
    that he "scans wholly by accents," yet he also states that stresses recur at equal intervals,
    and syllable resolution is explained in terms of timing. This is the turn-of-the-century desire
    to have the best of both worlds. But note Philbrick's accusation that Miller and through him
    Bright was guilty of outright plagiarism from Alden and others (D323, pp. 276-77). Still,
    Bright's 3-level system is a significant milestone in the correlation of Phonetic to Metric, to
    be compared with the later 4-level Trager-Smith structural-linguistic system. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E501">
   <bib>Brooks, Cleanth, and Robert Penn Warren, eds. Understanding Poetry. New York: Henry Holt,
    1938; rev. ed. 1950; 4th ed. New York: Holt Rinehart and Winston, 1976. </bib>
   <notes> See "Appendix B: Metrics," pp. 493-576, and the short comments on "Rhythm and Meter"
    beginning on pp. 49, 97, 162, 193, 251, 312 in the fourth edition. A long judicious discussion
    of prosody in what is probably the most influential introduction-to-poetry textbook in our
    century. Brooks and Warren's presentation of stress metrics has also had a comparable influence
    in scholarly circles. Contents: Accentual-Syllabic Verse (Rhetorical Variation, Significance of
    Rhetorical Variation, Some Practical Notes on Scansion, Quantitative Variation and Forced
    Pauses), Rhyme, Stanza-Forms, Onomatopoeia and Related Effects, The Music of Verse, Accentual or
    Stress Meter, Free Verse. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E502">
   <bib>Browning, Elizabeth Barrett. The Art of Scansion. Introd. by Alice Meynell. London: Clement
    Shorter, 1916. 12 pp. </bib>
   <notes> This is a private printing of a letter from E. B. B. to Sir Uvedale Price in 1827, which
    she wrote in response to reading his Essay on the Modern Pronunciation of Greek and Latin
    (1827). Inter alia, she insists on a distinction between anapestic and dactylic rhythms and on
    the existence of pyrrhics and choriambi, in English verse as in Greek and Latin. Noteworthy:
    "The plea of expression in versification is something like the plea of expediency in morals."
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E503">
   <bib>Brunhumer, Anne B. "Metrical Principles of English Poetry: A Course of Lectures by
    Professor Ruth Wallerstein." DA 21 (1961): 3087A (Wisconsin). </bib>
   <notes> Transcription of shorthand notes taken in Prof. Wallerstein's seminar, to take the place
    of a metrical handbook she did not live to write. Her theoretical position was traditional; her
    method was entirely inductive. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E504">
   <bib>[Bryant, William Cullen.] "On the Use of Trisyllabic Feet in Iambic Verse." North American
    Review 9 (1819): 426-31. </bib>
   <notes> Revised and rpt in his Life and Works. New York: 1883-84. Vol. 5, pp. 57-67. Averse to
    elision, Bryant endeavors to show the presence to trisyllabic feet in the best English poets,
    especially Milton. He speaks only of quantities but scans by accent. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E505">
   <bib>Bysshe, Edward. The Art of English Poetry. Containing I. Rules for making VERSES. II. A
    Collection of the most Natural, Agreeable, and Sublime THOUGHTS, viz. Allusions, Similies,
    Descriptions, and Characters, of Persons and Things, that are to be found in the best ENGLISH
    POETS. III. A Dictionary of RHYMES. London, 1702, 1705, 1708, 1710, 1714, 1718, 1724, 1737,
    1762, etc. </bib>
   <notes> The second and third editions were successively revised and expanded, but no substantive
    changes were made thereafter; the third edition therefore constitutes the copy-text for our
    purposes. Part I of the third edition has been reprinted by the Augustan Reprint Society
    (Publication no. 40) with an introduction by A. Dwight Culler, Los Angeles, 1953. There is also
    a facsimile of the first edition edited by R. C. Alston, Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar Press, 1968.
    Another reprint: New York: Garland, 1971. Bysshe's is not only the most influential prosodic
    work of the eighteenth century, it is also very likely the most influential prosodic handbook
    ever written. Many times reprinted in the eighteenth century and probably at least skimmed by
    anyone with the slightest literary aspirations at all, it was the major source for Walker's
    equally ubiquitious Rhyming Dictionary of the nineteenth century, a book which was itself the
    model and source for similar works in the twentieth. Hence, a close simulacrum of at least part
    of Bysshe's handbook can be picked up in any bookstore today nearly three centuries later. The
    Art of English Poetry itself was based on (indeed virtually a translation of) Claude Lancelot's
    Quatre Traitez de Poësies, Latine, Françcoise, Italienne, et Espagnole (1663) and on the Preface
    to Joshua Poole's English Parnassus (1657 and 1677; see E520), respectively a treatise in
    comparative versification and a popular handbook of the seventeeth century, and it is composed
    of three parts: the "Rules for Making Verses" (a short metrical treatise), a "Collection of
    Agreeable Thoughts" (a commonplace book, or rough equivalent of our dictionary of familiar
    quotations), and a rhyming dictionary. Now although Renaissance miscellany has its analogue in
    our modern anthology of verse, and the rhyming and quotation dictionary as well as prosodic
    manual are not recognizable sub-genres to us, the "poet's handbook" has not survived in
    unaltered form: in Bysshe's time it occupied a position between those of the modern-day students
    handbook and the technical or theoretical study of versification. In our time technical or
    theoretical study of versification. In our time poets prefer to shift for themselves, finding
    the thought of imitating traditional forms repugnant to their individual talents. Bysshe's
    influence on metrical theory is equally significant. His "Rules," which was the first explicit
    Prosodia written in England in nearly a century, is responsible for reasserting a fundamental
    principle of English meter which had been asserted with equal insistence only once before, in
    the early Middle English period (though even then not by treatise but by practice), syllabism.
    And insofar as any modern manual includes, as part of its definition of English meter,
    stipulation of a certain number of syllables, it is echoing Bysshe, behind him Chaucer, and
    ultimately the faint and distant sounds of the Chansons. Indeed counting of syllables is the
    essential criterion of metricality in Bysshe: the heroic line is for him composed of ten
    syllables (not counting feminine endings), and all lines failing this standard are simply
    unmetrical. "The structure of our Verse . . . consists in a certain Number of Syllables, not in
    Feet compos'd of long and short Syllables. . . ." So runs his first sentence, an opening salvo
    against his nemesis Charles Gildon (E164-165). In order to insure strict count of syllables
    Bysshe is obliged to devise very elaborate rules for elision. After Numbers, the two criteria to
    be observed are "the Seat of the Accent" and "the Pause." Bysshe recognizes accent ("an
    Elevation or a Falling of the Voice," i.e., based on pitch) but not feet; he stipulates only
    that the accent must fall on the 2nd, 4th, or 6th syllable of the decasyllabic line so that the
    caesura ("Pause") will be thereby correctly placed--all other placements are faults to be
    corrected. The "Rules" also give some lesser attention to rhyme and other types of meters and
    stanzas. See the immensely informative essay by Culler (E517), whose scholarship is a model of
    thoroughness, Gabrielson (C10), and Lancelot (L82). </notes>
  </item>





  <item id="E506">
   <bib>Carey, John. Key to Practical English Prosody and Versification. London: Baldwin, Cradock,
    and Son, 1809; 2nd rev. ed. 1816. 216 pp. </bib>
   <notes> The "Prosody" of some sixty pages summarizes principles: "in English poetry [metre]
    consists in the number of syllables, and the position of the accents." Eight types of feet are
    allowed (including tribrachs and amphibrachs). The remaining "Versification" section sets
    students verse construction and revision exercises. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E507">
   <bib>Cejp, Ladislav. [On English verse rhythm.] Casopis pro Moderni Filologii 33 (1950): 109-16.
    (In Czech.) </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E508">
   <bib>Childs, Barney. "Metrics Revisted," Trace, no. 51 (1963), pp. 265-76. </bib>
   <notes> Above the counterpointing of stressed meter to temporal rhythm there is another
    dimension, counterpointed to the first, of pulse, variable with each reader, not heard but felt.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E509">
   <bib>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor. Coleridge's Miscellaneous Criticism. Ed. T. M. Raysor. Cambridge,
    Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1936. </bib>
   <notes> Stray remarks on meter: see pp. 66-67, 72-73, 77-78, 90-91, 186-87, and 337-38. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E510">
   <bib>-----. [English Metres.] Coleridge's Shakespearian Criticism. Ed. Thomas M. Raysor. 2 vols.
    Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1930. Vol. 1, pp. 252-53. </bib>
   <notes> Coleridge listed on a flyleaf of an edition of Shakespeare twelve Greek metrical feet and
    observed that these will suffice to scan Shakespeare (using accent in place of length), while
    for Milton the compound feet--ionics, paeons, and epitrites--will be required. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E511">
   <bib>-----. [Metrical Experiments] and "Metrical Feet: Lesson for a Boy." In Poetical Works. Ed.
    Ernest Hartley Coleridge. London: Oxford University Press, 1912, 1967. pp. 511-16, 401-2. </bib>
   <notes> The latter poem, a bit of meter-teaching verse, was first published in 1834; the former
    is a set of twelve fragmentary exercises, not all by Coleridge in fact (see E1076). Notes by
    Saintsbury appended. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E512">
   <bib>-----. Table Talk. London: G. Bell, 1884; 1909; </bib>
   <notes> rpt as vol. 14 of The Collected Works of Samuel Taylor Coleridge. Ed. Kathleen Coburn. 15
    vols. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul. See s.v. June 7, 1823, on "Lord Byron's Versification"
    (short and depreciating); August 23, 1833, on "Greek Accent and Quantity" (C. Allows that the
    latter controlled the recitation of verse but argues that the utterance of prose was marked by
    the former); and June 2, 1834, on "Schiller's Versification--German Blank Verse" (Schiller
    writes blank verse like "a fly in a glass bottle"; the trochaic endings of German words make
    German blank verse "almost impracticable"). Notice also the passing remarks on "Greek and Latin
    Pentameter" on October 23, 1833. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E513">
   <bib>Conway, Gilbert. A Treatise on Versification. London: Longmans, Green, 1878. 113 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A vigorous statement of the Accentual theory of English metrics, as concise in its texts
    as it is voluminous in footnotes (many of them drawn from the original Latin and Greek). The
    prosody of English verse is posited upon accent not upon time or quantity, there being four laws
    of accentuation: (1) every word of more than one syllable has a "Tonic accent"; it has (2) one
    and only one such accent; (3) monosyllable accent varies with the relative importance of the
    word; and (4) accent rests on the entire syllable not the vowel. Similarly, there are four laws
    of verse: (1) verse-rhythm depends on repetition of accent, which can be (2) nothing other than
    word-accent [lexical stress]; (3) "no syllable not sounded in declaimed prose should be sounded
    in verse"; and (4) hiatus must be removed by elision. The metrical accents falling on the even
    positions of the decasyllabic Heroic line may occur in any of thirty-five possible combinations.
    Conway recognizes what will later be called the Allophonic Stress Principle (p. 30)--i.e., that
    the the second of any two equally stressed syllables dominates. He gives an exceedingly
    meticulous analysis of the metrical treatment of syllables, especially elision; the book ends
    with brief remarks on hypermetrical syllables, rhyme, stanzas, the sonnet, hexameters, and
    sound. In a real sense this dense little volume could be considered an early work in Comparative
    versification, since the Romance languages are treated as a whole, with references to and
    examples from Italian and the classical languages. But English is taken as the unquestionable
    head. Philbrick (D323, pp. 274-76) accuses Conway of plagiarizing from Crowe (E142). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E514">
   <bib>Cotterhill, H[enry] B. "On Rhythm in English Verse." Appendix I to his edition of Milton's
    Lycidas. London: Blackie &amp; Son, 1902. pp. 97-105. </bib>
   <notes> Emphasizes that English is scanned by stresses or beats rather than by "feet," and
    compares briefly (three pages each) the systems of stress metrics (Bridges) and musical metrics
    (French writers). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E515">
   <bib>Coward, W[illiam]. Licentia Poetica discuss'd: or, the True Test of Poetry. Without with It
    is Impossible to Judge of, or Compose, a Correct English Poem. . . . London: William Carter,
    1709. </bib>
   <notes> In the thiry-page Preface Coward approves the writing of English measures by "imitation"
    of those of the Greek and Latin Poets. In practice he never thwarts an English stress for a
    "long" syllable but he does promote and suppress his stresses rather erratically, making "ruine"
    a pyrrhic (Ë Ë ), "aeternal" a molossus (Ì Ì Ì ), "every" a tribrach, and "And bid the"
    antibacchic (Ì Ì Ë). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E516">
   <bib>Crapsey, Adelaide. A Study in English Metrics. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1916. rpt Boston:
    Milford House, 1972. 80 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Curious and interesting: Crapsey asserts that this study applies phonetics to metrical
    problems, but in fact this is a lexical-syntactic study: there are tables of data here on the
    incidence of monosyllables, disyllables, and polysyllables in nursery rhymes, Milton, Tennyson,
    Swinburne, Pope, and others. The rationale for this method is that metrics analyzes "units of
    verse-feet," and that we must similarly analyze "the basic phonetic units of speech--i.e.,
    phonetic word-forms" in order to possess concrete information for the study of "one of the
    fundamental problems of verse as a whole, the relation of the word to the foot." Thereafter, the
    author works to produce a "consistent theory of English verse-structure as a whole" by reviewing
    the metrical theory of the time (Saintsbuty, Omond, Bridges, and others), followed by remarks on
    the problem of "secondary accent." The author, a poet, died in 1914. I must confess to finding
    this work surprisingly well-informed. Cf. Creek (E18). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E517">
   <bib>Culler, A. Dwight. "Edward Bysshe and the Poet's Handbook." PMLA 63 (1948): 858-85. </bib>
   <notes> Based on his dissertation work at Yale in 1941, "Handbooks for Poets in the Eighteenth
    Century." With immense erudition Culler traces the sources, nature, and influences of Bysshe's
    enormously influential handbook (E506); indeed, it is not too much to say that Bysshe is the
    most important prosodic work produced between 1589 (Puttenham) and 1775 (Steele). Culler shows
    convincingly that Bysshe was heavily indebted to Joshua Poole's work (E520), and also that
    virtually every other poetic handbook, grammar, dictionary, rhyming dictionary, and commonplace
    book of the eighteenth century is derived, usually nearly entirely, from Bysshe. And through
    Walker's later rhyming dictionary, which also is Bysshe's progeny, he remained a standard source
    well into the twentieth century. If we remember that Bysshe meant his book as a reference and a
    handbook, not a prosodical treatise, we can obtain a rare glimpse of what the poets of the age
    took as an authority on versification, as opposed to the pronouncements of the scholars, the two
    being scarecely reconcilable at best. In terms of prosodic theory, however, Bysshe's influence
    was wholly pernicious, and quite extended. His system is entirely syllabic, basing meter on
    count of syllables instead of accents or feet. He obtained this system by lifting it wholesale
    from Claude Lancelot's 1663 French Treatise Quatre Traitiz de Poësies Latine, Françciose,
    Italienne, et Espagnole. Thus Bysshe simply attempted to force-fit the template of Romance
    prosody onto the English language, ignoring the fact that it did not--never could--fit, thereby
    perpetrating a misconception that would hold sway until the Romantic era (esp. Christabel). The
    Classical system would not fit the verse native to England, nor would the French, even though
    Bysshe could make men believe it for nearly a century. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E518">
   <bib>Cummings, Donald W. "Towards a Theory of Prosodic Analysis for English Metrical Verse." DA
    27 (1966): 177A (Washington). </bib>
   <notes> In contrast to all the other metrical theories of this century, Cummings' system
    conflates meter and rhythm rather than distinguishing them. In chapters 1 and 2 here a system
    for analyzing "rhythm phrases" is given which combines traditional metrics with acoustic
    phonetics under the aegis of a Gestalt theory of reader perception. The practical results are
    that in his scansions (model on p. 22; diagram of method on p. 14) he refuses to let the
    metrical divisions cut through words; he can provide no clearcut rules for scansion, and no
    discerning consistency is evident in the analysis. But in chapters 3-5 he maps out three new
    types of analysis which are sophisticated and intriguing: "extrinsic stress" analysis combines a
    marking of the phrase-boundaries with Trager-Smith stress levels, adjusted by "weighting," to
    produce Stress Contour graphs and concomitant Transitional Features charts; "intrinsic stress"
    analysis argues that primary stresses are no more equal than syllables are in general, and if we
    establish "intrinsic vowel scales" assigning a weight to each vowel in terms of stress, pitch,
    and duration in each consonantal environment, an improved Stress Contour results; analysis of
    sound patterning can be improved if vowels and consonants are grouped by phonetic families in a
    "fusion" analysis which will reveal asymmetrical (ground) and symmetrical (figure) repetition as
    well as heightening and muting of the meter in verse-lines by clustering and linking of sounds.
    A very detailed yet expansive study. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E519">
   <bib>Cummings, D. W., and John Herum. "Metrical Boundaries and Rhythm-Phrases." MLQ 28 (1967):
    405-12. </bib>
   <notes> "The perception of metrical effects depends on set expectations in the mind of a reader.
    These expectations provide . . . a norm, a predisposition toward a certain patterning." A
    Gestalt approach based on the premise that the experienced reader of English poetry "tries to
    perceive a segmentation into units corresponding to iambic feet" (italics added). The authors
    argue, that is, that there is a pressure in English poetry for the reader to perceive the iambic
    line not as pairs of syllables grouped accentually, but simply segmentally--by "phrasal
    segmentation after each strong stress"--the simple grouping of pairs of syllables. "The English
    iambic tradition rests upon more than the iambic accentuation normally seen as characteristic of
    it; it rests, too, on a norm of iambic segmentation." These segments, which are "the basic
    rhythmic units in English metrical verse." the authors term rhythm-phrases; they serve to
    resolve "the demands exerted by the grammatical, the rhetorical, and the metrical norms." The
    authors explore the problems of diaeresis, without terming it so, and discuss various
    segmentations which try to resolve the conflicting pressures in various lines. The whole
    argument is ingeniously simple and intriguing even though it clearly borders on circularity.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E520">
   <bib>D., J., [Joshua Poole? John Dryden?] "The Preface, Being a Short Institution of English
    Poesie." In Joshua Poole's The English Parnassus: Or a Helpe to English Poesie. London: 1657;
    2nd ed. 1677. </bib>
   <notes> A comparison of this with Daniel (E521) will show its principal source, I think; its
    principle influence is on Bysshe (E505), who takes over the general plan of the book--a short
    prosodia followed by a dictionary of rhymes, a collection of apposite epithets, and a compendium
    of choice phrases and quotations. The Preface treats mainly of the genres in poetry and of those
    things to be avoided in order to insure harmonious verses, viz.: any failure of "exact
    observation of the accent," syntactic dislocation, awkward elisions, feminine rhymes, near
    rhymes, rich rhymes, long polysyllables, and empty epithets (mere fillers). We are told that
    "harmony, in prose, consists in an exact placing of the accent. . . . in poesie, it consists
    besides the aforesaid conditions of prose in measure, proportion, and Rhime." It seems very
    unlikely that the author of this rather simpleminded preface was the young Dryden. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E521">
   <bib>Daniel, Samuel. A Defense of Rhyme [1603]. Rpt as Vol. 5 of The complete works of Samuel
    Daniel. Ed. A. B. Grosart. 5 Vols. London, 1895-96. Ed. Arthur Colby Sprague, Chicago:
    University of Chicago Press, 1930; rpt 1965. In Smith (A26), vol. 2, pp. 356-84. </bib>
   <notes> Daniel's reply to Campion's Observations (E134) defending the native versification would
    have swept the field even if Campion's advocacy of the classical meters had been timely and
    persuasive (instead of a decade too late). With remarkable vigor D. sets about the construction
    and application of an unmatchable engine of assault, binding plain act and force of argument
    with engaging eloquence: "All verse is but a frame of wordes confinde within certaine measure .
    . . which frame of wordes consisting of Rithmus or Metrum, Number or Measure." And in English
    "accent [is] the chief Lord and graue Gouernour of Numbers." It were outright folly to apply the
    laws of one language to the verse of another; "every language hath her proper number or measure
    fitted to vse and delight," enforced and given legitimacy by "both Custom and Nature." (Besides,
    "it is but a fantastike giddinesse to forsake the way of other men.") "For as Greeke and Latine
    verse consists of the number and quantitie of sillables, so doth the English verse of measure
    and accent. . . . so that the English verse then hath number, measure, and harmonie in the best
    proportion of Musike." Daniel is even willing to admit that the continual reappearance of rhyme
    in the couplet is tiresome (his suggested remedy is emjambement, which he thinks "graceful"),
    yet he denies, adamantly, that Rhyme is too flimsy a support for verse (it "hath more of delight
    than euer bare numbers," since its "known frame hath those due staies for the minde, those
    incounters of touch as makes the motion certaine, though the varietie be infinite"), or that the
    necessity of finding rhymes is any "impediment to [the poet's] conceit." Finally, he will not
    flinch to face Campion directly: "For what a doe haue we heere, what strange precepts of an Arte
    about the framing of an Iambique verse in our language, which when allis done, reaches not by a
    foote, but falleth out to be the plaine ancient verse consisting of tenne sillables or fiue
    feete, which hat euer beene vsed amongst vs time out of minde. . . . So that of all these eight
    seuerall kindes of new promised numbers [Campion's] you see what we haue. Onely what was our
    owne before, and the same but apparelled in forraine Titles. . . ." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E522">
   <bib>Davidson, James Wood. The Poetry of the Future. New York: John B. Alden, 1888. 182 pp. </bib>
   <notes> "The main aim of the following pages is to show that the one essential characteristic of
    verse--the language of poetry--in English is Rhythm. . . . We dismiss, at the outset . . . the
    long and learned-looking array . . . the endless but never-nameless array of metres . . . all
    the lumber of the old time prosodies. We shall retain only so much of the classical phraseology
    as we need in order to make plain the naturally easy subject of versification." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E523">
   <bib>de Ford, Sara, and C. H. Lott. Forms of Verse: British and American. New York:
    Appleton-Century-Crofts, 1971. 392 pp. An introductory handbook for students; each chapter
    traces the development of a metrical or stanzaic form. Exercises, Glossary, Index. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E524">
   <bib>Dennis, John. "Of Prosody." [1722]. Rpt in The Critical Works of John Dennis. Ed. Edward
    Niles Hooker. 2 vols. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1939. Vol. 2, pp. 236-40. </bib>
   <notes> See also the Prefaces to The Monument and to Britannia Triumphans (pp. 297, 375-79 in
    vol. 1) and accompanying Notes (499-500, 518) for Dennis's approbatory views on Blank Verse; on
    this see also s.v. "Versification," "Rhyme," and "Blank Verse" in the Index (end of vol. 2). The
    short essay "Of Prosody" originally appeared in James Greenwood's An Essay towards a Practical
    English Grammar [1722]. Dennis distinguishes Numbers, Measure, Cadence, and Rhyme, the
    definitions being relatively traditional. He disagrees with Bysshe only in allowing more
    metrical variation and deploring the use of rhyme. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E525">
   <bib>Earle, John. "Of Prosody, or the Musical Element in Speech." In his The Philology of the
    English Tongue. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1866; 1871; </bib>
   <notes> 3rd ed. 1880 (Omond thinks it the best); 4th ed. 1887. The final chapter touches on
    accent (the basis of modern verse, and to be distinguished from emphasis), alliteration,
    sound-mimesis in language (onomatopoeia), rhyme, and meter (sections 648-52). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E526">
   <bib>Eaton, Richard B., Jr. "The Contributions of James Rush to Prosodic Theory." West Virginia
    University Philological Papers 19 (1972): 1-11. </bib>
   <notes> Rhetorician and phonetician, Rush was author of the influential treatise The Philosophy
    of the Human Voice in 1827, which was one of the three works singled out for review by Patmore
    (E384). Indebted to Steele (E394) and Sheridan (E651), and repeating some of the commonplaces of
    the day, Rush is nevertheless important for his significant analysis of pitch in rhythm (tone-
    color and the emotive effects of intonation are also noteworthy topics in his book). Verse he
    believed regulated chiefly by accents, though he recognized that quantity, even though variable
    in English, is too significant a feature to be ignored entirely. Steele's musical analogy and
    scansion he declined to follow. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E527">
   <bib>Eichler, A. Taktumstellung und Schwebende Betonung." Archiv 165 (1934): 187-98. </bib>
   <notes> Tests for the hypothesized "inverted feet" and "hovering stress" in English and German
    recordings of Hamlet. Part 2 of the article treats German songs. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E528">
   <bib>"English Prosody." Edinburgh Review 213 (1911): 1-31. </bib>
   <notes> A long, generally laudatory review of Saintsbury (A8), which begins with his
    principles--equivalence and enjambment--and prose style ("it is a kindness to say the least
    possible"), then turns to an expansive summary history of English versification from Old English
    to the turn of the twentieth century. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E529">
   <bib>"English Prosody." The Quarterly Review 215 (1911): 69-96. </bib>
   <notes> An excellent critique of the theoretical position of Saintsbury (22 of the essay's 27
    pages are devoted to him), followed by quick glances also at Bridges, Stone, and Omond, some
    striking observations on the accentual vs. the syllabic impulses behing English meter (pp.
    92-93), and a distinction between meter and rhythm. Dispassionate and judicious, yet keenly
    discriminating, the article offers such provocative statements as: "an accent has more influence
    over the syllable which precedes than over that which follows it. Every musician will understand
    this." Who wrote it? Alden? </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E530">
   <bib>Evans, R[obert] W[ilson]. A Treatise on Versification. London: Francis &amp; John
    Rivington, 1852. 169 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Among the various efforts of its century, this book rests with a greater weight than most
    of the others, a weight and measure of contemplation, one might say, far removed from the usual
    treatises. Verse is based, we find, on "the regulated recurrence of a syllable which is
    peculiarly marked" by duration, tone, or emphasis in pronunciation; each of these latter has
    been used at some time, though stress "is the only basis of versification in every modern
    language." Chapters follow on Quantity and Stress, six chapters on the (non- metrical) Pause,
    and, late, two chapters on the Hexameter. The book is actually, though, a study in conparative
    versification, since Evans' emphasis (along with his examples) falls equally on the Ancient and
    the Modern languages. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E531">
   <bib>Everett, Erastus. A System of English Versification: Containing Rules for the Structure of
    the Different Kinds of Verse, Illustrated by Numerous Examples from the Best Poets. New York: D.
    Appleton, 1848. 198 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Chapter 1 is on Quantity, which, we are told, is the basis of English verse, but "the
    quantity of each word depends on its accent," so that even though the classical terms are
    explicitly used, Everett scans by stress. Monosyllabic words are "long" or "short" by parts of
    speech. But "long" syllables also take twice as long to pronounce as "short." Chapters on
    metrical types (eight kinds of feet), pause, hiatus, elision, rhyme, and (syntactic) inversion.
    See E263. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E532">
   <bib>Fogg, Peter Walkden. Elementa Anglicana; or the Principles of English Grammar. 2 vols.
    Stockport: J. Clarke for the Author, 1796. </bib>
   <notes> See Dissertations XI ("On Prosody") and XII ("On Versification") in vol. 2, pp. 185-202.
    (This second volume was later reissued as Dissertations Grammatical and Philological; there see
    pp. 55-72.) "The music of English verse depends on the disposition of accents." In degrees of
    accent he recognizes heavy, light, and very light; quantity he thinks may exist either by
    lengthening the vowel or dwelling on the final consonant. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E533">
   <bib>Fortescue, James. "Latin and English Prosody." Preface to his Pomery Hill, a Poem . . .
    With Other Poems. London, 1754. </bib>
   <notes> Not seen. No copy in the British museum. Cited in Omond (A5), p. 297. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E534">
   <bib>Fowler, Roger. "What is Metrical Analysis?" Anglia 86 (1968): 280-320; rpt in Fowler (A12),
    pp. 141-77. </bib>
   <notes> Fowler's metatheoretical inquiry into the components of an adequate theory of English
    meter appropriates Jakobson's pair of conceptual couples--verse design, verse-instance;
    delivery-design, delivery-instance--and adds one more, verse-type and metrical set, producing an
    ordered hierarchy: (verse) verse type verse design metrical set delivery design verse instance
    delivery instance (It will be seen that metrical set and verse instance thus correspond to
    reading design and reading instance, though Fowler does not make this explicit.) Each level of
    the heirarchy is then discussed in detail. "Verse is language with additional formal
    constraints." Verse-type is determined by the feature relevant to the verse--stress, quantity,
    or tone. Verse design is the inflexible pattern (e.g., iambic pentameter) set as invariant for
    the poem as a whole; actual variations (e.g. "trochaic substitutions") occur at the level of
    verse instance and "must not be spuriously reified" (this is a crucial nexus in the theory).
    Metrical set is "a reader's disposition, through past experience and through design- signals in
    the poem, to impose a familiar reading on any metre which does not absolutely forbid it."
    Thereafter the bulk of the essay tackles the critical and delicate problem of verse instance,
    Fowler giving a detailed account of that "whole area of descriptive metrics" whose
    responsibility is to show how a reader, operating under regular phonological and syntactic
    rules, (four such rules are given), determines which syllables in a line are ictic, whether or
    not the line is regular in number of syllables (Fowler thinks the theory of elision unlikely and
    prefers to admit extra-metrical syllables), and whether the number and positions of the
    syllables are acceptable (iambic pentameters frequently fail of five stresses, and reversed feet
    do occur). Actually "the ontology of verse instance remains uncertain," but since it partakes of
    both the objective linguistic features of the line, and also the reader's predisposed metrical
    set, the perfect pattern of the design need never be realized anywhere at all in a poem for it
    to be perceived as in that design. Fowler takes the position that even lines identical in
    syllable- count and stress-pattern are different verse instances, since their linguistic
    textures are different in many other respects. Concluding remarks on delivery. All this amounts
    to a theory of meter, as Fowler admits at the end. An advanced study, very dense in import and
    rather stiff in tone; not for students. The essay thoroughly substantiates its opening
    observation: "the verse situation is extremely complex." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E535">
   <bib>Fussell, Paul, Jr. "Meter" and "Metrical Variation." Princeton (A18), pp. 496-99, 500-1. </bib>
   <notes> See also s.v. "Alliterative Meter," "Ballad Meter," "Christabel Meter," "Scansion,"
    "Foot," "Compensation," and "Poetic Contractions." The head article on meter treats, in small
    compass, definition, origins, types, and functions. The definition is indecisive; the types are
    four--accentual, syllabic, accentual-syllabic, and quantitative; the functions include being
    "one of the primary correlatives of meaning," a distancing effect, and a framing or
    de-naturalizing effect. Metrical tension is also discussed. The metrical variations are the
    traditional mono-,di-, and tri-syllabic substitutions (Fussel allows the traditional but very
    problematic pyrrhics and spondees). Given the nature and scope of the Princeton, surely a more
    extensive treatment of this absolutely central subject was required. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E536">
   <bib>-----. "A note on Samuel Johnson and the Rise of Accentual Prosodic Theory." PQ 33 (1954):
    431-33. </bib>
   <notes> Notes an addition to the 4th edition of the Dictionary, written in response to criticism,
    wherein Johnson was willing to yield a bit on his earlier insistence on absolute regularity of
    stress and syllabism. The pre-Romantic movement toward accentualism was under way. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E537">
   <bib>-----. Poetic Meter &amp; Poetic Form. New York: Random House, 1965; 2nd rev. ed. 1979. </bib>
   <notes> The most widely disseminated student's manual of metrics available at present, the intent
    of which is not so much typological as heuristic: Fussell aims to "sensitize" students to the
    supple flexes of poetic form. But, as paradign of the perfect American consumer, he is more than
    willing to trade in precision for style, so that what this book gains in urbanity it more than
    loses in rigor. Fussell allows up to seventeen types of feet, and his scansions are
    consistently, sometimes wildly, unreliable. His theory in general is almost purely
    expressionist, even though none of the explanations of metrical effect he lists in chapter 1 is
    seriously maintained by anyone anymore. Worse, he can sometimes say the most embarrassing
    things: substitutions in meter "are governed by instinct, whim or taste rather than by rule";
    Old English meter has only a limited capacity for interplay"; the volta in a sonnet "occurs
    somewhere in the white space that separates line 8 from line 9." We should expect as much from
    anyone whose theory is that "to do something to the reader is the end of poetry." Metrical types
    are enumerated in chapter 3, stanzas in chapter 7. The revised edition alters a few judgments,
    prunes the Bibliography, and adds a chapter on Free Verse, which is also separately published
    (E1473). Whatever the beginning student might learn here about "sensitivity" cannot be valued
    over his learning a fundamentally licentious method; send him instead to Malof (E581) for
    information on forms, McAuley (E578) for scansion- technique, and Smith (B202) and Booth (B20)
    for close reading. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E538">
   <bib>Gascoigne, George. "Certayne Notes of Instruction concerning the making of verse or ryme in
    English, written at the request of Master Edouardi Donato." In his The Posies of George
    Gascoigne. . . . London: Richard Smith, 1575; </bib>
   <notes> thereafter rpt in The Whole Works of George Gascoigne, Esquire. . . .London, 1587. Rpt in
    the English Reprint Series, no. 11. Ed. Edward Arber. London, 1868; rpt New York: AMS Press,
    1966. Also in The Complete Works of George Gascoigne. Ed. John W. Cunliffe. Cambridge: Cambridge
    University Press, 1907-10; rpt Grosse Pointe, Mich.: Scholarly Press, 1969. Also, of course, in
    Smith (A26), vol. 1, pp. 46-57. Our first native treatise devoted entirely to native
    versification. Gascoigne's sixteen practical pointers emphasize the importance of Invention,
    syllabic regularity ("hold the just measure wherewith you begin your verse"), meter based on
    accent ("place every word in his natural Emphasis or sound . . . with such length or shortness,
    elevation or depression of syllables, as is commonly pronounced or used"; such accent has three
    degrees in English, grave, circumflex, and light, and "the grave accent is drawn out or elevate,
    and maketh that syllable long whereupon it is placed"), feet (Chaucer's verse, though seemingly
    uneven to the eye, is in fact regular to the ear, and he teaches us not to wrench any accent for
    the sake of the meter), monosyllables for facility and native origin, rhymes which do not strain
    the sense in order to chime, familiar diction and normal stanzaic order, caesuras, stanza (rime
    royal and other Italian forms, Poulter's Measure), correspondence of sentence with verse-unit,
    and riding rhyme. See also E40. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E539">
   <bib>"General Introduction to the Science of Metre and the Structure of Verse." Schipper (All),
    Book I, Part I, Chapter 1, pp. 1-14. </bib>
   <notes> Schipper's General Prologue sets forth the purposes and value of "the science of metre."
    Four varieties of stress are recognized--lexical, syntactic, rhetorical, and rhythmic--as well
    as four degrees--primary, subsidiary, weak, and absent. The cardinal rule of English stress is
    that it must fall on the lexical root syllable. Schipper bases English meter on stress, and "the
    measure or foot always remains the unity which is the basis of all modern metrical systems."
    Three types of rhyme are noted. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E540">
   <bib>Ghiselin, Brewster. "Paeonic Measures in English Verse." MLN 57 (1942): 336-41. </bib>
   <notes> Argues reasonably that sequences of three weak syllables are not all that uncommon in
    English verse, and that these ( / x x x ) should be acknowledged as Paeons rather than as
    dactyles (eliding one syllable) or double trochees (by secondary stress on the third syllable).
    A number of poems dense in paeonic feet are mentioned, and all four of the classical types of
    paeons are demonstrated, the second (x/xx) and third (xx/x) apparently being the most common.
    E541 Gill, Alexander. Logonomia Anglica [1619]. Ed. Bror and Arvid Danielsson. Stockholm Studies
    in English, nos. 26, 27. Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell, 1972. Gill was Milton's tutor.
    Sections 25-28 treat "Accent," "Metre," "Accented Rhymed Verse," and "Of Poetry Composed in
    Metres of Latin Poets." Though the term "meter" is used to describe the quantity of every
    syllable, of a foot, of metre properly speaking, and of poetry," "quantity" is used only to
    satisfy the adamant Latinists, since "every syllable which has an acute or circumflex accent is
    long," based on the premise that "our prosody should not be yoked to the rules of Greek or
    Latin, but should be measured by the yardstick of our own rules alone." Gill produces elaborate
    rules for determining "quantity" from accent. Though he will admit rhyme in English verse, he
    allows it only grudgingly, citing numerous other devices necessary to "moderate" the "nausea or
    wearying" of a too-frequent use. Metrical feet acknowledged for English: spondee, trochee, iamb,
    tribrach, molossus, dactyl, anapest, amphimacer, fourth paeon, and choriambus. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E542">
   <bib>Grew, Sydney. A Book of English Prosody. London: Grant Richards, 1924. 231 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in TLS, 20 March 1924, p. 171; in The Nation Athenaeum 34 (1924): 712; in English
    Studies 8 (1926): 56-58. A thoroughgoing handbook; it states at the very outset that "Verse is
    Metrical" and "Verse is Accentual." In meter, "the foot consists of an accented syllable (or
    rather accented place) to which are affiliated one or more weak places"; thus the meter is
    separated from the rhythm of verse. Indeed, Grew gives the fullest collection of apposite
    examples of rhythmic "Phrasing" against the metrical "Abstract Pattern" that I have seen; his
    only failing is that he insists on keeping the old and misleading terms (monosyllabic foot, weak
    foot, spondee, pyrrhic, ionic, paeonic, inversion, substitution, equivalence) as denoting
    variations in the meter, but these are in fact variations in the rhythm against the metrical
    paradigm, not flexes in the meter itself. In this book one can observe perhaps more clearly than
    anywhere else the nexus between the old prosody and the new. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E543">
   <bib>Guest, Edwin. A History of English Rhythms. 2 vols. London: William Pickering, 1838; 2nd
    ed. edited by W. W. Skeat in one volume. London: George Bell and Sons, 1882. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in The Gentleman's Magazine for June 1838; The Athenaeum, 1838, p. 551. See the
    critiques by Mayor (E594) and Jenkin (E299), and see E918. Under the influence of the early
    nineteenth-century revival of interest in Anglo-Saxon, Guest was encouraged to apply the
    principles of Old English verseform to the modern languages as well. The result, though
    fundamentally misconceived, is nevertheless a great early milestone in the history of English
    metrics. Against the general opinion of his time, Guest insisted that the basis of English meter
    was the succession of accents and not of time. By profession he was a philologist, not a
    literary critic, and indeed, in order to gather quotations for the first edition of this book,
    Guest was forced to copy out the great majority by hand from the original MSS themselves, there
    being no standard texts in 1838. Skeat, then, was forced to search out and verify these
    thousands of passages for the second edition. Guest's specialty, moreover, was Old and Middle
    English, a fact which insured that not only would the historical focus of the book be
    overweighted on the earliest times in our poetry, but also that he would draw his principles and
    methodology from the analogy with the Anglo-Saxon system. Thus, Guest identifies not "feet" but
    "sections" of syllable-groups as the basis of meter. He identifies twelve types of these
    sections, each type having three variants, Normal, Lengthened, and Doubly Lengthened. In Skeat's
    notation, where the capital A stands for an accented syllable and the lower-case b stands for an
    unaccented syllable, these twelve types of sections (hence rhythm-units) are: 1. AbA. 1l. AbAb.
    1ll. AbAbb. 5. bAbA. 5l. bAbAb. 5ll. bAbAbb. 9. 9l. 9ll. bbAbA. bbAbAb. bbAbAbb. 2. AbbA. 2l.
    AbbAb. 2ll. AbbAbb. 6. bAbbA. 6l. bAbbAb. 6ll. bAbbAbb. 10. bbAbbA. 10l. bbAbbAb. 10ll.
    bbAbbAbb. 3. AbAbbA. 3l. AbAbbAb. 3ll. AbAbbAbb. 7. bAbAbbA. 7l. bAbAbbAb. 7ll. bAbAbbAbb. 11.
    bbAbAbbA. 11l. bbAbAbbAb. 11ll. bbAbAbbAbb. 4. AbbAbbA. 4l. AbbAbbAb. 4ll. AbbAbbAbb. 8.
    bAbbAbbA. 8l. bAbbAbbAb. 8ll. bAbbAbbAbb. 12. bbAbbAbbA. 12l. bbAbbAbbAb. 12ll. bbAbbAbbAbb.
    Each type may be expanded (or replicated internally) so long as its nature is preserved; type 5
    may be either bAbA or bAbAbA or bAbAbAbA, etc. Guest also uses the colon to denote a caesura in
    the line, and an upright bar (|) to mark a preceding syllable as stressed. Thus Milton's
    "Anguish and doubt and fear, and sorrow and pain" may be scanned An| guish and doubt| and fear|
    : and sor| row and pain| and conveniently notated as 2:5. Structurally, the History of English
    Rhythms is divided into four Books: the first defines syllable, accent, quantity, rime, and
    pause; the second gives illustrations of each of the twelve rhythmic types, the third is a
    history of stanza forms. In many respects not even Saintsbury's three-volume History (A8) can
    rival the erudition, clarity, industry, and graceful tone of Guest's treatise, and though his
    system seems to us an odd one, it is easy to learn and use. As Henry James said in another
    place, the book "supports familiarity"; it will not weary the reader soon, as Saintsbury will.
    Though Guest's direct influence has been slight in the century after his work was first
    published, his Accentualist principles have pretty much won the field. Guest's system has been
    applied only by T. R. Price (E1278), however. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E544">
   <bib>Gummere, Francis B. A Handbook of Poetics for Students of English Verse. Boston: Ginn &amp;
    Company, 1885; 2nd ed. 1886; 3rd ed. 1890; 1902. </bib>
   <notes> A student handbook. Part III contains three chapters on metrical devices, one on the
    history of English meters, and one on stanzaic forms. In the custom of the time, Gummere admits
    three degrees of speech-stress (strong, half, and weak), and word-, sentence-, and verse-accent.
    The accentual basis of meter is clearly separated from the rhythm of equal time-periods. Along
    with that of Gayley and Scott (L46), Gummere's work was the most influential in America around
    the turn of the century, and though it is now nearly a century old, it remains well worth
    perusal: the exposition of the concepts of pitch, stress, and duration is historically
    organized, clearly presented, and solidly based on scholarship. See Gummere's further statements
    on meter in MLN 1 (1886): 35-36. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E545">
   <bib>Hall, William C. "Rhythm." Manchester Quarterly 43 (1924): 17-31. </bib>
   <notes> Half on the rhythm of prose, half on verse. Hall speaks confusedly of "quantitative
    stress" (apparently rhetorical emphasis deriving from syllabic "weight" of duration) and
    "emphatic stress" (emphasis resulting from accent). The rhythm of verse he considers to be based
    on both (i.e., the metrical ictus can be fulfilled sometimes by one, sometimes by the other, or
    both together). English meter has no predominant base-foot, he thinks, but is much more diverse
    than we usually believe; e.g., the first line of Paradise Lost actually comprises an iamb,
    monosyllabic foot, trochee, dactyl, and an anapest. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E546">
   <bib>Halpern, Martin. "On the Two Chief Metrical Modes in English." PMLA 77 (1962): 177-86. </bib>
   <notes> In a brilliant codification of the traditional concepts of English meter, Halpern shows
    that a more compelling distinction than that between stress meter and syllable-stress meter in
    English is the one between "the entire iambic tradition and all English verse written in
    strong-stress meter, whether syllable-counting or not." In iambic verse the important
    differences of stress between syllables are relative, within the two-member metrical foot (this
    is the Relative Stress Principle), whereas in all the other meters the differences are absolute.
    (I.e., in iambic verse, metrical foot demarcation precedes metrical stress assignment, whereas
    in the other meters metrical stress assignment follows directly from the linguistic stresses:
    the strong are strong and the weak weak). This explains our comon sensation that the beats in
    trochaic in the ternary meters are so "clear and emphatic" in comparison with the unstressed
    syllables, while they are not so in iambic meter: in iambic verse the gradations are modulated.
    The trochaic the ternary meters, like simple stress verse, are isoaccentual and isochronic
    (iambic verse is neither), but unlike stress verse, which achieves some modulation by varying
    the number of syllables, these meters, having a regular syllable-count, lose modulation
    altogether, which explains why we cannot bear them for extended runs. In iambic verse the only
    permissible variations are the addition or deletion of a syllable or reversal of a foot.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E547">
   <bib>Hamer, Enid. The Metres of English Poetry. London: Methuen, 1930. 334 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in TLS, 21 August 1930, p. 671; in Review of English Studies 7 (1931): 493; in MLR
    27 (1932): 113; in Englische Studien 67 (1932): 258-59; in Anglia Beiblatt 44 (1933): 291-94. A
    survey of metrical forms in English verse, with copious examples. Hamer's metrical principles
    are accentual (three degress of stress are identified--strong, mid, and weak), but no clear
    distinction is made between either (1) rhythm and meter, or (2) stress verse and
    syllable-counting verse, with this result: the four commonest feet are denoted the rhythmic
    base, with some twelve other feet admissible as modulations: stressed and unstressed
    monosyllabic feet, major and minor ionics, pyrrhics and spondees, choriambics, tribrachs,
    amphibrachs, bacchics, antibacchics, and second paeons. The result, predictably, is that Hamer's
    scansions are wildly unreliable. But the book offers four chapters on the evolution of Blank
    Verse, as well as one on French forms and one on Classical imitations. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E548">
   <bib>Harford, F[rederick] K. A Note on the Scansion of the Pentameter and Its Use in English
    Poetry. Oxford: 1900. </bib>
   <notes> A pamphlet. Not seen (not in the British Museum), but Omond looked at it or owned it, and
    it is annotated in Lafourcade (q.v. in Appendix D). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E549">
   <bib>Hearn, Lafcadio. Lectures on Prosody. Tokyo: The Hokuseido Press, 1929. 90 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A highly simplified account for Japanese students. Allows only the four commonest feet.
    Hearn, a well-known writer, forsook the west for Japan in 1890; see his biography by Vera
    McWilliams. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E550">
   <bib>Herbert, William (Dean of Manchester). Review of Mitford (E600); Edinburgh Review, 1805; </bib>
   <notes> rpt in his Works of the Late Honorable and Very Reverend William Herbert, Dean of
    Manchester. 3 vols. London: H. G. Bohn, 1842. Vol. 2, pp. 31- 79, 212-15 (Supplement). There is
    a summary on pp. 77-79, and Herbert gives his own view of English versification on pp. 65-71.
    The essay opens with a long discussion of Greek and English phonetics and Greek popular
    accentual poetry. Herbert argues that Greek speech and verse had tonic (stress) accents as well
    as quantity and that English stress does not lengthen a syllable (contrary to Foster, Sheridan,
    and Kames). On the modern accentual hexameters he observes keenly that since classical verse had
    both accent and quantity, to replace the one by the other is not to reproduce or even achieve an
    analogous effect but to confound, conflate, and wreck the original meter. The modern Romance
    meters were "not modern inventions, but the old accentual laws of Latin verse, which survived
    those of quantity." English meter is based on "accentual feet," one stress to the foot, but
    quantity "neither is, not ought to be entirely disregarded"; in fact, since many links have
    seven, eight, or nine long syllables, "variety of quantity is rather to be sought for than
    restricted." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E551">
   <bib>Herries, John. The Elements of Speech. London: Edward and Charles Dilly, 1773; </bib>
   <notes> facsimile reprint: Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar Press, 1968. A curious early work of
    rhetoric and elocution; the author believes that English verse is of precisely the same mold and
    material as Latin and Greek, yet he refuses to consder quantity at all (p. 123 ff), apparently
    thinking that Greek versification was based on accent. He recognizes the "absurd notion that has
    long prevailed, viz: that there was no difference between the accent and the quantity, in the
    English language"; his response: "an absurdity so glaring, does not need a refutation." His
    misconception of Greek leads him to a true conception of English; so the lame and the halt shall
    be first. Versification is discussed on pp. 123-88. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E552">
   <bib>Hodgson, Shadworth. "English Verse." In his Outcast Essays and Verse Translations. London:
    Longmans, Green, 1881. pp. 207-360. </bib>
   <notes> A seemingly indefatigable defence of the accentual basis of English versification against
    the views of Guest (E543), Mitford, Patmore, Ruskin, and others, though Hodgson seems to accept
    Guest's principle of sections early in part IV of the essay (p. 265 ff), and he asserts that
    "the distinction into feet, therefore, founded on the counting of syllables, is a thing which
    has no natural connection with metres based on stress." Parts I and II establish a phonetic
    basis for the stress-theory; part III surveys Old and Middle English meters; part IV expounds
    the author's system of analysis; V discusses the expressive devices of duration, pitch, and
    tone-color; VI surveys Blank Verse and VII the classical-imitative meters; VIII is the Summary.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E553">
   <bib>Hood, Tom. A Practical Guide to English Versification. London, 1869; </bib>
   <notes> new and enlarged edition, "to which are added </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E554">
   <bib>Bysshe's 'Rules for Making English Verse' etc." . London: John Hogg, 1877. 238 pp. </bib>
   <notes> [Title on Cover: Rules for Making English Verses] Saintsbury approved of this little
    book, though it is merely a versemaking handbook. Nearly half of the volume is taken up by a
    Dictionary of Rhymes and by the excerpted Bysshe. For us, now, the most interesting part is
    Chapter 1, which analyses Pope's "mimetic" lines in the Essay on Criticism. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E555">
   <bib>Hooker, [William] Bryan. "The Rhythmic Relation of Prose and Verse." The Forum 41 (1909):
    424-37. </bib>
   <notes> I should think this essay would be excellently useful for pedagogy: it covers a great
    deal of ground cogently and gracefully. Meter is seen as recurrence of accent at regular
    intervals, variation and phrasing are recognized as essential, and the distinction between
    metrical and speech stresses is carefully preserved. "The ultimate structural relation between
    Prose and Verse . . . is that each gains in beauty as it approaches the other, just so far as
    each clearly retains its own distinctive character." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E556">
   <bib>Howells, T. H., and A. A. Johnson. "A Study of Meter-Sense in Poetry." Journal of Applied
    Psychology 15 (1931): 539-44. </bib>
   <notes> Tests given to high school and college students asking them to pick out one line from a
    group of four, the meter of which (iambic, trochaic, dactylic, or anapestic) corresponds to that
    of a sample line (given but not scanned, of course). Banal results. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E557">
   <bib>Humphrey, Asa. The English Prosody, with Rules Deduced from the Genius of our Language and
    the Examples of the Poets. Boston: Crocker &amp; Brewster, 1847. </bib>
   <notes> Omond did not see this work, which, for its rather insular position, shows some
    unexpected perception. Humphrey identifies the qualities of sound in orthoepy (pronunciation) as
    accent ("stress of voice"), cadence (absence of stress), emphasis (rhetorical or sentential
    stress), tone (intonation, pitch), time, and quantity. Quantity is "the weight, or aggregate
    quantum of sounds, either longer or shorter" and thereby "differs materially from time: time
    only determines the length of sounds." Though these are two distinct entities, they both inhere
    in verse-structure; "they are both affected by accent and cadence, but quantity more than time,
    and quantity more than time also constitutes numbers." Humphrey realizes that though time was
    the origin for quantity in ancient Greek verse, quantity is in essence an abstract concept, and
    though it was called long and short in Greek, it would be more accurately termed "great and
    small quantity" in English. In short, he recognizes the hegemony of accent, even though the old
    terms are preserved. Twelve types of feet are allowed, five of them denoted as commonest. Rules
    for scansion and also for reading are given. The remainder of this little book treats stanzaic
    forms. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E558">
   <bib>Ikegami, Yoshihiko. Eishi no Bumpo [English Versification]. Tokyo, 1967. 238 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Also treats grammar, lexis, and semantics. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E559">
   <bib>Ishii, Hakuson. An Introduction to English Prosody. Tokyo: Shinozaki-shorin, 1964. 268 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Cited in MHRA (1964, #1900) but unlocated by the Library of Congress. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E560">
   <bib>James, VI, King of Scotland. "Ane schort Treatise, conteining some revlis and cautelis to
    be observit and eschewit in Scottis Poesie." In The Essays of a Prentise in the divine art of
    poesie. Edinburgh: Thomas Vautroullier, 1584. Ed. Edward Arber. English Reprint Series, no. 19.
    London, 1869. Rpt in Smith (A26), vol. 1, pp. 208-25. </bib>
   <notes> Written by the King when he was only eighteen, this treatise on the writing of native
    (not classical-imitative) verse speaks of quantities throughout (syllables are termed either
    long, short, or indifferent) without any deeper inquiry, and the only indication that he takes
    accent to determine quantity--and hence confounds accent with quantity--appears early on, when
    the versifier is enjoined to "ryme ay to the hinmest lang syllable (with accent) in the lyne" as
    in "byte and flyte, because the lenth of the syllable, and accent being there." None of his
    quantities violates accent. The rules for rhyme, sectioun (caesura), fitting of the words into
    the meter, stanzas, comparisons, and Inventions are all familiar enough; of interest are his
    terms flowing (for steady or smooth rhythm) and Literall and Tumbling verse (the former the old
    Alliterative line, the latter in anapests and said to be best for flyting (invective)). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E561">
   <bib>Jameson, R. D. "Notes on Dryden's Lost Prosodia." MP 20 (1923): 241-53. </bib>
   <notes> The substance of the treatise Dryden said he had prepared may be reconstructed by
    examining his scattered critical statements on: prosody (a body of mechanical rules); the
    functions of poetry (first to delight, then to instruct); the sources of delight in poetry
    (chiefly the versification itself); qualities of good verse (smoothness, variety, vigor);
    quantity [Jameson is obscure here]; measure (= verse, or line?). number (of syllables per foot,
    perhaps of syllables per line); feet (based on accent and strictly disyllabic); cadence
    (rhythm); pause (caesura?); synaloepha (to be eschewed); rhyme; and stanza. In constrast to
    Bysshe's, Dryden's metric is based on accentual (disyllabic) feet). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E562">
   <bib>Jesperson, Otto. "Notes on Metre" and "Postscript." In Linguistica: Selected Papers in
    English, French, and German. Copenhagen: Levin &amp; Munksgaard, 1933. pp. 249-74. </bib>
   <notes> Also rpt in Journal de Psychologie 30 (1933): 333-38; in Chatman and Levin (A21), pp.
    71-90; and in Gross (A23), pp. 111-30. Originally published in 1900, this essay remains a
    classic of early, clear-sighted argumentation in metrics: Jesperson's insights here are at least
    half a century ahead of their time. He attacks the "permissible substitutions" or "variations
    against the norm" theory of meter, showing it does not explain the facts. He rejects the idea of
    the metrical foot and of only two degrees--Stressed or Weak--in English meter, preferring
    himself four degrees of metrical stress. He asserts the Relative Stress Principle--the
    metrically relevant differences in stress are only relative not absolute. He acknowledges the
    Pause as metrically important and devises an entirely new scansion system to show the rises and
    falls between syllables in the [pentameter] line: a / b \ a / b \ a / b \ a / b \ a / b From our
    vantage, the whole essay remains unwavering in its strength and directness: the questions are
    the hard ones, the position taken is argued simply and clearly, the exemplification is adequate
    to its purpose. In metrics we are not very often in the presence of a first-order mind. See
    Minaishi (E597), and see L413. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E563">
   <bib>Johnson, Dr. Samuel. "Prosody." The final section in the "Grammar of the English Tongue"
    prefixed to his A Dictionary of the English Language. 2 vols. London: 1755. </bib>
   <notes> "Prosody comprises orthoepy, or the rules of pronunciation, and orthometry, or the rules
    of versification." Versification consists in "the arrangement of a certain number of syllables
    according to certain laws," i.e. placement of accent, the regularity of which renders every line
    "the more harmonious, as this rule is more strictly observed." The principle English meters are
    iambic and trochaic, though Alexandrines, fourteeners, and anapestic meters may also be
    observed. English versification allows but "few licenses," these being mainly varieties of
    elision. See also E536. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E564">
   <bib>Jones, William Caswell. Elements and Science of English Versification. Buffalo: The Peter
    Paul Book Company, 1897. 339 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A general introductory handbook. His metrical principles are accentual, and quantity is
    then consigned to be an element of rhythm rather than meter. He allows secondary accent and
    admits seven metrical feet--the common four and the spondee, amphibrach, and cretic. The book's
    three parts treat versification, figures, and genres. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E565">
   <bib>Jordan, Modeste Hannis. The Art of Verse Making. New York: Hannis Jordan, 1915. 61 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A pocket-sized manual surely as trivial at publication as now. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E566">
   <bib>Kames, Henry Home, Lord. Elements of Criticism. 3 vols. London, 1762; rpt Hildesheim,
    Germany, and New York: Georg Olms, 1970. </bib>
   <notes> See vol. 2, chapter 18, section 4, "Versification." The reader should notice p. 360 ff
    (the succeeding pages examine the classical Hexameter) but may begin in earnest at p. 381. Lord
    Kames is the voice of l'ancien régime: he prefers to speak of quantities, and though he
    recognizes the existence of accent, he thinks it can be dispensed with on the grounds that
    "accenting is confined to the long syllables." He allows thirty-four types of feet. The inquiry
    into verse-structure is ordered on the consideration of number, quantity, and arrangement of
    syllables, pause, (caesura-placement receives a very long treatment), and accent. He identifies
    four types of the heroic line (by the caesura after the fourth, fifth, sixth, or seventh
    syllable) but at the end comes finally to prefer Miltonic blank verse. Though the substance in
    this chapter is errant in many ways, the style is refreshingly clear, the method inductive and
    orderly. See E825. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E567">
   <bib>Kellog, George A. "Bridges' Milton's Prosody and Renaissance Metrical Theory." PLMA 68
    (1953): 268-85. </bib>
   <notes> An exposition and critical appreciation of the central argument of Bridges' landmark
    study (E491), augmented by a review of what little can be discovered about Milton's personal
    notions on versification, and also by an examination of some Renaissance prosodic manuals. The
    resultant triple focus illuminates more sharply the whole syllabic tradition operant in English
    verse since the Renaissance, the tradition which Bridges' theory of elision entails and
    confirms, in opposition to the Saintsbury heresy, "trisyllabic substitution." The syllabic
    metrical theory at the center of Milton's practice, as described by Bridges, is nearly identical
    to that set forth in the verse-manuals of the Italian Renaissance (e.g. Minturno's), which were
    themselves descriptions of the syllabic meters of such poets as Trissino. These four
    writers--two poets, two prosodists--represent the four most crucial figures in a metrical
    tradition spanning more than half a milennium. The influence of Alexander Gill (E541) on Milton
    is also discussed. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E568">
   <bib>Kenrick, William. "Rhetorical Grammar." Prefixed to his New Dictionary of the English
    Language. London, 1773; </bib>
   <notes> republished separately in 1784. Facsimile edition: Menston, Yorkshire: Scholar Press,
    1972. See Chapter 1, Section 6: "Of Prosody and Versification"; Chapter 2, Section 6: "Of
    English Prosody," Section 7: "Of Poetical Measures," and Section 8: "Of Vocal Melody." Kenrick
    ridicules prosodists for confounding the versification of modern languages with that of the
    ancients, yet he is inclined to believe English has "all the variety of long and short" that
    Greek and Latin had. But Greek speech was more like our song, the two being separated later, so
    that "the present meaning of the word accent bears no relation to its original use." In
    classical times speech was "a kind of song," but we have lost this "chaunt of accent" (i.e.,
    tone). In classical verse, accent and quantity did not coincide; neither do they in modern
    verse. Stress "supplies the place of" length for us. The term "feet" he rejects in favor of
    "measure." Frequent references to Mason (E586). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E569">
   <bib>Knight, Richard Payne. An Analytical Inquiry into the Principles of Taste. London: T. Payne
    and J. White, 1805; 4th ed. 1808. </bib>
   <notes> See pp. 312-13 of the review article in the Edinburgh Review 7 (1806): 295-328. The
    sections of interest in this treatise are Part 1, Chapter 4, Sections 10 and 12, and Part 2,
    Chapter 1, Sections 15-37. We are told that "English verse arises from a limited and regulated
    distribution of accents and pauses, as well as of quantities," which would leave the matter
    entirely unclarified, but for Knight to say that "the relations of measure and quantity are
    fixed and determinate. . . . they must therefore be the same in Greek as in English" pretty well
    establishes his position. Though he refers to verse as a "metrical and accentual arrangement of
    syllables," it seems that the accents serve only to mark the time-divisions; Knight is aware of
    both features of verse--accent and quantity--nearly equally, which means also that he is not yet
    willing to surrender the latter. He thinks Pope superb and Milton only capable of "the most
    rugged anomalies" in verse. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E570">
   <bib>La Drière, J. Craig. "Prosodic Notation." Princeton (A18), pp. 667-69. </bib>
   <notes> Identifying three possible notation systems for marking the suprasegmental features of
    speech (by diacritical markings; by complete graphic transcription, either phonetic or phonemic;
    or by an "abstract schematic symbolism"), La Drière supports the third system as being
    value-free, applicable to all languages, and restricted to the rhythmic features of interest.
    Various sorts have been tried, using as symbols (1) letters of the alphabet (Verrier, Stewart),
    (2) numbers, to mark intensity or position or both (Mayor, Lotz, Croll), (3) musical notation
    (Gildon, Lanier), or (4) arbitrary graphic markers (Steele, Skeat, Thomson, Heusler, and La
    Drière himself). The author's own system, employed in the following article, is explained: the
    syllable is abstractly symbolized as o, with diacritical marks for four degrees of stress and
    hovering stress, the comma for breaks between stress-groups, and the subscript caret for longer
    pauses. Marks for primary, secondary, tertiary, and weak accent (respectively): ó ò o oo.
    Hovering primary-secondary uses a hacek over the o. La Drière's system also differentiates group
    cadence [the rhythmic or phrasal groups of stresses determined by syntax], general cadence
    [meter, in effect], and measure [balance within the line and equalization between lines]. This
    system will also be found employed in the subsequent studies by Barry (E1448), Dougherty (D272),
    Holloway (E914), and Berg (E950). A more conventional scansion system is described in Princeton
    s.v. "Scansion," pp. 740-41. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E571">
   <bib>-----. "Prosody." Dictionary of World Literary Terms. Ed. Joseph T. Shipley. Boston: The
    Writer, Inc., 1970. pp. 253-57. </bib>
   <notes> This edition "completely revised and enlarged." Earlier editions are entitled Dictionary
    of World Literature (New York: The Philosophical Library, 1943; 2nd ed. 1953). Fairly abstract,
    but cogent and not particularly tendentious; La Drière promotes nothing of his own system except
    the distinctions cadence, grouping, and measure. For rhythm he adopts Scripture's term
    "centroid" for the dominating stress; for meter he discusses the various theories briefly. See
    also P. F. Baum's article on "English Versification," pp. 97-100, and A. R. Morris's on "Meter,"
    pp. 199-200. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E572">
   <bib>Langworthy, C. A. "Verse-Sentence Patterns in English Poetry." PQ 7 (1928): 283-98. </bib>
   <notes> An essay in metrical stylistics, or perhaps better, "syntacti-metrics": One of the best
    indices of a poetic style is the interwoven pattern of meter and syntax, since "in metrical
    composition the author is at the same time moulding syllables into prosodic groups and words
    into syntactic constructions." Seven major classes of Line-types are identified along with 22
    sub-species, and 42 passages (500 lines each) of major English poetry from Chaucer to Browning
    are analyzed, with results in tabular form. This sort of "grammetrics" is unquestionably both
    underexplored and valuable, yet one can only agree here that "it is apparently impossible to
    frame simple terms by which to describe most of these types of line-structure." See also E1234.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E573">
   <bib>Latham, R[obert] G[ordon]. The English Language. 2 vols. London: Walton and Maberly, 1841; </bib>
   <notes> 2nd ed. 1848; 3rd ed. "revised and greatly enlarged," 1855; many later editions. See Part
    VI, "Prosody," p. 439 ff. Latham's scansions are based entirely on accent ("Meter" is defined as
    "a general term for the recurrence within certain intervals of syllables similarly affected."),
    and he proposes a scansion notation of x and a for unaccented and accented syllables
    (respectively) which was deemed useful enough for adoption by Skeat and others after him. This
    Part of Latham's opus surveys the Classical meters, the Old Germanic alliterative meters, and
    the English syllable-stress meter. An especially long concluding chapter takes up English
    hexameters. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E574">
   <bib>Leathes, Sir Stanley. Rhythm in English Poetry. London: William Heinemann, 1935. 154 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in TLS, 17 October 1935, p. 655. An historical survey of the development of English
    verse on its accentual basis from Chaucer to 1900. But Leathes devotes considerable attention
    not only to stress but also to quantity, giving digressive chapters to the nature of quantity in
    Greek and Latin verse as well as modern German verse, taking the position that though stress
    governs our meters, still "in all the best English poetry quantity tells," and devoting a
    chapter to the quantitative verse of Swinburne and Bridges (the former wrote verse correctly to
    both quantity and stress patterns; the latter wrote in quantity alone, ignoring stress). Treats
    blank verse at some length, too, though with little fresh material. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E575">
   <bib>Lewis, Charlton M. The Principles of English Verse. New York: Henry Holt, 1907; </bib>
   <notes> 2nd ed. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1929. 142 pp. Rev: in Revue belge de philologie
    et d'histoire 10 (1931): 237. Lewis emphasizes that rhythm is composed of equal periods of time
    marked by stresses, and he differentiates (not at all clearly) meter as a measuring of syllables
    and stresses. He will allow six varieties of metrical feet, though he declines to defend that
    number in any way, a declination which characterizes the tone of the entire work. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E576">
   <bib>Lewis, C. S. "Metre." Review of English Literature 1 (1960): 45-50; </bib>
   <notes> rpt in his Selected Literary Essays. Ed. Walter Hooper. Cambridge: Cambridge University
    Press, 1969. pp. 280-85. An essay of wonderful simplicity, elegance and penetration: Lewis
    distinguishes meter ("an imaginary archetype or paradigm") from performance, the latter given to
    us either by Minstrels (who overdo the singsong meter) or Actors (whose flamboyant recitation
    ignores the meter entirely). And "metrical questions are profitable only if we regard them, not
    as questions about fact, but as purely practical." Scansions are not right, they are only more
    or less useful. The meter of a poem must be found by the norm of the entire poem, not by
    inductively categorizing all the line-types--that is not a meter. As for scansion, musical
    symbols will not do; the old conventional system still works best. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E577">
   <bib>Lucy, Seán. "Metre and Movement in Anglo-Irish Verse." Irish University Review 8 (1978):
    151-77. </bib>
   <notes> Lucy emphasizes the important contribution of frequent trisyllabic substitutions,
    trisyllabic meters for serious lyrics, and a native free-accentual line made by Irish poets in
    the history of English verse, especially Thomas Moore (influential for Byron, Shelley, Scott,
    and other Romantics) and Yeats. This, in the midst of a more sweeping review of Irish
    verse-forms, especially the anhrán. Long and valuable. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E578">
   <bib>McAuley, James. Versification: A Short Introduction. East Lansing, Michigan: Michigan State
    University Press, 1966. 84 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Also printed in Australia by Sidney University Press as A Primer of English
    Versification. (Identical text but different pagination.) Chapter 3 also appeared as: </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E579">
   <bib>-----. "Metrical Accent and Speech Stress." Balcony: The Sidney Review, no. 4 (1966), pp.
    21-31. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in Southern Review 3 (1967): 441-43; see also Pyle (E618). Chapter 1 presents the
    basic concepts of Meter: the fundamental unit of versification is the line; the metrical foot
    consists of a cluster of slacks around a single stress; monosyllabic feet are possible,
    therefore, but not pyrrhics or spondees; and speech-stresses vary in degree but are reduced to
    only two levels in meter. Chapter 2 treats Variation: substitution and elision, changes of line-
    length, and changes of meter. But it is the crucial Chapter 3 where the author reveals his
    excellent design for "exhibiting the essential duality of our experience of the line" by a
    double-tiered scansion system; but showing the actual rhythm above the paradigmatic meter, he
    can display cogently all the subtle effects of each against the other and the resultant scansion
    of the line. Chapter 4 treats the influence of meter on performance; 5, sound-patterning; 6,
    Accentual, Syllabic, and Free meters; followed by a Glossary. McAuley's handbook is easily the
    best text available for teaching metrics, and beyond that is one of the sanest things ever
    written on English versification. Nowhere is the distinction between the spheres of meter and
    rhythm--and the resultant "interanimations" of the two--better displayed. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E580">
   <bib>Mallam, Phosphor. An Approach to Poetry. New York: Thomas Y. Crowell, 1930. </bib>
   <notes> Chapter 2 treats alliteration, assonance, and rhyme; in chapter 3 rhythm is defined as
    stresses recurrent at equal periods of time, meter being a simplification and artificial
    division of rhythm. Correctly, and with a useful metaphor, the author recognizes that "the same
    rhythm may give us different kinds of metre according as to whether we cut into the rhythm at a
    rung, or between two rungs." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E581">
   <bib>Malof, Joseph. A Manual of English Meters. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1970; </bib>
   <notes> rpt Westport, Conn.: Greenwood Press, 1978. 236 pp. The best general metrical manual
    presently available--logically organized, clear in terminology, thorough. Malof accepts the
    structural-linguistic four degress of stress, then shows how these rhythmic four are reolved
    into the metrical two. Full chapters are given to Foot (Accentual-Syllabic) Verse, Stress Verse,
    Syllabic Verse, and Free Verse, and the Appendices include a glossary, bibliography, and
    checklists of rhyme and stanza forms. Malof's specialty is ballad meter, which he gives the
    piquant general term "Folk Meters"; these are explicated very fully in chapter 4. The only
    demure we might make to this useful "repository of information" is the unfortunate terming of
    metrical variation of "Exceptions to Regularity." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E582">
   <bib>-----. "Meter as Organic Form." MLQ 27 (1966): 3-17. </bib>
   <notes> More useful than the conception of meter as an abstract form--i.e., as container, or else
    one element contained--is the conception of meter as organic form, as a force for order within
    "a coherence of activities," "a system of dynamics," the poem. Within that dynamos energy is
    balanced against tension, so that the poem moves by "an accommodation of movement to the
    resistances against it," the antinomian forces generating "form" by their constructive and
    vitalic oppositions. Over all of these stands the impassive Meter, making its subtle Authority
    manifest only through the body of the lines, creating an immanent fixity and stricture of rule
    which is the paradoxical source of a nearly infinite range of variation. Throughout every supple
    or sudden divagation, underneath every gesture of hand or voice, nearly behind the field of view
    in every image, the form of the poem speaks Constancy, promises Order, satisfies Expectation,
    indeed nearly convinces us that all is for the best and that the poet is really very sane.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E583">
   <bib>-----. "The Native Rhythm of English Meters." Texas Studies in Literature and Language 5
    (1964): 580-94. </bib>
   <notes> A remarkable effort at synthesizing the entire history of English metrics into a single
    cogent interpretation that can be demonstrated within a very small compass: Malof's thesis is
    that the native English verseform, the old four-stress line, and the more complex foreign form,
    the (syllable-counting) pentameter line, have developed side by side, neither one very far from
    the other, throughout the entire history of English poetry: "the old native rhythm runs through
    much of our pentamenter verse, providing a basis for a continual modulation of counterpoint."
    Indeed, what one may say of the Romantic revolution and of the verse of the twentieth ventury,
    as of the late Shakespeare, is that the foreign verseform may "take over momentarily and
    denaturalize the native line, but that in time the native element reasserts itself and
    renaturalizes the line, transforming the foreign element into something new as it does so." In
    any period of crisis or uncertainty the sturdier native form will resurface. There is, then, a
    fundamental ambiguity between stress verse and foot verse; they permeate each other yet seem
    somewhat immiscible, so that much English verse more or less qualifies as either; the great
    success of our poetry has been to hold them both in solution together, productively. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E584">
   <bib>[Mason, John.] An Essay on the Power of Numbers, and Principles of Harmony in Poetical
    Compositions. London, 1749; rpt New York: Garland, 1970. 75 pp. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E585">
   <bib>-----. An Essay on the Power and Harmony of Prosaic Numbers. London, 1749; </bib>
   <notes> rpt Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar Press, 1967. 76 pp. Both revised and reprinted together as
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E586">
   <bib>-----. Two Essays on the Power of Numbers. London, 1961. </bib>
   <notes> Mason intends to scan by quantity, as he constructs verse of "time, syllables, feet, and
    measures," yet he is utterly undone by the confusion of quantity with accent. Though an
    unaccented syllable is naturally Short, he says, "yet if it be Accented in the Ordinary Way of
    Pronunciation, or the Sense requires the Emphasis to be laid on it, it becomes a long Quantity."
    He recognizes four disyllabic feet, eight trisyllabic, and sixteen tetrasyllabic, These last are
    formed of combinations of the disyllabic types and called "Dipodies"; whenever the two simple
    feet are dissimilar, they are termed a "Syzygy." More interesting historically, though, is the
    conjunction of poetic measure and music made in chapters 7 and 8. It is fair to say that Mason
    is heavily indebted to Say (E646). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E587">
   <bib>Masson, David. "Theories of Poetry." North British Review, 1853; </bib>
   <notes> rpt in his Essays Biographical and Critical, Chiefly on English Poets. London: 1856. pp.
    409-46. A review of E. S. Dallas (E288), widening to Aristotelian, Baconian, and other views of
    the nature and effects of poetry and verse; see especially pp. 444-45 on meter. E588 Matthews,
    Brander. A Study of Versification. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1911. 207 pp. A textbook-primer: he
    allows only the four common metrical feet, denying spondees and pyrrhics, yet calls the
    constituents "long" and "short," saying that a syllable may be emphasized sometimes by duration,
    sometimes by pitch or stress, sometimes by combination. Preservation of the old terminology is
    unfortunate, as is the liberal marking of metrical pauses; Matthews sesems incapable of
    distinguishing stress verse from accentual-syllabic verse. He applauds and elaborates on Oliver
    Wendell Holmes's theory (I30) that the line = one breath group. Not a reliable guide, since he
    shows every evasion about axioms. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E589">
   <bib>Maxwell, Ian R. Scansion Scanned. Melbourne: English Teachers' Group, 1967. 17 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A simple primer, with long notes at the end on Sprung Rhythm and Free Verse. Its virtues
    are (1) acceptance of the double levels of meter and rhythm, as in McAuley (E578), and (2) an
    interesting method of marking syntactic phrasing against metrical pattern in the line. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E590">
   <bib>-----. "What I Didn't Learn at School About English Metre." Meddelser fra
    Engelsklaererforeningen, no. 5 (1953), pp. 1-15. </bib>
   <notes> A good many of us could go to school here: Maxwell's thesis is metrical
    counterpoint--that effect wherein "every reader of poetry is quite well aware of two movements,
    the first a pattern borne in mind, the second a speech movement which, whether in identity or
    variation, is related to it, though a momentary forgetfulness of the relationship is possible
    and sometimes pleasing." His point, more specifically though, is "a clear distinction between
    the sort of feet which may compose the basic pattern [the meter] and those which may be
    introduced by way of variation [in speech]. The second sort may be made up in almost any way"
    [italics added]. Thus each syllable of Tennyson's line "Break, break, break" is a foot in the
    second system but not in the first. "The principle to be observed is that the basic pattern must
    always determine the number of metrical divisions" rather than the actualized variations. The
    reader of verse, then, feels "the need to follow two movements at once," yet surprisingly the
    effort produces not an added difficulty, but "a curious grace." That is the pleasure we take in
    the lines of accomplished actors. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E591">
   <bib>Mayor, Joseph, B. Chapters on English Metre. Cambridge: Camridge University Press,1886; </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E592">
   <bib>Mayor, Joseph, B. Chapters on English Metre. Cambridge: Camridge University Press,1886; 2nd
    ed. "revised and enlarged," 1901; rpt New York: AMS Press, 1969. 308 pp. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E592">
   <bib>Mayor, Joseph, B. A Handbook on Modern English Metre. Cambridge: Cambridge University
    Press, 1903; 2nd ed. 1912; rpt New York: Lemma Publications, 1972. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: By Gummere in MLN 2 (1887): 159-62. One of the lesser-known monuments of late
    Victorian metrics, but likely second only to Schipper (A9) in scope, method, and significance.
    Saintsbury said that "had Mr. J. B. Mayor's Chapters on English Metre been fuller, I had hardly
    written this book. . . . an unsound criticism is rare, an unsound scansion rarer."
    Unfortunately, though, Mayor compiled the book not by writing out his views on metrics directly
    but by collecting five essays he had previously published reviewing the major metrists who had
    preceded him--Guest, Abbott, Symonds, Ellis, Bridges, and Skeat (chapters 2, 3, 4, 5, and 7 of
    Chapters respectively), four essays on the history of Blank Verse (chs. 10-13), an essay on
    Shelley's meters (see E1017), and a chapter on the Hexameter, adding for the book publication
    only an Introduction, two Appendices, (the first on the Old French decasyllable, with an
    abstract of Zarncke's obscure monograph (L658), the second listing the terminology of classical
    versification), and two new essays on metrical classification (chapters 8 and 9). Thus we are
    forced to find Mayor out by indirections, watching his theory unfold in his reactions to the
    critical minds around him. That theory scans verse entirely by accent (Mayor thinks the concept
    of quantity very nearly ludicrous) but views the line as comprising metrical feet, not merely
    syllables. This position, the stress-and-foot theory, has become virtually High Orthodox in the
    century since Mayor's book. He is willing to retain the classical nomenclature (for
    convenience's sake), but oddly, he seems to think that the function of the metrist is to
    discover and categorize all the variations on strictly regular meter that are to be found in a
    poet's lines--ascending or descending, disyllabic or trisyllabic, truncated, hypermetrical, or
    downright irregular. In retrospect, that function seems necessary as a preliminary to the
    interpretation and criticism but worse than pedantic as an end. Mayor recognizes three degrees
    of stress, and he uses the 0, 2, 3 system of Ellis (C9) to mark them in scansions. Halpern
    (E546) believes that Mayor recognized the Relative Stress Principle in the 1870's, nearly thirty
    years before Jesperson. On Guest, Mayor demonstrates in too painful detail the easy recognition
    that his system is entirely perverse: to believe that the Old English prosody of "sections"
    (halflines) is the authentic metric of all English poetry up to the present is indeed to find
    that by such a system all the best modern poets have been bunglers and gross incompetents. So
    Guest's system, ponderously cumbersome, misrepresents those lines that it does not
    misunderstand. The accent-based metric of Edwin Abbott (E458) Mayor thinks the "true and
    natural" approach, though his distinction of word-accent, metrical- accent, and emphasis creates
    some needlessly complicated rules for assigning metrical ictus. Mayor argues for pyrrhics and
    spondees. In the case of A. J. Ellis's system, however, the complications are compounded beyond
    all reason. Hoping to avoid the very nebulous terms "accent" and "emphasis," Ellis distinguishes
    between force, length, pitch, weight, and silence in syllables, allowing a scale of nine degrees
    of gradation for each feature, each of the degress having an individual descriptive term--e.g.
    "superheavy," "sublong," "supershort"--producing, thus, forty-five terms altogether. Mayor can
    only "with difficulty repress a shudder at the elaborate apparatus he has provided for
    registering the minutest variations of metrical stress." The concept of weight is also
    questionable. Three other theorists are reviewed: Symonds (E1320) is censured for the
    dilettantism of his "intuitivism"; Bridges is judged by setting his theory of stress meter in
    Milton (E491) against his own work in The Feast of Bacchus and Nero, where its neglect of
    syllable-counting results in ineffective description (notice that Mayor's concern with
    syllable-counting, though, leads him in chapter 9 to a total misunderstanding of Hymn Meters);
    and Skeat (E646) is found confused and unnatural, his groupings of syllables around an accent
    more a matter of rhythm than of meter. Chapter 6, however, deserves final attention: there Mayor
    elaborates his method--which is, simply put, Empiricisim--in an attempt to arbitrate alternative
    scansions of problem lines. Two principles emerge: the prevailing context will control our
    scanning of any given line, and in general the range of permissible variations for a meter can
    be stated. But this sort of statement (p. 91) turns out to be rather unpleasantly extended and
    qualified, allowing only a cautious general rules: "one or two unaccented syllables preceding
    the initial accent or following the final accent of the line are non-essential to the rhythm."
    Such a result must surely cast doubt over the utility if not the validity of the method.
   </notes>
  </item>




  <item id="E594">
   <bib>-----. "Dr. Guest and Dr. Abbott on English Metre." Transations of the Philological
    Society, 1873-74, pp. 624-47. </bib>
   <notes> Expanded, revised extensively, and divided into chapters 2 and 3 of his Chapters on
    English Metre (E592), q.v. But note the discussion in TPS by the other members after Mayor had
    given his paper (pp. 644-45), and also the extract from Gaston Paris on the Old French
    decasyllabic meter (pp. 646-47); Mayor does not reprint the first of these in CEM. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E595">
   <bib>Miller, H. Augustus, Jr. Creative Writing of Verse. New York: American Book Company, 1932.
    190 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A student's manual which scans by stress but includes, illogically, isochrony in meter.
    It also, illogically, defines pyrrhic as a foot of two syllables unaccented in prose, one of
    which may however be accented in verse. Recommends assigning students blank metrical patterns to
    be fleshed out with words. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E596">
   <bib>Miller, Raymond D. Secondary Accent in Modern English Verse (Chaucer to Dryden). Baltimore:
    J. H. Furst Co.; 1904. </bib>
   <notes> His dissertation at Johns Hopkins in 1904. Miller, a student of Bright's (See E500),
    follows Huguenin (J133) and Brown (E1112) in extending Bright's theory over the whole range of
    English poetry. The crux of that theory is the point that three levels of phonetic stress may
    provide variety in verse when adjusted to the metrical two, secondary stress being optionally
    available for ictus. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E597">
   <bib>Minaishi, Fukujiro. "Estimation of Otto Jesperson's Four-degree Graduation of Stress in
    English." The Study of Sounds: Papers Delivered at the Second World Congress of Phoneticians.
    Tokyo: Phonetic Society of Japan, 1966. Vol. 12, pp. 406-14. </bib>
   <notes> Approves and explicates Jesperson's 4-3-2-1 notation for stress in verse (E562). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E598">
   <bib>A Mirrour for Magistrates. London: Thomas Marshe, 1559, 1563, 1571, 1578, 1587, etc. </bib>
   <notes> The standard modern text is that edited by Lily B. Campbell. Cambridge: Cambridge
    University Press, 1938; rpt New York: Barnes &amp; Noble, 1960. The Mirrour, an anthology of
    short "Tragedies" on the theme of the Fall of Princes and written generally in Alexandrines and
    rhyme royal, is a milestone in the early development of Elizabethan drama. Two points in
    particular stand out, prosodically, in the second edition: the short prose link [no. 24] after
    the tragedy of Richard, Duke of Gloucester, of which the narrator comments that "the matter was
    wel ynough lyked of sum, but the meeter was mysliked almost of all" (Richard is rebuked for his
    "uncertayne Meter," though, admittedly, his demeanor had become so notorious that "it were
    agaynst the decorum of his personage, to vse eyther good Meter or order"). Second, Sackville's
    "Induction" to the volume, which Saintsbury praised as "the finest piece of versifying in
    southern English between Chaucer and Spenser." (These are at pp. 371-72 and 298-317,
    respectively, in Campbell's ed.) </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E599">
   <bib>Mitford, William. An Essay upon the Harmony of Language. London: J. Robson, 1774. </bib>
   <notes> Revised and enlarged as: </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E600">
   <bib>-----. An Inquiry into the Principles of Harmony in Language and the Mechanism of Verse,
    Ancient and Modern. London: R. Cadell and W. Davies, 1804. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in the Critical Review 38 (1774): 137-43; by Herbert in the Edinburgh Review (see
    E550). Quite possibly our earliest English effort at a comparative versification for the modern
    languages as well as for the ancient. I treat the second edition here; the 1774 Essay was
    directed against Foster, but the Inquiry retracts a bit in favor of more general principles. For
    Mitford, harmony in language is the result of the combination of measure and melody. Accent or
    Tone he considers the result of both force (loudness, in three degrees) and higher pitch.
    "Emphasis" is rhetorical accent. Syllabic quantity is recognized--in regard to both long and
    short vowels and long and short syllables--as is length by position: a short vowel followed by
    two distinct consonants makes the syllable long. But Mitford is careful not to confound accent
    and quantity: stress does not lengthen syllables. The "rhythmus or cadence" of English speech is
    compared to music, but even though he can speak of "the identity of poetical and musical
    measures," in general he considers the relation of verse to music to be one of analogy. Verse,
    like music, runs in either common or triple time, the beats beginning the bars and hence
    disposed isochronously in relation to each other. Yet when Mitford comes to scansions, no
    musical apparatus is anywhere in sight: the accents end the iambic measures rather than begin
    them, and though quantities are marked throughout (virtually all syllables turn out to be long,
    of course), they clearly have no relation to the stressing. He recognizes that the
    irregularities of syllabic quantity are such that "the disposition of long and short quantities
    cannot be the foundation of that order which constitutes the order of verse." And "as the
    arrangement of music in bars has been decided by the convenience of the musical performer
    without any consideration of the competition of music with poetry, so the arrangement of the
    syllables in verse in feet should be decided by the convenience of metrical analysis, without
    regard to those divisions which music has established for its own separate purposes." In short,
    Mitford scans by accent alone, regardless of the theoretical genuflections he makes to the
    musical ideas of the day. (Elsewhere he calls accent "not the constituent but the indicant only
    of measure.") That order which does constitute the verse in English is one wherein "the
    alternate syllables are acuted." Permissible "aberrations of accent" include the doubling,
    absence, and reversal of the stress in the foot, and extra syllables are to be admitted as
    trisyllabic substitutions rather than removed as elisions (perspicuously, Mitford sees that "the
    poetical or metrical syllable is not precisely the same with the grammatical syllable" in some
    cases). Section 3 treats Quantity, 4 Accent, and 5 Cadence. Section 6 offers his theory of the
    mechanism of English verse. Section 7 on the history of English versification is also of
    interest. Summary (curious and interesting), pp. 108-9. Mitford is a landmark in the history of
    English versification. (Fussell's treatment of Mitford (E34) is inconsistent and confused; he
    finds there both strict syllabism and "anti-syllabism" (pp. 33 and 150).) </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E601">
   <bib>Monboddo, James Burnett, Lord. Of the Origin and Progress of Language. 6 vols. Edinburgh,
    1773-92; rpt New York: AMS Press, 1973. </bib>
   <notes> See chapters 4-6 of Book 2, and chapter 8 of Book 3, in volume 2. Monboddo's tediously
    repetitive treatise shows the great promise of a rigorous distinction between quantity and
    accent, until one recognizes that by "accent" he means pitch, not stress--an "acute or grave"
    quality of the voice, as opposed to "loud or soft" or "long or short." The Classical Greek
    language he holds to have been regulated by this "accent," not quantity--"the antient accents
    are real notes of music, or variations of the tone, by which the voice is raised higher. . . ."
    Such "accents" he denies exist in modern English (p. 298 ff); we have changes of tone, well
    enough, "but upon words or sentences . . . not upon syllables," and they admit of no rule. Thus
    Monboddo can back into the truth: "in English, syllabical accents . . . are of a quite different
    kind from the antient accents; for there is no change of the tone in them; but the voice is only
    raised more, so as to be louder upon one syllable than another. . . . the music of our language
    [is] in this respect nothing better than the music of a E602 drum, in which we perceive no
    difference except that of louder or softer. . . ." This last remark thereafter became one of the
    clichés of the day. Chapter 5 on Quantity is sensible: M. refuses to acknowledge length by
    position, accepting only (1) vowels naturally long or (2) diphthongs. Classical verse is ordered
    on the basis of such quantities, but these are quite extraneous to English meter (pp. 325-26).
    English verse, "as a species of rhythm" requires "both louder and softer sounds . . . and these
    must return at equal intervals, or such as have some other ratio to one another, otherwise,
    there is no verse." "There is however something more required to complete the verse; and that
    is, a certain number of syllables" (pp. 384-85). Added to this is only the "infinite variety" of
    quantity in English verse, and the definition is complete. The rest consists of approbation of
    Blank Verse and of Milton. Background reading: C. D. Abbott's "The Lesser Cham: Lord Monboddo."
    Sewanee Review 40 (1932): 161 ff. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E603">
   <bib>Morgan, Bayard Quincy. "Compulsory Pattern in Poetry." PMLA 75 (1960): 634-35. </bib>
   <notes> Seven remarks, addenda, and demurrers to Wimsatt and Beardsley (E700), "to suggest that
    meter in English verse is not arbitrary, but to a large extent inherent in and created by the
    rhythmic and poetic nature of our language." Notably, he argues for spondees, finding in the
    line "To sit in solemn silence in a dull, dark dock" that "each of the last three words makes a
    full metrical foot, and that no other reading is possible." Alexandrines are judged unwieldy and
    four-stressed pentameter lines "a contradiction in terms and impossible." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E604">
   <bib>Morton, Edward P. "A Method of Teaching Metrics." MLN 15 (1900): 97-101. </bib>
   <notes> There is a long synopsis also in PMLA 14 (1899): lx-lxi. The pedagogical sequence entails
    demonstrating: (1) that accent is the basis of meter, (2) the foot, (3) scansion of the iambic
    pentameter, (4) expressive metrical variation, (5) pausing and caesura-placement, (6) rhyme and
    couplet structure, (7) rewriting blank verse into couplets and vice versa, (8) stress verse, (9)
    the dynamics of stanza form, (10) alliteration, (11) other members and line- forms, (12) the
    Spenserian, (13) the sonnet, and finally (14) historical metrics. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E605">
   <bib>Motheré, J. "Quelques mots sur les théories du vers héroique anglais et ses relations avec
    la versification française." Review du l'enseignement des langues vivantes, 1886. Also rpt as an
    offprint at Le Havre, 1886. 54 pp. </bib>
   <notes> The subject of the essay is really English, though M. affirms that the two verse-systems
    are essentially identical. Beginning with a criticism of Witcomb and David Masson for accepting
    the doctrine of trisyllabic substitution, Motheré defends the principle of syllabism in English
    meter via contraction and elision. He distinguishes (semantic-syntactic) pause from (fixed
    metrical) caesura and recognizes the metrical principle of alternation in the placement of
    stresses. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E606">
   <bib>Nist, John. "The Word-Group Cadence: Basis of English Metrics." Linguistics, no. 6 (1964),
    pp. 73-82. </bib>
   <notes> Iconoclasm: the foot is not the basic unit in the meters of accentual languages. Outright
    audacity: the "word-group" or "cadence" is. "In English a cadence is that rhythmical pattern or
    accentual collocation which occurs between two accentualized major junctures. It is the basic
    unit of metrical structure." Simple myopia: the failure to distinguish between rhythm and meter.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E607">
   <bib>Odling, William. The Technic of Versification: Notes and Illustrations. Oxford: Parker,
    1916. 90 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A conventional primer of metrics, written by a professional chemist whose sentences
    uniformly lack verbs. Nothing new here; two-thirds of the book is given to examples. A prefatory
    page lists ten early works on versification (Harvey to Bysshe) the author found in the Bodleian
    Library. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E608">
   <bib>Pace, George B. "The Two Domains: Meter and Rhythm." PMLA 76 (1961): 413-19. </bib>
   <notes> Hoping to reverse the widening gap between literature and linguistics so apparent in
    versification, Pace suggests that the relation between traditional and structural metrics is
    exactly the same as that between meter and rhythm. Traditional metrics treats of "gross stress
    contrasts," by reducing all the minute degrees of stressing to one binary opposition. Meter in
    these terms is little more than a highly simplified recognition pattern. Structural metrics, on
    the other hand, describes more degrees of stressing, pitch, juncture, and other linguistic
    features, and as it increases its specificity of description it approaches the limiting case of
    one single realization (performance). This is the wide and various domain of rhythmics. But
    though we say a poem has a meter we cannot say it has a rhythm; it actually has "a rhythm
    potential (all readings) and a rhythm core (the best readings)." Thus, a Trager-Smith notation
    of a poem's rhythm core amounts to "a prescription for an ideal performance." Intonational
    ambiguities (which pertain to rhythm not meter) might be retained unresolved but would be better
    normalized. Contrast Pace's relegation of intonation to the domain of rhythm with Crystal's
    resolute inclusion of it in the domain of meter (E20). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E609">
   <bib>Pasco, Sam. "The Three Dimensions of English Prosody." DAI 34 (1974): 5924A (Auburn). </bib>
   <notes> An application of the theory of Nist (E606), wherein meter is subordinated to a more
    expansive conception of rhythmic structure which takes cognizance of syntax. The three levels or
    dimensions of analysis in their relation are: meter + prose cadence = poetic rhythm. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E610">
   <bib>Peery, William. "A Metrical Puzzle in the Mirror for Magistrates." MLN 56 (1941): 258-61. </bib>
   <notes> The tragedy of Thomas of Gloucester in the 1559 edition of the Mirror is clearly written
    in a four-stress line; in the 1578 edition, however, nineteen of the 203 lines have been
    inexplicably rewritten as iambic pentameters. See also Blenerhasset (E485) and the citation for
    the Mirror (E598). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E611">
   <bib>Pemberton, Henry. "Of Versification." Observations on Poetry, Especially the Epic;
    Occasioned by the Late Poem upon Leonidas. London: H. Woodfall, 1738. pp. 106-35. </bib>
   <notes> Mainly on Latin and Greek; English is discussed passim after p. 125. Pemberton recognizes
    that accent regulates English verse but confidently assumes that accent lengthens the syllable
    so that it is effectively long, the rationale being musical. Any variation in stress placement
    causes the verse to "labor under a deficit" (Pemberton is strict to the point of severity),
    metrical variation is deplorable in general except for verse-paragraphing, and trochaic
    substitutions are a license "least offensive" in first position. Music is often mentioned by
    Pemberton as the rationale for a practice, e.g. not mixing measures. He praises Milton and
    Glover. The heavy influence of Bysshe is obvious, though Pemberton's definitions of metre and
    rhythmus are noteworthy historically. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E612">
   <bib>Postgate, J. P. et. al. "A Canon for English Verse." Correspondence in TLS, 10 September-3
    December 1925, pp. 584, 600, 619, 639, 656, 675, 719, 739, 756, 772, 812, 835. </bib>
   <notes> Postgate attempts to formulate a rule for the number of stresses acceptable for a
    pentameter line to be deemed metrical--a minimum of three and a maximum of eight. Unfortunately,
    though, he will allow ictus to be filled by either quantity or stress. The other contributers
    haggle somewhat confusingly over peripheral issues. Sonnenschein muddies the waters with his
    phonetics and kymograph experiments, and there is talk of Persian meters in Tennyson. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E613">
   <bib>Pound, Ezra. "Treatise on Metre." ABC of Reading. New York: New Directions, 1934, 1960. pp.
    197-206; rpt in Bross (A23), pp. 102-8. </bib>
   <notes> Among Pound's acidic dicta on the wretched state of verse, music, learning, and the world
    at large, the prosodist will find detaining observations on rhythmical variety in the Greek
    hexameter, the origin of the stanza, and syllable-values (both "original weights and durations,"
    and those imposed on the syllable by others around it). Précis: "Prosody and melody are attained
    by the listening ear, not by an index of nomenclatures, or by learning that such and such a foot
    is called spondee. . . . you cannot hand out a receipt for making a Mozartian melody. . . .
    Hence the extreme boredom caused by the usual professional documentation on the aspiring thesis
    of prosody." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E614">
   <bib>[Puttenham, George.] The Arte of English Poesie. London: Richard Field, 1589. Ed. Edward
    Arber, London, 1869. Rpt in a facsimile edition: Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar Press, 1968. </bib>
   <notes> Rpt also of course in Smith (A26), col. 2, pp. 1-193. The best modern edition, however,
    is that edited by </notes>
  </item>




  <item id="E615">
   <bib>Willcock, Gladys D. and Walker, Alice. The Arte of English Poesie. Cambridge: Cambridge
    University Press, 1936; rpt 1970. </bib>
   <notes> (See esp. pp. lxiv-lxxiii in the Introduction on versification.) Puttenham's is the most
    extensive and important English treatise on verse- making, and also possibly the first; the
    latest editors present strong evidence of stratification in the text, the earliest draft of the
    Arte being written perhaps as early as 1569 and thus antedating both Ascham and Gascoigne.
    Puttenham made revisions steadily thereafter until the mid-Eighties, when there was a wholesale
    reworking of Book 3 and the last six chapters of Book 2. Thus the book was apparently twenty
    years in the making. Book 2 on "Proportion" is the one for us; Book 1 treats matter, Book 3,
    figures. In the first twelve chapters of Book 2 we find an earlier Tudor view of metrics, in
    contrast to the later (considerably altered) views expressed in the last six chapters on
    classical meters. In the early conception, Puttenham describes Greek and Latin verse as having
    Meters in Feet, which he denies in the vulgar languages; English is ruled solely by Number
    (syllabic regularity) and Rime (also termed cadence, or concord of tunable sound). To the modern
    way of thinking these seem too insignificant criteria, and we are surprised to see Puttenham
    making much of Rime, especially, but that is our own tinted vision. He also speaks often of
    Accent, but ambiguiously (p. 82 in Smith), seeming to mean by that term mostly pitch rather than
    stress; he also speaks of "motion and stir" and "times," but these too are hazy: "Meter and
    measure . . . [lie] with us in the number of syllables, which are comprehended in every verse,
    not regarding his feete. . . . by reason of the evident motion and stir which is perceived in
    the sounding of our words not always equal, for some ask longer, some shorter time to be uttered
    in." Thus Puttenham's (early) explanation for the inapplicability of classical versification
    rests on a (not very clear) argument about polysyllabicity vs. monosyllabicity; perhaps this is
    simply a confused realization that the times for producing English syllables are too infinitely
    graded to be classed either long or short. At one crucial point (p. 76 in Smith) Puttenham
    realizes that a line scans badly (weak iambs verge on dactyls) but cannot win his way to the
    right explanation. He does not understand Accent very clearly nor certainly in the modern sense
    of the term but he does perceive a cutting difference in the vernacular and the classical
    versifications. The bulk of the Arte is given over to his famous illustrations of staffe
    (stanza, by which he means line-lengths plus rhyme-schemes, the rhymes exerting a band or
    binding force), both for ear and eye, with a long digression on kingship. Chapter 13 and 18
    (corrected numbering) do indeed "say otherwise" and "seem contradictory," but the reference to
    classical meters as "scholastical toys" suggests a tone not entirely serious. And the strategy
    Puttenham is suggesting is indeed a clever one, designed to solve a conceptual problem by
    semantic sleight-of-hand, or casuistry. All of the "auncient feete" may be introduced into
    convenient and agreeable use, "according with our ordinary times and pronunciation," by a simple
    means, which is "to allow every word polisillable one long time of necessitie, which should be
    where his sharp accent falls in our owne ydiome most aptly and naturally. . . ." In short,
    quantity will be abstracted to the sense of ictus and filled in the lines by stress rather than
    length. No Law of Position will be allowed for English, since Puttenham believes that its
    justification even in Latin rests on nothing but "bare tradition." Of "auncient feet" he will
    allow twelve. In a moment of candor, though, he can confess that "in very truth I thinke [my
    remarks] but vaine and superstitious obseruations nothing at all furthering the pleasant melody
    of our English meeter . . . and rather wish the continuance of our old manner of Poesie,
    scanning our verse by [count of] sillables rather than by feete. . . ." Finally, note the
    half-confused conception of "breaking" in chapter 18; this is a groping realization that the
    metrical value of English syllables depends on where they are deployed in the line, rather than
    inhering in the syllable per se by definition, as in classical verse. Thus the shifting of words
    one slot over in the line will "break" an iambic rhythm into a trochaic. Puttenham grasps,
    dimly, that rhythm reinforces meter most strongly when word- and foot- boundaries coincide,
    though he admits he does not know why (p. 138 in Smith; see also pp. 130-31). Two supplementary
    studies which may be of interest: </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E616">
   <bib>Knauf, David M. "George Puttenham's Theory of Natural and Artificial Discourse." Speech
    Monographs 34 (1967): 35-42; </bib>
   <notes> and </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E617">
   <bib>Javitch, Daniel. "Poetry and Court Conduct: Puttenham's Arte of English Poesie in the Light
    of Castiglione's Cortegiano." MLN 87 (1972): 865-82. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E618">
   <bib>Pyle, Fitzroy. "Pyrrhic and Spondee: Speech Stress and Metrical Accent in English Five-Foot
    Iambic Verse Structure." Hermathena, no. 107 (1968), pp. 49-74. </bib>
   <notes> A lively and astute argument with McAuley (E578), defending the existence of pyrrhic and
    spondaic feet in English meter. The question is by no means closed, and Pyle is dead on target
    to identify the crucial determinant as the question "how far does the metre actually influence
    our rendering of stress as we read?" A strong influence results in McAuley's account, a weaker
    one, Pyle's. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E619">
   <bib>-----. "The Rhythms of the English Heroic Line: An Essay in Empirical Analysis."
    Hermanthena, no. 53 (1939), pp. 100-26. </bib>
   <notes> What are the minimum conditions required for a ten-syllable line to be perceived as
    "iambic," i.e. metrical? Some theorists have claimed that stresses on the fourth and sixth
    syllables of the decasyllabic line are sufficient, and Pyle shows that by shifting the whole
    line (and its stress-pattern) right or left under the metrical grid a fit can be obtained and
    the principle verified. The fourth or sixth position must be weighted, and if the eighth is
    weighted the tenth need not be, but if it is not then the ninth must be, in order to insure that
    a line will not be judged positively unmetrical, though for it to be judged positively metrical,
    more complex rules are required (pp. 122-24). (These are extended and simplified in Pyle's later
    study, above.) This study is to be placed with the other inductive studies--Mayor, Bridges,
    Young, and Tarlinskaja. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E620">
   <bib>Pyre, James F. A. A Short Introduction to English Versification. New York: F. S. Crofts,
    1929. 54 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in Englische Studien 67 (1932): 259-61. A pocket handbook. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E621">
   <bib>Raabe, David M. "Computerized Scansion of the Poetry of Robert Frost." DAI 36 (1976):
    8027A. </bib>
   <notes> In fact, all of Frost, "using a system based on lexical stress occurrence (as opposed to
    'positional')." The abstract is terse and obscure. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E622">
   <bib>Radavitch, David. "Toward a Less Primitive Prosody: Some Propositions (1)." Counterpoint
    (Kingston upon Thames, Surrey), no. 2 (1977), pp. 3-5. </bib>
   <notes> Part 1 of a 5-part series, to be published when completed by Court Poetry Press, in 1979
    (projected). The second installment is in Counterpoint, no. 3 (1977), pp. 3-6. Radavitch
    observes (correctly) that the traditional bivalent scansion system of metrics cannot express (or
    account for) certain kinds of information in the poetic line. (This observation raises the
    larger theoretical question of what kinds of features a metrical system should be designed to
    denote at all, though this question is unfortunatelynot explored here.) Radavitch then proposes
    an alternative scansion sysem with eight degrees of stress, indicated by numerical superscripts
    from 1 (weakest) to 8. (Note that this system doubles the members of each of the four categories
    in Trager-Smith.) He believes that "poetic stress" is a composite of four stresses: metrical,
    lexical, durational, and line-pattern. A middle section presents the differences between Music
    and Metrics (he is aware that the eight levels of the metric could correspond to the musical
    octave) and then applies the "numerical notation" to indicating pitch-patterns in musical lines
    (the confusions of this section are as instructive as its conclusions). Two sections explore
    four kinds of "governing rules" or "grammars" of the poetic line: these are rules of language,
    poetry, the poet, and the line itself; violation produces "language syncopation" (otherwise
    known as metrical variation). Concluding analysis of Stevens' "Anecdote of the Jar." Altogether,
    the exposition and terminology seem luxuriant. It would seem that the few criteria for "poetic
    stress" are so broad as to nearly eliminate any consensus on a correct scansion of a line, given
    the eight degrees of stress. But the author believes that a computer could be programmed to
    perform scansions automatically. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E623">
   <bib>Raith, Joseph. Englische Metrik. Munich: Max Hueber, 1962. 212 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in MLR 59 (1964): 622-23; in Lebende Sprachen 9 (1964): 145-46; in Archiv 202
    (1965): 60-63; in Zeitschrift für Anglistik und Amerikanistik 13 (1965): 178-80. Follows
    Spindler (E663). Twenty chapters on verseforms--e.g. Alliterative Verse, Blank Verse, Couplets,
    7-line Stanzas, Sonnets, Odes--with each chapter organized historically. An introduction to
    metrical forms, somewhat overbalanced toward stanza (156 pages of 185), but offering clear and
    orderly information on English meters for the German student. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E624">
   <bib>Ransom, John Crowe. "Criticism as Pure Speculation." In The Intent of the Critic. Ed Donald
    A. Stauffer. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1941; rpt 1969. pp. 92-124. </bib>
   <notes> Rpt in Critical Theory Since Plato. Ed. Hazard Adams. New York: Harcourt, Brace,
    Jovanovitch, 1971. pp. 881-90. The exposition on logical structure vs. local texture (pp. 885-86
    in Adams) is familiar and valuable; at the very end (p. 890), Ransom turns to reiterate his
    theory of meter as "pure design" quite divested of any content or "meaning" of the poem.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E625">
   <bib>-----. "Introduction of Speakers." National Poetry Festival Held in the Library of Congress
    Oct. 22-24, 1962, Proceedings. Washington, D. C.: Library of Congress, 1964. pp. 265-70. </bib>
   <notes> Paraphrase of the refulgent passage on pp. 268-69 seems a transgression. Ransom
    delineates four kinds of transactions between meter and sense in poetry: there is the "abstract
    meter with a simple repetitive rhythm," the "pure vocables," but at times this metrical pattern
    "must accommodate itself to the logical pattern of the words," and if at that point "some
    brilliant and perspicuous prose rhythm" can be found to overlay the simple meter, then the poet
    will have achieved a "counterpoint . . . the very special aural beauty of a metered work." But
    at the same time "the meaningful or signifying patterns of the words intend to be fully
    logical," but when the meter interferes, other words will have to be found. This might seem a
    shortcoming, "but often we feel that the greatest glory of the poem turns on its individual
    phrases when they conflict with but accommodate themselves to the meter. They will have come to
    their present form after much trial and error; and the successive versions will have been tested
    for their substantive brilliance as well as for their capacity for making oral counterpoint."
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E626">
   <bib>-----. "New Poets and Old Muses." In Literary Lectures Delivered at the Library of
    Congress. Washington, D. C.: Library of Congress, 1973. pp. 229-43. </bib>
   <notes> See especially pp. 241-43 on the "music" of meter versus the meaning in poetry--"music"
    being the regular sequence of orderly, steady, "fixed" units. Ransom's belief that these is a
    stratum of verbal music below that of verbal meaning in poetry is not fully articulated at its
    most crucial point--the explanation of how the metrical music affects us or conveys meaning to
    us in its own right--but he suggests here that meters "confer upon the delivery of poetry the
    sense of a ritualistic occasion." A sacramental function, in short. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E627">
   <bib>-----. "The Strange Music of English Verse." Kenyon Review 18 (1956): 460-77. </bib>
   <notes> Summary commentary on the five contributory articles in the Kenyon forum "English Verse
    and What It Sounds Like" (E714). Ransom devotes the preponderance of the essay to an approving
    estimate of the new linguistic approach to metrics (although he is concerned to confine the
    4-level system to speech-rhythm, preserving the binary system for meter), but he also offers
    observations upon the proper reading of verse, the ionic foot (he will admit it, in place of
    pyrrhic + spondee), and the metrical system as theology. Quotably, "the rhythm is the marriage
    of the meter and the language." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E628">
   <bib>-----. "Theory of Poetic Form." Texas Quarterly 9 (1966): 190-201. </bib>
   <notes> A discursive essay, generally concerning the "interaction between the sense and music" or
    "argument and rhythm" of poetry. Ransom cites four "coordinations" or mutual adjustments of the
    two realms to each other in the composition of a poem and concludes with remarks on Gross (E38),
    rejecting the notion that a rhythmic form divested of words can express meaning. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E629">
   <bib>-----. "Wanted: An Ontological Critic." In his The New Criticism. New York: New Directions,
    1941. </bib>
   <notes> Rpt in Chatman and Levin (A21), pp. 269-82, and often elsewhere. Beginning at section 4
    Ransom sets forth his famous diremption of the poetic object into "the meters and the meaning,"
    describing the mutual interactions and concessions of these two forces during the composition of
    a poem in a diagram showing Determinate and Indeterminate Meaning and Determinate and
    Indeterminate Sound. Examples follow: the pressure of the meter affecting the sense of lines in
    Wordsworth, Pope, Milton, and Marvell, and the pressure of the meaning bearing down on the meter
    in Shakespeare and Donne. Nothing better on the relation of meter and meaning has been written
    in this century. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E630">
   <bib>-----. "Why Critics Don't Go Mad." Kenyon Review 14 (1952): 331-39; rpt in his Beating the
    Bushes. New York: New Directions, 1972. pp. 157-69. </bib>
   <notes> Near the end of this review essay on Milton's poetry, Ransom takes Cleanth Brooks's
    suggestion that Milton's language was essentially Metaphysical rather than Spenserian as an
    occasion for thoughts on Meter: "It is depressing when a reader tells us how very 'natural' the
    meters seem. For it would then be as if the meters, or the poetic understanding which thought it
    was respecting the meters, were ceasing to function, and the meters did not know their own
    importance. Meters activated, as they are when the metaphysicals use them, seem at first to be
    restrictive, and obstructive, upon the flow of language, but actually they are what makes the
    phrases shine." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E631">
   <bib>Rivindranatha Datta. Prosody and Rhetoric. Calcutta: Das Gupta, 1915. 139 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A student's manual. Two kinds of accent--pitch and stress--are noted, with three degrees,
    though for metrical purposes only two are distinguished. Quantity may be short, long, or
    prolate, and though there are quantitative meters in the world's languages (Sanskrit, Greek, and
    Latin), English is not one of them. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E632">
   <bib>Rice, John. An Introduction to the Art of Reading with Energy and Propriety. London: J. and
    R. Tonson, 1765; rpt Ann Arbor: University Microfilms, 1953; rpt Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar
    Press, 1969. </bib>
   <notes> A grammar; chapters 5-6 treat Quantity, chapters 7-9, Accent, and chapters 10-12,
    metrics. Rice is insistent that "the heroic Measure is not confined to a certain Number of
    syllables," and, criticizing Say (E646), Mason (E584-86), and Dr. Johnson (E563), he allows that
    "though the Accent doth sometimes supply the Place of Time, in forming the Quantity, yet . . .
    it cannot do so to the exclusion of Time, without destroying the Propriety, Beauty, and . . .
    Harmony of the Numbers." In short, he conceives meter as comprising both Accent and Time.
    Elision is horrid. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E633">
   <bib>Robertson, Joseph. An Essay on the Nature of the English Verse, with Directions for Reading
    Poetry. London: Luke Hansard for J. Walter, 1799. 134 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A student's manual. Premises: "some learned writers would persuade us, that our verses
    are composed of iambs, trochees, spondees, pyrrhics, dactyls, &amp;, or a mechanical arrangement
    of long and short syllables. [He has Foster (M67) in mind.] This notion has involved the subject
    in darkness and perplexity . . . . [I have] considered the English versification as founded . .
    . on a certain order and succession of accented and unaccented syllables." That position is
    notable given its date, but otherwise the book has many eccentricities and warrants little
    interest. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E634">
   <bib>Rosenberg, Jim. Notes for the Foundation of a Theory of Meter: An Essay: Toward an
    Understanding of Projective Verse and Beyond. San Francisco: Grabhorn-Hoyem, 1970. 27 pp. </bib>
   <notes> An edition of 100 copies. Like Sylvester (E402), Rosenberg takes a mathematical approach
    to meter, though apparently he only intends his analysis to apply to Projective Verse. He writes
    rules to convert linguistic strings into abstract Stress Symbols, then rules to show how such
    sequences may be combined and how phrasal-stress patterns are adjusted when discrete phrases or
    words are marshalled together into meter, and finally rules to show when such sequences will be
    metrically admissible. He retains the concept of the metrical foot. His catagories of
    "stress-fixed" and "stress-shifting" metrical schemas sould like echoes of Chatman's
    "meter-fixed" and "meter-fixing" (E713), but one other distinction he makes is I think original
    and important: "for homomorphic metric schemes the conception of the foot break is prior to the
    conception of the line break, and the line breaks will respect the foot breaks. For
    non-homomorphic metric schemes, on the other hand, the line break is prior to the foot break and
    scansion can only occur once the line is determined." This merits "unpacking," as the
    philosophers say. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E635">
   <bib>Saintsbury, George. "English Versification." Introduction to The Rhymers' Lexicon. Ed.
    Lorris Andrews Lathrop [pseud.]. 2nd rev. ed. London: G. Routledge, New York: E. P. Dutton, n.
    p. pp. v-xxiv. </bib>
   <notes> A capsule history and exposition of the redoubtable Saintsbury system. An old Brit, we
    see, will uphold to the very end his Native Principles, in this case Equivalence, against the
    forces of Darkness--here, bathetically, Syllable Counting. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E636">
   <bib>-----. Historical Manual of English Prosody. London: MacMillan, 1910; rpt New York:
    Schocken Books, 1966. 340 pp. </bib>
   <notes> With an introduction by Harvey Gross. Speaking of the theory and method which lay behind
    his three-volume History of English Prosody (A8), Saintsbury himself observed: My object was not
    to construct an a priori theory of prosody at all, but to examine the prosodic substance of
    English poetry as a whole, and to discover, if possible, in what way it was constructed. I found
    . . . that a system of syllabic equivalence and substitution composing, and equating or
    contrasting, different prosodic units for which I kept the old traditional name of feet pervaded
    the whole of it. . . . Into the origin and nature, as distinguished from the contrasted value
    and arrangement, of long and short syllables I did not enter, beyond pointing out that neither
    accent, nor stress, nor except in a purely differential sense, quantity, would account for it
    satisfactorily. By differential, I mean that things of one kind were short, and those of another
    long, with an occasional faculty of change usually called commonness. And there was an end to
    it. (Some Recent Studies (E643)) Such a statement of principles--it is a relatively accurate
    self-assessment- -is dismaying, to say the least. As a serious method for intellectual inquiry,
    it seems to simply disdain all rational, orderly, self-conscious method. The judgment of it
    given by T. S. Omond (himself an opinionated but nevertheless a scrupulously fair critic) is not
    extreme: I think most readers of his volumes will share my surprise at the resolute way in which
    their author declines to discuss the phenomona which he chronicles. . . . He talks of "long" and
    "short" syllables, without saying what they mean, and says he might as well have called them
    "abracadabra and abraxas." His scansions are a glorious higgledy-piggledy of iambs and trochees,
    or dactyls and anapests, without any clue as to how these can be interchangeable. He not only
    does not know how feet are constituted, but he resolutely refuses to inquire. His really
    reckless use of the terms "long" and "short" with deliberate avoidance of their meaning leads
    him into terrible pitfalls when he comes to deal with quantitative verse. . . . Matchless as an
    historian of our verse, as an analyst he is not only nought but wishes to be so. No adequate
    account of our verse-structure is to be found in these otherwise admirable volumes. (A5, pp.
    250-51) It may be said, then, by way of synopsis, that whenever Saintsbury found himself in a
    tight place, and forced to explain himself fairly clearly, he always (forgive me) took to his
    feet. His metrical treatise adopts, wholesale, almost shamelessly, the old classical terminology
    of Longs and Shorts, and the scanning of verse in feet. For the study of classical verse, this
    apparatus had already been in use for over two milennia before Saintsbury's time, though as
    applied to the versification of English it had been a demonstrable source of confusion--and
    generally discredited--for over three centuries when Saintsbury took it up so fiercely. His
    theory treats its constituents, Quantity and the Foot, as utter abstractions, mere counters, not
    requiring the slightest natural explanation. "'Does length,' some people ask, 'really mean
    "duration of time" in pronouncing?' This question, and others, seem to the present writer
    unnecessary." So it is not vowel-length that determines quantity, nor will Saintsbury allow any
    Law of Position. His Foot Theory will have nothing to do with any Temporalist notions either, as
    witnesses his critique of Lanier (A8, vol. iii, pp. 493-97). Yet at the same time he confesses
    "of the isochronous interval" that "I believe in it myself, though I prefer to economise letters
    and call it a 'foot,'" (III, 439-40), and he does accept the concepts of the monosyllabic foot
    and the metrical pause, indeed to the point of allowing feet entirely filled by pauses, which in
    any syllable- and stress-counting metric is impossible. But the Accentualists suffer worse at
    his hands than any of the rest: "a man who goes by feet can never really go by accent . . . the
    pure accentual system is totally inadequate. . . . to rule accent altogether out of English
    prosody would be, to me, absurd. You must keep it in its place, and take care that that place is
    a minor or subsidiary one" (iii, 515, 496). However, a close inspection of Saintsbury's
    pronouncements on the accentual theory of meter suggests that he thought it counted stresses but
    not syllables; he seems to have had the misconception that stress-metrists believe all English
    verse to be merely accentual verse rather than accentual-syllabic verse. If so, that would
    indeed be a flagrant misprision, but not so flagrant as the one that Saintsbury commits in
    scanning the Old English and ballad meters as foot verse. He mistakes foot verse for stress
    verse and stress verse for the footed. Saintsbury rejects, then, both timing and stressing,
    though he misconceives, I think, both theories to some degree, while at the same time accepting
    some aspects of both theories. He was not one to be bound by the chains of consistency; But
    finally there can be, I believe, no middle ground. The two theories cannot be reconciled on the
    same plane. And on such a criterion, and even with all his evident ambivalences, Saintsbury must
    be said to scan mainly by stresses. In Saintsbury's defense, however, two things may be said.
    First his conception of Equivalence (Substitution) is a necessary and vital part of any coherent
    theory of meter (Saintsbury himself thought elision "hideous"). Trochaic substitutions in the
    fifth feet of iambic lines are unquestionably verboten. Second, the Foot Theory becomes vastly
    more attractive if we interpret Saintsbury's length or quantity to mean metrical ictus. The
    concept of ictus is a very respectable one these days, and not any the less so for its not being
    very well understood. It is in fact true that the ictus in English verse can be filled by any of
    a number of phonetic features--stressing, change of pitch, duration, timbre, any unusual feature
    of articulation. Since the phonetic basis of metrics still remains obscure in its fine details,
    we are in one sense no further along than Saintsbury was, and if we thought he knew what he was
    doing we might think him wise to refuse all pat and premature answers. It is for such reasons as
    those above that the first Book in the Historical Manual is essentially worthless, since it is
    there that Saintsbury presents his system. The second and third Books, however, presenting
    (respectively) the history of the poets' verse-technique and the metrists' theories, are
    admirably succinct. The fourth and last Book of "Auxilliary Apparatus" contains an unfortunately
    dogmatic Glossary and a too-brief bibliography, but it also contains two other resources nowhere
    else available--a list of major English poets, summarizing the prosodic achievements of each,
    and a list of major English verseforms, explaining the origin of each. Altogether, the design,
    scope, and convenience of the Historical Manual make it a useful work even yet, and after proper
    exhortations of caution, one can still recommend it to advanced undergraduates. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E637">
   <bib>-----. A History of English Criticism: Being the English Chapters of "A History of
    Criticism and Literary Taste in Europe." Edinburgh: William Blackwood and Sons, 1911; 2nd ed. </bib>
   <notes> "revised, adapted, and supplemented," 1925; rpt 1949. Saintsbury's one-volume history of
    criticism, with observations and remarks passim on prosody. He is especially close on Wordsworth
    and Coleridge (an entire chapter, one of eight, and the longest in the book). None of his
    opinions on prosodists seems altered significantly from those in the History of English Prosody
    (A8) or elsewhere. See especially his remarks beginning on pages 40, 273, 318, 504, and 511. See
    also his earlier: </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E638">
   <bib>-----, ed. Loci Critici. Boston and London: Ginn and Co., 1903, 1931. </bib>
   <notes> This is Saintsbury's earlier anthology of literary criticism, with useful introduction
    and notes to the excerpts. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E639">
   <bib>-----. "Lesser Verse-Writers." The Cambridge History of English Literature. Ed. A. W. Ward
    and A. R. Waller. 14 vols. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1907-16. </bib>
   <notes> Vol. 9, chapter 6, Part 2. pp. 194-214. Given fuller treatment in his History of English
    Prosody (A8), Vol. 2, Book 8. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E640">
   <bib>-----. "The Prosody of the Eighteenth Century." The Cambridge History of English
    Literature. Ed. A. W. Ward and A. R. Waller. 14 vols. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1907-16.
    Vol. 11, chapter 11, pp. 271-83. </bib>
   <notes> Given fuller treatment in his History of English Prosody (A8), Vol. 2, Book 8. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E641">
   <bib>-----. "The Prosody of the Nineteenth Century." The Cambridge History of English
    Literature. Ed. A. W. Ward and A. R. Waller. 14 vols. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1907-16.
    Vol. 13, chapter 7, pp. 250-82. </bib>
   <notes> Given fuller treatment in his History of English Prosody (A8), Vol. 3. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E642">
   <bib>-----. "The Prosody of the Seventeenth Century." The Cambridge History of English
    Literature. Ed. A. W. Ward and A. R. Waller. 14 vols. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1907-16.
    Vol. 8, chapter 9, pp. 253-73. </bib>
   <notes> Given fuller treatment in his History of English Prosody (A8), Vol. 2. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E643">
   <bib>-----. "Some Recent Studies in English Prosody." Proceedings of the British Academy 9
    (1919): 79-89; also published separately as an offprint by Oxford University Press in 1920. </bib>
   <notes> Saintsbury reviews four recent developments: (1) attempts at quantitative verse, (2) vers
    libre, (3) "Mechanics," or phonetic-laboratory analyses of verse, and (4) "Musicians," the
    school of metrists who emphasize time. All four are disparaged, as one would expect--the first
    as impossible, the second as feeble in result, the third as irrelevant, and the fourth as
    misguided into taking literally what is only analogy. E644 Sargeaunt, W[illiam] D[rake]. The
    English Syllable or Metrical Unit. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1924. 14 pp. A short pamphlet
    denying that syllables are indivisible and claiming that, phonetically at least, syllabic
    divisions are quite other than what we are told at school they are. An eccentricity. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E645">
   <bib>Saul, George B. "On English Metrics--and Certain Absurdities." College English 5 (1943):
    157-59. </bib>
   <notes> Of the latter, three. Saul cites two--application of classical nomenclature to scansion
    and pursuit of the musical analogy to verse. The third is this article, if he really believes
    "all speculation on metrics is essentially absurd." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E646">
   <bib>Say, Samuel. Poems on Several Occasions: and Two Critical Essays, viz. The First, on the
    Harmony, Variety, and Power of Numbers, whether in Prose or Verse. The Second, On the Numbers of
    "Paradise Lost." London: John Hughs, 1745. </bib>
   <notes> The first essay is reprinted by the Augustan Reprint Society, Publication no. 55. Ed.
    Paul Fussell, Jr. Los Angeles: University of California, 1956. Say's position in the evolution
    of eighteenth-century metrical theory is a transitional one: he is very intent to preserve all
    the old trappings of Quantity in his metric, yet he admits the ligitimacy of the substitute
    Accent, and he denotes syllables by musical notes as well. He defines the foot as "so many
    sounds as may be united together in One Movement"; "they are distinguish'd by different Names,
    according to the different Quantity or Disposition of the TIME in which we pronounce 'em, or the
    Stress of the Voice that is laid upon 'em." The equivocal or persists throughout. The syllables
    "Of Harmony," for example, "if we regard the Time only, [are] two Pyrrhicus's, but the Former,
    [of these is] distinguish'd by a strong Accent, which gives it, to an English Ear, the Force of
    an Iambick." He allows six elementary feet (spondee and tribrach), excluding the pyrrhic; its
    "Defect of Time is, in some measure, supply'd by a Stronger or Weaker Accent." The Appendix to
    the Postscript is noteworthy for the antipathy to elision that it expresses--a commonplace for a
    century thereafter--and for a couplet, contrived to illustrate the equality of timing in the
    lines despite variances in count of syllables, which become something close to a touchstone in
    the later prosodic literature. Say shows some indebtedness to Pemberton (E611), but he is
    important historically for his stiff resistance to strict syllable-counting ("Smooth and
    Unvaried Uniformity of Numbers") and his early approval of metrical expressiveness. Fussell's
    rapturious estimation of Say (E34, pp. 111-17) is, however, an over-reading. Both the temporal
    and the accentual theories of English meter are embraced by Say. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E647">
   <bib>Schlauch, Margaret. Zarys Wersyfikacji Angielskiej [An Outline of English Versification].
    Wroclaw, 1958. 72 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A dense, critically informed, historical survey. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E648">
   <bib>Schmidt, Friedrich. Short English Prosody for Use in Schools. Leipzig, 1904. 14 pp. </bib>
   <notes> This primer merited (?) a notice in Englische Studien 36 (1906): 408-9. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E649">
   <bib>Schulte, Edvige. Profilo Storico della Metrica Inglese. Naples: Instituto Universitario
    Orientale, 1960. 265 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Part 1 gives a historical sketch, Middle English to the present; Part 2 treats forms. A
    modern approach, and very well informed. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E650">
   <bib>Shapiro, Karl. "An ABC of Prosody." From Blake to the Present Day. Vol. 2 of British
    Literature. Ed. Hazelton Spencer et al. 2 vols. Boston: D. C. Heath, 1952. pp. 1059-64. </bib>
   <notes> It is a pity that this essay has not been more widely published: as a student's
    introduction it states in six pages what many handbooks cover less coherently in two hundred.
    Noting the presence and functions of time in rhythm, still Shapiro scans by stress and
    substitution. Even more valuable, though, is the careful separation of traditional, metered
    verse from our contemporary forms, since the prosody of the former is only bewildering to the
    student in the face of the latter. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E651">
   <bib>Sheridan, Thomas. Lectures on the Art of Reading, in Two Parts. Containing Part I. The Art
    of Reading Prose. Part II. The Art of Reading Verse. London, 1775; 2nd ed. 1781. </bib>
   <notes> Sheridan opposes application of all foreign metrical systems to English: it has neither
    the strict syllabism of the French nor the quantities of the classical meters. He is emphatic
    about the accentual basis of English meter: the English poet "need not pay the least attemtion
    to quantity." He even believes that accent regulates quantity in English, as did so many
    grammarians, but with a twist: in Sheridan's view the accent may fall on either the vowel or the
    consonant of an English syllable: if on the former, then the vowel is lengthened, as is the
    syllable, but if on the latter, then the syllable is shortened. This idea he reiterates in all
    four of his treatises. Metrical feet he thinks "correspond to bars in music," though he does not
    press the analogy and in fact keeps its members distinct. He allows eight feet, four disyllabic
    and four trisyllabic, giving them such names as "third trisyllabic," etc.; the monosyllabic foot
    ("syllabic iambus") is also allowed. Wooden regularity in meter is deplored, and trochaic,
    pyrrhic, and spondaic substitutions are allowed for variety. Strict regularity of stress in
    verse is of course proper, as it is in music, but is superseded by the demands of Variety and
    Expression. It is Sheridan's unique theory of accent which allows him to hold that English verse
    has both that which the classical verse had, and more--i.e., that our verse has feet formed on
    both quantity and accent: "we are not only allowed the use of all the ancient poetic feet . . .
    but we have duplicates of each, agreeing in movement, though differing in measure, and which
    make different impressions on the ear, an opulence peculiar to our language, and which may be
    the source of a boundless variety." But this bivalent system eventually leads to disaster, as
    Sheridan is forced to revert to the classical terminology for the quantitative feet while
    employing his own for the accentual feet, simultaneously; the double system becomes a double
    bind. The whole thing is clearly unsupportable, though Sheridan ploughs ahead manfully. Sheridan
    may have developed his theory as early as 1762 (cf. his Lectures on Elocution and Dissertation
    of that date). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E652">
   <bib>-----. "Prosodical Grammar" prefixed to his A Complete Dictionary of the English Language.
    London, 1780; 2nd ed. 1789. </bib>
   <notes> Especially the section "Of the Recitation of Poetic Numbers" at the end. The substance of
    this account is very similar to that in all Sheridan's earlier ones: he urges again his idea
    that the stress in English syllables may fall either on the vowel or on the consonant. He also
    urges that in the recitation of verse the lengthened vowel be held strictly twice the duration
    of the short vowel. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E653">
   <bib>Sidney, Sir Philip. An Apologie for Poetrie [1583? Later entitled The Defense of Poesie].
    London, 1595. </bib>
   <notes> There is an edition in the English Reprints series, ed. Edward Arber, London, 1868. Rpt
    also in Smith (A26), vol. 1, pp. 148-207. Facsimile edition: Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar Press,
    1968. There are stray remarks on versification passim ("the greatest part of poets have
    appareled their poetical inventions in that numbrous kind of writing which is called
    verse--indeed but appareled, verse being but an ornament and no cause to poetry.. . . One may be
    a poet without versing, and a versifier without poetry"), but Sidney only faces the issue
    squarely near the end. Though he had tried his hand at quantitative verses in the Arcadia, the
    mood for experimentation soon dissolved in the face of the prosodic realities of making verse in
    English: "Now, of versifying there are two sorts, the one Ancient, the other Modern: The Ancient
    marked the quantity of each syllable . . . the Modern observing only number (with some regard of
    the accent); the chief life of it stands in that like sounding of the words, which we call Ryme.
    . . . New, for the ryme, though we do not observe quantity, yet we observe the accent very
    precisely." See also: </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E654">
   <bib>Dowlin, Cornell M. "Sidney's Two Definitions of Poetry." MLQ 3 (1942): 573-81. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E655">
   <bib>Foster, Leslie, D. "'I Speak of the Art, and Not of the Artificer': The Logical Structure
    of Sidney's Defence of Poetry and the Concessive Arguments." Hebrew University Studies in
    Literature 5 (1977): 155-81. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E656">
   <bib>Skeat, W. W. "On the Scansion of English Poetry." Transactions of the Philological Society,
    1898, pp. 484-503. </bib>
   <notes> See criticism by Mayor (E592, Chapter 7). This half-buried and nearly-forgotten essay
    merits further work: Skeat was a distinguished scholar, and his metrical system presented here
    (taken from the 1888 Accent and Rhythm perhaps by J. Blake (E484)) is intriguing. He dismisses
    the concept of "foot" as a vestige of a foreign metric and argues instead that the metrical unit
    in English is a clustering of weak syllables around each stress. The groups he allows are: Tone
    (Ì ), Accent (Ë Ì ), Cadence (Ì Ë ), and Extension (Ë Ë ). (Reasons are given for excluding
    other possibilities.) These four types produce sixteen possible forms of five-stress (and also
    four-stress) lines. The principle for defining these metrical units is clearly
    morphemic-syntactic, and one is left to wonder what other priniciple might be preferable. What
    is lost here, one sees, is the counterpointing of metrical units against word- and
    phrase-boundaries. But then again some descriptive adequacy is gained. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E657">
   <bib>Smith, Oliver Cromwell. Vox Musarum: Rules and Suggestions for Developing the Power,
    Beauty, and Sublimity of the English Language. . . .Dodgeville, Wisconsin, 1907. 242 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A primer of grammar, prosody, orthography, pronunciation, etc., with Glossary. Pages
    16-73 treat versification--Smith has a penchant for the old Greek nomenclature. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E658">
   <bib>Smither, John M. Golden Bridle Poetry Patterns: Classic, Modern, Futuristic, for Students
    of Elaborated Poetry. Kansas City: Graphic Laboratory, 1939. 123 pp. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E659">
   <bib>Sorensen, Frederick, C. "Metre and Rhythm in English Prosody." Stanford University
    Abstracts of Dissertations 13 (1938): 50-51. </bib>
   <notes> Recognizing "the distinction between rhythm and metre. . . . the forced adjustment of
    natural speech rhythm to foreign metre within the English verse line," Sorensen employs a double
    scansion system; meter is based on accent, while rhythm is found to be composed of rhythma, the
    clusters of "syllables adhering to a major speech accentuation." By photographing oscilloscope
    patterns, he is able to identify thirty-two types of rhythma. Analysis of the first two scenes
    in Hamlet. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E660">
   <bib>Spalding, Charles. A Treatise on Versification and Poetry. New York: Printed for the author
    by Grattan, 1833. 67 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Not seen. Cited in NUC as located at the Library of Congress, but lost. E661 Spiers,
    A[lexandre]. Study of English Poetry . . . or a choice selection of the finest pieces . . .
    preceded by a treatise on English versification. London: Simpkin, Marshall, 1835. The text is a
    small, diachronically organized anthology. See the Introduction, pp. 10-62: "Of English verse
    the constituent parts are feet and pauses. All feet . . . can consist of but two or three
    syllables." Besides the three common feet, he allows five others: dactylic, pyrrhic, spondaic,
    amphibrachic, and tribrachic. This Introduction was reprinted at Paris in 1852 as E662 Traité de
    versification anglaise. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E663">
   <bib>Spindler, Robert. Englische Metrik in ihren Grundzügen on Hand ausgewáhlter Textproben
    dargestellt. Munich: Max Hueber, 1927. 229 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in Anglia Beiblatt 39 (1928): 178-82; in MLR 23 (1928): 226-28. in Neueren Sprachen
    37 (1929): 165; in Englische Studien 65 (1931): 266-70. A student's handbook of metrical and
    stanzaic forms, each chapter of which takes its illustrations from one major British poet. Scans
    by stresses alone. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E664">
   <bib>Stall, Lindon. "Robert Bridges and the Laws of English Stressed Verse." Agenda 11 (1973):
    96-108. </bib>
   <notes> Exegesis of the seven laws of stress verse formulated by Bridges in the chapter he
    appended to the 1901 edition of Milton's Prosody, followed by thorough analysis of three of his
    poems in that meter. The most interesting aspect of Bridges' whole theory is that he marks the
    feet of stress verse according to phrasal boundaries, since the stresses are said to control
    their proclitics and enclitics. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E665">
   <bib>Standop, Ewald. "Bermerkungen zu einer neuen Verslehre mit Analyse von East Coker IV."
    Anglia 76 (1958): 271-84. </bib>
   <notes> Applies the method of La Drière (E570) to Eliot. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E666">
   <bib>-----. "Sprachliche Kunstmittel: Stil and Metrik." Ein Anglistischer Grundkurs. Ed. Bernard
    Fabian. Frankfurt: Athenaum, 1971. pp. 63-103. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E667">
   <bib>Stein, Arnold. "A Note on Meter." Kenyon Review 18 (1956): 451-60. </bib>
   <notes> An eloquent meditation on the relations of the abstract metrical form and the natural
    rhythm of stresses, based on very close inspection of some lines by Milton. The point: "the
    interaction between meter and [rhythmic] context which is already sufficiently created to be
    there . . . and between meter and the context in the dynamic process of becoming context." In
    short, "the meter figures twice." See John Crowe Ransom's summary comments at E627. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E668">
   <bib>Stein, David N. "On the Basis of English Iambic Pentameter." DAI 36 (1976): 6652-53A
    (Indiana). </bib>
   <notes> Stein begins with an explicit assumption that iambic lines are composed of feet; the,
    "what is important is not which syllables can carry the ictus under what sematic readings." The
    Elizabethan usage of the auxilliary do is examined. Generative metrics is dismissed; temporalist
    metrics requires modification--the concept of isochrony must be modified, even though it "cannot
    in any reasonable way be used to describe certain varieties of iambic pentameter." From a very
    large sample of lines, a Paradigm is constructed for all the possible variations in the line
    which will not destroy the meter. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E669">
   <bib>Strunk, William. English Metres. Ithaca, N. Y.: Cornell Cooperative Society, 1922. 61 pp. </bib>
   <notes> An introductory student's manual: Strunk distinguishes rhythm from meter and accepts the
    foot, though somewhat freely (allowing up to four syllables). Chapter 3, "The Line and the
    Foot," is of interest; the rest is conventional. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E670">
   <bib>Suhamy, Henri. Versification Anglaise. Paris: Société d'Édition d'Enseignement Supérieur,
    1970. 277 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A surprisingly expansive yet readable introduction to English versification for French
    students, a book which avoids tedious technicalities on the one hand yet also avoids the
    temptations of impressionism on the other. Suhamy explicitly divides meter from rhythm, devoting
    a separate chapter to each, followed by (among others) chapters on the alliterative, syllabic,
    accentual, and quantitative meters in English. The general conception of verse set forth is
    double: the sounds function both rhetorically and rhythmically (as incantation) at once. See pp.
    23, 41-42 for some interesting speculations on the regularity of the breath-units underneath
    irregular phrasing, and a formulation: Thought : Breath = Rhythm : Sound. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E671">
   <bib>Swann, Robert, and Frank Sidgwick. The Making of Verse: A Guide to English Metres. London:
    Sidgwick &amp; Jackson, 1934, 1949. 160 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in TLS, 15 March 1934, p. 184. It would be a disparagement to call this book simply
    a primer: it has the great advantage of being utterly candid about its principles. It lucidly
    separates the stress-metered verse of English from the length-metering of Greek and Latin,
    acknowledging Omond's views of "duple time," and mentioning other systems of scansion as well.
    And its attention (three major sections of four) rests squarely on meter, unlike so many others.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E672">
   <bib>Taglicht, J[oseph]. "Phonology, Scansion, Metre." In Proceedings of the Conference Held at
    Tel Aviv University, December 1968. Tel Aviv: Association of [Israeli] University Teachers of
    English, 1969. pp. 37-49. </bib>
   <notes> An important essay, despite its location: Taglicht quarrels with Wimsatt &amp; Beardsley
    and others over the degree of abstraction that meter achieves over the phonological features
    that it organizes. His position is that an auditor can hear the meter in a proper poetic
    recitation, but that "by no process of abstraction . . . does it seem possible to arrive at the
    traditional metrical foot." The relevance of a given phonological feature for meter is not a
    matter of either-or [this is the received opinion] but of degree, so that a "scale of delicacy"
    is possible in analysis: the patterning of a feature may or may not be included in metrical
    analysis depending on what degree of description is desired. The terms "meter" and "rhythm" are
    nearly useless by now; "architectonic rhythm" and "pictorial rhythm" would be better. Syllables
    in English bear stress (here, "rhythmical stress"), "accent" (intonational prominence), and
    "tone" (pitch)--making up four degrees of prominence altogether. A metrical analysis
    discriminating all four varieties turns out to be (based on the examples here) remarkably
    delicate. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E673">
   <bib>Tarlinskaja, Marina. English Verse: Theory and History. The Hague: Mouton, 1976. 351 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by Bjorklund in PTL 4 (1979): 192-95; by Standop in Anglia 97 (1979): 218-32. I
    believe it was C. S. Lewis, in his essay on "Metre," who first articulated the modern
    disparagement of inductive studies of meter. Tarlinskaja's massive study should put that ghost
    finally to rest. Surpassing the work of Omond, Bridges, Smith, Stewart, Chatman, Halle-Keyser,
    and Tsur in both scope and detail, EVTH is the most extensive and most important study of
    English verse- structure produced in this century. Like the earlier analyses of Mayor, Bridges,
    and Young, Tarlinskaja's analysis is inductive, but unlike theirs her 230 pages of discussion
    and conclusions are based on a computer-assisted inventory of over 100,000 lines of verse from
    the 13th to the 19th centuries, the results of the analysis being displayed in 103 pages of
    statistical tables and charts. Hence, EVTH is truly the first work on English meter which we can
    legitimately acknowledge as both comprehensive in scope and based on a thorough examination of
    the evidence. It treats all three principal English metrical systems, the syllabo-tonic
    (accentual-syllabic), tonic (accentual), and free verse, specifically the dramatic and
    non-dramatic iambic pentameter, the iambic and trochaic tetrameter, four-stress meter (esp.
    ternary), and mixed forms--the mixed syllabo-tonic/tonic and the mixed syllabo-tonic/syllabic.
    In Tarlinskaja's theory, metrical position or ictus is distinguished from linguistic stress, the
    strong position (ictus) being filled by (a mandatory) one syllable and the weak position (non
    ictus) by (a permissible) one to two syllables. The concept of the metrical foot is affirmed and
    the five commonest meters are admitted: iambic, trochaic, anapestic, dactylic, and amphibrachic.
    Anacrusis is also noted. Meter is defined as "the alternation of ictuses and non- ictuses in a
    certain sequence, regardless of the phenomenon which serves as the basis of this alternation."
    In a given meter each of these two positions in the sequence, each of these two positions in the
    sequence will be one of two types: ictuses are either obligatorily stressed or predominantly
    stressed; nonictuses are either obligatorily unstressed or predominantly unstressed. For each
    meter investigated Tarlinkskaja develops a complex statistical profile of the accentual and
    syllabic variations, identifying the metrical norm, the deviations, (acceptable or anomalous)
    from that norm, and the metrical threshold at the far edge of deviation where the meter becomes
    some other meter or nonmeter. Chapters 1-3 treat premetrical problems, viz., the accentual
    structure of Middle and Early Modern English; Tarlinskaja affirms the existence of "doublets"
    and investigates the surprisingly high percentage (80 %) of monosyllables in English verse.
    Chapter 4 treats Middle English rhymed verse, chapter 5, the iambic and trochaic tetrameter,
    which weakened in their syllabic structure in an early stage to become four-stress verse
    (Tarlinskaja adopts the term for the Russian form of this meter, the "dol'nik"), both binary and
    ternary. Chapters 6 and 7 treat the dramatic vs. the non- dramatic iambic pentameter, and the
    final chapter, the odd hybrid verseform of Donne's Satyres. Four Appendices treat some curious
    and intriguing problems in comparative versification. This is a seminal monograph, full of a
    wealth of information by no means yet fully mined. It should also demonstrate to anyone not yet
    apprised of the fact that it is not the English who are pioneering the study of verse in this
    century. The study is based on ten years of previous research: </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E674">
   <bib>-----. "The Accentual Structure and Meter of English Verse (13th - 19th Centuries)."
    Linguistics, no 169 (1976), pp. 41-58. Originally published in Russian in Voprosy Jazykoznanija
    4 (1972): 100-11. </bib>
   <notes> In order to examine the realizations and simplifications of linguistic stress- patterns
    in meter, Tarlinskaja differentiates "the concepts of 'phrasal stress' and 'verbal stress' [i.e.
    lexical stress]," emphasizing and exploring the former. "The degree of phrasal stress of the
    syllable is determined first of all by semantic and grammatical (chiefly syntactic) factors. A
    scansion system is proposed for phrasal stress with three degrees ("strong phrasal stress,
    secondary stress, and lack of stress"), each degree having also two subdegrees, with different
    symbols for occurences in ictic and nonictic positions in the line (making twelve in all). (The
    system is adapted from G. P. Torsuev.) Lengthy statistical analyses of the English iambic
    pentameter line follow. E675 -----. "Akcentnye osobennosti anglijskogo sillabo-tonicheskogo
    stixa" [Accentual Features of English Accentual-Syllabic Verse]. Voprosy Jazykoznanija 3 (1967):
    81-91. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E676">
   <bib>-----. "Akcentuacija i jazykovoe napolnenie anglijskogo jamba." Uchënye zapiske. Pervyj
    Moscovskij gosudarstvennyj pedagogicheskij institut inostrannyx jazukov imeni Morisa Toreza 35
    (1966): 310-30. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E677">
   <bib>-----. "Evoljucija slogovoj i akcentnoj struktury anglijskogo sillabo-toniceskogo stixa"
    [The Evolution of the English Syllabo-Tonic Line]. Sbornik naucnyx trudov. Moskovskij
    gosudarstvennyj pedagogiceskij institut inostrannyx jazykov imeni Morisa Toreza 66 (1972):
    75-84. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E678">
   <bib>-----. "Meter and Rhythm of Pre-Chaucerian Rhymed Verse." Linguistics, no. 121 (1974), pp.
    65-87. Original Russian version appeared in Vosprosy Jazykoznanija 3 (1971): 73-88. </bib>
   <notes> Glossing Lehmann (L457), Tarlinskaja explains the shift from OE stress-verse to the
    accentual-syllabic verse of ME in terms of changes in the phonological and syntactic structure
    of the language. Statistical analyses of King Horn against six other ME poems and some ModE ones
    reveals their accentual, syllabic, and metrical structure. These patterns turn out to be
    "diffused," i.e. not clear-cut, but in general the ME line contained eight syllables, three to
    four stresses (almost equally distributed), and four ictuses. (King Horn has six, two to three,
    and three.) A considerable number of other specific features are also analyzed statistically.
    Conclusion: though ME poetry shows mixed and transitional forms, it mainly displays "an
    accentual-syllabic character." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E679">
   <bib>-----. "Nekotorye aspekty teorii i rezul'taty analiza anglijskogo stixa." In Metryka
    slowianska. Wroclaw, Warsaw, Krakow, and Gdansk, 1971. pp. 119-40. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E680">
   <bib>-----. Nekotorye osobennosti anglijskoj stixotvornoj rechi [Certain Features of English
    Poetic Speech]. Diss., Moscow, 1966. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E681">
   <bib>-----. "Ritm stroki i metr anglijskogo pjatistopnogo jamba" [The Rhythm of the Line and the
    English Iambic Pentameter]. Sbornik nauchnyx trudov. Moskovskij gosudarstvennyj pedagogicheskij
    institut inostrannyx jazykov imeni Morisa Toreza [Publications of the Moscow State Pedagogical
    Institute of Foreign Languages] 73 (1973): 305-13. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E682">
   <bib>-----. "Strukturnye osobennosti slov i forma anglijskogo stixa" [Structural Features of
    Words and the Forms of the English Line]. Voprosy romano-germanskoj filologii. Uchënye zapiski.
    Taskentskij gosudarstvennyj pedagogicheskij institut imeni Nizami 94 (1972): 279-98. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E683">
   <bib>-----. "The Syllabic Structure and Meter of English Verse From the Thirteenth Through the
    Nineteenth Century." Language and Style 6 (1973): 249-72. </bib>
   <notes> The article is about evenly divided between analyses of Stress Verse and Syllable-Stress
    (accentual-syllabic) Verse. In the first half (drawn in part from E678), Tarlinskaja examines
    the Middle English rhymed verse of the thirteenth and fourteenth centuries, especially King Horn
    and four other poems. Tabular data is presented on Number of Syllables per line, Number of
    Stresses, Number of Ictus Positions, Lines with Iambic beginnings, and Disyllabic occupancy of
    nonictic positions (the loosening of the accentual-syllabic pattern). Lines missing a syllable
    at the caesura also seem characteristic of the period. The second half of the essay examines
    Modern English verse with respect to syllabic variation (mono- or di-syllabic in nonictic
    positions) in Donne, Pope, Shelley, and Byron. Donne is found to be the poet closest to the pure
    accentual pattern, with more syllabic variation than his successors. E683a -----. Three Studies
    in English Verse: Shakespeare and Other Poets. The Hague: Mouton, forthcoming. [Superseded by
    her book on Shakespeare.] </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E684">
   <bib>Tarlinskaja, M. G., and L. M. Teterina. "Porogi metrichnosti anglijskogo stixa." Uchënye
    zapiski Vysshyx uchebnyx zavedenij Litovskoj SSR. Literatura XVI (3): Antichnaja i zarubezhnaja
    literatura, 1974. pp. 34-54. </bib>
   <notes> </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E685">
   <bib>-----. "Verse--Prose--Meter." Linguistics, no. 129 (1974), pp. 63-86. </bib>
   <notes> A lengthy statistical analysis of samples from nearly all the major English poets reveals
    the location of the limen between Metrical and Unmetrical in the poetic line. At what point does
    iambic verse becomes non-metrical? If more than 5% of the lines have disyllables in a weak
    (nonictic) position; if more than 25% lack stresses in nonictic positions; if more than 21% have
    stresses in nonictic positions. No more than 2% of the lines may have no more than 5
    "non-typical" syllables. Overall, English iambic verse contains about 2% unmetrical lines.
    Conclusions apply to "non-dramatic Modern English iambic pentameter." The method used here
    synthesizes concepts from both traditional and generative metrics in order to locate the
    "marginal thresholds." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E686">
   <bib>Tatsuma, Minoru. Eishi no Ritsudo [Rhythm in English Poetry]. Tokyo: Shohakusha, 1971. 529
    pp. </bib>
   <notes> An introduction to English metrics for Japanese readers which is surprising in that after
    four opening chapters on Accent, Time, Trisyllabic Meters, and Blank Verse, the preponderance of
    the remainder of the book is devoted to Hopkins' Sprung Rhythm, giving four chapters to the
    theory and eight chapters to interpretation of poems. Excellent Bibliography. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E687">
   <bib>Thompson, John. "Linguistic Structure and the Poetic Line." Poetics I (A16), pp. 167-76;
    rpt in Freeman (A22), pp. 336-46. </bib>
   <notes> A summary outline of the theory underlying The Founding of English Metre (E91), i.e., the
    three-level metrical paradigm comprises the abstract metrical pattern, the natural
    stress-patterns in the language, and the intermediate, "compromise," tensioned pattern--the line
    of poetry itself. The pattern in the meter imitates the sound pattern in the language itself,
    and the poetic line imitates the meter, thereby imitating--re-enacting, dramatizing--the
    structure of the language itself. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E688">
   <bib>-----. "Sir Philip and the Forsaken Iamb." Kenyon Review 20 (1958): 90-115. </bib>
   <notes> From the august, nearly rhapsodic tone of this piece I had almost thought it by Ransom;
    was it for him, at least? Thompson chides Stein for attributing to meter functions which are
    properly those of intonation, or performance; what meter is and does, utterly by itself, is not
    easy to see: the most one can say, Thompson concludes, is that "meter is nothing but an
    imitation of language. . . . Imitation itself is the sufficient reason of meter. For what poetry
    imitates . . . is the structure of the language itself. . . . Art comes to reality through
    artifice." Toward this end, T. shows that in Sidney's verse there are two attitudes toward
    meter: in the Arcadia, the linguistic stresses are matched precisely and supply to the metrical
    pattern; in Astrophel and Stella the correspondence is no less exacting, but "Sidney manages to
    combine a formal satisfaction of the metrical pattern with phrases whose stresses frequently
    violate that pattern." I. e., the meter so prevails over speech stresses which within their
    phrases so thwart it that nearly every syllable in the line is emphasized, giving a remarkable
    elevation to the whole throughout. Sidney's meter, then, is "supremely contrived," and it was
    his genius to see that two systems could interact while being kept separate. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E689">
   <bib>Trevelyan, R. C. "Prosody and the Poet Laureate." The New Statesman 24 (1924): 296-98. </bib>
   <notes> Criticism by Ralph Sutton (pp. 360-61) and H. O. Coleman (pp. 415-16). An attempt to
    write metrical rules for some Alexandrines by Bridges, based on the rules for stress-shift that
    Bridges himself developed for the later Milton and Shakespeare. Then, generalizing, Trevelyan
    observes the widening breach between the syllabic- and the stress-meters, which traditionally
    have been welded together in English poetry. In response, Sutton insists that Enlgish meter is
    based on number of feet and not number of syllables in the line; he also argues that Milton did
    not resort to elision to regularize the syllable-count in his lines. Coleman spurns this latter
    view. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E690">
   <bib>Trnka, Bohumil. Úvod do Anglické Prosodie. Praha: Statni Pedagogicke Nakladatelstvi, 1955.
    135 pp. </bib>
   <notes> incl. Bibliography and Glossary. A reduced history of English versification along the
    lines of Schipper and Kaluza, printed by offset from a typescript. The first half is historical,
    treating Old and Middle English verse through Chaucer; the second half is structural, surveying
    the commonest verseforms and devices. The bibliography is well informed. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E691">
   <bib>Van Dyke, Henry. "Some Remarks on the Study of English Verse." Atlantic Monthly 92 (1903):
    469-75. </bib>
   <notes> Lamenting the fact that we have not yet achieved anything like "an orderly and
    comprehensive knowledge of the laws and principles of English verse," Van Dyke argues that the
    only method which will yield such a result will be entirely inductive; for a set of generally
    acceptable descriptive terms, also requisite, he suggests stress for "the points and emphasis
    which are really the structural factors of the verse," bar for that group of syllables bound
    together and dominated by the stress, and iambic, etc., for the patterns. Sound- organization
    also discussed. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E692">
   <bib>"Verse-Forms Occurring in Modern English Poetry Only." Schipper (A11), Book I, Part 2,
    Division 3. pp. 219-69. </bib>
   <notes> Includes chapters on Blank Verse (Surrey through Arnold), Trochaic Meters, and Imitations
    of Classical Forms (Hexameters, Sapphics, and others). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E693">
   <bib>Victory, Louis H. "Elementary Metres and Licenses Therein." In his Imaginations in the
    Dust. 2 vols. London: Gay &amp; Bird, 1903. Vol. 1, pp. 9-25. </bib>
   <notes> The four commonest meters together with regular variations. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E694">
   <bib>Wadham, Edward. English Versification: A Complete Practical Guide to the Whole Subject.
    London: Longman's Green, 1969; rpt Philadelphia: R. West, 1977. 154 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Saintsbury's (A8) judgment of Wadham was that "he really knows . . . nothing whatever
    about the subject" (vol. 3, pp. 440-42), but this is too severe. Wadham's book may not detain
    anyone's notice beyond one inspection because the weight of the book rests on an eccentric
    (hence irritating) new terminology for all the old familiar devices. For that, oblivion. Yet he
    can also lucidly separate the quantitative from the accentual prosodies, recognizing that the
    old, dogged effort of the grammarians to preserve the Latin system and force it onto English, by
    calling accented syllables long and unaccented short, caused irreparable harm and literally
    centuries of delay in the advance of clear thinking. That recognition is just, salutary, and
    valuable. E695 Watts, Isaac. "The Author's Preface" to his Horae Lyricae. Poems, Chiefly of the
    Lyric Kind. London, 1706, 1709, etc. Many editions. See esp. pp. ciii-civ, cix-cx. The Preface
    elaborates a pious defense of poetry against the charge of profanation, maintaining that verse
    may properly be used by the Christian pen to win souls away from baser attractions. Watts
    approves of sonnets, "the free and unconfined numbers of Pindar," Miltonic blank verse, heroic
    verse (couplets), and "the narrow metre of our Psalm translators" (ballad meter) as appropriate
    forms. He considers Milton too long in his periods, too "harsh and uneasy" in numbers, and too
    quaintly uncouth in diction. But couplets should have an equal "variety of cadence, comma, and
    period. . . . It degrades the excellency of the best versification when the lines run on by
    couplets, twenty together, just in the same place, and with the same pauses." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E696">
   <bib>Webb, Daniel. Observations on the Correspondence between Poetry and Music. London, 1769;
    rpt in his Miscellanies. London, 1802. </bib>
   <notes> See esp. pp. 63-132: pp. 63-70 treat imitative sound, 76-115 meter, 115-23 improvement of
    language and versification, and 124-32 poetry and music. Webb believes that English verse has
    quantity like the Greek, but for us "the quantities of syllables are but the variations of
    accent." English meter has feet (but not monosyllabic ones); the pentameter consists of "five
    feet, or ten syllables" and must end in an iamb, two trochees in a row being offensive. But Webb
    is strongly in favor of trisyllabic substitutions for expressive effect. (On this point Fussel
    in E34 contradicts himself glaringly--see pp. 28 and 130-- even citing the same page in Webb.)
    His work offers a fresh view, unconstrained by conventionalities, and seems to have been an
    influential one. Reference: Omond (A5), pp. 64-67, though his page citations there are erroneous
    by one digit in the hundreds column. See also E1340. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E697">
   <bib>Wesley, Samuel. An Epistle to a Friend Concerning Poetry. London: Charles Harper, 1700. </bib>
   <notes> A broadside poem of about 1100 lines with a Preface. Much talk of "Numbers" and
    "Quantity" throughout, as well as on Pause, though the following— But little more of Quantity we
    know Than what our Accent does and Custom show: The Latin Fountains often we forsake, As they
    the Greek; nay diff'rent Ages take A diff'rent Path. Perfúme and Envy now We say, which Ages
    past would scarce allow. If no Position make our Accent strong Most Syllables are either short
    or long --suggests that the concept of quantity was purely conventional and the meter actually
    based on stress. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E698">
   <bib>Whitmore, Charles, E. "A Proposed Compromise in Metrics." PMLA 41 (1926): 1024-43. </bib>
   <notes> This empirical approach to (1) standard variations of the pentameter line, (2) "rising
    vs. "falling" rhythm, and (3) notation is indeed conciliatory, though slightly blurred. There is
    little to remark except for two points: the biological metaphor (elaborated on pp. 1025 and
    1042) Whitmore applies to metrical theory is apt and fruitful, and his conception of "points of
    support" in the pentameter line [these seem to be the crucial lexical and rhetorical stresses in
    the line, quite variable in number] with scansion notation thereof [three points of support on
    the second, sixth, and tenth syllables of a line would be notated 2-6-10) is, if not novel,
    still concisely expressed and useful. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E699">
   <bib>Wimsatt, W. K., Jr. "On Scanning English Meters." Michigan Quarterly Review 5 (1966):
    291-95. </bib>
   <notes> A review of Gross (E38); though Wimsatt is not especially excited to see a new statement
    of "the normal expressionist theory," yet he does admit its persuasiveness--he only wants more
    precision in description and explanation. So, too, Gross comes in for some chastisement for
    bardolatry of the moderns. Yet the two prosodists are in considerable agreement on the tenets of
    an accentual theory of meter, most of which Wimsatt sketches out. See, too, his very important
    observations on the "iambic?/trochaic?" problem [my term] at the end. There is much of Gross
    here, but more of Wimsatt. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E700">
   <bib>Wimasatt, W. K., Jr., and Monroe C. Beardsley. "The Concept of Meter: An Exercise in
    Abstraction." PMLA 74 (1959): 585-98. </bib>
   <notes> Rpt in Chatman and Levin (A21), pp. 91-114; in Gross (A23), pp. 150-67; abstracted in
    Seboek (A19), pp. 193-96. Followed by two very important exchange; see below. A landmark white
    paper in the history of English metrics: Wimsatt and Beardsley's essay is undertaken as an
    explicit restatement and defense of the traditional account of metrics against two newer
    systems, the structural- linguistic and the temporal-musical. The authors criticize Chatman for
    an "insufficient [pragmatic] concern for the normative fact of the poem's meter" over and above
    the level of linguistic features, and they criticize Whitehall for failing to differentiate the
    level of isochronism (rhythm) from the level of isoaccentualism and isosyllabism (meter). The
    Trager-Smith analysis "may be helpful" but it also "may be in excess of any strictly metrical
    need." But more generally, the objection to linguistic metrics is that "the poem is not to be
    identified with any particular performance of it, or any set of such performances. . . . not
    everything which is true of some particular performance will be necessarily true of the poem. .
    . . A performance is an event, but the poem itself, if there is any poem, must be some kind of
    enduring object." Temporal metrics may be classed together with linguistic--since timing is a
    linguistic phenomenon--as equally (mistakenly) performance-oriented. And the problem with
    musical scansion is that it specifies time-values too precisely; it is directive rather than
    descriptive. Verse can indeed be isochronic, but do we know that it is invariably so? Meter,
    however, inheres at "certain rudimentary levels of linguistic organization" where the only
    important feature is "relative degrees of stress . . . in certain positions." In the authors'
    view the two principles of English meter are not time and stress but rather stress-counting and
    syllable-counting; these produce the two chief metrical systems in English, stress verse and
    syllable- stress verse, relatives whose affinity is obvious but ancestry obscure. Northrop Frye
    was mistaken to identify the pentameter line as an overlay or higher level of the four-stress
    line. But it is the Relative Stress Principle--whereby the slack of one foot may be stronger
    than the stress of another, judgments being allowable only within the foot--that is the linchpin
    of English syllable-stress meter. (Wimsatt and Beardsley also accept the Allophonic
    Principle--the second of two equal impulses will be heard as louder--and its implication, the
    impossibility of pyrrhics and spondees.) Other metrical orderings are possible, such as the
    hierarchical multiples of "dipodic feet." The structural linguists, however, are right to focus
    on the matter of tension (the authors prefer to substitute the term "interplay" for the same
    idea), as in the promotion and supression of medial stresses so as to conform to the meter. The
    meter is one of the two poles generating that tension, and not the tension, or a result of the
    tension. How do we know? "You can write a grammar of the meter. And if you cannot, there is no
    meter. But you cannot write a grammar of the meter's interaction with the sense, any more than
    you can write a grammar of the arrangement of metaphors. . . . the free and individual and
    unpredictable parts of the poetry. You can perceive them, and study them, and talk about them,
    but not write rules for them. The meter, like the grammar and the vocabulary, is subject to
    rules." A retrospective, after two decades, may find some of the fine points of this essay
    decidedly blurry, and it may be surprised to notice a curious repetitiveness of structure, but
    these are mere quibbles against the solid mass of this seminal essay. Naturally, the essay
    provoked sharp responses soon after: see the ensuing exchanges between Wimsatt and Beardsley and
    Joseph Hendren (E357) then Elias Schwartz (E328). See also B. Q. Morgan (E603). (Written for or
    just after he returned from the Indiana Conference on Style in 1958; the Kenyon forum was 1956.)
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E701">
   <bib>Witcomb, Charles. On the Structure of English Verse. Paris: Mesnil-Dramard; London: Sampson
    Low, 1884. 162 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Scans by accent but allows sixteen types of feet. Mainly gives examples of meters,
    rhymes, stanzas, blank verse and couplets, sonnets, and classical imitations; a primer. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E702">
   <bib>Wode, Henning. "Linguistische Grundlagen verslicher Strukturen im Englischen." Folia
    Linguistica 4 (1970): 372-92. </bib>
   <notes> A study of Stress-placement and Segmentation in verse. The author refuses to allow that
    meter promotes stresses or that emphatic stressing influences the line: he will allow only
    "normal stressing." On line-division or segmentation he asserts that poems on the linguistic
    level do not have lines; only if a literary text can be produced can a graphic segmentation
    analysis be made. What is to be the unit of verse must be stipulated by arbitrary convention
    from the literary point of view not from linguistic (i.e. oral) analysis. Segmentation is more
    often phonological than grammatical. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E703">
   <bib>-----. Psycho-Linguistische Experimente zur englischen Metrik." Studien zur englischen und
    amerikanischen Sprache und Literatur: Festschrift für Helmut Papajewski. Ed. Paul G. Buchloh et
    al. Neumunster: Wacholtz, 1974. pp. 89- 115. </bib>
   <notes> An experiment designed to test Chatman's theory that the heard stresses depend on the
    "pressuring" of the "metrical set" (E713). The conclusion falls against that theory, though
    there was no consensus among the subjects, who were asked to mark down which syllables they
    heard as stressed when a poem was read aloud to them. Notice in the tables of results how
    agreement among subjects falls off, progressively. Wode notes that none of the subjects ever
    marked an unstressed syllable as stressed due to "set," but judges also--albeit
    tentatively--that from the notations of the subjects no reliable information about the
    linguistic structure of the text can be gained. Areas for further clarification: time allowed,
    and the poetic expertise and social structure in the group of subjects. But note that Wode does
    not distinguish stress-verse from foot-verse. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E704">
   <bib>Woodley, C. C. A Look at Rhythm, Rhyme, and Verse Form. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1968. 64
    pp. </bib>
   <notes> A pocket handbook. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E705">
   <bib>Woods, George. Versification in English Poetry. Chicago: Scott, Foresman, 1936 (25 pp.);
    rev. ed. 1958. 28 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A pamphlet reprint of a chapter from The Literature of England, an anthology edited by G.
    B. Woods, H. A. Watt, and G. K. Anderson, by the same publisher, 1936. Short sections on
    metrical, sonal, stanzaic, and verse forms. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E706">
   <bib>Young, F. E. Brett. Robert Bridges: A Critical Study. London: Martin Secker, 1914. </bib>
   <notes> Chapters 6, 7, and 11 present what is as much an original theory of versification as a
    study in Bridges, for it is indeed novel to maintain that neither Chaucer nor Milton wrote
    iambics, that the iambic pentameter is not accented on the even syllables, that Bridges
    misunderstands Milton's prosody in every way, that the whole of English versification is one
    long, gross "mistake." Young patiently explains to us that English verse is actually scanned by
    speech- cadences and simple isosyllabism of line, but concludes that the right road for poetry
    in the future is that of true quantitative hexameters. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E707">
   <bib>Young, Sir George. An English Prosody on Inductive Lines. Cambridge: Cambridge University
    Press, 1928. 279 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: in MLR 24 (1929): 488-90; by Baum in JEGP 28 (1929): 589-91; by Dobrée in the
    Nation-Athenaeum 43 (1928) 564; in The New Statesman 31 (1928): 640; in TLS, 26 July 1928, p.
    548; in Review of English Studies 6 (1930): 116-20; in Revue Belge de Philologie et d'Historie 9
    (1930): 186-88. Too much neglected. Young's survey offers both theory and history of English
    meters in a more diminished form than Saintsbury or Schipper. He is firmly a "Stresser" (p. 86)
    and will hear nothing of isochrony; he explicitly separates the domains of rhythm and meter. Six
    chapters on theory treat the norm and its variations by "stress-shift," "defect of syllable,"
    "extra syllable," and "mid-line primary variations." The remainder of the book traces the
    history of the "cinquepace" (pentameter) line in all its forms from Middle English to Tennyson,
    with chapters on Milton and "Shakespeare as a Metrist." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E708">
   <bib>Zhigadlo, V. N. "Postpozitibvnoe opredelenie i ritm v sovremennom anglijskom jazyk."
    Uchënye zapiski Leningradskogo gosudarstvennogo universiteta 156 (1952): 300-12. </bib>
   <notes> See also: B40, B83, B181, B187, B195, B203, B225, B240, C34, D331, E423-24, E757, E814,
    E1210, F150, I51, J114. </notes>
  </item>
 </chapter>
</bibliography>
