<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
 <chapter title="">
  <item id="E709">
   <bib>Chatman, Seymour. "Comparing Metrical Styles." Sebeok (A19), pp. 149-72; rpt in Chatman and
    Levin (A21), pp. 132-55. </bib>
   <notes> More a systematic argument in the theory than an inductive comparison of the metrical
    styles of Donne and Pope at Satires. Chatman follows an unimpeachable definition of meter--"a
    systematic literary convention whereby certain aspects of phonology are organized for aesthetic
    purposes"--with an enumeration of the types of metrical variation--"intra-systemic variation,"
    either by displacement of metrical points or a change in syllable-count, or "countermetrical
    variation," either by weak stresses under ictus or strong stresses outside of ictus or else by
    the choice of junctures--an explanation of "the impression of speed" in verse (if it is not a
    "lexically-induced illusion" it is caused by addition of extra syllables or else weak stresses
    under ictus), a very succinct survey of the types of elision, and a distinction between poetic
    style, interpretation, and performative style. On sound-patterning he deprecates mimesis, offers
    an anatomy of devices, and observes that "the rhyme actually may provide information by limiting
    the possibilities of interpretation." Close analyses of the poets are interpolated. N. B.: "I
    have never been able to discover a good reason for assuming that a metrical accent point has any
    closer connection with the zero that it follows than with the one that it precedes." Very
    important essay. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E710">
   <bib>-----. "Mr. Stein on Donne." Kenyon Review 18 (1956): 443-51. </bib>
   <notes> A part of the symposium "English Verse And What It Sounds Like" and a reply to Arnold
    Stein's notes on Donne's meters (E1070). Applying the Trager-Smith inventory, Chatman is
    insistent that there can be no ambiguity or ambivalent "hovering" in meter (as Stein maintains);
    any ambiguity in traditional scansion "is a paper ambiguity only. . . . [it] demands a
    resolution in oral performance." "The very act of performance . . . forces the reader to resolve
    ambiguities, to decide between alternatives. . . . ambiguity can only exist between the printed
    page and the reader's eye. . . ." Cf. Levin (I35). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E711">
   <bib>-----. "New Directions in Metrics." The Concise Encylopedia of English and American Poets
    and Poetry. Ed. Stephen Spender and Donald Hall. New York: Hawthorn Books, Inc., 1963. pp.
    229-33. </bib>
   <notes> A simplified, clear, direct discussion of rhythmicity in verbal structures and that
    higher ordering, meter, which is "a species of rhythm." In a sequence of regularly recurring
    events, the key aspect is the prominences which mark regularity; for languages, specifically
    English, these seem to be stresses. But though it is true to insist, No metric without its
    phonetic, still no amount of phonetic analysis can discover, explain, or produce meter, since
    meter is a convention arbitrarily imposed on the language. Chatman sketches out the two most
    recent linguistic accounts of meter, Trager-Smith and Bolinger. The latter has so far been
    scarcely explored, but its early findings are intriguing. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E712">
   <bib>-----. "Robert Frost's 'Mowing': An Inquiry into Prosodic Structure." Kenyon Review 18
    (1956): 421-38. </bib>
   <notes> The first published application of structural linguistics to metrics, an analysis
    "envisaging a tension between two systems: the abstract metrical pattern . . . and the ordinary
    stress-pitch-juncture system of spoken English" which "incorporates both formula and
    performance." The Trager-Smith system can elucidate the actual performance, so Chatman
    transcribes eight readings of the Frost poem (one of them Frost's) and marks their intonation
    patterns in order to resolve ambiguities of interpretation. The principle of tension between
    oral performance and abstract metrical pattern is the central concept in structural- linguistic
    metrics. See also John Crowe Ransom's summary comments at E627. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E713">
   <bib>-----. A Theory of Meter. The Hague: Mouton, 1965. 229 pp. Pages 102-27 are reprinted as
    "The Components of English Meter" in Freeman (A24), pp. 309- 35. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by C. F. P. Stutterheim in Levende Talen 239 (1967): 265-68. Up to its time the most
    significant treatise in the field of metrics since Bridges (E491); Chatman provides a full-scale
    theory of an order which has been rarely matched. His procedure is empirical throughout, and the
    study never strays very far from its data. "Meter itself is a system, parallel to and actualized
    by, but not to be confused with, the linguistic system." Chapter 2 surveys the psychology of
    rhythm, since meter is, by general consensus, a species of rhythm. A very long Ch. 3 reviews
    elementary phonology, since the relevant event or unit-object in meter is the syllable, followed
    by the nature of prominence or ictus in meter; length, stress, and pitch are closely examined,
    "stress" is defined, and the importance of pitch in stress is emphasized (following Bolinger).
    Chapter 4 reviews earlier Objective studies of meter as well as Russian Formalist/American
    Structural-Linguistic work. Chapter 5, the crux, states the theory: inductively, we do scan
    poems--meter is agreed to exist--but no one linguistic feature can be shown to be an invariable
    signal of metrical ictus. "Lexical stress unambiguously marks metrical ictus . . . unless
    overridden by [phrasal stress]"; in confusing or ambiguious contexts, the "metrical set" of
    expectations will then act to denominate the ictus and pre- serve meter. Scansion is a notation
    of the meter of a recitation, while metrical analysis is a composite summing of all the
    scansions; "the meter in this sense is a consensus, not a normative formulation." The foot is
    defended on grounds of theoretical elegance and the pyschological reality of grouping. Four
    degrees of syllable-stress are denoted (a, b, c, d) producing thirty-two varieties of disyl-
    labic feet, excluding spondees, pyrrhics, ambiguous feet, and mono- and trisyllabic
    sybstitutions [hence, no "metrical pause"], which are also allowed. Chapter 6 provides a sample
    analysis of Shakepeare's Sonnet 18; eleven professional recordings are analyzed on a sound
    spectrograph then checked against the judgments of a panel of expert judges; conclusions, pp.
    182-83. A final chapter speculates on the functions of meter--an important and much- neglected
    subject. See also Wode (E703). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E714">
   <bib>"English Verse and What It Sounds Like." Kenyon Review 18 (1956): 411-77. </bib>
   <notes> The famous and influential Kenyon symposium which inaugurated the new
    structural-linguistic approach to metrics in essays by Harold Whitehall (E735) and Seymour
    Chatman (E712, E710), followed by responses and appraisals by two of the most distinguished of
    traditional literary critics, Arnold Stein (E667 and E1070) and John Crowe Ransom (E627).
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E715">
   <bib>Epstein, Edmund L., and Terence Hawkes. Linguistics and English Prosody. Studies in
    Linguistic Occasional Papers, no. 7. Buffalo: University of Buffalo Department of Anthropology
    and Linguistics, 1959. 50 pp. </bib>
   <notes> The monograph which constitutes the formal application of the methods of structural
    linguistics (the Trager-Smith phonology; see D32) to English metrics. Dispensing with the
    traditional binary metrical system (stressed- unstressed), the structural analysis notates all
    the intonational features present in the normal production of speech, in four degrees of each:
    stress: primary secondary teriary weak /, /\, \, Ë; pitch: highest high mid lowest 4, 3, 2, 1;
    juncture: end-of-word end of phrase end-of-clause end-of-sentence +, |, ||, #. Assuming also,
    then, the Relative Stress Principle (stress differences on syllables are relevant only within,
    not across, the boundaries of the metrical foot) and what later came to be called the Allophonic
    Principle (the second of two objectively equal syllables will be heard as louder--subsequently a
    much- disputed rule), the iambic foot may be redefined as "weaker-stronger," and if the metrical
    pause is allowed as well, the Epstein-Hawkes analysis yields 186 types of possible iambic feet
    (taking into consideration only stress and juncture; adding pause yields another 44, and the
    inclusion of pitch as well [the authors consider pitch peripheral, however] produces a total of
    "only" !) 6,236 types of iambic feet in English). The method is applied to Samson Agonistes.
    Varieties of trochees: 96 (stress and juncture only), besides 86 more (pause), or a total of
    2,460 (including pitch). Possibilities for the anapest run several thousand higher, with those
    for the dactyl being somewhat less, though in both cases the stress differences between the
    three syllables of the foot are characteristically quite pronounced. And though the authors
    define the metrical line typograph- ically, as a line of print, they reiterate that the basic
    patterning (unit) in meter must be binary for sheer simplicity of description. Probably the
    strongest feature of the whole structural-metric analysis is its efficacious demolition of
    larger metrical units in favor of the traditional binary and ternary units, even of binary alone
    (the ternary may be subsumed under the binary isochronically). The authors conclude that English
    verse is fundamentally iambic. On the strophic leve they recognize that the context controls the
    scansion of specific problematic lines, under a principle of greatest prevailing metrical
    consistency. The strophe does in some sense define and determine the line (meter), so it is at
    this level that an index of metrical tension becomes practicable for a text (see p. 49), an
    index which would score gradations in its features both above and below the norm ("matrix").
    "This is the difference between fine and coarse analysis," true enough, but structural metrics
    also clearly proceeds from an assumption not that meter is made out of language but that meter
    is language. In practice the authors ignore the conventionality of meter, in its reduction of
    the linguistic system. This represents, in Jakobson's terms noted by Fowler, a confusion of
    verse design and verse instance. No reader perceives six thousand types of iambs. Meter, both to
    be written and to be read, must be a very simple pattern, underneath its elaborations. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E716">
   <bib>Fowler, Roger. "'Prose Rhythm' and Meter." Fowler (A14), pp. 82-99; rpt in Freeman (A22),
    pp. 347-65. </bib>
   <notes> This lambent essay adapts the recent insights and concepts of structural metrics to
    explain how meter interacts with grammar at both its higher and its lower levels, syntax and
    phonology. The "counterpoint" of meter against syntax is essentially that of the line against
    the sentence, and Fowler shows through examples that it would be possible to construct a "scale
    of enjambement," an index sensitive to the force of the meter, essentially discontinuous,
    pulling against the force of the syntax, toward continuity. (Note that counterpoint must be
    sustained to deserve its name.) The play of metrical paradigm against the phonological structure
    of the language (stress), however, is properly termed "syncopation" not "counterpoint." The
    metrical pattern must be kept visible in order for tension to be created; otherwise the rhythm
    is "sprung" out of its proper sphere of concessions and aggressions into a simple stress verse.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E717">
   <bib>-----. "Structural Metrics." Linguistics, no. 27 (1966), pp. 49-64; rpt in Chatman and
    Levin (A21) pp. 156-69; rpt in Fowler (A12), pp. 124-40. </bib>
   <notes> A thorough, careful review of Seymour Chatman's A Theory of Meter (E713), exploring not
    only the book and its arguments but also the assumptions and methods of structural metrics in
    America since 1951. Fowler's own differences from Chatman's principles and conclusions are
    twofold, but not severe: he worries about systems in which "metre is easily and relevantly
    described according to the practices of the linguists," and he urges the adoption of the full
    Trager-Smith four-level phonological system (which Chatman rejects), believing that the "full
    suprasegmental pattern . . . is metrically significant," since ictus can be created in several
    ways. The reader who hasn't the time to read Chatman entire may safely trust this essay for a
    solid and accurate understanding. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E718">
   <bib>Fraser, G. S. Metre, Rhyme, and Free Verse. Critical Idioms Series, no. 8. London: Methuen,
    1970. 88 pp. </bib>
   <notes> A pocket-sized student's manual, the first of that sort to explictly adopt the
    Trager-Smith four-level stress system. Chapters on Stress Meters, Syllable- Stress Meters,
    Quantitative and Syllabic Meters, Rhyme, and Free Verse. Clear, non-technical explanations.
    Fraser allows six actualizations of the metrical iamb (weaker-stronger), taking 4 as the weakest
    stress and 1 as the strongest: 4-3, 4-2, 4-1, 3-2, 3-1, and 2-1 (Epstein and Hawkes (E715)
    allowed fourteen). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E719">
   <bib>Hawkes, Terence. "The Matter of Metre." Essays in Criticism 12 (1962): 413-21. Reply by F.
    W. Bateson, pp. 421-23. </bib>
   <notes> Thereafter the controversy widens: Hawkes, Terence, and F. W. Bateson. "The Matter of
    Metre." EIC 13 (1963): 198-201. Then: Ridland, J. M., and F. W. Bateson. "The Matter of Metre."
    EIC 14 (1964): 102-6. Then: Michel, Laurence. "The Emperor's Clothes (Again) or, Is Criticism
    Possible? (Again)." EIC 15 (1965): 239-43; reply by Richard Stack, "Contre Michel, Or, the
    Atomist as Contextualist," pp. 471-73. Finally: Hawkes, Terence. "New Prosodists for Old?" EIC
    16 (1966): 258; rejoinder by Michel, "The Vanity of Zeugmatising--A Correction," p. 259. Hawkes'
    review of Thompson (E91) complains of inadequacy and inconsistency in his application of the
    Trager-Smith system, as if Thompson did not quite understand how to use his tools, as it were.
    Bateson observes that the Trager-Smith system will allow comparisons of the weights of different
    metrical feet and lines, but he also identifies the effort "to detach metre from poetry" as "the
    prosodic fallacy," and he rejects the Allophonic Principle (the second of two equal sounds will
    be heard as louder). This last he reiterates. Ridland interjects that meter is more conventional
    than linguistic; metrical rules are like the rules of any game. Bateson seconds that by
    stipulating a necessary intermediary between speech and meter, Line. Michel also criticizes
    Thompson but in the process thoroughly discredits himself (as Stack shows) by a flagrant
    misrepresentation, for which he later apologizes. The entries in vols. 15 and 16 may be ignored.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E720">
   <bib>-----. "The Problems of Prosody." Review of English Literature 3 (1962): 32-49. </bib>
   <notes> Are the results of unwieldy and inaccurate conceptual machinery. The Trager- Smith
    analysis is substituted, yielding fourteen types of iambs, six trochees, ten anapests, and two
    dactyls, or thirty-two altogether. This system certainly allows better description of the
    linguistic texture of a line, but it rests on the false assumption that the metrical system is
    identical to the linguistic system underneath it. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E721">
   <bib>Hewitt, Elizabeth K. "Prosody: A Structuralist Approach." Style 6 (1972): 229-59. </bib>
   <notes> An expansion and refinement of her earlier presentation of a structuralist metric
    (below). Hewitt criticizes the Halle-Keyser framework for failing to admit first trochaic feet
    in iambic lines, final iambic feet in trochaic lines, contiguous strong stresses, and the
    allophonic-stress principle; Magnuson and Ryder for mistakenly basing their metric on syntax;
    and Beaver for the convenient optional status of the stress-exchange rule. She then presents a
    refined version of her own theory, which contains three levels--Meter (marking ictus), Cadence
    (juncture and strong stress), and Measure (pitch pattern and stress). Thus she has a tripartite
    criterion for evaluating the metricality of a line: unmetrical, uncadenced, unmeasured. A line
    that fails all three is "irregular." Finally, she tests the efficacy of her system against
    Halle- Keyser and Magnuson-Ryder in twenty-three lines from Shakespeare's Sonnets, with detailed
    analysis. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E722">
   <bib>-----. "Structure and Meaning in T. S. Eliot's Ash Wednesday." Anglia 83 (1965): 426-50. </bib>
   <notes> The scansion system of traditional metrics is too primitive, Hewitt argues, to describe
    the complex transactions and levels of English language and verse, and so she produces a
    "three-level prosodic analysis," and levels--meter, measure, and cadence--showing
    (respectively)--ictus, stress, and pitch, and stress and juncture. The meter level is binary;
    measure is rising or falling and comprises units of one stress and up to four slacks; cadence
    comprises eleven poetic and five prose feet (in Eliot). The analysis of the poem correlates
    these metrical forms with meaning, particularly the "fixity and flux" Eliot contemplates in
    "Reflections on Vers Libre." These scansions are easily the most complex I have seen. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E723">
   <bib>Hill, Archibald. "English Metrics: A Restatement." Published privately in his Essays in
    Literary Analysis. Austin, Texas: Dailey Diversified Services, 1952. pp. 6-18. </bib>
   <notes> Argues that a scansion which denotes (four degrees of metrical) stress, juncture, and
    (isochronous periods of) time should supplant the two inadequate, "pre- phonemic" metrical
    systems which cause such confusion in metrics--the one using the classical terminology, the
    other based on music. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E724">
   <bib>Kellogg, Robert L., and Oliver L. Steele. "On the Punctuation of Two Lines in The Faerie
    Queen." PMLA 78 (1963): 147-48. </bib>
   <notes> The authors contest Seymour Chatman's reading of "And like a Persian mitre on her
    head/She wore" (in C45), citing parallel examples from Spenser as support, and defending both
    the necessity of linguistic analysis of verselines and also the value of the Trager-Smith
    notation of specific features against the criticisms of these procedures by Wimsatt and
    Beardsley (E700). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E725">
   <bib>Loesch, Katherine T. "Prosodic Patterns in the Poetry of Dylan Thomas." DA 22 (1962): 3295A
    (Northwestern). </bib>
   <notes> Trager-Smith analysis of Thomas's recordings of six of his major poems, vis à vis rhythm,
    meter, and sound patterning. The poems seen to be in both syllabic- and foot-verse, with some
    tendency toward dipodism. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E726">
   <bib>Lozano, Ann. "Phonemic Patterning in Keats's 'Ode on Melancholy.'" Keats-Shelley Journal 17
    (1968): 15-29. </bib>
   <notes> A full Trager-Smith scansion of the poem reveals that it is generally isochronous, with
    two differing durations between stresses. A full analysis of segmental patterning shows general
    features of regularity, complementarity, and overlapping. Other matters of interest: Keats shows
    a surprising preference for only a few vowels on the seventh syllable in the line; there is a
    variance in distribution between those sounds that pattern horizontally and those vertically;
    y-glides are frequent in rhymes; phonemes tend to be patterned in groups of threes. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E727">
   <bib>Mosher, Harold F., Jr. "Organic Form in Gerard Manley Hopkins' 'Hurrahing in Harvest': A
    Linguistic Reading." Language and Style 2 (1969): 172-89. </bib>
   <notes> Applies traditional metrical analysis to the poem, treating it as if it were in
    accentual-syllabic meter, to discover that no discernible pattern of traditional feet appears.
    Mosher insists that the Trager-Smith system is the only adequate approach. Close analysis of
    rhyme, alliteration, and consonance round out the paper. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E728">
   <bib>Smith, Henry Lee, Jr. "Toward Redefining English Prosody." Studies in Linguistics 14
    (1959): 68-76. </bib>
   <notes> Amplification and reassertion of the author's view that "all of English 'metered' verse
    is predominantly iambic." This thesis he bases on the structural-linguistic framework (four
    degrees of stress) and two principles, the Relative Stress Principle (ictus falls "on the
    syllable bearing the stronger of any two of the four stress phonemes") and the Allophonic
    Principle (it also falls "on the second of two successive syllables bearing the same stress
    phoneme"). Examples from Donne. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E729">
   <bib>Stack, Richard C. "From Sweetness to Strength: A Study of the Development of Metrical Style
    in the English Renaissance." DA 29 (1968): 616A (Stanford). </bib>
   <notes> Stack distinguishes two broad metrical traditions in the Renaissance: one, running from
    Surrey to Spenser, sought to develop viruosity by adapting the syntax to the meter as
    mellifluously as possible; the other, best exemplified by Donne, sought to exploit the
    possibilities for contrast, tension, and clash between the rhythm and the meter. Trager-Smith
    notation of suprasegmentals is employed throughout to render more precise prosodic descriptions.
    Concludes that Donne's verse reveals not metrical roughness or license but a remarkable
    assimilation of natural speech within complex, severely constraining formal structures. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E730">
   <bib>Stein, Arnold. "George Herbert's Prosody." Language and Style 1 (1968): 1-38. </bib>
   <notes> No American critic has so successfully assimilated the precise descriptive instruments of
    Trager and Smith into graceful yet incisive critical analysis as has Arnold Stein; this essay is
    a showpiece of method [though protracted at times, one feels], explicating the rhythmic focus
    and control of "the particular discriminations of . . . meanings" in "Employment" and "The
    Crosse." Following the first four pages justifying his ways to men, Stein identifies three types
    of phrasing--metrical, colloquial, and rhythmical [these terms are inaccurate]--in order to show
    "the inventive ease with which [Herbert] adjusts colloquial and metrical phrasing to each
    other," isolating also an important principle of "advancing intensity of stress" characteristic
    of Herbert. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E731">
   <bib>-----. The Movement of Words." In his George Herbert's Lyrics. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins
    University Press, 1968. pp. 45-84. </bib>
   <notes> Stein's consistently articulate prose and steady insight is here reinforced with the
    precise descriptive apparatus of Trager and Smith (D32), using the numbers 1-4 to denote stress
    and the standard bars and cross-hatches for juncture. Stein's purpose here, though, is less to
    pursue a reading of Herbert than to establish the apparatus, and to show how Herbert's meters
    and rhythms function "in both establishing and discovering meanings." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E732">
   <bib>Sutherland, Ronald. "Structural Linguistics and English Prosody." College English 20
    (1958): 12-17: rpt in Gross (A23), pp. 181-90; rpt in Readings in Applied English Linguistics.
    Ed. Harold B. Allen. New York: Appleton-Century-Crofts, 1958; 2nd ed. 1964. pp. 492-99. </bib>
   <notes> A succinct argument of the central position of Structural Metrics--i.e., that metrical
    analysis can be considerably refined and augmented in descriptive power by adding pitch,
    juncture, and two degrees of stress to the repertoire of features denoted in scansion. The new
    method is compared to traditional scansion in a detailed analysis of Yeats's "Speech After Long
    Silence." The advantage the structural method offers is not greater understanding but clearer
    understanding. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E733">
   <bib>Taylor, Clyde R. "Developments in English Prosody." Revue de l’Université de Sherbrooke
    (Quebec) 3 (1962): 9-20. </bib>
   <notes> Taylor establishes the very salient point that traditional metrics (a la Saintsbury) and
    structural-linguistic metrics are in fact "describing different aspects of prosody [the first,
    meter, the second, rhythm], and are not at all in competition with each other." Rejecting the
    musical theory of meter and the analysis of stress-verse, Taylor then reviews the linguistic
    work, questioning the selection of the subjects chosen to perform poems for recording and
    analysis. The problem of poetic ontology at the end. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E734">
   <bib>Wells, Rulon, et al. "Comments to Part Five." Sebeok (A19), pp. 197-200; </bib>
   <notes> rpt in Chatman and Levin (A21), pp. 127-31. Responses and general discussion follow on
    pp. 200-9 (in Sebeok), and notice also the summary comments on metrics by John Hollander (pp.
    402-3) and René Wellek (pp. 413-14). Actually a study in poetic ontology (or epistomology),
    alternatively): Wells distinguishes carefully between the poem, the (original) record of the
    poem, all exact copies thereof, and adequacy vs. inadequacy in records of the poem. Conventional
    orthography gives only a fairly adequate record; a phonetic transcription would be a much better
    version. Though rules for determining meter can be given, the problem for the reader of poetry
    is that he has to (1) infer an adequate record and (2) determine the meter simultaneously,
    usually forcing him to use hypotheses about each problem to help solve the other. In the ensuing
    discussion, the participants all manage to ignore each other at length. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E735">
   <bib>Whitehall, Harold. "From Linguistics to Criticism." Kenyon Review 13 (1951): 710- 14. </bib>
   <notes> Reprinted in the symposium on "English Verse and What It Sounds Like" (E714), pp. 411-21.
    The essay reviews and anatomizes Trager and Smith's Outline of English Structure (D32), adding a
    section on "Prosodic Implications." Whitehall's position: "as no science can go beyond
    mathematics, no criticism can go beyond its linguistics." He illustrates how the Trager-Smith
    4-level stress system can be adapted to the traditional 2-level system in metrics: the two
    middle levels of stress may be variously promoted to ictus or suppressed to nonictus depending
    on environment. English verse is (surprisingly?) also said to be isochronic, our language being
    "stress-timed." Whitehall concludes with an outline of global verse-systems: ________syllabic
    rhythms_______ | | non-configurational configurational verse | | | | syllabic verse isotonic |
    isoaccentual | | | | Vedic | quantitative | | | | Chinese Greek Old English _non-syllabic
    rhythms_ | | isosyntactic isochronic | | Hebrew English The configurational forms mark or weight
    with one feature. English verse he suggests is "isoaccentual counterpointed with isochronic."
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E736">
   <bib>Whitehall, Harold, and Archibald A. Hill. "A Report on the Language-Literature Seminar."
    Readings in Applied English Linguistics. Ed. Harold B. Allen. New York: Appleton-Century-Crofts,
    1958; 2nd ed. 1964. pp. 488-92. </bib>
   <notes> The seminar topic was the examination of metrics "in light of phonemic theory," since
    "there is no phase in literature where there is a more intimate relation between the structure
    of the language and the structure of the literary work than in metrics." The components of meter
    are three: stress (using Trager-Smith's four levels in the language and two levels in meter),
    juncture (three levels--rising, falling, level--vulgarly known as "caesura"), and isochronism.
    Two primary metrical traditions in English are identified: the isochronous (the native form) and
    the isosyllabic (the foreign, syllable-counting form borrowed in Middle English); there are also
    two main theoretical traditions: the traditional metrists (with concepts derived from classical
    verse), whose system is adequate only for isosyllabic verse, and the musical metrists (Lanier,
    etc.), whose system only describes isochronous verse. Both systems are said to be prephonemic."
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E737">
   <bib>Williams, Joseph M. "Caliban and Ariel Meet Trager and Smith, or Descriptive Linguistics
    and Teaching Literature." College English 24 (1962): 121-26. </bib>
   <notes> Reviews several studies which apply structural-linguistic methods to literature,
    especially on stress-metrics, criticizing them for describing single features in isolation and
    mistaking description for interpretation. Offers a sample contrastive analysis of consonant
    clustering and light stresses in the speeches of Caliban and Ariel to support intuitions about
    verbal texture and characterization. See also: B32-33, B167, E67, E89-90, E608, E703, E1130,
    E1490, E1513, Ill, I25, E35, E38-39. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E738">
   <bib>Barnes, Mervin, and Helmut Esau. "Gilding the Lapses in a Theory of Metrics." Poetics n.s.
    8 (1979): 481-87. Commentary follows by J. C. Beaver, pp. 489- 90. </bib>
   <notes> Both the original and revised theories of generative metrics are unsatisfactory, the
    authors argue, because they judge unmetrical all lines such as Keats's "How may bards gild the
    lapses of time" which pose the problem of "double trochee after syntactic juncture." But
    trochees are unquestionably admissible after juncture at the beginning of the line, so why not
    elsewhere? Subsequent trochees after juncture are simply generalizations of the line-initial
    case. Beaver replies politely (and correctly) that the authors do not define "juncture"
    adequately. He does not mention the fact that they do not pursue their thesis to its logical
    end, where "Never, never, never, never, never" would then be an acceptable iambic pentameter.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E739">
   <bib>Beaver, Joseph C. "Contrastive Stress and Metered Verse." Language and Style 2 (1969):
    257-71. </bib>
   <notes> The first to coin the term "generative metrics," Beaver here examines the problem which
    H-K describe as "emphatic stress" (known to traditional metrists as "inverted feet") and
    elaborates a rule for reversing stress which is to stand between the lexical and the phrasal
    stress rules in the phonological cycle. On restrictiveness (optional or obligatory) no
    conclusion is drawn. A theoretical essay on rule-ordering in a particular (the metrical)
    environment. E740 MOVED to D44a. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E741">
   <bib>-----. "Current Metrical Issues." College English 33 (1971): 177-97. </bib>
   <notes> Beaver rejects the "totally accommodating" "performance grammar" of Magnuson-Ryder (while
    approving the use of Distinctive Features). His purpose here is to establish a scale of
    metricality, so glaringly absent in Halle- Keyser, based on stress rules more effective than
    those ("correspondence rules") offered in "Illustration and Defense" (E778), including his
    "Stress-Exchange Rule." This approach differs markedly from the Halle-Keyser metric, since
    Beaver's rules disclose "several kinds of stress maxima." Throughout, careful and equanimitous
    intellection. For a fuller exposition of Beaver's rules, see his E748 below. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E742">
   <bib>-----. "Generative Metrics." Princeton (A18), pp. 931-33. </bib>
   <notes> A summary review of the development of the school; Beaver elaborates the direct analogy
    between transformational-generative grammar and generative metrics, argues that the new theory
    is "more rigorous" than any of its predecessors, rebukes structural linguists ("the concept of
    stress is not a phonetic one but a phonological one, and the theory is therefore in no direct
    sense dependent on performance"), reviews the Magnuson-Ryder "Distinctive Feature" alternative,
    and cites historical precedents for the generative approach. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E743">
   <bib>-----. "Generative Metrics: The Present Outlook." Poetics 12 (1974): 7-28. </bib>
   <notes> A later reassessment of the evolution of the theory and its problems; Beaver generally
    defends his "extended original theory" against the original 1966 theory (E775) and the "revised
    theory" (E777). Triple meters, nursery-rhyme verse, competence/performance, and free verse are
    topics also treated; the section on nursery rhymes is particularly suggestive. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E744">
   <bib>-----. "Generative Metrics: Revised Version I and II." University of Illinois Department of
    Linguistics Newsletter 3 (1972): 11-12. </bib>
   <notes> A note which argues that the author's own modification of the original Halle- Keyser
    system is more adequate than their own revised version. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E745">
   <bib>-----. "A Grammar of Prosody." College English 29 (1968): 310-21. rpt in Freeman (A22), pp.
    427-47. </bib>
   <notes> An influential early article providing revision, evaluation, and "critical commentary" on
    the Halle-Keyser system. Beaver also turns to shorter-lined and trochic verse, finding that the
    "greater rhythmic regularity" in verse of short lines may be explained generatively: short lines
    are 50% denser in stress maxima. Triple meters seem to rely heavily on set syntactic formulae,
    such as prepositional phrases, which put stress on the third syllable. The traditional "foot,"
    enjambement, initial inversion, and metric stylistics are then considered in turn. Beaver
    suggests revised stress rules but insists that Halle-Keyser's metrical principles offer a
    "unified explanation" of the iambic pentameter line. The generative system, however, is
    augmented by Chatman's analysis of five types of syllables (E713). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E746">
   <bib>-----. "Progress and Problems in Generative Metrics." Papers from the Fourth Regional
    Meeting Chicago Linguistic Society. Ed. B. J. Darden, C. J. N. Bailey, and A. Davison. Chicago:
    University of Chicago Department of Linguistics, 1968. pp. 146-55. </bib>
   <notes> An introduction, summary, and review of the work of Halle-Keyser (E775), Beaver (E745),
    and Freeman (E766) on the conceptual structure of generative metrics, concluded by brief
    discussion of the problems of phrasal stress rules, contrastive stress, secondary accent,
    syntactic juncture, and vowels. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E747">
   <bib>-----. The Prosody of John Donne. Chicago: Northeastern Illinois University Department of
    Linguistics, 1976. </bib>
   <notes> A bound typescript--not listed in MLA. Rev: in Style 12 (1978): 55-57. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E748">
   <bib>-----. "The Rules of Stress in English Verse." Language 47 (1971): 586-614. </bib>
   <notes> Recognizing that "stress maxima are created in different ways," Beaver examines stress
    rules from Chomsky and Halle's Sound Pattern of English: The Nuclear Stress Rule frequently and
    the Compound Stress Rules sometimes place stress maxima in unmetrical positions. Two additional
    rules are proposed--a Stress Exchange Rule and an Alternating Stress Rule--to account for
    various causes of stress maxima. A recognition of the possible rule combinations of all these
    rules, Beaver argues, will account for "degrees of metricality." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E749">
   <bib>-----. "A Stress Problem in English Prosody." Linguistics, no 95 (1973), pp. 5-12. </bib>
   <notes> Reviewing "three approaches to the problem of how to handle back-to-back strong
    stresses," Beaver again proposes his Stress Exchange Rule, whereby word-stress may be reversed
    due to metrical context. The three positions are Traditional Prosody vs. Generative,
    Magnuson-Ryder, and Chomsky-Hall stress rules. More interesting, though, is his comparison of
    variant abstract descriptions of the same empirical phenomena on pp. 6-7. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E750">
   <bib>-----. "A Stress Swapping Rule in English Verse." Papers from the Sixth Regional Meeting
    Chicago Linguistic Society. Chicago: Chicago Linguistic Society, 1970. </bib>
   <notes> pp. 447-53. Noting that the Nuclear Stress Rule creates a dilemma for the Halle-Keyser
    system, Beaver proposes a later rule which would have the effect of exchanging stresses in cases
    where the NSR creates an unmetrical line--the rule is obligatory for metered verse and optional
    otherwise. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E751">
   <bib>Bloomfield, Morton W. "Generative Grammar and the Theory of Literature." Actes de Xe
    Congres International des Linguistes. Ed. A. Graur et al. Bucarest: Éditions de l'Academie
    R.S.R., 1970. Vol. 3, pp. 57-65. </bib>
   <notes> A very discursive survey of the uses of the new linguistics for literary analysis and
    theory, focusing at one point on metrics. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E752">
   <bib>Bowley, C. C. "Metrics and the Generative Approach." Linguistics, no. 121 (1974), pp. 5-19. </bib>
   <notes> Argues that Halle and Keyser's conception of the "standard theory of metrics" (against
    which they are reacting) is erroneous: the perfect pentameter line is not the "norm" from which
    all variations (initial trochees, etc.) are deviations; rather, the consensus in traditional
    metrics has been that variations are a part of the norm. Nor is the perfect pentameter line any
    "ideal," since poets have so obviously labored to vary it. Thereafter, protracted attributions
    from Bridges, Saintsbury, Omond, and McAuley follow. Finally, Bowley offers his own set of four
    metrical rules, which will "account for all possible metrical patterns": these differ from the
    generative account in that "metrical variation is . . . accounted for by differences in the
    underlying metrical patterns, not by differences in the way the correspondence rules apply." A
    tumid article but a trenchant criticism. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E753">
   <bib>Buss, Karen O. H. "Stress-Placement in Milton's Verse: Implications for the Halle- Keyser
    Theory of English Iambic Pentameter." DAI 35 (1974): 3727A (Brandeis). </bib>
   <notes> A comparison of Halle-Keyser and Weismiller on trochaic feet in Milton, which are found
    to comprise less that 1% of the lines in the canon. Both the two approaches are corroborated,
    though Buss proposes an amended stress- placement rule, the effect of which is to suggest that
    "the traditional concept of the foot is a meaningful one." Finally, the problem of the "relative
    stress prominence" in two adjacent stressed syllables is examined in Pope and Milton, along the
    lines of Beaver's work. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E754">
   <bib>Cable, Thomas. "A Garland of Pomposities: Comment on Halle-Kayser Prosody." College English
    34 (1973): 593-95. </bib>
   <notes> Three substantial objections are raised: (1) the Halle-Keyser theory "assumes the
    adequacy of the system" a priori in order to judge the adequacy of poetic lines, rather than
    vice versa; (2) it makes "the assumption that there should be no violations, for the sake of
    meter, of the 'linguistic givens'"--or, in other words, that rules for the general language will
    account for poetic language, there being no such thing as "poetic license" or poetic
    "deviation"; and (3) the theory excludes lines from actual poetry (Shelley) while admitting
    strings of ordinary prose and other random discourse--i.e. it admits both too much and too
    little. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E755">
   <bib>-----. "Recent Developments in Metrics." Style 10 (1976): 313-28. </bib>
   <notes> A lucid critique of generative work to 1976. Cable criticizes the Halle-Keyser theory for
    "two crucial flaws": (1) taking the stress maximum rather than the foot as the metrical unit,
    and (2) assuming that only stress ("segmental units") matter for meter, rather than other
    "linguistic givens" (i.e. "suprasegmentals" such as pause, duration, pitch, juncture). The "only
    progress [in Halle-Keyser] was the articulation of an explicit goal [Rules for determining
    Metricality] for the study of meter." Moreover, Cable argues persuasively that the generativists
    have been scornful of if not oblivious to much of the earlier scholarship of real value in
    metrics. He considers Beaver's work to yield some progress, in that it tries explicitly to work
    out other and better rules for metrical generation. Magnuson and Ryder's theory is dismissed
    because it lacks generalization altogether: any rule written applies only to that line and no
    other. Altogether, he concludes, the sole advance of the generative approach is the effort to
    make the metrical rules explicit. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E756">
   <bib>-----. "Timers, Stressers, and Linguists: Contention and Compromise." MLQ 33 (1972):
    227-39. </bib>
   <notes> Puckishly, Cable skewers the generative theory for two major flaws--the "Prosaic Fallacy"
    ("some linguists cannot read poetry" because of their dogma about No Violations of Linguistic
    Givens for the Sake of Meter) and the "Inclusive Fallacy" (the theory will admit almost any
    random string as a metrical line). The objections to the generative metrics are "unanswerable."
    The latter hald of the article argues for the existence of the "metrical pause." In sum it is an
    elegantly written piece by a sometime Timer; cf. his position in the later Style article
    (previous entry). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E757">
   <bib>Devine, A. M., and L. D. Stephens. "The Abstractness of Metrical Patterns: Generative
    Metrics and Explicit Traditional Metrics." Poetics (o.s. 16) n.s. 4,4: 411-29. </bib>
   <notes> A comparison of traditional and generative metrics in order to show that some traditional
    procedures are more effective than present generative ones and that the two might therefore be
    usefully conjoined. "Once traditional metrics is made explicit, it becomes evident that the
    label 'generative' is not really the prerogative of the so-called 'generative' approach to
    metrical theory." (The examples are taken from the Classical meters.) </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E758">
   <bib>Dilligan, Robert J. "Ibant Obscuri: Robert Bridges' Experiment in English Quantitative
    Verse." Style 6 (1972): 38-65. </bib>
   <notes> A detailed anatomy of the concepts of stress, quantity, and pitch in Latin, Greek,
    English, and in the work of Bridges and Stone, coupled with a computed scansion based on
    Beaver's revised definition of the "stress maximum." A system for scanning stresses can be
    applied to Bridges' work because he produced "a combination of accentual and quantitative
    meter." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E759">
   <bib>-----. "Verse Design in the Poetry of the Hopkins-Bridges Circle: An Essay in Computational
    Metrics." DAI 31 (1970): 1755A (Wisconsin). </bib>
   <notes> A computerized analysis of Hopkins, Bridges, and Patmore using a method of a "linguistic
    orientation" (no more is divulged); these three poets were selected because their metrical
    theories are concentrated on, respectively, stress, syllables, and time. Moreover, "Hopkins'
    Sprung Rhythm and Bridges' experiments in quantitative verse are examples of phonemic and
    nonphonemic verse-conventions for which linguistic, as contrasted with traditional, prosody is
    [a] particularly suitable basis for analysis." The methodology is apparently generative.
    Computer programs provided as an appendix. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E760">
   <bib>Dilligan, Robert J., and Karen Lynn. "Computers and the History of Prosody." College
    English 34 (1973): 1103-23. </bib>
   <notes> The assumption behind all of Dilligan's work is that the only way to avoid impressionism
    in prosodic studies is quantification: assertions are to be validated by distributions and
    percentages. This essay describes the computer- program for an analysis of Hopkins, following
    the revised theory presented in English Stress (E777) (since "in linguistics one finds a
    methodology . . . that satisfies the need for explicitness and logical consistency"). But
    Dilligan is clear about the recognition that "the statistics, then, are in no sense an
    interpretation within themselves; they are simply a significant preliminary to interpretation."
    All a computer can do is count and sort. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E761">
   <bib>Dilligan, Robert J., and T. K. Bender. "The Lapses of Time: A Computer-Assisted
    Investigation of English Prosody." The Computer and Literary Studies. Ed. A. J. Aitken et al.
    Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 1973. pp. 239-52. </bib>
   <notes> Description of the four phases of the computer analysis, particularly the third--
    cataloguing--since it is the computer's ability to sort very large files that is of use. A
    sample of the running tallies on thirty-eight metrical variables by poem and by corpus is shown.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E762">
   <bib>Fowler Rowena. "Metrics and the Transformational-Generative Model." Lingua 38 (1976):
    21-36. </bib>
   <notes> A survey-commentary on the development of transformational-generative linguistics as
    applied to metrics: the linchpin of Fowler's argument is that the application is based on an
    analogy (there is a "grammar of prosody" equivalent to the grammar of the language) which has
    decided limitations. Most conspicuously, the linguistic model exaggerates the extent of
    poetry-as-a- piece-of-language: "although their basic material is linguistic and therefore
    subject to description in linguistic terms, metrical and literary conventions are non-linguistic
    aspects of form." Less conspicuously, the key concepts of T-G grammar, such as abstract pattern,
    tranformational rules, deep structures, competence, or grammaticality, have shown only very
    limited uses in metrics. Fowler distinguishes between the methods of theoretical metrics and
    metrical stylistics and then enumerates advantages and disadvantages. A reflective essay which
    scores some hits and some misses. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E763">
   <bib>Fox, Allan B. "Chaucer's Prosody and the Non-Pentameter Lines in John Heywood's Comic
    Debates." Languages and Style 10 (1977): 23-41. </bib>
   <notes> Follows Ian Robinson (K318) in believing that "Chaucer's line is a non- pentameter, more
    dependent on the alliterative accentual tradition of native verse. . . ." Analysis of Heywood
    supports the further argument that his metric is better than most prosodists believe and that it
    represents a coherent and substantial (alliterative) tradition throughout late-medieval and
    early-Tudor poetry. His metrical unit, then, is neither the foot nor the (generative) position
    but the phrase, or half-line. Rules on p. 29. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E764">
   <bib>Freeman, Donald C. "Current Trends in Metrics." Current Trends in Stylistics. Ed. B. B.
    Kachru and Herbert R. W. Stahlke. Edmonton (Canada): Linguistic Research, Inc., 1972. pp. 67-80. </bib>
   <notes> Distinguishes the schools of metrists as Traditional (Shapiro, Beum, Fussell, Malof),
    Structural (Epstein, Hawkes, Chatman, Fowler) and Generative, offers a sample analysis of
    Dickinson's "Safe in Their Alabaster Cloisters" according to each system, argues for the
    existence of a metrical "stressed rest", and concludes that the poem is a conflation of both the
    syllabontonic (iambic pentameter) and accentual (Germanic four-stress verse) systems, which only
    generative metrics can account for. The logic in all this is confused, and Freeman takes a his
    model Halle-Keyser 1966 (E775) rather than 1971 (E777). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E765">
   <bib>-----. "Metrical Position Constituency and Generative Metrics." Language and Style 2
    (1969): 195-206. </bib>
   <notes> Freeman is interested in synaloepha (metrical position:syllable = one:many) and diaeresis
    (position : syllable = many : one); the essay interprets the data provided in Sipe (E1304) on
    Shakespeare in order to derive the rules for permissible filling of metrical slots. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E766">
   <bib>-----. "On the Primes of Metrical Style." Language and Style 1 (1968): 63-101; rpt in
    Freeman (A22), pp. 448-91. </bib>
   <notes> An early affirmative appraisal of Halle-Keyser, with application to Renaissance dramatic
    blank verse. Granting that the forte of generative metrics is its mechanism for sorting metrical
    from unmetrical lines, Freeman confronts the further, harder issue: "What are we to ask beyond
    metricality? What does such a theory allow us to say about metrical style?" An entire set of
    metrical-stylistic categories (a terminology) is needed which does not presently exist (none is
    given here). Freeman criticizes the stylistic adequacy of structural metrics and shows the
    stylistic "effects" of various stress-maxima realizations as the groundwork for a full-blown
    generative theory of metrical styles. Detailed interpretation of statistics and examples. A
    survey very extensive in scope and implication and superior to many that followed it. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E767">
   <bib>Freeman, Margaret H. "Emily Dickinson's Prosody: A Study in Metrics." DAI 33 (1972): 2915A
    (Massachusetts). </bib>
   <notes> Generative metrics is particularly useful for describing Dickinson's unusual verse
    because her enigmatic dashes "often serve to prevent unmetricality," but two rules need to be
    added to the system stipulating when "stress rests" need to be supplied, since in E. D.'s verse
    both the number and the positions of the stresses are important. Freeman concludes that
    Dickinson wrote in two modes- -"syllabotonic rhythm" and "stress-rest rhythm." Surprisingly, she
    also applies Creed's rules for Beowulf (J61) to E. D., in order to establish a connection
    between the Germanic meter and the English ballad. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E768">
   <bib>Greenblatt, Daniel L. "The Effect of Genre on Metrical Style." Language and Style 11
    (1978): 18-29. </bib>
   <notes> Plotting each degree of complexity on the Halle-Keyser scale against the number of lines
    rated at that degree produces a graphic distribution curve for Ben Jonson which turns out to be
    virtually identical to a standard Poisson distribution. Similar analyses of a reduced corpus
    sorted by genre for each of six major seventeenth-century poets shows that (1) all except
    Marvell vary their metrical style (as shown by complexity distributions) considerably among the
    different genres, though (2) all six poets treat each genre essentially the same way metrically.
    Genre exerts a "powerful" effect on metrical style. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E769">
   <bib>-----. "Generative Metrics and Seventeenth-Century Prosody: A Quantitative Study." DAI 35
    (1975): 4476A (Michigan). </bib>
   <notes> An argument that generative metrics is superior to traditional metrics for quantitative
    (computer-counting) studies. Analysis of concepts and procedures. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E770">
   <bib>-----. "Generative Metrics and the Authorship of 'The Expostulation.'" Centrum 1 (1973):
    87-104. </bib>
   <notes> Concludes in favor of Jonson. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E771">
   <bib>-----. "Variable Rules and Literary Style." Computers and the Humanities 11 (1977): 193-97. </bib>
   <notes> Interested in the concept of the variable rule in linguistics, the author analyzes 1136
    pentameters of Herrick and Jonson, writing such a rule to test for Weak- position stress
    assignment. The rule is "systematically variable and context- senstive" and states that the
    probability of stressing a W-position "increases when that position is preceded and/or followed
    by an unstressed syllable, or when no major syntactic break is adjacent to it." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E772">
   <bib>Guéron, Jacqueline. "Children's Verse and the Halle-Keyser Theory of Prosody." Children's
    Literature: The Great Excluded, II. Storrs, Ct.: University of Connecticut Press, 1973. pp.
    197-208. </bib>
   <notes> A narrow application of the Halle-Keyser framework to English and French nursery- and
    counting-rhymes, which turn out to have the same deep metrical structure, four stresses to the
    line. Nowhere does the author distinguish ballad- meter as stress verse from accentual-syllabic
    verse, but her realization rules allow filling of W-positions with from one to three syllables.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E773">
   <bib>-----. "The Meter of Nursery Rhymes: An Application of the Halle-Keyser Theory of Meter."
    Poetics 12 (1974): 73-112. </bib>
   <notes> The meter is syllabotonic, not tonic as in Old English, and the stress is clausal. Cf.
    Burling (L19). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E774">
   <bib>Halle, Morris. "On Meter and Prosody." Progress in Linguistics. Ed. M. Bierwisch and K. E.
    Heidolph. The Hague: Mouton, 1970. pp. 64-80. </bib>
   <notes> Abstracted in Actes du Xe Congres International des Linguistes. Ed. A. Graur et al.
    Bucarest: Éditions de l'Academie R.S.R., 1970. p. 97. A theoretical discussion and typology of
    Meter, Actualization, and Mapping Rules in the meters of a number of different languages.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E775">
   <bib>Halle, Morris, and Samuel J. Keyser. "Chaucer and the Study of Prosody." College English 28
    (1966): 187-219; rpt in Freeman (A22), p. 366-426. </bib>
   <notes> The original statement of the theory of generative metrics, as applied to the iambic
    pentameter in Middle English; the definitions and concepts given here were much criticized and
    amended later, and this article has no final authority. See the revised version of the theory at
    E777. Halle and Keyser fix the fundamental aim of prosody as the distinguishing of metrical from
    unmetrical lines. To this end they define the abstract (deep) metrical pattern of the iambic
    pentameter line as having ten metrical positions, five even, five odd. Second, they define the
    conditions under which a postion may be occupied by more than one (surface) syllable. Third,
    they define the stress maximum (a syllable with stress greater than that on both syllables
    adjacent to it), which may (or may not) occupy an even position but may not occupy an odd one,
    as the fundamental criterion of metricality. The stress rules to be applied are lexical, and a
    provision is made for caesurae (stress maxima undergo "neutralization" across "a major syntactic
    boundary"). Two Condition rules allow disyllabic occupancy of the metrical positions. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E776">
   <bib>-----. "English: III. The Iambic Pentameter." Wimasatt (A20), pp. 217-37. </bib>
   <notes> Since Wimsatt's anthology appeared (1972) after the publication of Halley and Keyser's
    English Stress (1971), this article takes account (in the Notes) of the additions to the theory
    by Hascall, Beaver, and Freeman, and the objections by Wimsatt and Magnuson-Ryder, even though
    the article itself is a simplified version of chapter 3 of English Stress (next entry). </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E777">
   <bib>-----. English Stress: Its Form, Its Growth, and its Role in Verse. New York: Harper &amp;
    Row, 1971. 186 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Rev: by Beaver in Language Sciences, no. 18 (1971), pp. 33-37. A theory of both phonology
    ("The Stress System of Modern English" and "The Evolution of the English Stress System") and
    metrics ("A Theory of Meter"). Chapter 3 should be considered the definitive statement of the
    revised Halle-Keyser theory of generative metrics. It contains an introductory section on
    general principles, a section on Old English alliterative verse, and a section on the iambic
    pentameter. The revised rules are as follows: For Old English verse ABSTRACT METRICAL PATTERN:
    (i) A verse line is composed of a first and second half-line (ii) The first-half-line is
    composed of (X)*X (iii) The second half-line is composed of X(W)* CORRESPONDENCE RULES: (i) Each
    X corresponds to a single S, or One X in a half-line may correspond to an S and a W in either
    order DEFINITION: If in two or more stressed syllables the zero or more consonants that pre-cede
    the vowel are identical or begin with an identical consonant or s-cluster, the syllables
    alliterate. (ii) Syllables in S positions alliterate; syllables in W positions do not alliterate
    For modern English verse ABSTRACT METRICAL PATTERN: (W)*SWSWSWSWS(X) (X) where elements enclosed
    in parentheses may be omitted and where each X position may be occupied only by an unstressed
    syllable CORRESPONDENCE RULES: A position (S, W, or X) corresponds to a single syllable or to a
    sonorant sequence incorporating at most two vowels (immedi-ately adjoining or separated by a
    sonorant conso-nant) DEFINITION: When a fully stressed syllable occurs between two unstressed
    syllables in the same syntactic constituent within a line of verse, this syllable is called a
    "stress maximum" (ii) Fully stressed syllables occur in S positions only and in all S positions,
    or Fully stressed syllables occur in S positions only but not in all S positions, or Stress
    maxima occur in S positions only but not in all S positions, Since the Correspondence Rules are
    ordered from least to greatest generality, lines which violate them will be progressively less
    metrical in the same order. Lines violating rule (1) will normally be considered acceptable
    variations, while lines violating rule (iii) are simply unmetrical. Counting each infraction of
    each rule as one unit will give a numerical score of the metrical complexity (i.e. degree of
    metricality) of the line. (This procedure is unchanged from the original version of the theory.)
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E778">
   <bib>-----. "Illustration and Defense of a Theory of the Iambic Pentameter." College English 33
    (1971): 154-76. </bib>
   <notes> Published after the codification of their theory in English Stress (which appeared in
    Feb. 1971), Halle and Keyser here reprint a succinct account of the modified theory and respond
    directly to the criticisms of Wimsatt (E814) and Magnuson-Ryder (E821). They reject Wimsatt's
    view that the meter "exerts a certain kind of coercion . . . a quiet 'promotion' of certain
    weaker syllables"--i.e., that the meter can "tilt" the "linguistic givens." The Halle- Keyser
    view is that "meter is an abstract pattern embodied in linguistic material by virtue of specific
    correspondence rules"; Wimsatt's approach is "contentless." They defend the concept of the
    "stress maximum." The Magnuson-Ryder theory is examined at length and dismissed, its rules
    having no applicable generalization beyond the separate lines they describe. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E779">
   <bib>Hascall, Dudley L. "The Prosody of John Lydgate." Language and Style 3 (1970): 122-46. </bib>
   <notes> A modification of the Halle-Keyser scansion system, recognizing changes in the language
    between Chaucer and Lydgate; the original Halle-Keyser theory alone "does not work" for Lydgate.
    The conclusion is that Lydgate is more regular metrically than is usually assumed, and that he
    simply used, extensively, line types which are exceptional in Chaucer. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E780">
   <bib>-----. "Some Contributions to the Halle-Keyser Theory of Prosody." College English 30
    (1969): 357-65. </bib>
   <notes> Close technical work: amendments to the Halle-Keyser 1966 rules (E775), and contravention
    of their position on rhyme and stress. Also contradicted is their "No Violations of the
    Linguistic Givens." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E781">
   <bib>-----. "A Theory of English Meter: Accentual-Syllabic Verse." DAI 31 (1970): 2899A
    (Harvard). </bib>
   <notes> A twofold study: Hascall argues for the teaching of meter in high-school poetry classes
    as the "only coherent internal structure" in poetry (à la Bruner); his method is "largely within
    the framework" of Halle-Keyser. "The syllabic-accentual meters of English are determined as
    iambic, ballad, trochaic, and triple meters." Finally, he considers problems of line length,
    secondary stress in compounds, and rhyming of unstressed syllables, proposing solutions based on
    a redefinition of "relative stress" and other features. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E782">
   <bib>-----. "Triple Meter in English Verse." Poetics 12 (1974): 49-72. </bib>
   <notes> An extension of the generative framework: Hascall discovers that triple meters (1) have
    fewer applicable rule conditions, (2) depend much more heavily on phrasal stress than lexical
    for the rhythm, (3) employ contrastive stress more frequently, and (4) require, for the
    sacrifice in flexible line-length, stronger marking of stress in the ictus position. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E783">
   <bib>-----. "Trochaic Meter." College English 33 (1971): 217-26. </bib>
   <notes> Taking Nowottny as his text, Hascall applies Halle-Keyser yet once again, this time to
    trochaics. The conditions turn out to apply much less often than in iambics, unmetrical trochaic
    lines are rare; the meter is fixed at the very outset of the line; more positions are fitted by
    stress maxima. There is "less distance, in trochaic verse, between the metrical line and the
    poetic line." Provocative suggestions near the end. See also Newton (E779), Steward (E331),
    Atkins (E467), and Creek (E18). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E784">
   <bib>Heller, Janet Ruth. "Enjambement as a Metrical Force in Romantic Conversation Poems."
    Poetics 6 (1977): 15-26. </bib>
   <notes> A suggestion to revise the Halle-Keyser definition of "stress maximum" so as to allow its
    occurrence in position 10 of emjambed lines; in effect, therefore, a complete abandonment of the
    concept of "line" as "the ultimate domain" in the generative system. Under the revised
    definitions, the number of stress maxima rise sharply (12-16%) and the distribution patterns of
    course change. E785 -----. "Syntactic Juncture and the Halle-Keyser Theory of Iambic
    Pentameter." Language and Style 11 (1978): 164-67. Sharp criticism of Halle and Keyser's
    treatment of major syntactic junctures. Their later view--that juncture neutralizes stress
    maxima--contradicts their original position, prohibits their results from being compared with
    those of other researchers (Freeman), produces undesirable redundancies in the theory, is based
    on a flimsy definition of terms, and does not differentiate pauses from larger junctures, in sum
    creating more problems than it solves. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E786">
   <bib>Ihwe, Jens. "On the Foundations of 'Generative Metrics.'" Poetics n.s. 4,4(o.s. 16)(1975):
    367-400. </bib>
   <notes> A metatheoretical and metaprocedural essay. Ihwe believes that in fact "genera-tive
    metrics" is not particularly generative and that it will not become so until it establishes an
    adequately descriptive metalanguage. He examines the work of Kiparsky (E827) approvingly, and
    the work of Halle (E774), and others: the tranformational framework must be more rigorously
    applied, he concludes, in order to explain precisely how "the structure of national languages
    permits the introduction and development of metrical systems and makes them thus accentually
    possible." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E787">
   <bib>Jussel, Richard F. "A Linguistic Analysis of Pope's Prosody." DAI 36 (1975): 2780A
    (Northern Colorado). </bib>
   <notes> Jussell claims that the generative theory "does not deny the validity of any of the other
    critical approaches to the study of Pope." In fact "it supports them," since it "deals with
    placement of linguistic stress, not metrical stress." Also examined: the linguistic and metrical
    aspects of metaphor, tone, and stylistic development. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E788">
   <bib>Keyser, Samuel J. "The Linguistic Basis of English Prosody." Modern Studies in English. Ed.
    David A. Reibel and Sanford A. Schane. Englewood Cliffs: Prentice-Hall, 1969. pp. 379-94. </bib>
   <notes> Keyser finds the precedent for prosodic rules in Bridges (E491). This article presents
    modifications of Halle-Keyser 1966 (E775); in general it is a simplified, non-technical
    introduction to the generative theory for iambic pentameter. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E789">
   <bib>-----. "Old English Prosody." College English 30 (1969): 331-56. </bib>
   <notes> A "companion piece" to Halle-Keyser 1966 (E775), with rule-adjustments for accentual
    verse. In addition, a detailed response to Sievers, with glanes at Pope (prosodist), Sir Gawain,
    and nursery rhymes. Notice that in the generative account of the OE verse only one full stress
    need appear in a half-line to confirm it as metrical. And the matter of "resolved stresses" is
    dispensed with. See the revised rules for Old English meter at E777. And see E807. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E790">
   <bib>Klein, Wolfgang. "Critical Remarks on Generative Metrics." Poetics 12 (1974): 29- 48. </bib>
   <notes> Beginning with the notion that "metrics deals with the order of marked and unmarked
    elements in discourse," Klein isolates fifteen Questions any metrical theory must answer. He
    contrasts at length the generative theories to the earlier "taxonomical" (descriptive) ones and
    rejects the notion of a "metrical competence" in speakers analogous to the linguistic
    competence. "The main fault of standard theory is . . . that it tries to grasp all possible and
    allowable deviations by means of a list" (rather than a rule). But the generative theory, on the
    other hand, "is not able to distinguish between metrical and unmetrical lines," is flagrantly
    accomodating, and "cannot establish a difference between iambic and trochaic lines." The older
    empirical theory is to be preferred to the newer theory, which is "fundamentally inadequate"
    because its formulation is "a statement on the nature of the infinite set of possible iambic
    pentameters." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E791">
   <bib>Küper, Christoph. "Moglichkeiten and Grenzen der Generativen Metrik." Linguistische
    Berichte 27 (1973): 8-40. </bib>
   <notes> Reviews the standard and revised Halle-Keyser theories and the Magnuson- Ryder approach,
    then tests the standard and revised theories on the verse of Dylan Thomas and G. M. Hopkins in
    order to discover the limits of the Halle-Keyser theory's applicability. These limits turn out
    to be rather severe, though Thomas can be described more adequately than Hopkins: (1) lines in
    the same meter but with different lengths cannot be usefully compared; (2) intentional shifts of
    meter in mid-line, common in Hopkins, are classed as unmetrical; (3) mixed meters cannot be
    described; (4) the theory misunderstands Old English meter by not paying attention to the number
    of slacks; (5) Sprung Rhythm, in which the stress-count varies, cannot be adequately explained;
    (6) no adequate justification for a scale of complexity is given; and (7) no clear line is drawn
    between complex and unmetrical. Küper gives Correspondence Rules for Sprung Rhythm at the end.
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E792">
   <bib>Levin, Samuel R. "A Revision of the Halle-Keyser Metrical Theory." Language 49 (1973):
    606-11. </bib>
   <notes> A cogent demonstration of the incoherence of Correspondence Rule 52bii in English Stress
    (E777). Levin offers a simplified, ordered, more conceptually elegant set of three rules, each
    of which "describes a metrical type," and defines the violation of the next more complex
    metrical type, thus producing a simpler and clearer index of metrical complexity. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E793">
   <bib>Lynn, Karen. "Chaucer's Decasyllabic Line: The Myth of the Hundred-Year Hibernation."
    Chaucer Review 13 (1978): 116-27. </bib>
   <notes> Based on her dissertation, DAI 34 (1974): 4210A (U.S. C.). Computer analysis (using the
    Dilligan programs) of samples of the verse of the Post-Chaucerians disproves the thesis that
    these poets misunderstood the master's versification; rather, they extended metrical variation
    beyond the limits Chaucer allowed himself as well as adding new possibilities. Specifically,
    they more frequently (1) filled one metrical position with two syllables, expanding the range of
    permissible elisions, (2) elided unstressed suffixes to their roots, (3) dropped a syllable in
    position 5, leaving a rest after the caesura (Lydgate's "broken-backed" line), and (4) rhymed
    stressed syllables with unstressed. Metrical complexity scores: Chaucer, 1.8; Dunbar, 2.0;
    Hoccleve, 2.7; and Lydgate and Skelton, 3.0. Chaucer's grace and "lightness" of line result from
    stresses often falling under ictus; his followers, in contrast, often weighted their lines by
    spreading stresses into non-ictic positions. But more interesting still is the discovery that
    stress-neutralization by adjacent syntactic break is radically different from neutralization by
    adjacent stress, producing a much smoother effect stylistically. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E794">
   <bib>Meyers, Gerald W. "Modern Theories of Meter: A Critical Review." DAI 30 (1970): 3912A
    (Michigan) </bib>
   <notes>. After identifying the functions of a metrical theory as (1) historical analysis, (2)
    characterization of styles, and (3) close study of a text, Meyers distinguishes three schools of
    metrists: Traditional (e.g. Fussell, Wimsatt &amp; Beardsley, Fowler), Performance (Charman,
    Epstein and Hawkes), and Language-Competence (Halle-Keyser). Traditional metrics is "in essence
    a psychological theory" and "workable but unnecessarily complicated." The extreme variation in
    oral performances of poetry has not yet been adequately comprehended in a notation system, and
    so Performance metrics is not yet successful. Linguistic metrics, however, is "the most
    promising of modern theories of meter," because it assumes that "the language . . . together
    with the shared competence of speakers of the language, provides sufficient information for
    describing the metrical situation." In short Meyer prefers the Halle-Keyser apparatus. He does
    however admit its difficulties and suggests as partial solutions a revised notation system and a
    reduction from Halle-Keyser's de facto three levels of stress to two by dismissing the notion of
    neutralization. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E795">
   <bib>Miller, D. Gary. "Language Change and Poetic Options." Language 53 (1977): 21- 38. </bib>
   <notes> Argues that the rules for "options" in poetry (i.e. various metrical styles) are
    identical to those for changes in language in general--i.e., rule relaxation, rule- reordering,
    rule generalization, and rule inversion. Distinguishes three types of complexity--linguistic,
    metrical, and rhythmic--and criticizes both Halle- Keyser and Kiparsky for measuring the wrong
    type of complexity and failing to define the domains of each type. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E796">
   <bib>Mintzer, Paul. "Linguistics and the Art of Criticism." DAI 38 (1978): 6696A (Northwestern). </bib>
   <notes> Chapter 3 constructs a model for "extending the Halle-Keyser metrical system to rhythmic
    verse," whatever that is. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E797">
   <bib>Napoli, Donna Jo. "A Note on Synalepha and Stress Mexima." Poetics n.s. 4,4(o.s. 16)(1975):
    401-10. </bib>
   <notes> Examines the interaction of two Correspondence Rules (Synalepha and the Stress Maximum
    Constrant), without any final resolution. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E798">
   <bib>Neufeldt, Victoria E. "The Metric of English Alliterative Verse: Piers the Plowman and
    Beowulf." DAI 39 (1978): 2226A (Toronto, 1976). </bib>
   <notes> Demonstration that Halle and Keyser's generative theory for alliterative verse is
    seriously inadequate and should be replaced with a model, "based on the hypothesis that the
    phonological phrase is the basis of the traditional Germanic alliterative half-line," which will
    more adequately describe Langland's meter. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E799">
   <bib>Newton, Robert P. "Trochaic and Iambic." Language and Style 8 (1975): 127-56. </bib>
   <notes> The author collects a number of apparently trochaic lines with initial iambic
    substitutions in order to show that they can be proven metrical by the Stress Maximum Principle
    though not by traditional scansion. [Note however that the examples are nearly all in tetrameter
    verse, that the percentages for occurrence in pentameter and tetrameter verse vary widely and
    consistently, and that Newton admits several of the sample poems are in mixed meters.
    Traditional metrics would say these lines are regular headless iambics.] Initial inversion is
    four times more prevalent in iambic verse than trochaic, and medial inversions have similar
    frequencies. Newton criticizes Hascall's approach (E783) and concludes that Structural Metrics
    by nature will never be able to give a coherent differentiation of "trochaic" and "iambic"
    lines. Halle and Keyser never will either until their generative rules are revised. Newton's own
    approach (summarized on pp. 146-52), based on the experiments of Snell, Woodrow, Warner Brown,
    and the like, specifies differences in rhythmical grouping: trochaic feet are shorter than
    iambic; the length of stress to slack is 2:1 in iambic but 1:1 in trochaic. An essay very wide
    in scope, but discomfitingly disorganized. Cf. Hascall (E783), Creek (E18), Stewart (E331), and
    Atkins (E467). E800 Olsen, Leslie A. "A Description of the Blank Verse Prosodies of John Milton,
    James Thomson, Edward Young, William Cowper, and William Wordsworth." DAI 35 (1974): 3002A
    (U.S.C.). The methodology is Halle-Keyser, using a computer program (developed by Dilligan) to
    examine stress maxima, assonance, alliteration, and elisions. Wordsworth and Milton turn out to
    be more similar to each other metrically than to the other three, and Wordsworth "nearly
    re-attains the level established by Milton" in "some quantitative supportable ways." Thomson and
    Cowper seem to compose verse using "syntactic formulas." Young's blank verse shows a strong
    influence from the couplet. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E801">
   <bib>Rehor, Rosalind J. "This Round Dome: An Analysis of Theme and Style in the Poetry of Robert
    Lowell." DAI 33 (1972): 1709A (Case Western Reserve). </bib>
   <notes> Includes a Halle-Keyser analysis of meters and a lexical-syntactic concordance. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E802">
   <bib>Roach, Bruce V. "On S. J. Keyser's Rules of Prosody." College English 36 (1974): 217-18. </bib>
   <notes> Rebukes Keyser for failing both at accuracy and at completeness in his abstract
    "model-building" and suggests an alternative version of the Abstract Metrical Rules which will
    solve the problem. And, since Roach believes that all generative theories suffer "problems in
    bridging the gap between phonemics and syllabics," he offers a Saussurean phonemic rule. Keyser
    declines to reply. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E803">
   <bib>Sapora, Robert W., Jr. A Theory of Middle English Alliterative Meter with Critical
    Applications. Speculum Anniversary Monographs, no. 1. Cambridge Mass.: Mediaeval Academy of
    America, 1977. 117 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Based on his dissertation of the same title, DAI 36 (1976): 7395A (Connecticut). Using
    the Halle-Keyser framework, Sapora proposes a system of twenty-three levels of metrical
    complexity for alliterative verse, based on the stressed (and alliterating) syllables but
    ignoring all unstressed syllables in between as metrically irrelevant. One wonders how anyone
    could wish to defend such a position, since Sievers, Pope, Cable, and others have shown that
    even in Old English "stress verse" the weak syllables are metrically significant. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E804">
   <bib>Schap, Keith. "A Transformational Study of John Dryden's Metrical Practice." DAI 33 (1973):
    5692A (Indiana). </bib>
   <notes> Conjoins Halle-Keyser scansion and Richard Ohmann's notion of deep- and
    surface-structures vis à vis style in order to analyze the relationship of meter to meaning in
    MacFlecknoe and The Medal. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E805">
   <bib>Schultz, Hartwig. "Engwicklungsmöglichkeiten der generativen Metrik." Linguistische
    Berichte 37 (1975): 27-35. </bib>
   <notes> Agrees with Ihwe that generative-metrical rules have only taxonomic value and that what
    they predict is either tautological or nonexistent. The only new and valuable concept is that of
    the "filter." "Complexity" is attractive, too, though the counting-method of complexity ranking
    eliminates any possibility for an explanation of the nature of complexity. A study of the
    position of more complex lines in a poem would give us more information than the present
    "leveling" method. Kiparsky's system has gaps and cannot indicate hierarchies of accentu- ation.
    His alternation rule will not serve even if refined because it pays insufficient attention to
    secondary stresses in W-positions. The "constrastive" and "emphatic" stresses of Bierwisch also
    will not do. Schultz argues that the cyclical application of the stress rules in classical
    generative phonology will suffice. Application to the verse of Stefan George. </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E806">
   <bib>Scott, Charles T. "Towards a Formal Poetics: Metrical Patterning in 'The Windhover.'"
    Language and Style 7 (1974): 91-107. </bib>
   <notes> A demonstration that although the poem appears to be Old English alliterative verse, "the
    underlying metrical pattern of the poem is iambic." This is accomplished by redividing the
    fourteen lines of the poem (into twenty-one) and scanning them via Halle-Keyser 1971 (E777).
   </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E807">
   <bib>Sledd, James. "Old English Prosody: A Demurrer." College English 31 (1969): 71- 74. </bib>
   <notes> Most immediately a response to Keyser's "Old English Prosody" (E789). Sledd methodically
    demonstrates a "reprehensible irresponsibility" of scholarly method and concludes that the
    Halle-Keyser theory is an "unrelieved disaster," being "altogether too accomodating." Reply by
    Keyser, pp. 74-80. Keyser's argument in reponse is that Sledd's demonstration of gross factual
    errors in scholarship in no way infringes the validity of the theory itself. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E808">
   <bib>Standop, Ewald. "Die Metrik auf Abwegen--Eine Kritik der Halle-Keyser Theorie."
    Linguistische Berichte 19 (1972): 1-19. </bib>
   <notes> Translated into English as "Metric Theory Gone Astray: A Critique of the Halle-Keyser
    Theory." Language and Style 8 (1975): 60-77. Would a Temporalist want his sister to marry a
    Generativist? Standop delivers a stinging criticism of the assumptions, aims and ends of the
    Halle-Keyser theory, particularly its treatment of lexical stress, but also of its conceptions
    of "stress maximum," "position," and "complexity." The generative theory is "a fatal step
    backwards" in metrics. More generally, Halle-Keyser are guilty of both ignoring Rhythm (i.e.
    hebungen and pauses) altogether and also of an "assumption that the poet is guided principally
    by the verbal material." Deviations in the number of syllables . . . are felt to be rhythmically
    more seriously deviant than . . . deviations in stress." The Conclusion ("Do We Need a
    Generative Theory of Metrics?"), though, is (surprisingly) judicious and open. "The root of
    Halle-Keyser's failure is not in the generative idea itself but in the hypotheses and
    assumptions which have gone into their theory." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E809">
   <bib>Stillings, Justine T. "A Generative Metrical Analysis of Sir Gawain and the Green Knight."
    Language and Style 9 (1976): 219-46. </bib>
   <notes> Citing both Halle-Keyser and Kiparsky as theories inadequate for Gawain, Stillings
    adjusts the rule categories, arguing that "if an iambic foot contains three syllables, the
    underlying metrical representation contains three positions." Metrical Base Rules are redefined
    as Lexical Constraints (Correspondence Rules). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E810">
   <bib>Tsur, Reuven. A Perception-Oriented Theory of Metre. Tel Aviv: Porter Israeli Institute for
    Poetics &amp; Semiotics, Tel Aviv University, 1977. 244 pp. </bib>
   <notes> Despite the date of publication, most of this theory was worked out from 1969-72; it
    represents an attempt to embed the basic Halle-Keyser framework within a much wider, more highly
    formalized psychological (Gestalt) theory of meter which integrates (1) some of the current
    understanding of human processing of perceptual patterns and (2) the concept of Performance at a
    fundamental level in the theory, in order to achieve greater refinements of explanatory power,
    i.e. greater "delicacy" of description, by converting Halle and Keyser's dichotomous metrical
    determinations (metrical, unmetrical) to a continuum of finer discriminations of metrical
    complexity. The five fundamental categories of Tsur's theory along with their components are:
    DIMENSION: conventional--i.e. formal, as in meter linguistc--the phonological rules of stress
    and syntax performative--the set of conditions in which the elements of the conventional and
    linguistic dimensions tend to group into, and establish themselves as, perceptual units. Here
    the metrical set, syntactic set, and other perceptual character- istics of the auditor, the
    performer's style, and the prosodic givens pertain. CORRESPONDENCE: (essentially the three
    Halle-Keyser Correspondence Rules) Linguistic stresses in relation to metrical positions may be:
    confirming, non-confirming, or infirming, the result of which may be compensation, violation, or
    neutralization of the meter. Grouping may be either backward or forward. UNIT: Beat is the unit
    of stress, meter, and performance. STRUCTURE: Systematic hierarchical ordering of units. The
    "foot" serves as the unit of both stress and meter; above it is the line. Normal
    stress-placement in meter creates a stress-maximum; stress-displacement to the left creates a
    stress-valley, to the right a stress-grade. STYLE: At the highest level, convergent or
    divergent. A large number of specific types of metrical variations may be graded on both
    quantitative and qualitative scales in order to define, describe, and weigh features of style.
    Chapters treat Metricality, Caesura, Iambic/Trochaic and Ternary meters, Rhythmical Performance,
    Perception of Poetic Rhythm [perhaps the core of the book], Perceptual Forces on meter, syntax,
    and sense, Converg- ent/Divergent Patterns, and the Stanza. A long Epilogue appraises the
    problem of critical estimation of metrical style. The general structure of the entire argument
    is set forth in a twenty-page prefatory Synopsis. Much more is treated in the text, of course,
    and in fact the theory goes far beyond the Halle- Keyser framework (Tsur manages to put
    considerable distance between himself and them in chapter 1). Section 8 on Performance is
    especially stimulating. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E811">
   <bib>Valesio, Paolo. "On Poetics and Metrical Theory." Poetics 2 (1971): 36-70. </bib>
   <notes> "The theory of generative phonology does not need to modify its distinction of two levels
    in order to accommodate metrical structures, but . . . accommo- dations are necessary, albeit in
    a different direction, if the theory has to give a systematic account of metrical structures. .
    . . The structure of the line is a phonologically mixed one." </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E812">
   <bib>Wedge, George F. "A Model for Generative Metrics." From Soundstream to Discourse. Ed.
    Daniel G. Hays and D. M. Lance. Columbia: University of Missouri, 1972. pp. 142-47. </bib>
   <notes> Generative metrics must establish a definition for the line ("if we are to discover how
    we intuit that a given line is metrical, we must first discover how we intuit that a line is a
    line") and also must clarify its notion of "major syntactic boundary." Line-end may be generated
    from caesura and the metered line therefore built up from syntax. E813 Wilson, Peter. "Reading a
    Poem Metrically: A Discussion of the Practical Implications of Using the Halle-Keyser System."
    Language and Style 12 (1979): 146-57. Taking Halle-Keyser as "the most cogent system available,"
    the author tinkers a bit with the stress assignment rules then discovers via application that
    the correlation between stress-maximum actualization and complexity-score is actually inverse
    even when an improved treatment of stress neutralization is included. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E814">
   <bib>Wimsatt, W. K. Jr. "The Rule and the Norm: Halle and Keyser on Chaucer's Meter." College
    English 31 (1970): 774-88; rpt in Literary Style: A Symposium. Ed. Seymour Chatman. New York:
    Oxford University Press, 1971. pp. 197- 215. </bib>
   <notes> Discussion follows, pp. 215-20. The response of a distinguished Traditional prosodist to
    the generative theory. Wimsatt approves of the abstract concept of "position," objects to the
    negativeness of the definition of "stress maximum," and questions its entire validity by
    observing that the iambic pentameter has traditionally been defined precisely by its five
    stress-units. Several invented examples serve as "a challenge to the notion that a sweeping
    negative rule (plus a merely optional rule about major positive features) will render certain
    minor positive features irrelevant to a definition of a meter." The Halle-Keyser rules give
    description of metrical complications in the iambic pentameter line but not explanations how or
    why these particular complications should exist (and not others). Wimsatt adopts the
    (Structural) position that the meter alters or adjusts the mid-range stresses in speech. But
    "rules of language do not include rules of meter. The meter . . . is something that the poet
    adds to the linguistic givens, without contravening them." Finally, Wimsatt urges the
    recognition of a difference between the rule (the outer limits of legitimacy) and the norm (the
    varying, average, inner realization). </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E815">
   <bib>Youmans, Gilbert. "Test Case for a Metrical Theory: "La Belle Dame Sans Merci." Language
    and Style 7 (1974): 283-305. </bib>
   <notes> An argument that Halle and Keyser's optional rules Conditions 1 and 2 are in fact
    constrained and need amplification. In a discussion of the excessive accomodation of the theory,
    Youmans insists on the importance of a stress- maximum in position 10--"There is probably no
    need to restrict the definition of the stress maximum to a single line of verse." The analysis
    of two versions of the Keats poem allows stylistic comparison, and Youmans proposes "a balance
    principle" in "our perception of meter" as an addition to the Halle- Keyser system. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E816">
   <bib>Zbozny, Frank T. "The Metrical Structure of Chaucer's ABC." DAI 31 (1970): 2359A
    (Pittsburgh). </bib>
   <notes> The Halle-Keyser metrical theory is a superior analytical treatment to those of Schipper
    (A11) and Southworth (K367). The unusual line-initial stresses in this poem seem to "illuminate
    the abecedarian structure of the poem aurally." See also E67, E89-90, E721, E820-21, E1375,
    E1386, E1494, I11, J192, K137, K234, L19, L141, L320, L1093, L1129, L1158, L1196, L1203, L1301,
    L1508-9, L1536, L1687. ii: Magnuson-Ryder </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E817">
   <bib>Bjorklund, Beth. "Elements of Poetic Rhythm: Stress, Syllabicity, Sound, and Sense."
    Poetics n.s. 8 (1979): 351-65. </bib>
   <notes> Synopsis of and addenda to the author's monograph (next entry) on the functions of
    syllabicity in meter: disyllables are "meter-fixing," whereas monosyllables are "meter-fixed."
    Since German is a highly polysyllabic language in comparison with English, it lends itself well
    to ternary meters, whereas English, originally and still heavily monosyllabic, naturally
    generates binary meters. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E818">
   <bib>-----. A Study in Comparative Prosody: English and German Jambic Pentameter. Stuttgarter
    Arbeiten zur Germanistik, no. 35. Stuttgart: Akademischer Verlag Hans-Dieter Heinz, 1978. 494
    pp. Based on her dissertation, DAI 36 (1976): 7383A. </bib>
   <notes> This very substantial treatise examines the similarities and differences in English and
    German verse by applying the Magnuson-Ryder (E819-21) framework, as well as American Structural
    and Russian Formalist theories. The author observes the facts that English verse differs from
    German in that it has dropped unstressed syllables, resulting in the occurrence of contiguous
    (stressed) lexical stems in the verse, while German on the other hand, preserving its wider
    inflectional system, has preserved unstressed syllables between lexical stems, which "thus
    allows for a closer approximation to the metrical scheme." Thus English verse has a higher
    degree of apparent irregularity or "freedom." And in contrast to these two languages, Russian
    has "such a highly developed inflectional system and consequently such a high degree of
    poly-syllabicity that it does not allow for the occurrence of stress on alternate syllables."
    The general assumption throughout the work is that the possibilities of metrical form "appear to
    be connected more with the distributional properties of the language itself than with
    constraints specifically of prosody." Perhaps this will turn out to be one of the axioms of
    comparative metrics. Too, the whole area of the relation of meter and morphology, explored here
    by Bjorklund, has been ignored traditionally and deserves further, more systematic
    investigation. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E819">
   <bib>Magnuson, Karl. "Rules and Observations in Prosody: Positional Level and Base." Poetics 12
    (1974): 143-54. </bib>
   <notes> A re-view, in an effort to support the Magnusen-Ryder theory's adequacy of
    generalization. No conclusion. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E820">
   <bib>Magnuson, Karl, and Frank G. Ryder. "Second Thoughts on English Prosody." College English
    33 (1971): 198-216. </bib>
   <notes> In the second round, the authors conclude that all the various amendments to the original
    Halle-Keyser theory have "generally weakened" it. The article is a detailed comparison of the
    two competing generative theories, with long side glances at Jesperson, Wimsatt, and Beaver.
    Magnuson and Ryder state their own assumptions explicitly on p. 206. It is fair to say that so
    far their approach has been considered unfruitful by most metrists. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E821">
   <bib>-----. "The Study of English Prosody: An Alternative Proposal." College English 31 (1970):
    789-820. </bib>
   <notes> The second generative theory advanced. The authors criticize Halle and Keyser for
    inadequate and imprecise categories and "procedural incongruities," citing work on Shakespearean
    Sonnets which confounds the theory. They attack the aim of Halle-Keyser prosody (sorting
    metrical from unmetrical lines) on the grounds that since all lines imperfectly fulfill the
    abstract pattern, a heirarchy or gradient of metricality is what is needed. Finally they
    reiterate that the theory accepts too much. The Magnuson-Ryder theory proposes a metrical grid
    of ten slots, five Even, five Odd; features marked are Word-Onset, Weak, Strong and Pre-Strong.
    Of these latter, there are sixteen possible combinations. Then a set of Base Rules states the
    relations between metrical slots. See also: E721, E741-42, E749, E755, E776, E778, E791, E814,
    E824, L320. iii: Kiparsky </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E822">
   <bib>Barnes, Mervin, and H. Esau. "English Prosody Reconsidered." Language and Style 11 (1978):
    212-22. </bib>
   <notes> A revised version of </notes>
  </item>


  <item id="E823">
   <bib>-----. "Generative Approaches to English Prosody: Assessment and Outlook." The Fourth LACUS
    Forum, 1977. Ed. Michel Paradis. Columbia, S. C.: Hornbeam, 1978. pp. 469-83. </bib>
   <notes> A criticism of Kiparsky's first theory (E827) on both general and specific grounds.
    Generally, (1) his system finally reduces itself to his "monosyllable constraint," whereby "the
    metricality of a line of poetry depends solely on whether or not the odd positions--if they are
    stressed--are filled with monosyllabic words"; (2) a metrical theory based on the line as unit
    and on the counting of its syllables cannot very well distinguish iambic from trochaic.
    Specifically, (1) Kiparsky's rules are too narrow to be borne out in the corpus of English
    verse; (2) they are also too accomodating in other respects, admitting unmetrical lines; (3)
    they are "not explanatory of English metrical practices but rather give only a superficial
    description of the syntax"; and (4) his "prosodic rule," by grading out all stresses but
    primary, ignores metrically relevant secondary stresses. Note too the important recognition made
    on p. 219. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E824">
   <bib>Chisholm, David. "Generative Prosody and English Verse." Poetics n.s. 6 (1977): 111-53. </bib>
   <notes> At once both a formidable and extended critique of Kiparsky (E827) and also an
    affirmation and modification of Magnuson-Ryder. Chisholm cites "serious flaws" in Kiparsky's
    theory, such as unacceptably weak constraints (e.g., an imprecise classification in the
    Monosyllable Constraint) and the use of four levels of metrical stresses instead of the
    customary two. But worst is Kiparsky's double-headed "failure to distinguish the three separate
    domains of music, meter, and language. On the one hand he equates musical rhythm with poetic
    meter; on the other he confuses meter with language . . . [since] his notation for the
    underlying metrical pattern consists of integers which designate stress- levels in the language.
    . . . Above all, the Kiparsky theory fails to specify precisely . . . all the categories with
    which it operates." In Chisholm's view the inadequacy of both Halle-Keyser and Kiparsky is their
    failure to postulate "an intermediate level of abstraction," the Prosodic, between the (surface)
    Linguistic and the (deep) Metrical. He then sets forth his modifications of Maguson-Ryder based
    on the work in L319-21. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E825">
   <bib>Dillon, George L. "Kames and Kiparsky on Syntactic Boundaries." Language and Style 10
    (1977): 16-22. </bib>
   <notes> Finds striking similarity in the rules for pauses in syntax and the caesura in
    verse-lines in the work of Lord Kames (E566) and Kiparsky (E827). The rules state the syntactic
    "bonding force" between various constituents, or conversely the naturalness of pauses between
    these constituents. One rule of note is that inversion of syntactic elements will create pauses
    which were otherwise impermissible. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E826">
   <bib>Kiparsky, Paul. "The Rhythmic Structure of English Verse." Linguistic Inquiry 8 (1977):
    189-247. </bib>
   <notes> In a major strategic revision of his 1975 theory Kiparsky adapts the very recent work on
    phonological stress by Liberman (see Liberman and Prince, D83), the central feature of which is
    that stressing is derived and expressed via tree notation (as in transformational syntax)
    instead of by numbers. This procedure is adopted because it permits major simplifications in the
    design of the theory, but more importantly because "superficially identical stress patterns are
    differentiated in the Liberman notation in a way that point by point corresponds to distinctions
    in versification." The basic pattern for the iambic pentameter in its most neutral realization
    is established as STRESS METER /\ /\ /\ /\ /\ W S W S W S W S W S Of hand, of foot, of lip, of
    eye, of brow /\ /\ /\ /\ /\ W S W S W S W S W S The metrical complexity of the line, or the
    degree of its metricality, is then a function of the matching of these two trees. Mismatches may
    be either permissible or impermissible. Kiparsky's sole criterion for impermissible matching-
    -i.e. the one situation that will render a line unmetrical--is a lexical stress (S) over a
    metrical slack (W). That is, lexical stresses must always fall on metrical ictuses. Such
    vertical mismatches are termed labeling types; bracketing types (horizontal mismatches, as it
    were), e.g. STRESS METER /\ /\ /\ W S W S W S W or summer, winter, autumn /\ /\ /\ W S W S W S W
    [i.e. trochaic words in an iambic line], are also important determinants of metrical complexity.
    Inversion or foot-reversal Kiparsky explains handily by showing that "such a labeling mismatch
    never occurs together with a bracketing mismatch." Other aspects of the theory work out
    secondary stresses, syllabification and traditional elision, level stress, metrical idiolects,
    the iambic/trochaic dispute, extrametrical and missing syllables, the ordering of Metrical
    Rules, and stipulation of three Prosodic Rules. </notes>
  </item>



  <item id="E827">
   <bib>-----. "Stress, Syntax, and Meter." Language 51 (1975): 576-616. </bib>
   <notes> The first formal statement of the third theory of generative metrics to be proposed so
    far. Kiparsky criticises Halle and Keyser for failing to exclude non- verse and failing to
    distinguish a sufficient number of degrees of stress. His view of Magnuson and Ryder is that
    "their metrical rules are adhoc and do not lead to any explanations," revealing "a failure to
    draw the right distinctions between phonology and metrics." His own theory, claiming not only
    descriptive but also explanatory and predictive adequacy, defines meter as "a system of
    correspondences between musical and linguistic rhythm" (Kiparsky speaks also of "the musical
    rhythm that underlies verse," but this seems adventitious), admits four degrees of metrical
    stress (denoted by the numbers 1- 4, strongest to weakest) which correspond to the four degrees
    of stress in the language (though Kiparsky's actual examples betray this statement and reveal
    that his metrical levels are effectually binary), and takes account of word and phrase
    boundaries as well as patterning of stresses, on the argument that meter organizes not only
    phonological but also morphological and grammatical features as well. The system includes six
    components: Acual Phonological Representation The line itself. ^ | Prosodic Rules) Specify how
    the patterns are to ^ be mapped onto linguistic strings | (by defining what counts as a |
    "syllable," etc.), i.e. how | metrical positions may match | syllables. | Derived Metrical
    Patterns These "correspond to the ^ natural rhythm of speech." | | (Metrical Rules) ß
    ---------------- Metrical Tension Index ^ ^ | | | | | | These are two. MR1 states Gauges the
    difference between that only odd syllables in abstract and derived patterns the iambic
    pentameter line and orders the constraints are constrained. MR2 into hierarchies so as to states
    that stresses in rank stylistic variations in weak positions may occur poets and genres. only on
    monosyllables or ^ after intonation breaks. | ^ | | | Abstract Metrical Patterns | A small
    inventory. In the revised version of this theory (E826), Kiparsky admits many of its original
    inadequacies and takes a new, more profitable tack. See also the criticisms by Chisholm (E824)
    and Barnes and Esau (E822-23). See also: B117, E786, E795, E805, E809, L1464, L1510, L1542.
   </notes>
  </item>
 </chapter>
</bibliography>
