<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="">
        <item id="E828">
            <bib>Adams, Helen R. "The Prosody of Emily Dickinson." M. A. Thesis, University of
                Pennsylvania, 1932.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E829">
            <bib>Aiken, W. E. "Poetic Form in Conquistador." MLN 51 (1936): 107-9.</bib>
            <notes> MacLeish's 1932 poem show distinct characteristics of the Old English allitera-
                tive line. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E830">
            <bib>Boyer, Robert H. "Anglo-Saxon and Middle English Influences in the Poetry of W. H.
                Auden." DA 31 (1970): 1262A (Pennsylvania).</bib>
            <notes> Aside from influences on imagery, theme, and voice, Boyer notices Auden
                imitating Anglo-Saxon alliteration, stress patterns, and asyndetic syntax. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E831">
            <bib>Brooke-Rose, Christine. "Notes on the Metre of Auden's 'The Age of Anxiety.'"
                Essays in Criticism 13 (1963): 253-64.</bib>
            <notes> A recently discovered rare incunabulum antedating the two Atomic Wars has been
                subjected to Total Metrical Analysis; compared with the Anglo-Saxon Fragments
                preserved in the sub-Himalayan vaults, this poem shows much less skill in
                alliteration, both in faulty verse-types and in a wooden, repetitive style.
                Altogether the poet's use of alliteration seems self-conscious and forced, as if he
                were out of touch with the tradition or trying to imitate a moribund tradition
                rather than merely being incompetent. Too, his verse frequently falls into a
                "trim-pom-trim-pom" rhythm, varied by "pom-petty-pom," which seems to be evidence
                supporting the hypothesis recently advanced that there also existed a rhymed,
                syllabic verse-tradition in Old British poetry (none of which has survived, of
                course). Whether such a syllabic tradition was only beginning at this time, or
                whether it already existed and was influencing this poet's attempt at revival of an
                earlier form, we do not know. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E832">
            <bib>Coffman, Addie. "Emily Dickinson's Verse Forms and Techniques." M. A. Thesis,
                University of Wyoming, 1942.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E833">
            <bib>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor. "Preface" to Christabel. London. 1816. Rpt in Poetical
                Works. Ed. Ernest Hartley Coleridge. London: Oxford University Press, 1967. pp.
                213-15.</bib>
            <notes> Coleridge gives all the appearances of genuinely believing that his four-stress
                Accentual meter was "founded on a new principle: namely, that of counting in each
                line the accents, not the syllables. Though the latter may vary from seven to
                twelve, yet in each line the accents will be found to be only four." See E843, E845,
                and E851. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E834">
            <bib>Doyle, Esther. "The Nature of Verse in Drama, with Special Reference to J. B., a
                play in verse by Archibald MacLeish." DA 25 (1964): 4299A (Northwestern).</bib>
            <notes> Argues that the play is written in a four-stress line. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E835">
            <bib>Howarth, R. G. "Yeats's 'My Own Music.'" Notes and Queries 189 (1945): 167- 68;
                190 (1946): 175.</bib>
            <notes> Yeats himself considered "The Lake Isle of Innisfree" his first poem with
                something of his own music in it, that rhythm being characterized especially by "a
                succession of stresses"; the comparison with Sprung Rhythm comes im- mediately to
                mind (see E919), and Howarth lists a number of antecedent po- ems in stress verse.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E836">
            <bib>Leiblein, Emil. Prinzipien und Verwundung des Stabreims in W. Morris' "Sigurd the
                Volsung" Diss., Würzburg, 1913. 102 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E837">
            <bib>Lightfoot, Marjorie J. "Purgatory and The Family Reunion: In Pursuit of Prosodic
                Description." Modern Drama 7 (1964): 256-66.</bib>
            <notes> Both plays are in stress verse, the norm being a four-stress line, with fairly
                regular syllable-count in both though more so in Yeats's, which may well have
                encouraged Eliot to tighten his own line in his next play The Cocktail Party.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E838">
            <bib>-----. "T. S. Eliot's The Cocktail Party: An Experiment in Prosodic Description."
                DA 25 (1965): 6630A (Northwestern).</bib>
            <notes> Application of a Temporalist theory of meter to this play (and others by Eliot)
                discloses that it is written in a four-stress line in triple time, this norm varied
                considerably by character and scene. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E839">
            <bib>-----. "The Uncommon Cocktail Party." Modern Drama 11 (1969): 382-95.</bib>
            <notes> A tediously overinflated essay which demonstrates, through comparison of the
                text of Eliot's play The Cocktail Party with a recording of a performance ap- proved
                by the author, that Eliot used a four-stress line. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E840">
            <bib>Lindberg-Seyersted, Brita. The Voice of the Poet: Aspects of Style in the Poetry
                of Emily Dickinson. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1968.</bib>
            <notes> The second chapter examines Diction, but the focus of our attention should rest
                on chapter 3, "Mighty Metres and Jingling Bells: A Poet's Prosody," a long
                examination of metrical theory (the author is extraordinarily well-informed on
                metrics since 1950), "meter and speech rhythm" (she goes so far in distin- guishing
                the two as to offer separate scansions for a given line), rhyme, and "graphic
                representations of sound and meaning." Accepting "intensity" (stress) as the basis
                of meter, the author adapts the notation system of La Drière (E570). ED's metric is
                found to derive from hymnody, her most frequent choice being Common Meter. This is
                probably the most rigorous technical treatment of ED's poetry in print. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E841">
            <bib>Matthews, William. "Alliterative Song of an Elizabethan Minstrel." Research
                Studies of the Washington State University 32 (1964): 134-46.</bib>
            <notes> Esp. pp. 142-46. The minstrel sang before Queen Elizabeth in 1575; the song
                shows heavy, unmistakable features of poetry in the high alliterative tradition.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E842">
            <bib>Niles, John D. "The Old Alliterative Verse Form as a Medium for Poetry." Mosaic 11
                (1978): 19-33.</bib>
            <notes> Surveys the best twentieth-century poems imitating the Old English meter and
                annexes a short excursus on the history of the Old Germanic verse tradition.
                Non-technical. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E843">
            <bib>Nitchie, Elizabeth. "Coleridge and Metre." Saturday Review of Literature 7 (1930):
                146.</bib>
            <notes> Upholds Coleridge's precedence in creating a new accentual rhythm in English
                poetry by suggesting that the Christabel-meter is very close to Sprung Rhythm.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E844">
            <bib>Otto, Lon J. "Medieval Prosody and Four Modern Poets: The Accentual Poetry of
                Hopkins, Hardy, Pound, and Auden." DAI 35 (1975): 4447A (Indiana).</bib>
            <notes> All four poets employ accentual meter "almost exclusively for subjects of major
                importance and seriousness" and also to express "a sense of directness, honesty, and
                personal engagement." Hopkins of course created an entire prosody out of
                overstressing. Hardy uses stress meters relatively little on the whole, yet they
                appear repeatedly in his most intensely expressive passages. Pound uses them both as
                archaisms and to convey a sense of tragedy, loneliness, and tersely emotional
                speech. Auden uses the Old English meter as a more formalized convention, its
                associated heroic themes thereby forming an ironic contrast to modern life. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E845">
            <bib>Patterson, Charles I. "An Unidentified Criticism by Coleridge Related to
                Christabel. PMLA 67 (1952): 973-88.</bib>
            <notes> See Whalley (E262). Discovery of Coleridge's review of Samuel Horsley's 1796
                work on Greek and Latin metrics (M104) provokes a full review of Coleridge's
                readings in and theorizing on metrics, given the prosodic ambience of the day. A
                surprising--very surprising--conclusion emerges: Patterson argues that Coleridge's
                metrical theory (he must have read Foster and Gally (M66-74) besides Horsley, in
                addition to his own classical training at school) was "quan- titative," though it
                recognized that accent in English "lengthens out" the time of the stressed syllable,
                so that the Christabel line is to measured by temporal regularity, each equal to all
                the rest in total time, and generally containing four stresses with isochronous
                intervals between them. In effect, then, Christabel was for Coleridge not
                stress-verse but timed verse (count of stress being of secondary importance), and
                his metrical theory was Temporal. The "foot" is to be discarded and the line taken
                as the metrical unit. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E846">
            <bib>Pierson, Robert M. "The Meter of 'The Listeners.'" English Studies 45 (1964):
                373-81.</bib>
            <notes> De La Mare's eerie poem seems to be written in four-(perhaps three-) stress
                verse, the even lines being much stricter than the odd, and the passages on the
                Traveller being metrically "wilder" than those on his Listeners. An intelligent and
                careful analysis raises interesting theoretical implications. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E847">
            <bib>Porter, David T. The Art of Emily Dickinson's Early Poetry. Cambridge: Harvard
                University Press, 1966.</bib>
            <notes> Chapter 4 examines the hymn meters which Dickinson so frequently used as a
                "constant occasion for irony," the implications in the meter of a simple pious faith
                standing as the backdrop to her wit, rebelliousness, skepticism, and exu- berance in
                word and thought. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E848">
            <bib>Ranta, Jerrald. "The Metrics of 'Rugby Chapel.'" Victorian Poetry 10 (1972): 333-
                49.</bib>
            <notes> The poem seens to be in stress verse, the metrical norm being a line of three
                stresses and from six to nine syllables, though possibly Arnold meant it to be an
                imitation of the Greek hexameter hemistich, the hemiepes. Nearly half the lines are
                of the form / x x / x x /, which Ranta considers a rising rhythm. There is some
                slight evidence for stanzaic patterns. But the poem is too loose to admit of any
                firm determinations. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E849">
            <bib>Read, Sir Herbert. "Basil Bunting: Music or Meaning." Agenda 4 (1966): 4-10.</bib>
            <notes> His verse is a reversion to the Anglo-Saxon metric. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E850">
            <bib>Severns, Carrol. "Emily Dickinson: Experiments in Metrical Variations." Emily
                Dickinson Bulletin 16-19 (1971): 139-47.</bib>
            <notes> A sophomoric essay which begins with the biographical fact that ED grew up with
                a close knowledge of hymnals, and hence of Common Meter, Long Meter, Short Meter,
                and the rest. Severns' view is that Dickinson's develop- ment as a poet lay in
                learning to mix these meters in one poem for blending of effects. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E851">
            <bib>Snell, Ada L. F. "The Meter of 'Christabel.'" The Fred Newton Scott Anniversary
                Papers. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1929, rpt 1968. pp. 93-115.</bib>
            <notes> An argument that the poem is actually written in an accentual-syllabic meter-- a
                fairly regular iambic tetrameter--with monosyllabic and anapestic substitu- tions.
                Snell also shows how variations in the texture of the meter correlate with thematic
                shifts, and she collects many of Coleridge's recorded remarks on meter. A nexus for
                arguments about the relationship between purely accentual and accentual-syllabic
                meters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E852">
            <bib>Sochatoff, A. Fred. "The Use of Verse in the Drama of T. S. Eliot." Carnagie
                Series in English, no. 2. Lectures on Some Modern Poets. Pittsburgh: Carnegie
                Institute of Technology Press, 1955. pp. 59-75.</bib>
            <notes> Examines Eliot's developing sense of verse as an adequate medium for drama, from
                Sweeney Agonistes and The Rock through Murder in the Cathedral (where he was
                dissatisfied with the choral and the prose passages) to the most flexible form he
                devised, the three-stress (with caesura) line of The Cocktail Party. No scansions,
                but solid perspective. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E853">
            <bib>Stamm, Edith P. "Emily Dickinson: Poetry and Punctuation." Saturday Review of
                Literature 46 (1963): 26-27, 74.</bib>
            <notes> Argues that some of the curious punctuation marks in the MSS are not varie- ties
                of dasshes but rather marks indicating how the poem is to be read, marks which were
                taken from the standard elocution and rhetoric manuals of the day. Cf. Wylder
                (E856). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E854">
            <bib>Webster, A. Blyth. "Translation from Old into Modern English." Essays and Studies
                5 (1914): 153-71.</bib>
            <notes> Translation of verse, that is. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E855">
            <bib>Woody, Lilian. "Masefield's Use of Dipodic Meter." PQ 10 (1931): 277-93.</bib>
            <notes> Employs the notation of Stewart (E333). In Masefield the appearance of the meter
                correlates fairly highly with poems on the theme of the sea; his stylistic traits
                are a frequent use of the metrical pause, variation of the seven-stress line with a
                six-stress line, very frequent dropping of unstressed syllables, caesuras, a line
                (wholly devoid of slacks) that seems to slip over into music and demand a musical
                scoring, expressive metrical irregularities, and (commonly) a four-line stanza. But
                the scansions and types given here seem so unsystematic as to call into question the
                validity of the description. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E856">
            <bib>Wylder, Edith P. "The Voice of the Poet: Selected Poems of Emily Dickinson with an
                Introduction to the Rhetorical Punctuation of the Manuscripts." DA 28 (1968): 4194A
                (New Mexico).</bib>
            <notes> "The four seemingly irregular notations appearing throughout the Dickinson
                manuscripts correspond exactly in form to the four basic inflectional symbols of
                nineteenth-century elocution" as outlined in Ebeneezer Porter's Rhetorical Reader,
                which ED read at the Amherst Academy. And "the capital l letter in Dickinson's line
                is the signal for strong stress." Cf. Stamm (E853). See also: B30, B178, B189, B207,
                C151, E282, E451, E453, E472, E773, E866, E1036, I3, J332. BALLAD AND HYMN METER,
                METRICAL PSALTERS To all outward appearances, the stress meter of English folk verse
                has remained un- changed for well over a milennium. Moreover, the three or four
                commonest ballad meters also happen to be the musical meters of many hymns and
                popular (secular) songs as well, and so command an extraordinary latitude. Such
                unexpected modal solidarity implies that our oldest and finest lyrics are, at least
                in one sense, indeed "all, all of a piece throughout." The best recent account of
                ballad meter is that given by Malof (E581), though George R. Stewart Jr. is still
                the authority on the subject; see his two books and numerous articles. Note too that
                many of the articles in Appendix C on the setting of verse to music are con- cerned
                with ballads; see especially Boswell's work. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E857">
            <bib>Ainsworth, E. G. "An Unrecorded Work by Christopher Smart." TLS, 15 October 1938,
                p. 661.</bib>
            <notes> Reports the discovery of the accompanying music for Smart's psalter. See W. F.
                Stead's letter, "Christopher Smart's Metrical Psalters," on 22 October, p. 677.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E858">
            <bib>Beckerlegge, Oliver A. "An Attempt at a Classification of Charles Wesley's Metres:
                A Contribution to the Study of English Prosody." London Quarterly Review 169 (1944):
                219-27.</bib>
            <notes> Catalogues 55 ballad meters used by Wesley in his hymns; apparently the man used
                more hymn meters than all the other hymn writers put together. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E859">
            <bib>Bett, Henry. "John Wesley's Translation of German Hymns in Reference to Metre and
                Rhyme." London Quarterly Review 165 (1940): 288-94.</bib>
            <notes> For the 33 hymns Wesley translated between 1737 and 1742, he used only 6 meters;
                the German originals used 29 meters in all. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E860">
            <bib>Brunner, Karl. "Zum Balladenrhythmus." Archiv 140 (1920): 259-61.</bib>
            <notes> Metrical analysis of "Sir Patrick Spens" and the Older Chevy Chase ballad in
                comparison with the later Chevy Chase version and Coleridge shows the "stateliness"
                of the folk ballad in contrast to the "shrillness" of the street ballads. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E861">
            <bib>Buchan, A. M. "Word and Word-Tune in Burns." SP 48 (1951): 40-48.</bib>
            <notes> Mainly on dialect, but p. 42 discusses the smoothing out of meter which Burns
                was able to achieve by the dropping of consonants. Why has no one defini- tively
                studied the relations of meter and morphology? </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E862">
            <bib>Byard, Herbert. "A Sternhold and Hopkins Puzzle." Musical Quarterly 56 (1970):
                221-29.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E863">
            <bib>Calendar, Carl E. "Metrical Translations of the Psalms in France and England:
                1530-1650." DAI 33 (1973): 6863A (Oregon).</bib>
            <notes> The metrical irregularities in the translations by Wyatt, Sidney, and Sandys are
                attributed to a desire to translate the structures of parallelism in the original
                Hebrew. Cf. Schmutzler (E888), Weir (E895), Huttar (E874), Lowell (E882), and Smith
                (E890). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E864">
            <bib>Coffin, Tristram P. "Remarks Preliminary to a Study of Ballad Meter and Ballad
                Singing." Journal of American Folklore 78 (1965): 149-53.</bib>
            <notes> A full counterweight to Bronson (N16); Coffin argues vigorously that the bal-
                lad originated in Anglo-Saxon alliterative verse and in "recited narrative obitu-
                ary verse" not in singing; the influence of music (and the device of end- rhyme) was
                only felt by the ballad later. This fact, that the ur-ballads were "more dependent
                upon linguistic than musical principles for their metrical form" can be further
                borne out by noticing that ballads are still set as stress verse, so that "not
                counting the unstressed syllables offers an area for extempo- rization in singing or
                reciting." An analogous situation appears in modern jazz. The ballad is, in short,
                verse before it is song. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E865">
            <bib>Crawford, Richard. "Watts for Singing: Metrical Poetry in American Sacred
                Tunebooks, 1761-1785." Early American Literature 11 (1976): 39-46.</bib>
            <notes> Literary and publishing history of early American psalters and hymnbooks.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E866">
            <bib>Franke, Wilhelm. Der Stil in den epischen Dichtungen Walter Scotts. Diss., Berlin,
                1909. 128 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Metrik," pp. 58-73, and "Alliteration," pp. 112-13. Franke's inventory covers a
                plethora of familial forms of meters, stanzas, rhyme-schemes, and alliterations,
                since Scott wrote in ballad meter, loose four-stress verse, even looser accentual
                meters, short couplets, and stricter forms such as the Spenserian. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E867">
            <bib>Freer, [Wilbert] Coburn. "The Countess of Pembroke in a World of Words." Style 5
                (1971): 37-56.</bib>
            <notes> Though she was only marginally competent, inventive, and graceful at versi-
                fying, Mary Herbert (Countess of Pembroke) managed 71 stanza-forms in 107 metrical
                Psalms, no two of them having both identical stanza and meter. But though we may
                admire her attention to formal variety as an end in itself, her meters (and sense)
                are shuffling, stumbling, even lame, especially in her revi- sions of her brother's
                (Sidney's) psalms. This essay is a companion to Freer on Sidney (E869). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E868">
            <bib>-----. Music for a King: George Herbert's Style and the Metrical Psalms.
                Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1972.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation, DA 29 (1968): 869A (Washington). Essential reading
                for the history of versification in the seventeenth century. Freer charts out
                contiguities between the lyrics of The Temple and the old, established metrical
                forms of the Psalter (Psalms), demonstrating carefully the metrical styles of some
                of Herbert's Renaissance predecessors (esp. Wyatt and Sidney) as foils to Herbert's
                own craft and purpose (Chapters 3 and 4). Since the chief feature of all the
                Psalters was the uniform wretchedness of their verse, and since Herbert's own craft
                was subtle and complex, Freer's conclusion about Herbert's motices (religious and
                personal) and achievement (in the han- dling of his prosodic materials) is also,
                appropriately and subtly, complex. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E869">
            <bib>-----. "The Style of Sidney's Psalms." Language and Style. 2 (1969): 63-78.</bib>
            <notes> Freer shows how Sidney expanded the range of his expressiveness immensely, in
                his psalms, by learning to control enjambement, feminine rhyme, and syn- tax, while
                varying his metrical and stanza forms, until he had become a poet who "[thought]
                through and by means of his forms. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E870">
            <bib>Gummere, Francis B., ed. "Metre, Style, and Form." Appendix 2 of Old English
                Ballads. Boston: Ginn and Company, 1894. pp. 303-9.</bib>
            <notes> The only essential characteristics of ballad meter are stanza and rhyme;
                allitera- tion is merely an ornament. Gummere catalogues the metrical types, finding
                the "general movement" of the meter to be iambic, and notes that the tradi- tional
                explanations of origin--the septenarius of Church Latin hymns and the old native
                alliterative meter--are scarecely tenable either chronologically or formally.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E871">
            <bib>Hendren, J[oseph] W. A Study of Ballad Rhythm, with special reference to ballad
                music. Princeton Studies in English, no. 14. Princeton: Princeton University Press,
                1936. 177 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation at Princeton in 1934. Rev: in Anglia Beiblatt 48
                (1937): 131-33; in MLN 53 (1938): 618-19; in JEGP 37 (1938): 584-85; in Journal of
                American Folklore 52 (1939): 324-25. Hendren is still the standard and most
                comprehensive sourse available on the subject. His general method is to examine "the
                rhythm of ballad poetry by studying it primarily as a element of folk-song"; in
                other words, he conceives of metrical language as simply one of the elements in [and
                not, alternatively, a correlate to] the larger rhythmical framework of the music.
                Consequently he applies the musical notation system to verse as well, following the
                earlier Mu- sical metrists Thompson (E404) and Croll (E344). Like Lanier (E364), but
                un- like Omond (E310), Hendren thinks that the temporal basis of verse is triple
                time, not duple. The bulk of the study is organized by the ballad meters (Common
                Meter, Long Meter) and stanza-patterns. See Hendren's later monograph at E356.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E872">
            <bib>Hodgart, Matthew J. C. The Ballads. London: Hutchinson's University Library, 1950;
                2nd ed. 1962.</bib>
            <notes> Chapter 3, "The Music of the Ballads," gives a useful discussion of ballad
                tunes, ballad meters, musical modes, and stanza forms. Scansions are expressed in
                the musical system. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E873">
            <bib>Holland, John. The Psalmists of Britain: Records, Biographical and Literary, of
                Upwards of 150 Authors Who Have Rendered the Whole or Parts of The Book of Psalms
                into English Verse. 2 vols. London: R. Groombridge, 1843.</bib>
            <notes> See section 7 of the Introduction, "Metrical Versions," pp. 41-61, for notes on
                early- and pre-Renaissance MSS of psalters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E874">
            <bib>Huttar, Charles A. "English Metrical Paraphrases of the Psalms, 1500-1640." DA 17
                (1957): 631A (Northwestern).</bib>
            <notes> Part II gives attention to metrics. The psalms of the literary writers are
                scarcely superior to those of the religious writers, and "both their meter and their
                dic- tion are generally bad." A number of meters, including quantitative, were at-
                tempted. Useful Appendices. Cf. Calendar (E863), Schmutzler (E888), Weir (E895),
                Lowell (E882), and Smith (E890). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E875">
            <bib>Illing, R. "The Literary and Musical Evolution of the English Metrical Psalter
                1562 and the Scottish Metrical Psalter 1564." Australian Universities Language and
                Literature Association: Proceedings of the Thirteenth Congress. Ed. J. R. Ellis.
                Melbourne: AULLA, 1970. pp. 386-88 (Synopsis).</bib>
            <notes> Reports a complete photocopy collection at Flinders University. Praises very
                highly the 1889 essay by H. W. Wooldridge printed as an appendix to Grove's
                Dictionary of Music and Musicians. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E876">
            <bib>Julian, John. A Dictionary of Hymnology. 2nd rev. ed. London: John Murray, 1907;
                rpt New York: Dover Publications, 1957.</bib>
            <notes> S. v. "Psalters, English." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E877">
            <bib>Kupke, Lothar. Erscheinungsformen und Funktionen des Achtergewichts in der
                englisch- schottischen Volksballade. Frankfurt on Main, Bern, and Las Vegas: Peter
                Lang, 1977.</bib>
            <notes> This is mainly a study of the partitioning of ballad narratives into dramatic
                scenes, of which Kupke says there are generally three; originally there were five,
                but compression of the final three into one produced the "end- weighting" or
                climactic form that is so characteristic of the ballad. The con- clusion must be
                prepared for, hence thematically there is a steady heightening throughout the three
                scenes, while rhythmically there is usually a falling-off or dimunition in the
                second part as a brief respite before the end, though of course both dimensions are
                proceeding simultaneously. The tripartite structure was termed by Axel Olrik an
                "Epic Law." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E878">
            <bib>Laws, G. Malcolm, Jr. "Broadside Ballad Forms and Variants." American Balladry
                from British Broadsides. Publications of the American Folklore Society,
                Bibliographical and Special Series, vol. 8. Philadelphia: American Folklore Society,
                1957. pp. 84-122.</bib>
            <notes> Laws seems oblivious to the distinction between stress verse and foot verse; he
                believes the broadsides to be in iambic tetrameters and trimeters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E879">
            <bib>Leach, MacEdward, ed. "Introduction: Reading of Ballads: Ballad Meter." The Ballad
                Book. New York: Harper &amp; Brothers, 1955. pp. 23-27.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E880">
            <bib>Livingston, Neil, ed. The Scottish Metrical Psalter of A. D. 1635. Glasgow,
                1864.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E881">
            <bib>Lovegrove, Glenda S. "Introduction to Hymn Meter and the Development of Prosodic
                Regularity in Sixteenth-Century Poetry." Diss., Harvard University, 1974.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E882">
            <bib>Lowell, Virginia M. "English Metrical Paraphrases of the Bible, 1549-1696." Diss.,
                University of Illinois, 1947.</bib>
            <notes> Cf. Calendar (E863), Huttar (E874), Schmutzler (E888), Weir (E895), and Smith
                (E890). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E883">
            <bib>Macmeeken, John W. History of the Scottish Metrical Psalms. Glasgow: McCulloch and
                Co., 1872.</bib>
            <notes> See Appendix 17, pp. 200-6, on "The Various Measures Used in the Old Psalter."
                Also the fine plates at the end. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E884">
            <bib>Mitsui, Töru. "Another Ballad Metre." Bungaku-Ronso (Literary Symposium) 29
                (1963?): 1-33.</bib>
            <notes> Criticizes G. R. Stewart (E892) for assuming that ballad meter is fundamen-
                tally a "four-foot dipodic line," that is, Long Meter, or the equivalent of 4/4 time
                in music; Mitsui thinks a significant number of the ballads are in 3/4 (tri- ple)
                time, or dactylic meter (i.e., the familiar ballad quatrain is actually dactylic
                tetrameter couplets). A troublesome essay, both structurally and conceptually; the
                scansions are especially obfuscatory. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E885">
            <bib>Moore, Verna L. "Psalmes, Teares, and Broken Music." Bulletin of the John Rylands
                Library 46 (1964): 411-28.</bib>
            <notes> Analysis of texts and music of the most popular Elizabethan songbooks of
                metrical psalms. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E886">
            <bib>Phillips, Charles S. Hymnody Past and Present. New York: Macmillan, 1937. 301
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Passim. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E887">
            <bib>Rohr-Sauer, Philipp Von. English Metrical Psalms From 1600 to 1660: A Study in the
                Religious and Aesthetic Tendencies of that Period. Diss., Freiburg, 1938. 128
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> No separate section on meter, but the close comparisons of the same Psalm in the
                hands of different writers, which form the body of the text, very frequently focus
                on versification. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E888">
            <bib>Schmutzler, Karl E. "George Sandys' Paraphrases on the Psalms and the Tradition of
                Metrical Psalmody: An Annotated Edition of Fifty Selected Psalms, with Critical and
                Biographical Introduction." DA 17 (1957): 1076A (Ohio State).</bib>
            <notes> Sandys' edition appeared in 1636 and therefore shows considerable variety of
                metrical forms and an accomplished smoothness of articulation not found in his many
                sixteenth-century predecessors. Cf. Calendar (E863), Weir (E895), Huttar (E874),
                Lowell (E882), and Smith (E890). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E889">
            <bib>Shelton, Edgar H. Versification and Hymnology. Frederick, Okla.: Enterprise Pub.
                Co., 1914. 39 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A primer emphasizing forty-six varieties of hymn meters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E890">
            <bib>Smith, Hallet. "English Metrical Psalms in the Sixteenth Century and Their
                Literary Significance." Huntington Library Quarterly 9 (1946): 249-71.</bib>
            <notes> Still unsurpassed as the best available introduction to the subject of metrical
                psalters. Smith surveys the general cultural context and the psalm-translations of
                Coverdale, Wyatt, Sternhold and Hopkins, Parker, and Sidney. Though the central
                Sternhold-Hopkins psalter seems to have had an important influence on stabilizing
                iambic meter in English, its verse is in Common Meter, chosen apparently as a
                mnemonic device. Cf. Calendar (E863), Huttar (E874), Lowell (E882), Schmutzler
                (E888), and Weir (E895). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E891">
            <bib>Stewart, George R., Jr. "The Meter of the Popular Ballad." PMLA 40 (1925): 933-
                62; rpt in The Critics and the Ballad. Ed. MacEdward Leach and T. P. Coffin.
                Carbondale: Southern Illinois University Press, 1963. pp. 161-85.</bib>
            <notes> Condensation and extension of the method developed in his first monograph (next
                entry), wherein Stewart argues that the metrical structure of ballad verse is not
                simply accentual but also (hierarchically so, i.e.) dipodic. Thus, the most common
                "septenary" form (otherwise known as Common Meter), has the form X / X \ X / X \ | X
                / X \ X / , the second most common being Long Meter in the four-stress a b c b
                quatrain. The dipodic foot need not always have only four syllables, however--it may
                range from two to six by employment of rests or by elision. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E892">
            <bib>-----. Modern Metrical Technique as Illustrated by Ballad Meter (1700-1920). New
                York: n.p., 1922. 120 pp.</bib>
            <notes> His dissertation. Rev: in Anglia Beiblatt 34 (1923): 232-35; in JEGP 23 (1924):
                308-16. An inquiry into the development of the most popular and prolific form of
                verse in English during the last two centuries, the stress verse of ballads. Stew-
                art devotes chapters to four varieties of metrical variation--(1) trisyllabic sub-
                stitutions, (2) monosyllabic feet, (3) metrical pause, and (4) dipodic verse. His
                metrical theory is Temporal, defining the foot as an approximately regular
                time-interval. His subject is delimited because "for the period under discussion
                metrical freedom began earlier and developed further in this form of verse than in
                any other. . . . The general course of metrical development in the past two
                centuries has been toward greater metrical variation. An accompaniment of this
                process has been the return of the native popular measures to literary us- age." Two
                preliminary chapters describe the standard form of ballad meter and its development
                before 1700. But two features of this study especially stand out: one is the chapter
                on Dipodic Verse; the other is one's realization here that the Temporal theory of
                meter is particularly suited to describing the structure of stress verse. See
                Stewart's later monograph at E333. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E893">
            <bib>Stopes, Mrs. Charlotte C. "The Metrical Psalms and 'The Court of Venus.'" The
                Athenaeum, 24 June 1899, pp. 784-86.</bib>
            <notes> Some important close research here on the early history of the metrical psalms
                in England. There was an early collection of (bawdy?) secular ballads, no copy of
                which survives, called The Court of Venus, which apparently was rewritten by some of
                the early religious reformers into a more virtuous form, two frag- ments of which
                survive; it is this "reformed" version that may represent the crucial transitional
                stage in the writing of the Psalms in ballad meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E894">
            <bib>Truron, Walterus [Biship of Truro]. "The Rhythm of Metrical Psalm-Tunes." Music
                &amp; Letters 9 (1928): 29-33.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E895">
            <bib>Weir, Richard B. "Thomas Sternhold and the Beginnings of English Metrical
                Psalmody." DAI 35 (1975): 7275A (N.Y.U.).</bib>
            <notes> His metrical paraphrases of the psalms are written in ballad form, based on the
                old tunes Sternhold knew, and should be judged more as "ballads with music" intended
                as free adaptations of the originals than as pure poetry intended as lit- eral or
                faithful translations. Cf. Calendar (E863), Schmutzler (E888), Huttar (E874), Lowell
                (E882), and Smith (E890). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E896">
            <bib>Wither, George. A Preparation to the Psalter. London: Nicholas Oakes, 1619; rpt
                Manchester: "For the Spenser Society," 1884.</bib>
            <notes> In chapter 2 (section 4) and in chapter 9, Wither defends the propriety of
                translating the Holy Word into verse, and more specifically into a "variety of
                Numbers," on the grounds that the original Hebrew is indeed verse, even though not
                of the sort found in Greek and Latin poetry, and not in such pen- tameters or
                hexameters as are familiar to us (though if the lines seem syllabi- cally unequal,
                he reasons, doubtless the original proununciation would not have made them so), and
                on the grounds that the Hebrew does indeed Rhyme, as the Church Fathers have told
                us. And since "the Hebrews are full of variety in their Numbers, and take great
                liberty in their Verses," and since the subjects of the Psalms themselves are also
                various, it is therefore fitting that they be translated into "many kinds of Verse."
                In short, Wither believes that the Hebrew original has isosyllabism and rhyme, these
                two being sufficent cri- teria to make it "verse." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E897">
            <bib>Woodford, Samuel. A Paraphrase Upon the Canticles, and some Select Hymns of the
                New and Old Testament, With other occasional Compositions in English Verse. London,
                1679.</bib>
            <notes> In the Preface Woodford gropes through an opaceous argument for the ad- mission
                of trisyllabic feet into duple meters (especially in blank verse) as a sur- rogate,
                in the modern languages, for "Rhythm"--i.e. Rhyme, Woodford con- flating and
                confounding the two terms by false etymology throughout. Most of the unstated
                assumptions (hence definition of terms) here are derived from contemporary
                conceptions of the (quantitative) meter of Hebrew verse; see Baroway (L1596-1600).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E898">
            <bib>Young, Thomas. The Metrical Psalms and Paraphrases. London: A. &amp; C. Black,
                1909.</bib>
            <notes> A simplified introduction to the Scottish psalter, with a useful history of the
                English and French versions as well, from the original translation by Cover- dale,
                through the standard edition by Sternhold and Hopkins (1548), the Old Scottish
                Psalter, up to the present Authorized Psalter based on the texts (1641- 1650) by
                Francis Rous. See also: C167, C233, E274, E276, E344, E581, E772, E981, E1211, G5,
                G6, G32, G34, K216, L19, L44, L924, N4, N6-10, N14, N16-17, N44, N56, N71, N104,
                N137-38. SPRUNG RHYTHM The novel theory of Sprung Rhythm developed by Gerard Manley
                Hopkins in the 1870's has not yet been fully assayed by metrists, though we have
                begun to sift what Hopkins thought he was doing and said he was doing from what he
                actually did, which is the essential preliminary. Sprung Rhythm means stress meter
                no syllable-counting meter, and ultimately the theory pivots on precisely that
                phenomenon which will unhinge or un- spring the normal accentual-syllabic (i.e.
                alternating-stress) meter in English, contiguous strong stresses. The interested
                student must be willing to tackle the whole subject entire, for Hopkins' own
                statements are not in themselves entirely reliable. But he critical commentary here
                is not yet so voluminous as to be intimidating, as it is elsewhere in metrics.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E899">
            <bib>Abbott, Claude Colleer, ed. Further Letters of Gerard Manley Hopkins, including
                his Correspondence with Coventry Patmore. London: Oxford University Press,
                1938;</bib>
            <notes> 2nd ed. "revised and enlarged," 1956. It is the sequence of letters to and from
                Coventry Patmore that is of interest, but see also s.v. "Versification" in the
                Index. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E900">
            <bib>-----. The Letters of Gerard Manley Hopkins to Robert Bridges. 2 vols. Vol. 2
                titled The Correspondence of Gerard Manley Hopkins and Richard Watson Dixon. London:
                Oxford University Press, 1935;</bib>
            <notes> rpt 1955. The letters touching on matters of versification are too numerous to
                cite. It is difficult to imagine that the student would not be interested in reading
                the letters entire, but if time is at a premium see s.v. "Versification" in the
                Index at the end of volume 2. Also "Music," "Milton," "Hopkins, Gerard Manley, As a
                Poet," and "Bridges, Robert, As a Prosodist." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E901">
            <bib>Baum, Paull F. "Sprung Rhythm." PMLA 74 (1959): 418-25.</bib>
            <notes> If, a century ago, a brilliant young student [Hopkins], his brain afire with an
                intoxicating new approach to poetry, had written out his theses and taken them to
                the Professor of Poetry [Saintsbury, Baum, anyone with the requisite ossification of
                metaphysics] for a review, he would have received in answer a version of this essay:
                "As exposition [young man,] this is disappointing. . . . I shall try to translate
                some of [your] picturesque language . . . into the conven- tional terms in ordinary
                writings on prosody . . . it still seems best to deal pa- tiently with [you], if
                only because [you are] an impetuous novice in prosody, too impatient to think [your]
                theories through before [you begin] to explain them." In any event, such is
                precisely what Hopkins receives here. Baum con- siders Sprung Rhythm "not a form of
                verse, to be scanned by feet, but a form of Prose Rhythm not amenable to scansion
                and therefore not to be explained as verse." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E902">
            <bib>Bonn, John., S. J. "Greco-Roman Verse Theory and Gerard Manley Hopkins." Immortal
                Diamond: Studies in Gerard Manley Hopkins. Ed. Norman Weyand. London: Sheed &amp;
                Ward, 1949. pp. 73-92.</bib>
            <notes> Hopkins' theoretical studies in Greek metric were undertaken after his own
                creative work had been accomplished, in the main, and they bear little relation to
                his actual practice, which is Anglo-Saxon in nature and not at all like Greek. In
                fact, Hopkins' understanding of Greek metric was by and large sim- ply mistaken, as
                was that of most of the authorities of the day whom Hopkins read. (He was also led
                astray by his penchants for music and mathe-matics.) But here we may observe the
                remarkable aesthetic phenomenon of a false the- ory yielding excellent results in
                practice--even an entirely new form--by a fer- tile misapprehension. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E903">
            <bib>Bowers, Robert O. "Hopkins and Welsh Prosody." Renascence 8 (1955): 71-74,
                87.</bib>
            <notes> Far from discovering and adopting his alliterative techniques from his study of
                Welsh, Hopkins, who was by nature given to a poetic vision of "complex im- mediacy,"
                a vocabulary of multiple perceptions," and "the peculiar impression of a single
                complex stroke of poetry rather than a sequential utterance," devel- oped these
                features in his own early alliterative experiments and only later found their
                "counterparts," a more fully developed system, in the Welsh cyng- hanedd. Cf. E907,
                E910, E911, E920, and E924. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E904">
            <bib>Cohen, Selma J. "The Poetic Theory of Gerard Manley Hopkins." PQ 26 (1947):
                1-20.</bib>
            <notes> Also separately published as an offprint. Based on her dissertation at Chicago
                in 1947. The essay concerns the religious foundations of Hopkin's aesthetic. Sprung
                Rhythm (discussed on pp. 12-20) is the perfect embodiment of that aesthetic because
                it provides, at once, naturalness (the rhythms of speech), regularity (in
                stressing), and variation. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E905">
            <bib>Donoghue, Denis. "Technique in Hopkins." Studies 44 (1955): 446-56.</bib>
            <notes> A test of Donoghue's belief that poetry is most successful when meter and all
                other elements co-operate in creating sense, against the counter-theory (Ran- som,
                Hopkins at times) that meter provides merely an "independent phonetic pleasure," by
                undertaking to show that "when in Hopkins the internal [rhyme, alliteration, or
                lexical compounding] pattern is heavier than the sense pattern, there is grave risk
                of an uncreative distortion of the language." In short, Donoghue reacts to an
                unqualified admiration of Hopkins' technique by trying to show that at times it
                falls short of or overreaches its mark, the perfect fusion of sound and sense.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E906">
            <bib>Etman, A. "Haunting Rhythm." Tijdschrift voor Taal en Letteren 27 (1939).</bib>
            <notes> Not seen. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E907">
            <bib>Gardner, W. H. "G. Manley Hopkins as a Cywyddwr." Transactions of the Honorable
                Society of the Cymmrodorion, 1940, pp. 184-88.</bib>
            <notes> Discovery of a Cywydd written (badly) by Hopkins in the cynghanedd meter. Cf.
                E903, E910, E911, E920, and E924. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E908">
            <bib>-----. Gerard Manley Hopkins (1844-1889): A Study of Poetic Idiosyncrasy in
                Relation to Poetic Tradition. 2 vols. London: Martin Secker &amp; Warburg.</bib>
            <notes> Vol. 1, 1944; 2nd rev. ed. 1948. Vol. 2, 1949. See in vol. 2 chapters 2 and 3
                (on the influences and parallels in Greek and Latin, Welsh, Old English, and Modern
                English stress-verse) and Appendices A-E. Then see chapters 3 and 4 (on
                sonnet-structure (ten Types), and diction and syntax), and Appendices A-C in vol. 1.
                Chronologically the subjects of the chapters in vol. 2 precede those of the chapters
                in vol. 1. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E909">
            <bib>Ghiselin, Brewster. "Reading Sprung Rhythms." Poetry 70 (1947): 86-93.</bib>
            <notes> In short compass Mr. Ghiselin carefully dissects and diposes of Harold White-
                hall's argument (E947) that Hopkins' meter was actually dipodic rather than
                accentual. The counterargument rests on Hopkins' own remarks and a dem- onstration
                that a dipodic scansion distorts the lines. G. R. Stewart's scansion- markers (E333)
                are used. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E910">
            <bib>Gibson, Francis. "The Influence of Welsh Prosody on the Poetry of Hopkins." Xavier
                University Studies 6 (1967): 21-28.</bib>
            <notes> Emphasizes the influence as much as possible, citing examples in Hopkins of the
                four types of cynghanedd and of the three principal meters, englyn, cy- wydd, and
                awdl, besides other devices of syntax (dyfalu), alliteration, and rhyme. Cf. E903,
                E907, E911, E920, and E924. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E911">
            <bib>Griffith, Ll. Wyn. "The Welsh Influence [in Hopkins' Poetry]." New Verse, no. 14
                (1935), pp. 27-29.</bib>
            <notes> Admiring Hopkins' effective uses of compound words, compression, conso- nantal
                repetition, and overstressing, Griffith still reminds us that he did not employ the
                cynghanedd meter strictly. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E912">
            <bib>Healy, Sister M. Aquinas, R.S.M. "Milton and Hopkins." University of Toronto
                Quarterly 22 (1952): 18-25.</bib>
            <notes> Hopkins dispised Milton the man and had little to say of Milton the versifier as
                the greatest master of all time, ahead of his own age and still ahead of ours. Healy
                thinks Hopkins was "probably the first critic who thoroughly under- stood Milton's
                prosody." Near the end she also takes up Hopkins' extensive influence on Bridges'
                prosody and poetry. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E913">
            <bib>Heseltine, H. P. Unspeakable Stress: Some Aspects of the Poetry of Gerard Manley
                Hopkins. Sydney: English Association, 1969. 23 pp.</bib>
            <notes> In search of a fully satisfying rationale for Sprung Rhythm, the author rejects
                the polar critical assessments of irrelevance (F. R. Leavis) and also obscurity or
                artificiality (A. D. Hope), finding the motivation for the technical devices in
                Hopkins' desire to "weave into [the poem] the very quality of his own sensi- bility
                without formally appearing to do so . . . . the unremitting vividness and intensity
                of [the poem's] auditory organization . . . works to tell us how truly hearfelt the
                poem is. . . .[and provides the nexus between the self and the world." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E914">
            <bib>Holloway, Sister Marcella M. The Prosodic Theory of Gerard Manley Hopkins.
                Washington, D.C.: Catholic University of America Press, 1947. 117 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Her dissertation at C.U.A., in 1947. Rev: in MLR 43 (1948): 534-35; in MLN 64
                (1949): 200-1. Still the fullest study of Sprung Rhythm available in English, though
                cf. Ludwig (E925). H. argues that criticism of Hopkins' theory of Sprung
                Rhythm--considered purely as a theory--has always been unfavorable because critics:
                (1) rely on his "Author's Preface" to his Poems, which is unsatisfactory in many
                ways, being more an explanation of his own practice than a general theory, (2) have
                judged his theory by his practice (H. explicates the theory from the surviving
                letters and documents), and (3) give undue attention to features relatively minor in
                the context of the whole theory, such as scansion. Beyond this she does not
                go--giving an effect similar to a translation of a Rus- sian text into French for an
                English reader: we are one step closer, but not en- tirely home. See esp. chapters 3
                and 4. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E915">
            <bib>Hopkins, Gerard Manley. "Author's Preface." Poems of Gerard Manley Hopkins now
                first published. Edited with notes by Robert Bridges. London: Oxford University
                Press, 1918;</bib>
            <notes> 3rd ed. "enlarged and edited with notes and a biographical introduction by W. H.
                Gardner," 1948; 4th ed. 1967; rpt 1970. Hopkins' six-page preface summarizes the
                principal concepts of his theory, Running Rhythm and Sprung Rhythm. It has not been
                entirely favorably re- ceived by metrists as representing an accurate account of his
                practice, but it unquestionably represents an accurate account of his own conception
                of his practice. See chapter 5 or Holloway (E914). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E916">
            <bib>House, Humphry, Ed. The Note-Books and Papers of Gerard Manley Hopkins, edited
                with notes. London &amp; New York: Oxford University Press, 1937;</bib>
            <notes> 2nd ed. completed by Graham Storey as </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E917">
            <bib>The Journals and Papers of Gerard Manley Hopkins. London: Oxford University Press,
                1959.</bib>
            <notes> See esp. the Lecture Notes: Rhetoric and s.v. "Poetry, Verse, Versification" in
                the last Index of both editions; also the "Philological Notes" in Appendix III of
                the second. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E918">
            <bib>Howarth, R. G. "An Unconscious Prophet of Hopkins [Edwin Guest]." Notes and
                Queries 204 (1959): 443-44.</bib>
            <notes> Notices a striking similarity between Guest's idea that the old native stress
                meters were worthy of further development and would reappear, and Hop- kins' theory
                and practice of Sprung Rhythm. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E919">
            <bib>-----. "Yeats and Hopkins." Notes and Queries 188 (1945): 202-4.</bib>
            <notes> When, in 1935, Yeats first began to read Hopkins for inclusion in the Oxford
                Book of Modern Verse, his recorded observations of Sprung Rhythm were to the effect
                that it was uncongenial to him; nevertheless, he essayed the meter in The Herne's
                Egg and (especially) in the late Purgatory. Cf. E835. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E920">
            <bib>Jones, Glyn. "Hopkins and Welsh Prosody." Life and Letters Today 21, no. 22
                (1939): 50-54.</bib>
            <notes> Hopkins' use of the Welsh meters is "capricious and faulty" but effective. Cf.
                E903, E907, E910, E911, and E924. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E921">
            <bib>Klotz, Rose M. "Verbal Counterpoint in the Poetry of Gerard Manely Hopkins." DA 27
                (1939): 50-54.</bib>
            <notes> Hopkins' use of the Welsh meters is "capricious and faulty" but effective. Cf.
                E903, E907, E910, E911, and E924. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E921">
            <bib>Klotz, Rose M. "Verbal Counterpoint in the Poetry of Gerard Manley Hopkins." DA 27
                (1966): 1058A (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> The conception of simultanous "overthought" and "underthought" which Hopkins
                derived from his reading of Greek dramatic lyrics reveals more about his own modes
                of order than it does about the Greek forms themselves. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E922">
            <bib>Kwan-Terry, John. "Pattern in the Carpet: Hopkins' Sprung Rhythm Re- Considered."
                Studies in English Literature (Tokyo), English Number, 1973, pp. 19-40.</bib>
            <notes> "Sprung Rhythm Rejected," it should have been: the author argues that Hop- kins
                neither understood or theorized about his own practice very accurately, so that
                "outrides," "overreaving," and metrical bars beginning with a stress are in-
                validated. Sprung Rhythm "is obviously a matter of degree and is not found in every
                line of a poem . . . . there is nothing very strict in Sprung Rhythm as far as
                stress-scheme and the metrical pattern are concerned." It can manage only "the hint
                of a basic metrical structure." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E923">
            <bib>Lahey, G[erald] F., S.J. "The Craftsman." In his Gerard Manley Hopkins. London:
                Oxford University Press, 1930. pp. 87-106.</bib>
            <notes> Simplified explication of Hopkins' theories and practice: note the schematic
                diagram of Rhythms on p. 94 and the scansion of "The Windhover," pp. 103-4. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E924">
            <bib>Lilly, Gweneth. "The Welsh Influence in the Poetry of Gerard Manley Hopkins." MLR
                38 (1843): 192-205.</bib>
            <notes> A much more detailed and careful study of syntactic, metrical, and especially)
                sonal influences than most of the other essays on this question, such as Gibson's
                (E910). See also E903, E907, E911, and E920. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E925">
            <bib>Ludwig, Hans-Werner. Barbarous in Beauty: Studien zum Vers in G. M. Hopkins'
                Sonnetten. Munich: Wilhelm Fink, 1972. 396 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Standop in Archiv 211 (1974): 134-41. Ludwig's book amounts to an
                extended exposition of Hopkins' theory of Sprung Rhythm. It is not, and was never
                intended to be, a neutral analysis or a critical commentary: Ludwig accepts Hopkins'
                system, which he wishes to dis- play with the utmost clarity, without pursuing any
                higher clarity which might modify or contravene the theory. This strategy is
                excoriated repeatedly by the implacable Standop in his bearish review (that is, he
                criticises Ludwig for not doing something he never intended to do), a review which
                very soon turns into a direct frontal attack on the theory of Sprung Rhythm itself.
                Ludwig accepts the distinctions betwen meter, rhythm, and perform- ance, and hence
                the conception of interplay or tension between the abstract metrical pattern and its
                linguistic filling. Chapter-subject: 1, general concepts of metrical theory and of
                Sprung Rhythm in particular; 2, scansion notation; 3, metrical treatment of
                syllables; 4 verse-stress and sentence-stress; 5, line- and sonnet-types; 6,
                enjambement; 7, rhetorical devices; 8, sound; 9-11, sample microanalyses of three
                sonnets; 12, short conclusion. Supplementary statistical tables. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E926">
            <bib>McBrien, William C. "Likeness in the Themes and Prosody of Gerard Manley Hopkins
                and Dylan Thomas." Diss., St. Louis University, 1959.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E927">
            <bib>Mariani, Paul L. "Appendix B: A Note on Hopkins' Prosody." A Commentary on the
                Complete Poems of Gerard Manley Hopkins. Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell University Press,
                1970. pp. 330-35.</bib>
            <notes> The serious student of Sprung Rhythm may safely ignore this. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E928">
            <bib>Marken, R. "Hopkins and the Word." Diss., University of Alberta, 1972.</bib>
            <notes> Cited in McNamee (q.v. in Appendix D) but not in CDI. Not seen. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E929">
            <bib>Mathison, John K. "The Poetic Theory of Gerard Manley Hopkins." PQ 26 (1947):
                21-35.</bib>
            <notes> Virtually nothing on Sprung Rhythm. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E930">
            <bib>-----. "The Poetical Relationship of Gerard Manley Hopkins, Coventry Patmore, and
                Francis Thompson." DA 12 (1952): 67 (Princeton, 1943).</bib>
            <notes> Part I summarizes biographical data; Part II summarizes the theories of the
                three; Part III analyzes then compares poems. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E931">
            <bib>Milroy, James. The Language of Gerard Manley Hopkins. London: Andre Deutsch,
                1977.</bib>
            <notes> A broad study of Hopkins' verse, including chapters on vocabulary, syntax, the
                Victorian philological milieu, and (particularly) "Patterns of Sound" (pp. 114- 53),
                meaning both Sprung Rhythm and the various devices of sonal pattern- ing. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E932">
            <bib>Mooney, Stephen. "Hopkins and Counterpoint." Victorian Newsletter, no. 18 (1960),
                pp. 21-22.</bib>
            <notes> The term has confused students of Sprung Rhythm; Hopkins knew it first in the
                musical sense--simply "plural melody," two melodic lines proceeding si-
                multaneously--which obviously will not apply to verse. A metrical counter- point
                could only be "a plurality of metrical lines"--i.e. the ideal metrical pat- tern
                against the real metrical embodiment in words. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E933">
            <bib>Noon, William T., S.J. "The Three Languages of Poetry." Immortal Diamond: Studies
                in Gerard Manley Hopkins. Ed. Norman Weyand. London: Sheed &amp; Ward, 1949. pp.
                252-74.</bib>
            <notes> The concluding section on "Free Verse" discloses how antipathetic the whole
                free-verse movement is to Hopkins' conceptions of craft, order, repetition, and
                figure in poetry. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E934">
            <bib>Nowell-Smith, Simon, J. G. Ritz, Geoffrey Tillotson, W. H. Gardner, and Norman
                Mackenzie. "Bridges's Debt to Hopkins." TLS, 12 May-1 September 1961, pp. 293, 408,
                549, 588.</bib>
            <notes> An obscure remark by Bridges in 1880 to the effect that his 1872 poem "Poor
                withered rose and dry" was written in Sprung Rhythm, even though Hopkins did not
                seriously begin to develop his theories until late 1873, is assented to by Ritz and
                Tillotson but denied energetically by the other three. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E935">
            <bib>Ogden, C. K. "Sprung Rhythm." Psyche 16 (1936): 1-50. See also 15 (1935): 8-13
                (also 14-18).</bib>
            <notes> Extended exemplification of printers', prosodists', and critics' incompetence,
                ignorance, and insensitivity to Hopkins' system, followed by a very close expli-
                cation of Hopkins' conceptions of "counterpointing," "outrides" or "hangers,"
                caesura, "obscure" language, and rhyme. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E936">
            <bib>Ong, Walter J., S.J. "Hopkins' Sprung Rhythm and the Life of English Poetry."
                Immortal Diamond. Ed. Norman Weyand. London: Sheed &amp; Ward, 1949. pp.</bib>
            <notes> 83-174; rpt in part as "Sprung Rhythm and English Tradition" in Hopkins: A
                Collection of Critical Essays. Ed. Geoffrey H. Hartman. Englewood Cliffs, N.J.:
                Prentice-Hall, 1966. pp. 151-59. Too long by half, Father Ong's close scrutiny of
                the chronology of Hopkins' readings establishes that he could not have derived his
                theory of Sprung Rhythm from Milton, Old English, or anywhere else; all these
                studies come after the crucial notes of 1873-74 and the writing of the Deutschland
                in 1875. Hopkins only gradually realized the full extent of the new rhythm he was
                hearing, but he was "hearing it everywhere," which shows it was in the grain of the
                language itself, not contrived. What is remarkable is that Hopkins was the only
                major poet of his age in touch with the primary rhythms of the lan- guage. Ong's
                detailed study of Running, Counterpoint, and Sprung Rhythms reveals their
                "affinities" with Old English, with the rhythm (alternating stresses) of the
                language, and with the mainstream of English poetry continuously from Chaucer to the
                end of the nineteenth century. Hopkins did not invent "sense- stress rhythm"; he
                discovered it. Points of interest here: Ong rejects Whitehall's dipodic theory of
                Sprung Rhythm; he considers Hopkins' practice of beginning every metrical unit with
                a stress "a mere convenience" even for Hopkins himself and so he discards it and
                argues that scanning should proceed across the line-end break; he notes the
                frequency of parallel half-lines and judges that Hopkins' rhymes are "only fuller
                developments continuous with effects built everywhere into the verse." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E937">
            <bib>Patmore, Derek. "Three Poets Discuss New Verse Forms: The Correpondence of Gerard
                Manley Hopkins, Robert Bridges, and Coventry Patmore." The Month n.s. 6 (1951):
                65-78.</bib>
            <notes> A convenient source, not easily available elsewhere, for letters between the
                three poets on the subject of metrics. E938 Ritz, Jean-Georges. Robert Bridges and
                Gerard Hopkins, 1863-1889: A Literary Friendship. London: Oxford University Press,
                1960. Rev: in Review of English Studies n.s. 12 (1961): 317-18; in MP 58 (1961):
                290-92; in MLR 57 (1962): 254-55; in Études Anglaises 15 (1962): 85-86; in English
                Studies 44 (1963): 462-65; in Anglia 83 (1965): 114-17. There is much on meter
                throughout, and the whole book is required reading for students of Sprung Rhythm or
                Bridges' experiments in verseforms. See es- pecially section four ("Bridges tries
                his Hand at Sprung Rhythm," pp. 98-105) in the important Chapter IV, and section one
                ("Prosody and Milton," pp. 112- 22) in Chapter V. The friendship and correspondence
                between Hopkins and Bridges had very significant effects on the metrical theories of
                both men: Bridges tried parodic and authentic sprung rhythm, Hopkins was intensely
                in- terested in Milton, and both explored a mutual interest in the structure of
                music. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E939">
            <bib>Ronninger, Karl. Versuch einer systematischen Ordnung der metrischen Theorien
                Gerard Manley Hopkins. Diss., Vienna, 1941. 186 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E940">
            <bib>Scheve, Charles J. "The Prosodic Practice of Gerard Manley Hopkins in The Wreck of
                the Deutschland." DA 30 (1969): 1150A (Catholic University of America).</bib>
            <notes> From the abstract one gleans nothing about results and little about method be-
                sides the rather obvious: a statistical analysis of line and strophe is made, based
                on a phonetic/prosodic transcription of the poem. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E941">
            <bib>Schneider, Elisabeth W. "Sprung Rhythm: A Chapter in the Evolution of
                Nineteenth-Century Verse." PMLA 80 (1965): 237-53.</bib>
            <notes> The new metric called Sprung Rhythm first presented in The Wreck of the
                Deutschland was less revolutionary an accomplishment than one might other- wise
                expect; when placed in the context of the increasing metrical experi- mentation of
                the nineteenth century--the more frequent use of the anapest, leading to logaoedic
                duple-triple meters--and especially when viewed against the background of a number
                of very similar effects developed slightly before Hopkins by Swinburne, The Wreck
                will be seen as not an "altogether novel invention" metrically but actually "a blend
                of conventional and sprung rhythm, with the former predominating," i.e. "an
                anapestic poem in a sprung frame." Indeed, the preponderance of the poem scans
                remarkably well as conventional mixed duple-triple meter. Hopkins' new rhythm was
                achieved with startlingly little modification of the traditional metric of English.
                As a distinct new meter the advantages of Sprung Rhythm were greater "naturalness
                and flexibility"; its disadvantages were a "frequent lack of both rhythmical and
                rhetorical clarity" (since no regular subliminal metrical pattern exists to help us
                assign stresses and disambiguate meaning in problematic phrases, we have to try to
                make out the meaning itself before we can discern the scansion; the meter itself is
                not a guide to meaning), the loss of the subtler shadings of articulation, and the
                loss of the complex counterpoint between language and meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E942">
            <bib>Singh, Yashoda N. "Gerard Manley Hopkins: A Problem of Prosody." An English
                Miscellany (St. Stephen's College, Delhi) 2 (1963): 49-56.</bib>
            <notes> Not seen; the library of the College in Delhi was unable to locate the item.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E943">
            <bib>Skarda, Patricia L. "'The Music of his Mind': Gerard Manley Hopkins as Literary
                Critic and Theorist." DAI 34 (1973): 2579A (Texas).</bib>
            <notes> On the influence of the Romantic poets and the Victorian critics in shaping
                Hopkins' poetics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E944">
            <bib>Stobie, Margaret R. "Patmore's Theory and Hopkins' Practice." University of
                Toronto Quarterly 19 (1949): 64-80.</bib>
            <notes> Following Whitehall's suggestion (E947) that Hopkins' verse conforms to Pat-
                more's metrical theory (E384), Stobie summarizes (approvingly) Patmore's no- tions
                of time, quantity, and the dipodic foot in verse, then attempts to show that Sprung
                Rhythm is actually dipodic too, a position the precariousness of which forces her to
                hold also that Hopkins not only read and understood Pat- more but actually corrected
                his mistakes and improved his theory. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E945">
            <bib>Tierney, Michael, Herbert Read, R. S. Stanier, and Humphry House. "Gerard
                Hopkins's Metres." Correspondence in TLS, 16 February-9 March 1933, pp. 108, 127,
                147, 167.</bib>
            <notes> In the first letter Tierney implies very strongly that Hopkins' theories were
                derived from the 1878 English translation of J. H. Schmidt's Leitfaden in die
                Rhythmik und Metrik der classischen Sprachen (M183), but the other con- tributers
                dispose of this theory easily, so he shifts his ground in the final letter, urging
                only significant parallels. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E946">
            <bib>Tonkin, Humphrey. "Hopkins' "Inversnaid' and its Stylistic Devices." Language and
                Style 3 (1970): 274-92.</bib>
            <notes> A "conservative" metrical analysis (pp. 277-83) of the rhythmic progression
                particular to each stanza of the poem finds anapests and choriambs, thus em-
                phasizing Hopkins' metrical similarities with his contemporaries instead of the
                reverse. Syntax, diction, and imagery also analyzed. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E947">
            <bib>Whitehall, Harold. "Sprung Rhythm." Kenyon Review 6 (1944): 333-54; rpt in Gerard
                Manley Hopkins: A Symposium by the Kenyon Critics. New York: New Directions, 1945.
                pp. 28-54.</bib>
            <notes> Despite Hopkins' explicit statements that his metrical theory was based squarely
                on stress, Whitehall--skeptical of poets' critical acuity--advances the thesis that
                the stresses of Sprung Rhythm demarcate isochronous measures of time which are
                dipodic, in the sense defined by Coventry Patmore (E384). In deed, Hopkins, albeit
                unconsciously, wrote sprung-rhythm verse that "follows Patmore's theories almost to
                the letter." W. adopts the sigla of G. R. Stewart (E333) for scansions--Hopkins'
                favored patterns are SpLp, SpLO, SOLp, and SpPp--and turns in his final section to
                consider overstressing and alliteration also. See also Stobie (E944), and chapter 4
                of Holloway (E914). See also B54, B56, B205, C76, C255-56, E370, E417, E470, E590,
                E686, E759-60, E791, E806, E843, E1173, G27, I16, I27, L201, L215, L262. SYLLABIC
                VERSE Mainly by Marianne Moore and Robert Bridges. Serious interest in a meter which
                regulates only number of syllables is a modern phenomenon, an emblem of our de- sire
                to Make It New, though the more general principle of syllabism has always been an
                important aspect of English versification, especially in early Middle English and in
                the early eighteenth century. Bridges' Testament of Beauty seems to be the longest
                syllabic poem in the language, though (undeservedly) now nearly forgotten. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E948">
            <bib>Abercrombie, Lascelles. "Technique and The Testament of Beauty." Bookman 79
                (1930): 166-67.</bib>
            <notes> "For Bridges, to experiment in technique was to speak his heart and mind."
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E949">
            <bib>Beloof, Robert. "Prosody and Tone: The 'Mathematics' of Marianne Moore." Kenyon
                Review 20 (1958): 116-23.</bib>
            <notes> A subtly complex argument sketched out too briefly: in all but her very latest
                work, Marianne Moore employs sporadic rhymes, fracturing of words across line-end,
                and other prosodic devices to altogether minimize the effect of her syllabic verse
                and thus render it as similar as possible to free verse, which is the form she
                originally began working in--a form where there is a distinct sense of the line as
                rhythmic unit. The "mathematical" tone which critics have noted in her poems is
                derived not from the versification but from other elements. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E950">
            <bib>Berg, Sister Mary Gretchen. The Prosodic Structure of Robert Bridges' "Neo-
                Miltonic Syllabics." Washington, D. C.: Cathoic University of America Press, 1962.
                196 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Using La Drière's system (E570), the author analyzes 10% of the roughly five
                thousand lines of syllabic Alexandrines that Bridges wrote from 1921 up though the
                1929 The Testament of Beauty, marking the variations in general cadence (meter) and
                group cadence (rhythmical-syntactic groups). Appendices of scansions, tables, and
                bibliography follow the text (116 pp.). See Baum (next entry) and Wright (E958).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E951">
            <bib>Beum, Robert. "Profundity Revisted: Bridges and His Critics." Dalhousie Review 44
                (1964): 172-79.</bib>
            <notes> Confounds the two generally accepted yet immiscible views of Bridges--that his
                lyrically smooth verse lacked profundity, and that he was a mere mechani- cal
                metrists--by close analysis of one of his poems, "Eros." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E952">
            <bib>-----. "Syllabic Verse in English." Prairie Schooner 31 (1957): 259-75.</bib>
            <notes> Undertakes a general examination of this form and its constraints, with steady
                attention to Bridges. "In syllabics the metrical organization is not achieved by an
                arrangement of elements within the line but rather by the effect of the repetition
                of the syllabically-uniform end-paused lines themselves." Three dif- ferentia seem
                indispensable to the form: a fixed number of syllables, a roughly fixed duration of
                time or breath for each line, and an end-of-line pause (pro- duced by syntax or a
                stressed syllable). The work of Daryush, Rexroth, M. Moore, and Dylan Thomas is also
                noticed. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E953">
            <bib>Boas, Cicely, "The Meter of The Testament of Beauty." London Mercury 22 (1930):
                147-53.</bib>
            <notes> An apologia for the syllabic meter. "We are not to try to scan every verse slav-
                ishly, but to accent each word as the English language requires it to be ac- cented
                with no regard for feet or verses at all. Throughout the poem the me- tre--not the
                rhythm--is so broken that it is scarcely ever possible to feel there ought to be an
                accent in a syllable because it occupies a certain position in the verse, although
                the sense requires it to be unaccented." And, almost as an aside, "rhythm in verse
                is to metre what rhythm in music is to time." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E954">
            <bib>Bridges, Robert. "New Verse: Explanation of the Prosody of My Late Syllabic 'Free
                Verse.'" In his Collected Essays, Papers, &amp;. London: Oxford University Press,
                1933. Vol. 2, no. 15, pp. 86-91.</bib>
            <notes> Written 1923. The staple meter of Bridges' "Neo-Miltonic Syllabics" is a line of
                twelve syllables without caesura. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E955">
            <bib>Carey, Sister Mary Cecilia, O. P. "The Poetry of Marianne Moore: A Study of Her
                Verse, Its Sources, and Its Influence." DA 20 (1959): 1023A (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> Some attention to versification. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E956">
            <bib>Fuller, Roy. "An Artifice of Versification." Wascana Review 4 (1969): 5-20; rpt in
                his Owls and Artificers. London: Andre Deutsch, 1971. pp. 44-68.</bib>
            <notes> An urbane consideration of the devices which render Marianne Moore's syl- labic
                verse so effective: avoiding the complexities of stanza and rhyme, she cre- ates
                "poetry without adventitious musical aid, whose units are arguments and paragraphs .
                . . not prose or the prose-poem but poetry with prose's rhetoric, complexity and
                ease." Inclusion of quotations, apt phrases and allusions, and avoidance of regular
                stress and lines with even numbers of syllables (both tending always toward the
                iambic) also secure the novelty and vigor. Milton's late work and the brilliant
                footnote to Housman's 1933 Stephens Lecture are also discussed. Syllabic verse,
                Fuller concludes, is "an extension of more tradi- tional meters, not a denial of
                them." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E957">
            <bib>Ghose, Zulfikar, et al. "A Defense of Syllabics." TLS, 16 January–14 May 1964, pp.
                53, 67, 93, 107, 127, 147, 215, 235, 277, 381, 415.</bib>
            <notes> The column "Syllables Are Not Enough" on p. 47 quarrels with Ghose's claim that
                "syllabics are as legitimate a metrical device as any other," though the majority of
                the other correspondents are supportive. The whole exchange quickly digresses to a
                mélange of other related prosodic subjects, such as the role of syllable-counting in
                metrical theory. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E958">
            <bib>Wright, Elizabeth Cox. Metaphor, Sound and Meaning in Bridges' "The Testament of
                Beauty." Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1951.</bib>
            <notes> Three of her chapters present in detail Bridges' positions on the prosodic
                issues of his time: "The Invention of a New Meter" (pp. 13-27), "The Theoretical
                Justification of the New Meter" (pp. 28-46), and "The End-Pause" (pp. 47- 76). The
                "Neo-Miltonic" meter which Bridges created for The Testament of Beauty is a syllabic
                one, twelve syllables to the line, employing Miltonic eli- sion, a "loose
                Alexandrine," with "no decided enforced accent in any place"-- i.e., having neither
                metrical accent nor quantity but rather speech-rhythms. See also: E1509. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E959">
            <bib>Albert, Franz. Über Thomas Heywoods 'The Life and Death of Hector,' eine
                Neuebearbeitung von Lydgates Troy Book. Münchener Beiträge zur romanischen und
                englischen Philologie, vol. 42. Leipzig: Deichert, 1909.</bib>
            <notes> Chapter 2, "Metrik," pp. 18-35, discusses the metrical treatment of syllables,
                stressing, meter, and rhyme in this 1614 play (written in six-line stanzas) at-
                tributed to H. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E960">
            <bib>Alscher, Rudolf. Sir Thomas Wyatt und seine Stellung in der Entwicklungs-
                geschichte der englischen Literatur und Verskunst. Wiener Beiträge zur deutschen und
                englischen Philologie. Vienna: Wilhelm Braumüller, 1886.</bib>
            <notes> See "Wyatts Versbau," pp. 43-143. Cf. 1027. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E961">
            <bib>Astley, Russell. "Browning's Logaeodic Measures." Victorian Poetry 16 (1978):
                357-68.</bib>
            <notes> Suggests three types of metrical variation in Browning: (1) substitution of
                feet, as iambic-anapestic; (2) substitution in identical positions so regularly that
                it ceases being variation and becomes pattern; and (3) mixing of "light" and "heavy"
                feet, as in dipodics and paeonics. Astley implies that all of this verges on
                metrical indecision if not imcompetence and suggests frequent analogues to classical
                meters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E962">
            <bib>Baldi, Sergio. "La Struttura del Verso." La Poesia di Sir Thomas Wyatt, Il Primo
                Petrarchista Inglese. Firenze: Le Monnier, 1953. pp. 91-164.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E963">
            <bib>Barrie, Robert. "Structure in Richard Crashaw's Poetry." DAI 32 (1972): 5173A
                (North Carolina).</bib>
            <notes> Chapter 5 treats the "rhythmic structure" in three Crashaw poems. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E964">
            <bib>Beatty, Arthur. "Browning's Verse-form, its organic Character." Diss., Columbia
                University, 1897.</bib>
            <notes> Omond (A5) and Lafourcade (see Appendix D, s.v.) both misspell the name. The
                dissertation mainly catalogues metrical and stanzaic forms in the canon, with a
                final chapter on Browning's Blank Verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E965">
            <bib>Beljame, Alexandre, ed. Tennyson's "Enoch Arden." Paris: Libraire Hachette,
                1892;</bib>
            <notes> often reprinted. Extensive introductory notes on the versification of the poem,
                pp. 23-56. He scans by accent, allows secondary accent between full and slack, and
                uses nu- merical superscripts in scansion: 0, 1, 2. Spondees are allowed, these
                being configurations 1, 2 , 2, 1 , or 2, 2; pyrrhics however may only be 0, 0. Also
                discussed: pronunciation, elision, caesura, enjambement, and alliteration. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E966">
            <bib>Beloof, Robert. "Strength in the Exquisite: A Study of John Crowe Ransom's
                Prosody." Annali Instituto Universitario Orientale, Napoli, Sezione Germanica 4
                (1961): 215-22.</bib>
            <notes> The distinctive mark of Ransom's mature versification is "the perilous main-
                tainance of the metric (usually iambic) speech flex in spite of its constant de-
                struction. The strange beauty and tension of his rhythm depends largely upon the
                enormous skill with which Ransom, in rapid alternation, destroys, then re-
                constructs, his iambic mode." Ransom's strict meter, that is, often passes into
                plainer prose rhythms, creating a verse at once indecisive yet forceful. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E967">
            <bib>Beum, Robert. "Yeats's Idealized Speech." Michigan Quarterly Review 4 (1965):
                227-33;</bib>
            <notes> rpt as chapter 9 of his The Poetic Art of William Butler Yeats (B12). Actually
                about "the rationale of Yeats's adherence to meter" more than dic- tion: Beum is
                intent to show that Yeats's lines become progressively rougher, moving from strict
                meter to a looser iambic to "cadence" and even to "speech cadence," as he explores
                more colloquial forms of speech. But Yeats never lost his faith in meter or rhyme,
                and his increasing use of "highly irregular iambic meter" should be recognized as
                "the acquiring of new instruments, not the abandoning of the older ones." This essay
                could stand greater conceptual pre- cision, but its thesis is persuasive. Compare
                the scansions in Dougherty (D273). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E968">
            <bib>Bond, Christopher, J. "II: The Auditory Dimension in Arnold's Search for a
                Distinctive Poetic Voice: Prosodic Commentaries in Selected Poems of Matthew
                Arnold."</bib>
            <notes> (Three-part dissertation.) DAI 35 (1974): 3725A (Rutgers). Wordsworth's
                influence on Arnold's metrics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E969">
            <bib>Brinton, Daniel G. "The New Poetic Form as Shown in Browning." Poet-Lore 2 (1890):
                234-46.</bib>
            <notes> Brinton examines "the underlying harmonics of cadences, rests, and tone-
                colors," eschewing "the rubbish of prosody." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E970">
            <bib>Burke, Brother Fidelian. Metrical Roughness in Marston's Formal Satire.
                Washington, D. C.: Catholic University of America Press, 1957.</bib>
            <notes> A condensed version of his dissertation. The change in Elizabethan dramatic
                taste in the 1590's toward imitations of classical satire produced plays which,
                following the misconception of the time, were "rough" or crude in taste, themes, and
                versification. Concerning the lat- ter, "rough" seems to have meant irregular
                cadences, juxtaposed stresses, and perhaps rapid tempo. Burke analyzes the 1598 play
                The Scourge of Villanie using the scansion-method of La Drière (four degrees of
                stress); the analysis confirms Marston's own statement that he wrote Satires
                "rougher" than other genres. Burke's primary interest, though, is in the relation of
                the meter to the rhythmic phrasing-groups, those phrases and clauses set off in the
                syntax by pauses or commas. Extensive statistical tables delineate the nature and
                degree of these congruences/divergences, and indeed, I know no better study than
                this available on the complex relation of syntactic phrasing and meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E971">
            <bib>Busskohl, James L. "Studies in Tennyson's Prosody." DAI 31 (1971): 3497A (Southern
                Illinois).</bib>
            <notes> This analysis, which takes into account the stratification between rhythm and
                meter, takes as its methodological axes the two principal traditions or modes in
                English verse, the accentual and the syllabic, in order to distinguish the prop-
                erties of each mode, as evidenced in (hundred-line samples from) sixteen po- ems by
                Tennyson. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E972">
            <bib>Carrington, Richard H. "Archibald MacLeish: A Study of his Prosody for the Oral
                Interpreter." DAI 25 (1965): 6821A (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> Actually a study of the four stages in MacLeish's prosodic development. His
                general prosodic characteristics are a four-stress line in falling rhythm and asso-
                nantal rhyme. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E973">
            <bib>Cayley, C. B. "The Pedigree of English Heroic Verse," Transactions of the
                Philological Society, 1867, pp. 43-54.</bib>
            <notes> Derives the English decasyllabic line (both blank and rhymed) from the Italian
                hendacasyllabic, that from the Latin senarius (Sappho and Catullus), and that from
                the Greek dramatic iambic trimeter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E974">
            <bib>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor. "Versification of Donne." The Literary Remains of Samuel
                Taylor Coleridge. Ed. Henry Nelson Coleridge. London: William Pickering, 1836. Vol.
                1, pp. 148-49; rpt in John Donne's Poetry. Ed. A. L. Clements. New York: W. W.
                Norton, 1966. pp. 109-12.</bib>
            <notes> "To read Dryden, Pope, &amp;c., you need only count syllables, but to read Donne
                you must measure Time, and discover the Time of each word by the sense of Passion. I
                would ask no surer test of a Scotchman's substratum . . . then to make him read
                Donne's satires aloud. If he made manly metre of them, and yet strict metre;
                then--why, then he wasn't a Scotchman." "This beautiful and perfect poem ["Song"]
                proves . . . that all Donne's Poems are equally met- rical . . . but in poems where
                the writer thinks, and expects the reader to do so, the sense must be understood in
                order to ascertain the metre." All the re- marks collected here are refulgent.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E975">
            <bib>Colvin, Sidney. John Keats: His Life and Poetry, His Friends, Critics, and After-
                Fame. London: Macmillan, 1917.</bib>
            <notes> Chapters 4 and 7 offer extensive discussion of Keats's metrical achievements in
                the sonnet and couplet forms. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E976">
            <bib>Connolly, Thomas E. "Sandals More Interwoven and Complete: A Re-Examination of the
                Keatsian Odes." ELH 16 (1949): 299-307.</bib>
            <notes> Simply compares the results of Garrod and Ridley (E1053) on Keats's metrical
                craftsmanship in his major Odes. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E977">
            <bib>Croll, Morris W. The Works of Fulke Greville. Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott,
                1903. His dissertation at Pennsylvania in 1901. 59 pp.</bib>
            <notes> On classical meters see pp. 4-5; on metrical characteristics of his sonnets, 11-
                17; on the verseform of his dramas, 33-34. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E978">
            <bib>Daalder, Joost. "Wyatt's Prosody Revisited." Language and Style 10 (1977):
                3-15.</bib>
            <notes> Scholarship on Wyatt has traditionally been divided, one side viewing his verse
                as iambic (if primitive), the other side viewing it as a last vestige of
                alliterative verse (showing "phrasal" units rather than feet). The present article
                accepts both positions and takes a middle course: in an age of transition, Wyatt's
                met- ric shows features of both traditions. Was that assertion even necessary?
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E979">
            <bib>Damon, S. Foster. "The Chariot of Genius." William Blake: His Philosophy and
                Symbols. New York: Houghton Mifflin, 1924; rpt Glouchester, Mass: Peter Smith, 1947,
                1958. pp. 45-60.</bib>
            <notes> Remarks on Blake's inventiveness in meter and rhyme--i.e. blank verse (espe-
                cially tetrameters), mixed meters, and "metrical prose" for the early lyrics, the
                iambic and anapestic septenary (with alexandrines and occasional classical hex-
                ameters), for the Prophetic Books. The later Long Line Damon takes to be in stress
                verse, and he notes that Blake seemed little concerned whether his work was "prose"
                or "verse." Relies on Saintsbury (A8). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E980">
            <bib>Davie, Donald. "Yeats and Pound." Dublin Magazine 30 (1955): 17-21.</bib>
            <notes> "Pound, more than Yeats and much more than Eliot, has the gift of melodic
                invention in verse." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E981">
            <bib>Davis, Thomas M., and V. L. Davis. "Edward Taylor's Metrical Paraphrases of the
                Psalms." American Literature 48 (1977): 455-70.</bib>
            <notes> Texts of recently discovered MSS, along with remarks on their metrical and
                stanzaic form; the verses seem to have been meant to be sung. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E982">
            <bib>Day, Martin S. "Anstey and Anapestic Satire in the Late Eighteenth Century." ELH
                15 (1948): 122-46 (one chapter of his dissertation at Johns Hopkins in 1948).</bib>
            <notes> Day examines the major shift in tone in late-eighteenth-century satire (from
                invective to burlesque) which was articulated in a major shift in form (from couplet
                to stanza). The only two exceptions to this tonal/formal shift were (1) the
                preservation of octosyllabics essentially unchanged and (2) the introduction of
                anapestic tetrameters by Christopher Anstey in his 1766 New Bath Guide, a volume of
                satirical light verse. The form held sway until well into the nine- teenth century.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E983">
            <bib>Dillow, H. C. "A Study of the Metrics of Donne and Jonson in the Context of the
                Interrelations between Stress and Metrical Verse Principles and Modern Critical
                Appraisal." Diss., University of London, 1970.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E984">
            <bib>Douds, John R. "Donne's Technique of Dissonance." PMLA 52 (1937): 1051-61.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E985">
            <bib>Endicott, A. M. "A Critical Study of the Metrical Effects in the Poetry of Sir
                Thomas Wyatt, with Some Reference to Analogous Effects in Elizabethan Poetry."
                Thesis, London University, 1963.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E986">
            <bib>Ensley, Helen. "The Rhythm of Poe's Poetry." DAI 32 (1971): 2638A
                (Tennessee).</bib>
            <notes> A study of the range, versatility, and proficiency Poe demonstrates at
                versifica- tion in the composition and revision of his poems. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E987">
            <bib>Evans, Robert O. "Some Aspects of Wyatt's Metrical Technique." JEGP 53 (1954):
                197-213.</bib>
            <notes> A critique of Swallow's analysis of the "broken-backed" line in Skelton and
                Wyatt (K389). Evans shows that the inflectional ending -eth (also -es) was regularly
                employed not only in Middle English but also in Middle Scots up to the fifteenth
                century as an optional metrical device for regularizing syllable- count. It is so
                used by Wyatt as well, and he also uses it for metrical elision--to regularize
                stress-placement (the inflectional -e is an entirely different problem, but only a
                minor one in Wyatt). Hence many of Wyatt's pentameters are more regular than has
                been thought. His early work is scarcely less regular than his mature work, and
                statistically, both are quite comparable in irregularity to that o Milton and
                Wordsworth. Some of his lines were experimental, and some others were meant to be
                tetrameters. Wyatt seems rough to us because he used metrical devices in ways
                unfamiliar to us, but they are the same devices used by all the major English poets.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E988">
            <bib>Fairchild, B. H. Jr. "Melos and Meaning in Blake's Lyric Art." Blake Studies 7
                (1975): 125-41.</bib>
            <notes> Reminding us of the tripartite nature of Blake's art--song, poetry, image--
                Fairchild explores the melos--word-music, stress meters, song--of Blake's early
                lyrics, noting such devices as the trochaic meters (thwarting our conventional-
                ized, hence easy, expectation of the iambic), and drawing out the metri-
                cal/stylistic differences between the Songs of Innocence and the Songs of Ex-
                perience. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E989">
            <bib>-----. "'Such Holy Song': Music as Idea, Form, and Image in the Poetry of William
                Blake." DAI 36 (1975): 900A (Tulsa).</bib>
            <notes> Primary emphasis falls upon Blake's knowledge of music (e.g. the Songs as
                songs), but a secondary concern is "the liberal prosodic theory contemporary with
                [Blake] which equated the musical and poetic lines." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E990">
            <bib>Foxwell, A[gnes] K. "Comparison of Wyatt's Versification with Pynson's Edition of
                Chaucer." A Study of Sir Thomas Wyatt's Poems. London: University of London Press,
                1911; rpt New York: Russell &amp; Russell, 1964. pp. 39-51.</bib>
            <notes> Subsequent chapters explore Chaucerian, French, and Italian influences on Wyatt,
                both in forms and themes. The preceding chapter (pp. 29-38) discusses "Wyatt's
                Language and Grammar." Foxwell sets forth in detail sixteen metrical rules which
                Wyatt obeyed, and, finding eight of these in the first thirteen lines of the General
                Prologue of the 1526 edition of Chaucer known to Wyatt, she concludes that Chaucer
                was unquestionably Wyatt's model for meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E991">
            <bib>Haber, Tom B. "Housman's Poetic Ear." Poet-Lore 54 (1948): 257-69.</bib>
            <notes> Intent to diminish the critical commonplace that Housman knew only the iambic
                tetrameter, Haber displays trochaic lines, variations, feminine endings, and
                onomatopoeic effects, pausing at the end to praise Housman's 1933 essay on poetry
                and its famous footnote (E297). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E992">
            <bib>Hamilton, Kenneth G. John Dryden and the Poetry of Statement. East Lansing:
                Michigan State University Press, 1969.</bib>
            <notes> Chapter 3 ("Sound") particularly (and to a lesser extent Chapter 1 on "Religio
                Laici") demonstrates the vigor of the speech-rhythms which Dryden was able to fix in
                his couplets, these rhythms "serving rather to enliven and emphasize the statement
                than to articulate an independent meaning of their own." A long and perspicuous
                treatment of Dryden's rhythmical control. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E993">
            <bib>Hashiguchi, Minoru. [Rhythms of Wyatt and Surrey]. Eigo Seinen (The Rising
                Generation) 119 (1974): 702-3.</bib>
            <notes> Compares alternative scansions of lines from one sonnet by each. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E994">
            <bib>Hatcher, Harlan H. The Versification of Robert Browning. Ohio State Contributions
                in Languages and Literatures, no. 5. Columbus: Ohio State University, 1928. 195
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> His dissertation at Ohio State in 1927 (he was a pupil of C. E. Andrews).
                Organized into two major parts, one on the blank, the other on the rhymed, verse.
                Hatcher's metrical principle is to scan by equal time, and he adopts the Musical
                practice of placing the bar before the accent (though he never uses notes).
                Introductory section on Browning's habits of composition and known views on
                versification; penultimate chapter on his accentual hexameters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E995">
            <bib>Heine, Ingeborg. "The Metrical Intentions of Wyatt's Sonnets: "Who So List to
                Hount,' 'I Fynde No Peace,' and 'The Longe Love.'" Kwartalnik Neofilologiczny
                (Warsaw) 25 (1978): 407-20.</bib>
            <notes> Argues that Wyatt intentionally counterpoises sections in iambic pentameter
                against sections in the older native four-stress line in his sonnets. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E996">
            <bib>Heinemann, Alison K. T. "The Style of Robert Herrick's Lyrics." DAI 32 (1972):
                6377A (Pennsylvania).</bib>
            <notes> The final chapter treats versification. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E997">
            <bib>Hemphill, George. "Dryden's Heroic Line." PMLA 72 (1957): 863-79.</bib>
            <notes> A very thorough analysis of the metrical variations in (1) syllable count and
                (2) stress placement in Dryden's pentameter lines both blank and coupled, focus- ing
                especially on elision, trisyllabic substitutions, and pyrrhics and spondees. N. B.:
                "the history of English versification cannot be understood as the checkered career
                of the trisyllabic foot." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E998">
            <bib>-----. "The Meters of the Intermediate Poets." Kenyon Review 19 (1957):
                37-55.</bib>
            <notes> Surveying the mid-century generation of poets in the Rinehart Fifteen Mod- ern
                American Poets, H. gives rules for their metrical practice: they take greater
                liberties than their predecessors with anapestic substitutions, reversed feet, ionic
                feet, initial and medial truncations, line- and stanza-length, and rhyme. Loose
                iambics and stress verse greatly outnumber strict iambics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E999">
            <bib>Hickson, Elizabeth C. The Versification of Thomas Hardy. Philadelphia: n.p., 1931.
                129 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Her dissertation at Pennsylvania in 1931. Rev: in JEGP 31 (1932): 627-29; in
                Anglia Beiblatt 44 (1933): 316-17; in MLN 50 (1935): 61-62. Actually only chapter 3
                on Form and the long, valuable Appendix listing met- rical and stanzaic patterns in
                the Hardy canon may be legitimately said to ex- amine versification; the remainder
                of the book takes up style and diction. Prin- ciples of versification are nowhere
                explained; the bibliography is heterogene- ous, and though she marks stresses,
                metrical pauses are allowed and Omond's nomenclature from A Study of Metre (E310) is
                adopted, so one must conclude that Hickson is confused about method. From this study
                (which is mainly of stanza form, at that) one cannot say what Hardy himself took as
                his metric, much less what we might now understand that metric to be. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1000">
            <bib>Hollander, John. "Blake and the Metrical Contract." From Sensibility to
                Romanticism: Essays Presented to Frederick A. Pottle. Ed. Frederick W. Hilles and
                Harold Bloom. New York: Oxford University Press, 1965. pp. 293-310.</bib>
            <notes> Expanded into "Romantic Verse Form and the Metrical Contract" in Romanticism and
                Consciousness: Essays in Criticism. Ed. Harold Bloom. New York: W. W. Norton, 1970.
                pp. 181-200; rpt in Hollander's Vision and Resonance (A13), pp. 187-211. If one of
                the crucial functions of meter in poetry is expressive, the other is purely
                conventional: a poet's choice of meter is an implicit commitment to certain metrical
                styles, types, modalities, and genres, these establishing conti- nuity and
                comprising traditions, as Hollander shows in giving capsule histories of the iambic
                tradition, blank verse, the sonnet, lyric stanzas, and the anapestic elegaic meter,
                traditions which may be revised or broken at certain crucial points, "metrical
                crises," where the metrical contract between poet and reader (as defined by
                Wordsworth) is redrawn--think of Chaucer, Wyatt, Davenant, Milton, Blake, Whitman,
                Hopkins, and pound, for example. Perhaps the para- digmatic case of all is Blake,
                whose subversive-restorative metric must be the ultimate source for the twentieth
                century's obsessive-dismissive interest in meter: Blake accepted certain metrical
                conventions of his day and rejected others, reshaping everything that fell under his
                touch in that pragmatic ap- proach to meter so characteristic of the Romantics.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1001">
            <bib>-----. "Donne and the Limits of Lyric." John Donne: Essays in Celebration. Ed. A.
                J. Smith. London: Methuen, 1972. pp. 259-72; </bib>
            <notes>rpt in his Vision and Resonance (A13), pp. 44-58. Donne's strenuous--but
                lawful--modulations of stress to meter created excep- tional problems for composers
                attempting settings of his lyrics, the most inter- esting of which is the problem of
                contrastive stress, which Hollander examines in detail. More interesting still: "the
                setting of any poem to music recapitulates, in a strange way, the very process of
                metrical composition in a language." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1002">
            <bib>Honan, Park. "The Iron String in the Victorian Lyre: Browning's Lyric
                Versification." In Browning's Mind and Art. Ed. Clarence Tracy. London: Oliver &amp;
                Boyd, 1968. pp. 82-99.</bib>
            <notes> Browning fits his metrical style to the subject not to the genre, and he seems
                discordant at times because, unlike other poets who usually exploit the possi-
                bilities for cacophony--metrical variation, articulatory difficulty, and syntactic
                breaks within the line--only in one dimension, while compensating for it in the
                other two, Browning usually provides no compensation to smooth out the intensities
                of his expressive dissonance. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1003">
            <bib>Johnston, Arthur. "Gray's Use of the Gorchest y Beirdd in The Bard." MLR 59
                (1964): 335-38.</bib>
            <notes> Actually Gray never used this Welsh meter exactly, though he considered do- ing
                so in an early draft of the poem. Johnston discusses, more widely, the use of the
                metre in other poets and Gray's other prosodic impulses. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1004">
            <bib>Kado, Maria. Swinburne's Verskunst. Normannia: Germanish-Romanische Bücherei, vol.
                9. Berlin: Emil Felber, 1911. 132 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Mainly on metrical- and stanza-forms; the metrical theory adopted is Tempo- ral.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1005">
            <bib>King, Lauren A. "The Verse Technique of Alfred, Lord Tennyson." Diss., Ohio State
                University, 1930.</bib>
            <notes> 250 pp. + Appendices of extensive statistical tables. Seemingly exhaustive
                metrical analysis. Scans flexibly, avoiding both prose- stressings and the
                metronome, using three degrees of stress. Further compres- sion would have yielded a
                fine book. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1006">
            <bib>Klug, Adam. Untersuchungen über Robert Browning's Verskunst. Diss., Erlangen,
                1908. 201 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Treats syllabification, metrics, sound-patterning ("ornamentation"), and espe-
                cially stanza forms. Note the final section on twenty-six of Browning's poems in
                four-stress meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1007">
            <bib>Knedlik, Janet L. "The Prosodic Structure of John Donne's Formal Satires." Diss.,
                Harvard University, 1976.</bib>
            <notes> Not seen. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1008">
            <bib>Kroder, Armin. Shelleys Verskunst. Münchener Beiträge zur romanischen und
                englischen Philologie, no. 27. Diss., Munich, 1902. 242 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A mere list of foot-types; Charlton Lewis scorches the dissertation in his re-
                view in JEGP 6, no. 1 (1906-7): 128-33. Rev. also by Van Dam in Englische Studien 33
                (1904): 86-95. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1009">
            <bib>Kumbier, William. "Blake's Epic Meter." Studies in Romanticism 17 (1978):
                163-92.</bib>
            <notes> Actually, "Blake's Epic Rhythm": Kumbier employs musical notation for "rhythmic
                scansion." Blake's verse shows rudiments of a formulaic style, both lexically and
                metrically, and K. sets semantically correlate passages from the various Prophetic
                Books alongside each other to show three types of repeti- tion--verbatim, adaptive,
                and complex--and the nature of Blakean meter, which is "a meter of interruption, a
                highly controlled interruption, though, whereby the contesting metrical voices are
                brought into the sharpest possible contrast, often with remarkable economy." Can
                such be a meter? It is not the foot or the line that is the metrical unit, K.
                argues, but this metrically formu- laic phrase; indeed, the distinctive feature of
                the scansions here is that they change time signatures within the line very
                frequently, K. claiming a change of meter within a change of rhythm. (This seems
                extreme.) Finally, he argues that Blake's statement in the Preface to Jerusalem that
                "the terrific numbers are re- served for the terrific parts--the mild &amp; gentle
                for the mild &amp; gentle parts, and the prosaic for the inferior parts: is fully
                justified so long as no one-to-one correspondence of metric mode to meaning is
                expected. the modes are com- plexly interpermeated. In any event, the pre-eminent
                mode of the Prophetic Books, the "mild &amp; gentle," is a manifestation of the
                limited vision of Beulah, hence unreliable. K's suggestion that caesura determines
                meter is a novelty. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1010">
            <bib>Langworthy, C[harles] A. "Dryden's Influence on the Versification of Lamia."
                Research Studies of the State College of Washington 2 (1931): 117-24.</bib>
            <notes> Counting shows that Keats was indeed influenced by Dryden's Fables in writ- ing
                Lamie, specifically in his use of Alexandrines and triplets and in his avoid- ance
                of feminine rhymes. But in the more important matter of meter-in- relation-to
                syntax, statistical surveys of "clause-group endings" and couplet- types (three)
                show that Lamia is much closer to the earlier Endymion than to anything in Dryden;
                consequently, the influence must be said to be slight. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1011">
            <bib>Legouis, Émile. Quomodo Edmundus Spenserus ad Chaucerus se fingens in eclogis "The
                Shepheardes Calender" versum heroicum renovarit ac refecerit. Paris: G. Masson,
                1896.</bib>
            <notes> A study of the young Spencer's prosodic indebtedness to, and growth beyond, his
                master Chaucer. Unfortunately, Legouis believed that the standard Chau- cerian line
                was neither iambic nor pentameter but a four-stress line, and it is this form which
                he also finds in Spenser. Imitation of classical meters is also discussed. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1012">
            <bib>Legouis, Pierre. "Appendix A." Donne the Craftsman: An Essay on the Structure of
                the "Songs and Sonnets." Paris, 1928; rpt New York: Russell &amp; Russell, 1962. pp.
                85-94.</bib>
            <notes> Following Thomas Gray's suggestion (B83), Legouis proposes that a certain number
                of Donne's lines are actually "four-foot decasyllabics." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1013">
            <bib>Lindsay, Jack. "The Metric of William Blake." Preface to his Metrical Sketches by
                William Blake, With an Essay on Blake's Metric. London: The Scholartis Press, 1927.
                pp. 1-20.</bib>
            <notes> A critique of the "blighting" influence, the "mildew" of Miltonic metric on the
                early Blake, which he threw off then later (inexplicably) returned to in the
                "dissolution" of verseform of the Prophetic Books. Against this late, "slovenly
                violence of rhythm," however, there is the supple, instinctive lyricism of the early
                Poetical Sketches. Blake would have approved this sometimes-lambent
                sometimes-incadescent prose. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1014">
            <bib>Löwe, Ernst. Beiträge zur Metrik Rudyard Kipling's. Marburger Studien zur
                englischen Philologie, no. 10. Marburg: N. G. Elwert, 1906. 103 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Englische Studien 40 (1908-9): 90-93. Analysis of syllabification,
                sound-patterning, meters, and stanza-forms, mainly this last. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1015">
            <bib>Mauss, Aloisia. Stil, Metrik und deren Wechselwirkung in Scott, Byron, und
                Tennyson. Diss., Innsbruck, 1922.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1016">
            <bib>Maxwell, Sue. "Robert Herrick the Metrician." Poet-Lore 52 (1946): 353-59.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1017">
            <bib>Mayor, Joseph B. A Classification of Shelley's Metres. Bickersteth, 1888; rpt New
                York: Haskell House, 1971. 48 pp.</bib>
            <notes> An edition of 25 copies. Added to E592 as chapter 14. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1018">
            <bib>Melton, Wightman Fletcher. The Rhetoric of John Donne's Verse. Baltimore: J. H.
                Furst, 1906. 206 pp.</bib>
            <notes> His dissertation at Johns Hopkins. Rev: in MLR 3 (1907-8): 80-82; in Englische
                Studien 39 (1908): 91-94. Melton, a student of Bright's (E500), follows the theory
                of "secondary accent" here explicitly, giving a full account in Chapter Two after a
                review of Donne criticism in the first. The third chapter (half the book) presents
                Melton's thesis: the stylistic idiosyncrasy which he finds to mark Donne's
                versification indelibly is the repetition of the same word usually in the same line
                but with opposite stress (first stressed, then unstressed, or vice versa): this
                feature he calls "arsis- thesis variation." Dense complexes of such words occurring
                close together turn out to be very frequent in Donne. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1019">
            <bib>Miller, Terry. "The Prosodies of Robert Lowell." Speech Monographs 35 (1968):
                425-34.</bib>
            <notes> Though one can trace an evident loosening of metrical form in Lowell's work
                (from the early "The Quaker Graveyard in Nantucket" to the late "Skunk Hour") under
                the influence of Elizabeth Bishop, the later style represents not a weakening of
                control but rather a suiting of rhythm and rhyme to the sense rather than to a
                tight, formal, abstract pattern. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1020">
            <bib>"Mr. Swinburne as a Master of Metre." The Spectator 102 (1909): 605-6.</bib>
            <notes> "Swinburne understood how to use every metrical device that had ever been
                attempted in English verse, but he was not born with that melodious instinct which
                belonged supremely to Shakespeare." Praises the poet's capacity for perfecting
                metrical forms found undeveloped in the work of other poets. Cf. this appraisal with
                Omond's (E1029). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1021">
            <bib>Moll, Otto E. E. "Metrum" and "Versrhythmus." Der Stil von Byron's "Child Harold's
                Pilgrimage." Normannia: Germanisch-Romanische Bucherei, vol. 10. Berlin: Emil
                Felber, 1911. pp. 35-45.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1022">
            <bib>Moloney, Michael F. "Donne's Metrical Practice." PMLA 65 (1950): 232-39.</bib>
            <notes> Pace Stein (E1067), the most important technical features in Donne's verse are
                elision and stress-shift. The 1616 lines of the Songs and Sonets show 159 eli- sions
                (1 in every 10.2 lines) and 124 speech-contractions (together, 1 in every 5.7 lines)
                whereas there are nearly three times as many (elisions, 1 in every 4, elisions and
                contractions, 1 in every 3.5 lines) in the Satyres. Stress-shifts result in what La
                Drière calls "centroidal grouping" in the rhythm. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1023">
            <bib>Musgrove, Sidney. "Yeats and Arnold: A Common Rhythm." Southerly 3 (1942):
                25-26.</bib>
            <notes> Tenders the judgment that Arnold's "Haworth Churchyard" is the model for Yeats's
                metrical variety. See A. W. V.'s contemptuous reply in Notes &amp; Que- ries 185
                (1943): 20-21. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1024">
            <bib>Nethercot, Arthur H. "The Reputation of John Donne as Metrist." Sewanee Review 30
                (1922): 463-74.</bib>
            <notes> Traces the history of his prosodic reputation after Dryden. The radical shift in
                critical assessment in this century seems to have sprung from a realization that
                Donne "was the author of other poems than satires." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1025">
            <bib>Oberg, Arthur. "John Berryman: Prosody and Overneeds." John Berryman Studies 1
                (1975): 27-29.</bib>
            <notes> Reminding us of the diremption of the poem seen and the poem heard, Oberg also
                notices Berryman's tactic of giving special stresses to words of in- tense pain or
                emotion in his poems, a technique Oberg suggests we call "overstressing." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1026">
            <bib>Ogowa. Kazuo. Igirisu Roman Shi no Shiho [Prosody of English Romantic Poetry].
                Tokyo: Kenkyusha, 1976. 244 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1027">
            <bib>Ogle, Robert B. "Wyatt and Petrarch: A Puzzle in Prosody." JEGP 73 (1974):
                189-208.</bib>
            <notes> Censuring Alscher (E960) while approving Southall (E1065), Ogle argues that
                Wyatt's metrical line in his sonnets is not intended to be a pentameter at all: it
                was meant to be an imitation most directly of the Italian hendecasyllable and,
                through that, the classical logaoedic meters--the Sapphic, Alcaic, Phalaecean, and
                Asclepiadic. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1028">
            <bib>Olds, Sharon S. C. "Emerson's Innovations in Prosody: Poems (1847)." DAI 34
                (1973): 330A (Columbia).</bib>
            <notes> Critics have labelled Emerson's prosody "inept" because they have failed to
                discern that half of the poems in the 1847 Poems are prosodically conservative,
                while the other half are intentionally experimental in form. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1029">
            <bib>Omond, T. S. "Swinburne as a Metrician." The Academy 76 (1909): 32-33. See also p.
                66.</bib>
            <notes> Cf. this article with E1020. Both by Omond? </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1030">
            <bib>Ostriker, Alicia. "Song and Speech in the Metrics of George Herbert." PMLA 80
                (1965): 62-68.</bib>
            <notes> The two metrical modes misced in Herbert's lyrics derived from sources that a
                century earlier were quite divergent: the singing voice in lyric and the speak- ing
                voice in blank verse. The former is manifested in Herbert mainly in stanza-
                structure, the latter in intralinear metrical variation. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1031">
            <bib>-----. "Thomas Wyatt and Henry Surrey: Dissonance and Harmony in Lyric Form." New
                Literary History 1 (1970): 387-405.</bib>
            <notes> A piece of plain axiological cogency: "The greater degree of formal regularity
                in Surrey's verse . . . does not make him either a better poet . . . or a worse one
                . . . but first of all a different kind of poet." Wyatt is not a fumbler, and Surrey
                is not monotonous; it is simply that they have antipodal features of character, and
                hence, treatments of the verbal medium. Wyatt exalts individual experience in all
                its rough-ness; he advances himself; he loves conflict, tension; he bends and breaks
                forms to serve his will. Surrey, in contrast, values smoothness, "sweetness"; he
                prefers the submission of self in the embracing bonds of convention, the controlling
                artifice of pattern; he approves of order, resolution, law. In short, Wyatt and
                Surrey are the paradigms for two types of poet: "smooth lyric poets . . . whose
                music tends to control and contain their meaning, and rough lyric poets . . . who
                make form obey matter." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1032">
            <bib>-----. "The Three Modes in Tennyson's Prosody." PMLA 82 (1967): 273-84.</bib>
            <notes> A refulgent explication of Tennyson's prosodic development from 1830 (date of
                the earliest non-derivative work, the Poems, Chiefly Lyrical) to 1842 (when his
                poetic art had unquestionably matured), which shows that his development was not
                erratic but simply richly diverse, and coherent: Tennyson worked in three major
                metrical modes simultaneously--the irregular ode forms (mainly four-stress lines;
                very ornate), stanzaic forms (the early ones spectacular, the later simpler but more
                durable), and sustained forms (essentially the mature, musical, but grave and
                elevated blank verse). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1033">
            <bib>-----. Vision and Verse in William Blake. Madison: University of Wisconsin Press,
                1965. 224 pp. </bib>
            <notes>Based on her dissertation at Wisconsin in 1964. Rev: in MLR 61 (1966): 684-85; in
                Criticism 8 (1966): 289-93; in Papers in Language and Literature 2 (1966): 274-82;
                in South Atlantic Quarterly 65 (1966): 410-11; in JAAC 24 (1966): 107-9; in JEGP 66
                (1967): 461-63; in MP 65 (1967): 79-81. The only full-length monograph on Blake's
                versification yet written, Ostriker's book places Blake's two poetic modes, the
                short lyric and the long prophecy, in the context of both conservative and
                rebellious eighteenth-century verse- systems (couplet and blank) as a prelude to
                examining the metrics and sonics of his major poems. See especially chapters 5 and
                6. Methodologically, however, the work staggers and totters: Ostriker firmly
                distinguishes meter (pattern) from rhythm (realization) yet then pro- ceeds to use
                "basically Saintsbury's foot-scansion," marking stresses but assum- ing that "the
                structural basis of verse is the sense of regular recurrence in time." Most of the
                time only two degrees of stress are marked. This is a ground- breaking survey; we
                await now a concrete foundation. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1034">
            <bib>Padelford, Frederick M. "The Scansion of Wyatt's Early Sonnets." SP 20 (1923):
                137-52.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Anglia Beiblatt 34 (1923): 363. Recanting earlier views, the author now
                considers all of Wyatt's sonnets, early and late, written in the pentameter
                tradition, and not partly in the older tradi- tion of four-stress lines. Identifies
                fifteen permissible variations, the most dis- putable being the "monosyllabic foot
                after caesura" (arguments for alternatives are reviewed). Compares Wyatt's practice
                to that of Chaucer, Lydgate, Barclay, and Skelton to establish the existence of a
                tradition. Scansions of six sonnets conclude. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1035">
            <bib>-----. "Surrey's Contribution to English Poetry." The Poems of Henry Howard, Earl
                of Surrey. Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1920.</bib>
            <notes> 2nd rev. ed. 1928; rpt New York: Haskell House, 1966. pp. 45-46. Summarizes the
                author's view of Wyatt's prosody (see above) then appends general remarks on
                Surrey's, especially vis à vis blank verse and the sonnet form. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1036">
            <bib>Parkinson, Thomas F. "The Passionate Syntax." W. B. Yeats: The Later Poetry.
                Berkeley: University of California Press, 1964. pp. 181-231.</bib>
            <notes> Based on Yeats's interest in song-verse, his MSS scansions and notes, and his
                reading of Thomas MacDonagh (E302), P. concludes that his major metrical mode was
                stress verse, not foot verse, with some regularity of syllables as well, producing a
                loose, "mixed" metric wherein lines could be acceptable by either stress- or
                syllable-count. But Yeats's prosodic range was extraordinary, as wit- nessed by his
                command of tight stanzaic forms and formalized off-rhyme. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1037">
            <bib>Parry, John J. "A Note on the Prosody of William Morris." MLN 44 (1929):
                306-9.</bib>
            <notes> Argues that many of Morris's prosodic irregularities--especially rhyming
                stressed with unstressed syllables and identical rhymes--will dissolve if we see the
                lines as written in the Welsh cynghanedd meter rather than in any English meter.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1038">
            <bib>Paterson, Morton L. "The Prosody of John Donne." Diss., Yale University,
                1962.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1039">
            <bib>Peterson, Jane E. "Metric and Syntactic Experimentation in Blake's Prophecies of
                1788-1795." DAI 36 (1975): 3661A (Arkansas).</bib>
            <notes> Examination of metrical variations and idiosyncratic forms of syntax reveals a
                fairly clear division between the prophecies of 1788-94, wherein Blake was
                interested primarily in the possibilities of the fourteener, and those of 1794-95,
                where his interest turned to developing a "double syntax" correspondent to his wider
                double vision. The syntactic features most of interest are the use of a word to
                modify the words both preceding and succeeding it, and the equating of two words to
                a third, whereby they become equilibrated to each other. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1040">
            <bib>Pope, G[eorge] U. "Hints on the Metre." St. John in the Desert: An Introduction
                and Notes to Browning's "A Death in the Desert." London: Henry Frowde, 1897;</bib>
            <notes> rpt under the subtitle in 1904. pp. 87-89. Undeserving of attention. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1041">
            <bib>Propst, Louise. An Analytical Study of Shelley's Versification. University of Iowa
                Humanistic Studies, vol. 5, no. 3. Iowa City: The University, 1933. 74 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Based on her dissertation at Iowa in 1932. Rev: in MLN 48 (1933): 408-13; in MLR
                28 (1833): 545; in Anglia Beiblatt 44 (1933): 342-44; in Review of English Studies
                10 (1934): 493-94. A study of metrical variation and stanzaic form in Shelley's
                shorter lyrics (tabular data in the Appendices). Propst treats Shelley's meters as
                foot verse throughout, which is untrue and also inconvenient for analysis, but she
                scans closely by stresses, slacks, and missing syllables even though her prose com-
                mentaries use the exasperating, evanescent terminology of duple and triple times and
                rising and falling rhythms. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1042">
            <bib>Purves, Alan C. "Formal Structure in "Kubla Khan.'" Studies in Romanticism 1
                (1962): 187-91.</bib>
            <notes> In view of the general critical opinion of the fragmentary nature of "Kubla
                Khan," the poem is surprising in light of its great lack of metrical irregularity.
                The organization of line-lengths and rhyme schemes is very tight and orderly,
                suggesting that the poem is more complete and less fragmentary than it seems.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1043">
            <bib>-----. "The Verse Technique of Samuel Taylor Coleridge." DA 21 (1960): 190A
                (Columbia).</bib>
            <notes> Metrical analysis of the verse from 1787-1802, with separate considerations of
                all the major poems and a study of the revisions of the "Dejection" Ode, to show
                that Coleridge developed (1) independently of Wordsworth, (2) in two distinct
                styles, and (3) toward an isoaccentual (stress) meter. Seven appendices. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1044">
            <bib>Pyre, J[ames] F. A. The Formation of Tennyson's Style. A Study, Primarily, of the
                Versification of the Early Poems. University of Wisconsin Studies in Language and
                Literature, no. 12. Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1921. 249 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation at Wisconsin in 1897. Rev: in TLS, 17 November 1921,
                p. 748; by Elton in MLR 17 (1922): 427- 29; in JEGP 21 (1922): 705-9; in The Nation
                114 (1922): 23. A significant study of Tennyson's stylistic development through the
                1842 po- ems, with lesser attention to the 1850 In Memorium, the 1855 Maud poems,
                and late work. Careful tabulation of stanzaic patterns, inversions and extra syl-
                lables in the meter, and stylistic changes in revisions of poems make this book
                indispensable for any consideration of Tennyson's craft or reputation, though his
                quantitative work needs more treatment here. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1045">
            <bib>-----. "The Versification of Tennyson's Early Poems." PMLA 24 (1909): xxxii</bib>
            <notes> (Proceedings). Abstract. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1046">
            <bib>Raine, Kathleen. "A Note on Blake's 'Unfettered Verse.'" William Blake: Essays for
                S. Foster Damon. Ed. Alvin H. Rosenfeld. Providence: Brown University Press, 1969.
                pp. 383-92.</bib>
            <notes> Rapt and profuse admiration for "Blake's most characteristic line . . . a hep-
                tameter"; its origins are found in Biblical parallelisms and Macpherson's ca-
                dences. Blake's heptameter, we find, includes spondees, pyrrhics, and choriam- bics,
                but no caesura, and at times it approaches Common Meter (Chapman's influence) or
                else becomes an even longer octameter. Dictum: "In his use of the long line [Blake]
                is unequalled among English poets." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1047">
            <bib>Ramsey, Paul. The Art of John Dryden. Lexington: University of Kentucky Press,
                1969.</bib>
            <notes> To the study of Dryden's prosodic practices and (more troublesome, because less
                consistent) theoretical observations the author brings what surely must be the
                requisite temperament--supple and appreciative. The resultant book is more apologia
                than analysis. The second chapter treats the absorbing question of prosodic mimesis,
                or "representative meter"; subsequent chapters examine specific forms (the lyric,
                the quatrain, the couplet) and the major poems. The first chapter grapples with the
                most difficult issue, Dryden's theoretical posi- tion(s). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1048">
            <bib>-----. "James Dickey: Meter and Structure." James Dickey: The Expansive
                Imagination. Ed. Richard Calhoun. Deland, Florida: Everett-Edwards, 1973. pp.
                177-94.</bib>
            <notes> "The metrical history of James Dickey can be put briefly and sadly: a great
                lyric rhythm [the rising trimeter] found him, he varied it, loosened it, then left
                it, to try an inferior form [long-lined free verse]." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1049">
            <bib>Rees, D. G. "Sir Thomas Wyatt's Translations from Petrarch." Comparative
                Literature 7 (1955): 15-24.</bib>
            <notes> Wyatt's imitative work is characterized only by "jerky, stumbling, staggering
                rhythm" and a "deficient technique" which shows nothing better than the poet's
                "dogged determination to overcome technical difficulty"; his original work, however,
                shows remarkable power, invention, and control yet is supple and smooth. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1050">
            <bib>Reibetanz, Julia M. "Traditional Meters in Four Quartets." English Studies 56
                (1975): 409-20.</bib>
            <notes> The normative four-stress accentual line which Eliot developed after The Waste
                Land freed him from traditional forms and also freed him to return to them: East
                Coker IV is predominantly in iambics, while The Dry Salvages I is in dactylics.
                N.B.: the erroneous "cretic" on p. 419 suggests larger category mistakes beyond.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1051">
            <bib>Richter, Rudolf. "Der Vers bei Dr. John Donne." Beiträge zur neueren Philologie.
                Ed. Jakob Schipper. Vienna and Leipzig: Wilhelm Braumüller, 1902. pp. 391-415.</bib>
            <notes> Metrical analysis of the verse, citing frequencies and copious examples of in-
                verted stress, hovering stress, anacrusis, extra weak syllables within the line,
                elision, syncope, apocope, caesura placement, enjambement, near-rhyme, as- sonance,
                and feminine rhyme. Unfortunately the text is Grosart's 1872 edition. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1052">
            <bib>Richter, Walter J. H. Der Hiatus im englischen Klassizismus (Milton, Dryden,
                Pope). Dissertation. Schramberg: Gatzer and Hahn, 1934. 139 pp.</bib>
            <notes> As preliminary, Richter summarizes the classical, French, and Renaissance views
                of vowel-haitus. He distinguishes nine "rubrics" or types of hiatus. The bulk of the
                book simply lists examples, of course (being what it is), but the fi- nal chapter is
                of interest, giving statistics and charts on the frequency of each type in each
                author by work. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1053">
            <bib>Ridley, M. R. Keats' Craftsmanship: A Study in Poetic Development. Oxford, 1933;
                rpt New York: Russell &amp; Russell, 1962.</bib>
            <notes> Passim; se s.v. "Metre" in the Index. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1054">
            <bib>Robertson, John M. "Form in Poetry." English Review 8 (1911): 377-97.</bib>
            <notes> See also pp. 545-67. Mainly on Tennyson's radical innovations in the metrics of
                Maud, but, supported by a historical survey, Robertson urges the broader
                generalization that radical innovations of form and convention, "like threat- ened
                men and institutions, live long." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1055">
            <bib>Rudenstine, Neil L. "Style as Convention." Sidney's Poetic Development. Cambridge,
                Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1967. pp. 75-105. Rev: in Style 5 (1971):
                196-202.</bib>
            <notes> Demonstrates the extent of Sidney's purposefulness in employing the prosodic
                tools of rhyme and meter to create an ornate, highly rhetorical style. Scruti-
                nizing closely the analysis given by John Thompson (E91), the author shows that the
                relatively leaden verse of Arcadia was transformed into the expressive, supple
                medium of Astrophel through Sidney's mastery of the variations of stressing on
                monosyllables. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1056">
            <bib>Saintsbury, George. "Byron as a Prosodist." Byron the Poet: A Collection of
                Addresses and Essays. Ed. Walter A. Briscoe. London: Routledge &amp; Sons, 1924. pp.
                89-90.</bib>
            <notes> Short excerpts from Saintsbury's remarks on Byron in his History of English
                Prosody (A8). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1057">
            <bib>Schwartz, Elias. "The Meter of Some Poems of Wyatt." SP 60 (1963): 155-65.</bib>
            <notes> It is unacceptable, Schwartz argues, to hold that Wyatt wrote in sometimes ac-
                centual, sometimes accentual-syllabic meter, changing metrical conventions even
                within a single poem. A preferable alternative, he proposes, is to hold that all of
                his verse is in the old four-stress accentual meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1058">
            <bib>Sembower, Charles J. "A Note on the Verse-Structure of Carew." Studies in Language
                and Literature [for] James Morgan Hart. New York: Henry Holt, 1910. pp.
                456-66.</bib>
            <notes> His prosodic fingerprints are (1) varying line-lengths, (2) verse-paragraphs,
                (3) illative development, and (4) (usually) a six-line stanza rhyming a b a b c c.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1059">
            <bib>Siemens, Lloyd. "Hardy and the 'Jewelled Line' of Poetry." Four Decades of Poetry
                1 (1976): 40-50.</bib>
            <notes> Hardy's stark, spare, deliberately harsh prosodic style rests in part on his
                notions of a "cunning irregularity of rhythm" and on speech rhythms which thwart
                rather than counterpoint the meter. But in his willingness to experiment with
                verse-forms, meters, and diction Hardy was inspired not by his own beliefs but by
                his polyglot neighbor William Barnes, who also influenced Hopkins strongly. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1060">
            <bib>Sigwart, Gustave A. "The Roughness of John Donne's Verse." DA 33 (1972): 4364A
                (Fordham).</bib>
            <notes> Collects (1) treatises on versification from the period of Donne's youth, (2)
                Donne's practice in his second and fourth Satyres to compare with the theo- ries,
                (3) all known critical comments on Donne's versification, and (4) Pope's imitations
                of the Satyres for contrast. Jonson's famous comment is found to be baseless.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1061">
            <bib>Sinfield, Alan. The Language of Tennyson's "In Memorium." Oxford: Basil Blackwell;
                New York: Barnes and Noble, 1971. Se Chapter 10, "Rhythm: Norms and Variations," pp.
                173-95.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1062">
            <bib>Skelton, Robin. "Craft and Ceremony: Some Notes on the Versecraft of Robert
                Graves." Malahat Review, no. 35 (1975), pp. 37-48.</bib>
            <notes> Graves's earlier work is distinguished by the virtuosity with which he imitates
                the complex sound patterns of Welsh meters; his later work seems to be in Sprung
                Rhythm. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1063">
            <bib>Smith, Hallet. "The Art of Sir Thomas Wyatt." Huntington Library Quarterly 9
                (1946): 323-55.</bib>
            <notes> Versification is discussed steadily throughout, but see esp. pp. 327 ff and 347
                ff. Smith makes a persuasive case for the integrity of Wyatt's craftsmanship and
                censures sharply the methods and conclusions of Foxwell (E990) and Padelford
                (E1034). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1064">
            <bib>Spenser, Edmund. Shepheards Calendar: Containing Twelve Eclogues Proportionable to
                the Twelve Months. Ed. C. H. Herford. London: Macmillan, 1914.</bib>
            <notes> In section 25 of the Introduction on "Verse" (pp. lxvi-lxxi, but based on pp.
                xlviii-1) Herford identifies three meters in the Calendar: Accentual, Ballad, and
                Strophic. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1065">
            <bib>Southall, Raymond. The Courtly Makers: An Essay on the Poetry of Wyatt and his
                Contemporaries. Oxford: Basil Blackwell; New York: Barnes and Noble, 1964.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation at the University of Birmingham in 1961. In chapter 10
                on "Harmony of Numbers" Southall makes caustic remarks on the work of Foxwell (E990)
                and Padelford (E1034), jeering at their lists of ac- ceptable deviations and,
                indeed, any attempt of "classical prosody" to see Wyatt's lines as iambic
                pentameters. The following chapter explicates the author's own view of "The
                Construction of Wyatt's Verse": Wyatt's line "tends to fall into phrasal units
                separated by pauses, the values of which depend upon the general significance of the
                communication, so that the fundamental char- acter of the rhythm is due to the
                requirements of intonation, a feature that re- ceives no recognition from classical
                prosody." In short, it is a recognizable remnant of the older hemistichic line.
                Southall believes that manuscript punc- tuation (esp. the virgule) was used to
                denote rhythmical phrasing. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1066">
            <bib>Stein, Arnold. "Donne's Harshness and the Elizabethan Tradition." SP 41 (1944):
                390-409.</bib>
            <notes> The term "harsh" seems to have meant any disappointment or thwarting of the
                verse-reader's expectations, either metrical or semantic. The English Parnassus (see
                E520) offers "sweet" and "harsh" (presumably antithetical) as descriptions for the
                placing of "Accents." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1067">
            <bib>-----. "Donne's Prosody." PMLA 59 (1944): 373-97.</bib>
            <notes> Donne's metrical idiom commonly includes stress-shift (unusually frequent),
                missing syllables at the beginning or end of the line or around the caesural pause,
                the pyrrhic + spondee double foot, elision (required and optional), and allowable
                (or essential) extra syllables. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1068">
            <bib>-----. "Meter and Meaning in Donne's Verse." Sewanee Review 52 (1944): 288-
                301.</bib>
            <notes> It is only by meaning that we will come safely to meter in Donne, and not the
                other way around. His "wrenched accents" are rhetorical and intentional; they reach
                for a higher plane of sense--and art--than that of an invariant, regular meter.
                Coleridge recognized this. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1069">
            <bib>-----. "Structures of Sound in Donne's Verse." Kenyon Review 13 (1951): 20-36,
                256-78.</bib>
            <notes> Pages 261-63 are revised, expanded, and republished as </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1070">
            <bib>"Donne's Prosody" in the the symposium "English Verse and What It Sounds
                Like"</bib>
            <notes> (E714) with a following response by Seymour Chatman, "Mr. Stein on Donne"
                (E710). A larger passage, pp. 256-68, is reprinted in a further revised form as the
                section </notes>
        </item>




        <item id="E1071">
            <bib>"Meter and Meaning" in Stein's John Donne's Lyrics: The Eloquence of Action
                (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1962), pp. 38-46</bib>
            <notes>, which is again reprinted in Gross (A23), pp. 193-201. Mr. Stein seems to have
                been content to rest there, publishing the same material only four times, but note
                also his four other studies on the same subject antecedent to the Kenyon forum,
                E1066, E1067, E1068, and E1419. Section 2 of the original essay discusses the
                quasi-accentual verse tradi- tion visible in Wyatt, as in Donne; it is not the same
                tradition that runs, iambi- cally, from Surrey to Spenser. Section 3 focuses on
                Donne as "a conscious master of harshness"; sections 4, 5, and 6 inquire into the
                possibilities for imi- tation or at least reinforcement of sense by sound. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1072">
            <bib>Stein, Harold. "A Note on the Versification of 'Childe Harold.'" MLN 42 (1927):
                34-35.</bib>
            <notes> Over the four Cantos enjambement steadily increases in frequency. Metrical
                constraints in the first two are very tight, suggesting that Byron is effectually
                writing couplets. By the fourth, however, this couplet-structure is abruptly
                discarded, perhaps under the influence of the ottava rima. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1073">
            <bib>Stokes, Edward. "The Metrics of Maud." Victorian Poetry 2 (1964): 97-110.</bib>
            <notes> Extraordinarily detailed inspection of the poem, section by section. Stokes is
                able to show that the frequent metrical shifts are motivated by concomitant shifts
                in tone or character much more successfully that he is able to find valid
                descriptors for the meters themselves--are they iambic and anapestic, or tro- chaic
                and dactylic? The labels do not serve well at all here. There is a lesson in this.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1074">
            <bib>Thurnwald, Helene. Der Metrik Christina Georgina Rossetti's. Diss., Vienna,
                1906.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1075">
            <bib>Van Doren, Mark. The Poetry of John Dryden. New York: Harcourt, Brace, 1920; </bib>
            <notes>rev. ed. 1931; rpt 1946; rpt as John Dryden: A Study of His Poetry. Bloomington:
                Indiana University Press, 1960. Especially chapter 3. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1076">
            <bib>Wallerstein, Ruth C. Richard Crashaw: A Study in Style and Poetic Development.
                University of Wisconsin Studies in Language and Literature, no. 37. Madison:
                University of Wisconsin Press, 1935.</bib>
            <notes> Remarks on meter, passim, esp. on pp. 39-46. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1077">
            <bib>Wallins, Roger P. "Prosody in 'Dover Beach', Lines 1-10." Arnoldian 4 (1977):
                9-10.</bib>
            <notes> Scansion reveals adumbrations of the theme of the poem--the shift from tran-
                quility to quickening, troubling change--in the meter of the first stanza. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1078">
            <bib>Wasserman, Earl R. "Coleridge's 'Metrical Experiments.'" MLN 55 (1940): 432- 33;
                63 (1948): 491-92.</bib>
            <notes> See E511. These two articles, along with Otto Ritter's "Coleridgiana" in Eng-
                lische Studien 58 (1924): 377, are able to show that three of the seven poems are
                not Coleridge's but simply copied out by him. Wasserman therefore ques- tions his
                authorship of any of them. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1079">
            <bib>Weaver, Bennett. "Shelley Works Out the Rhythm of 'A Lament.'" PMLA 47 (1932):
                570-76.</bib>
            <notes> "To Shelley poetry came hard," and judging from the evidence of several pre-
                liminary drafts of this poem, he worked from both a few key nouns and a fairly
                explicit rhythmical pattern (here, basically iambic trimeter), allowing both the
                semantic and metrical domains to interaffect each other during com- position.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1080">
            <bib>White, Rita A. S. "The Prosody of Michael Drayton's Pastorals." DAI 32 (1972):
                4583A (Tennessee).</bib>
            <notes> Drayton's revisions of his pastorals from 1590 to 1630 show a stead develop-
                ment toward metrical simplicity, precision, and "delicacy." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1081">
            <bib>Williams, Francis H. "Browning's Form." Poet-Lore 2 (1890): 300-5.</bib>
            <notes> Compares Browning's metrical variations to those of Milton and Tennyson: on
                internal pauses and feminine endings he is much more conservative; on foot-
                substitution he is more liberal (Temporalist scansion accepted). Then metrics is
                dismissed altogether as "machinery." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1082">
            <bib>Wilson, J. Dover. "A Note on Elisions in The Faerie Queene." MLR 15 (1920):
                409-14.</bib>
            <notes> Objecting to Bayfield's theory (E1093) which denies elision in Shakespearean
                lines, Wilson turns to Spenser, where he finds copious examples of the apos- trophe
                used to denote syllabic loss for the sake of the meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1083">
            <bib>Yohannan, J. D. "Tennyson and Persian Poetry." MLN 57 (1942): 83-92.</bib>
            <notes> The author's suggestion that Tennyson interested himself in Persian metrical
                forms is denied by W. D. Paden in his reply, 58 (1943): 652-56, with rejoin- der by
                Yohannan, p. 656. Paden again responds, with a bit of additional evi- dence, at 60
                (1945): 284. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1084">
            <bib>Young, James D. "The Possibility of Form: A Study of the Prosody of Sir Thomas
                Wyatt." Diss., Rice University, 1956.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1085">
            <bib>Ziesenis, Otto. Der Einfluss des Rhythmus auf Silbenmessung, Wortbildung,
                Formenlehre, und Syntax bei Lyly, Greene, und Peele. Diss., Kiel, 1915. Heidelberg:
                Carl Winter, 1915. 118 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Extends the work of Stroheker (E1319) on "doublets" to three other Renais- sance
                poets. See also: B12-13, B63, B171, B188, C79, D294, D309, E56, E1149, E1213, I2,
                I15, K389-90, N92. </notes>
        </item>





    </chapter>
</bibliography>
