<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="">

        <item id="E1086">
            <bib>Addison, Joseph. The Spectator [1711-12]. Ed. Donald F. Bond. 5 vols. Oxford:
                Clarendon Press, 1965.</bib>
            <notes> In nos. 58-63 Addison defines "false wit," which, as opposed to "true wit,"
                which discerns a surprising resemblance of ideas or of similar features in oth-
                erwise-dissimilar objects (discordia concours), produces a mere similarity of
                letters (anagrams, acrostics), syllables (doggerel rhymes, bouts-rimées), words
                (puns), or "whole sentences or poems, cast into the figures of eggs, axes, or
                altars." In no. 285 (on perspicuity and sublimity of Milton's language), Milton is
                praised for the variety he acheives in his numbers by elisions. No. 39 defends blank
                verse as the proper medium for tragedy. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1087">
            <bib>Alexander, Peter. "Conjectural History, or Shakespeare's Henry VIII." Essays and
                Studies 16 (1930): 85-120.</bib>
            <notes> The student lacking time for a discursive essay should read only section IV,
                where Alexander supports the view that Shakespeare was the sole author, by attacking
                the metrical tests of Spedding, Hickson, and the others, on the grounds that the
                stylistic characteristics claimed to be distinctly Fletcher's in fact occur often in
                the later Shakespeare. But no statistics are given in support. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1088">
            <bib>Allen, John D. Quantitative Studies in Prosody II: Elements of English Blank
                Verse. Johnson City: East Tennesee State University Press, 1968.</bib>
            <notes> A historical-statistical survey of metrical features, Spenser to Frost. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1089">
            <bib>Baker, Howard. "The Formation of the Heroic Medium." Introduction to Tragedy: A
                Study in a Development of Form in "Gorboduc," "The Spanish Tragedy," and "Titus
                Andronicus." University, La.: L.S.U. Press, 1939. pp. 48-105.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1090">
            <bib>-----. "Some Blank Verse Written by Thomas Norton Before Gorboduc." MLN 48 (1933):
                529-30.</bib>
            <notes> It was used in a passage from the Aeneid in Calvin's Institute of the Christian
                Re- ligion translated by Norton. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1091">
            <bib>Banks, Theodore H., Jr. "Miltonic Rhythm: A Study of the Relation of the Full
                Stops to the Rhythm of Paradise Lost." PMLA 42 (1927): 140-45.</bib>
            <notes> Banks notes that since nearly half of Milton's sentences end in mid-line, and
                since he uses inversions of accent freely, we should recognize that the "sen- tence
                structure" in the verse is superordinate to the meter (line structure). Re- ply by
                Diekhoff (E1143); see also Treip (E1327). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1092">
            <bib>[Bathurst, Charles.] Remarks on the differences in Shakespeare's versification in
                different periods of his life and on like points of difference in poetry generally.
                London: John W. Parker and Son, 1857; rpt New York: AMS Press, 1970. 218 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Two of the nine sections in the book (nos. 2 &amp; 3) are on Shakespeare; the
                in- forming principle is that the style of each play (not isolated passages within
                the plays) is sufficiently distinct from all the rest to allow dating on such
                evidence. Section 2, however, gives mainly only long extracts from the plays;
                section 3 summarizes the general conclusions. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1093">
            <bib>Bayfield, M. A. A Study of Shakespeare's Versification, With an Inquiry into the
                Trustworthiness of the Early Texts, An Examination of the 1616 Folio of Ben Jonson's
                Works, and Appendices, Including a Revised Text of "Antony and Cleopatra."
                Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1920; rpt Norwood, Pa.: Norwood Editions,
                1976.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Anglia Beiblatt 34 (1923): 325-38; by Tatlock in MP 18 (1921): 504-5; by
                Bright in MLN 36 (1921): 63-64; in TLS, 26 February 1920, p. 136. This book draws on
                three earlier articles published in TLS, 23 May-13 June 1918, pp. 242, 265, 277,
                290; discussed in subsequent correspondence by Simpson, Wilson, and O'Neill, pp.
                301, 313, 325, with a summary reply to all three by Bayfield on 1 August, pp.
                361-62. See also Wilson (E411, N136). Bayfield's theory has two principal features:
                he believes that metrical eli- sions were not intended by Shakespeare but were the
                result of house styling for the First Folio; they therefore should be "resolved"
                (i.e., expanded), re- sulting in many trisyllabic feet. (This theory is as queer as
                it sounds, but in fact Saintsbury too thought elisions "hideous.") Second, he
                believes that English verse is actually trochaic rather than iambic--it is only that
                poets regularly add an extra upbeat syllable and drop the requisite final syllable,
                for some reason or other. This view, which is nothing but eccentricity in the finest
                English tradi- tion, is also propounded in E336 and in E1094 "Our Traditional
                Prosody and an Alternative." MLR 13 (1918): 157-82. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1095">
            <bib>Berdan, John M. Early Tudor Poetry: 1485-1547. New York: Macmillan, 1920.</bib>
            <notes> Some notes close to the end on Surrey and blank verse; see also pp. 145-52 on
                the medieval conception of "rithm." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1096">
            <bib>Bernhart, A. Walter. Ein metrisch-rhythmische Vergleich der beiden Fassungen von
                Wordsworths "Prelude." [A Metrical and Rhythmical Comparison of the Two Versions of
                Wordsworth's Prelude Employing a Graphical Method of Analysis Based on Phonological
                Principles.] Diss., University of Graz (Vienna), 1973. Vienna: Verband des
                Wissenschaftlichen Gesellschaften Osterreichs, 1973.</bib>
            <notes> Summary in English and American Studies in German: A Supplement to Anglia, 1972,
                pp. 98-100. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1097">
            <bib>Beum, Robert. "So Much Gravity and Ease." Language and Style in Milton. Ed. Ronald
                D. Emma and John T. Shawcross. New York: Frederick Ungar, 1967. pp. 333-68.</bib>
            <notes> The one sharp focus of proper perspective, we remember, is a resultant of fused
                twin perspectives: Beum offers here both (1) a lengthy and careful survey of the
                history of theories about Milton's verse-structure--from Henry John Todd and Dr.
                Johnson to James Whaler and F. T. Prince--emphasizing re- peatedly that it is the
                line as a whole, not the foot ("Milton is not a foot proso- dist") which is the
                metrical unit for Milton, a view for which he need not have gone to the Italians to
                learn; and also (2) a very full characterization of Milton's verse itself, in terms
                of rhymelessness (it offered sublimity, austerity, natural- ness, plasticity,
                dramatic propriety), alliteration and assonance, enjambment (the lines nevertheless
                end on heavy syllables), hypermetrical lines, elision, mellifluousness, strictness,
                and sonority. Beum concludes that "we need not radically revise the traditional
                description of Milton's epic verse" but reasserts his central point: the Miltonic
                line is essentially decasyllabic but not iambic. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1098">
            <bib>Binyon, Laurence. "A Note on Milton's Imagery and Rhythm." Seventeenth Century
                Studies Presented to Sir Herbert Grierson. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1938. pp.
                184-91.</bib>
            <notes> Finds that "rhythm tends to control the imagery." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1099">
            <bib>"Blank Verse." Cornhill Magazine 15 (1867): 620-40.</bib>
            <notes> Historically arranged, with examples mainly from Renaissance drama. Platitu-
                dinous. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1100">
            <bib>"Blank Verse." The Spectator 80 (1898): 372-73; commentary, pp. 409-10.</bib>
            <notes> Also in Living Age 217 (1898): 325-28. Argues that the Elizabethan playwrights,
                and Milton after them, never cared at all for the perfect iambic decasyllable:
                "their practice was to distribute the ac- cents almost at will . . . [in] absolute
                freedom." The correspondents, however, take up the Kalevala meter in Longfellow's
                "Hiawatha" and the possibility of Catullian hendecasyllabics in Browning's "One Word
                More." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1101">
            <bib>Bordukat, Gertrud. Die Abgrenzung zwischen Verse and Prosa in den Dramen
                Shakespeares. Diss., Königsberg, 1918.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Anglia Beiblatt 34 (1923): 306-8. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1102">
            <bib>Borinski, Ludwig. “Vers und Text in den Dramenmanuskripten der Shakespeare- zeit.”
                Anglia 75 (1957): 391-410.</bib>
            <notes> A review of the various explanations for metrical irregularites in the dramatic
                texts, including Simpson and Van Dam's argument over the admission of alex- andrines
                and anacrusis, the textual-corruption explanation, evidence of house- styling, and
                the theory allowing textual influence by theatrical prompbooks. The author denies
                categorically that metrical irregularities exist that are not resolvable by elision
                or expansion. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1103">
            <bib>Boyle, Robert. "Beaumont, Fletcher, and Massinger." Englische Studien 5 (1882):
                74-96; 7 (1884): 66-87; 8 (1885): 39-61; 9 (1886): 209-39; 10 (1887): 383-
                411.</bib>
            <notes> Extends the metrical-tests work begun by Fleay in order to try to corroborate or
                revise his findings about the shares of each of the three dramatists in the plays
                attributed publicly to the first two. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1104">
            <bib>-----. "Blank-Verse and Metrical Tests." Englische Studien 16 (1892):
                440-48.</bib>
            <notes> A stinging, tendentious denunciation of the methods and results of the whole
                school of verse-testers, German and English, such as Fleay, Schröer, Wilke, and
                especially König, for whom Boyle reserves his highest contempt. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1105">
            <bib>-----. "Pericles." Englische Studien 5 (1882): 363-69.</bib>
            <notes> Adduces evidence from his own metrical tests to argue for three authors in the
                play, Shakespeare, Wilkins, and Rowley. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1106">
            <bib>Bradley, A. C. "Note BB: The Date of Macbeth: Metrical Tests." In his
                Shakespearean Tragedy. London: Macmillan, 1904;</bib>
            <notes> 2nd ed. 1905. pp. 470-80. Bradley applies the Speech-Ending, Overflow, and Light
                and Weak Ending Tests to Macbeth and reaches the traditional conclusions that (1) it
                is the latest of the five tragedies, and that (2) it shows a distinct internal
                transition between the middle style and the style of the late plays. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1107">
            <bib>Bradner, Leicester. "A Test for Udall's Authorship." MLN 42 (1927): 378-80.</bib>
            <notes> In view of the extensive metrical confusion and variety shown in fifteenth-
                century texts, the high frequency and stability of Alexandrines in Ralph Roister
                Doister, Jacob and Esau, and Respublica suggest strongly that Udall is the author of
                all three. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1108">
            <bib>Brashear, Lucy M. "Character and Prosody in Shakespeare's Measure for Measure."
                DAI 30 (1969): 3424A (North Carolina).</bib>
            <notes> Finds distinctive, prosodically motivated "speech-patterns" for each character
                in the play, patterns which reveal character and hence yield an interpretation of
                the play. Separate chapters on Isabella, Angelo, the Duke, Lucio, Claudio, Juliet
                and Mariana, and Escalus. -----. Bridges, Robert. Milton's Prosody. See E491.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1109">
            <bib>Brook, G. L. The Language of Shakespeare. London: Andre Deutsch, 1976.</bib>
            <notes> Includes "Syntax," "Accidence," "Pronunciation, Spelling, and Punctuation,"
                "Metre." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1110">
            <bib>Brooke, Tucker. "The Marlowe Canon." PMLA 37 (1922): 367-417.</bib>
            <notes> See pp. 396, 406-8 for metrical evidence for and against Marlowe's hand in
                various plays. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1111">
            <bib>-----. "Marlowe's Versification and Style." SP 19 (1922): 186-205.</bib>
            <notes> Marlowe first made the blank-verse line a truly native form and a supple for-
                mal instrument; Brooke analyzes the hallmarks of his metrical style in Tambur-
                laine: the single line as unit and the verse paragraph; octosyllabics, nonasyl-
                labics, and Alexandrines; weak and hypermetrical line-ends; repetitions of phrasing
                and entire lines; and others. These features are then traced through Marlowe's later
                plays up to Edward II; his metrical style develops toward vari- ety, even as the
                lines steadily lose their ornate rhetoric and diction. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1112">
            <bib>Brown, George Dobbin. Syllabification and Accent in the "Paradise Lost."
                Baltimore: John Murphy Co.;, 1901. 73 pp.</bib>
            <notes> His dissertation at Johns Hopkins. Brown, a student of Bright's (E500), here
                applies Bright's theory of "pitch- accent" (normally unstressed syllables falling on
                a ictus position in verse are marked by a rise in pitch instead of stress) to
                Milton. That theory to the side, this work is more immediately useful for providing
                a review of the major metrical theories about Miltonic verse and an analysis of
                syllable-division and stress-placement within the line. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1113">
            <bib>Browne, George H. Notes on Shakepeare's Versification, With an appendix on the
                Verse Tests, and a short descriptive Bibliography. Boston: Ginn, Heath, and Co.,
                1884;</bib>
            <notes> 4th ed. 1901; rpt New York: AMS Press, 1973. 34 pp. A student's manual intending
                to teach a proper understanding of Shakespear- ean metrics by showing Elizabethan
                usages for caesura, accent, and contrac- tion/expansion of syllables (phonetics).
                Draws on the work of Ellis, Sweet, Abbott, Mayor, and others, but some of the
                examples are quite fanciful. Two appendices: one reviews the published work on
                metrical tests, and the other notes works on metrics from Mitford (1804) to Schipper
                (1881). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1114">
            <bib>Buell, Llewellyn M. "A Prose Period in Shakespeare's Career?" MLN 56, no. 2
                (1941): 118-22.</bib>
            <notes> Statistics to supplement the metrical tests. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1115">
            <bib>Burris, Quincy G. "'Soft! Here Follows Prose'--Twelfth Night 2, 5, 154."
                Shakespeare Quarterly 2 (1951): 233-39.</bib>
            <notes> Looking for a criterion for Shakespeare's selections of prose and verse in his
                plays, Burris rejects three common assumptions--that prose is used for (1) the lower
                classes, (2) agitation or "abnormal state of mind," or (3) "buffoonery" or low
                sentiments--and concludes that no single criterion is evident. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1116">
            <bib>Candy, Hugh C. H. Milton: the Individualist in Metre. London: Nisbet, 1934. 23 pp.
                Rpt from Notes &amp; Queries 159 (1930): 165-67, 189-92.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in TLS, 21 June 1934, p. 447; in MLR 30 (1935): 413. Examines Ovidian
                stanzas attributed to Milton; Candy argues that non- decasyllabic and metrically
                irregular lines are "frequent" in Milton. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1117">
            <bib>Chambers, David L. The Metre of "Macbeth": Its Relation to Shakespeare's Earlier
                and Later Work. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1903. 70 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Though this little monograph does explicate the metrical structure of Macbeth
                exhaustively, it is also intent to place the play in the wider context of Shake-
                speare's developing craftsmanship; the reader will find here, therefore, an equally
                valuable treatment of Shakespeare's metrical skill across the whole canon. Summary
                table of statistics on p. 68. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1118">
            <bib>Chambers, E. K., Sir. "Appendix H: Metrical Tables." William Shakespeare: A Study
                of Facts and Problems. 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1930. Vol. 2, pp.
                397-408.</bib>
            <notes> Eight Tables with Notes present statistics on Line-structure (External, Prose,
                Rhyme, Blank), Rhyme, Blank Verse Length and Syllabic-Variation, and Blank Verse
                Pause-Variation for both the "Normal Plays" and the "Abnormal Plays." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1119">
            <bib>Clark, Arthur Melville. "Milton and the Renaissance Revolt Against Rhyme." In his
                Studies in Literary Modes. Ediburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1946. pp. 105-41.</bib>
            <notes> The historical precedents and local contexts of Milton's renunciation: in Italy
                (sixteenth-century versi sciolti); in Spain (the versos sueltos); in France (almost
                nonexistent); in Germany (the Reimlosigkeit delayed by experiments in classical
                meters); and in England (Surrey and the quantitative experiments there as well).
                Concludes with a long analysis of seventeenth- and eighteenth-century opinions on
                the subject. Altogether, an excellent purview of the subject-- thorough yet
                reasonably brief. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1120">
            <bib>Clemen, Wolfgang, and Fritz Lichtenhahn. "Die dramatischen Impulse in Vers und
                Rhythmus." Jahrbuch der Deutsche Shakespeare-Gesellschaft West, 1969, pp.
                10-29.</bib>
            <notes> Clemen argues that though rhythm is one of the most powerful elements in drama,
                its effects are unconscious and its dramatic functions scarcely under- stood. Thus,
                ordinary naming, counting, and scanning of meter is useless. Be- sides stress,
                pitch, tempo, tone-color, volume, and ease of articulation are im- portant, as well
                as diction, register, rhetoric, and dramatic delivery. Lichten- hahn, an actor, adds
                that technical knowledge of Shakespeare's versification is crucial for the actor's
                interpretation, though beyond that point the sheer power in the lines can be
                harnessed only by rhythmic stylization. He cites three ex- amples in Lear where
                verse-technique creates character. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1121">
            <bib>Cobb, Charles W. "Milton and Blank Verse in Spain." PQ 42 (1963): 264-67.</bib>
            <notes> Following Prince, Cobb suggests referents for the "Spanish poets of prime note"
                who used blank verse, mentioned by Milton in the Preface to Paradise Lost. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1122">
            <bib>-----. "A Type of Four-Stress Verse in Shakespeare." New Shakespeareana 10 (1910):
                1-15.</bib>
            <notes> Cobb's argument that Shakespeare's lines are actually read (temporally speak-
                ing) as tetrameters even if they are called pentameters is an enthymeme, and his
                assumption that "a line is in no particular meter until it has been read" is simply
                false. Neither of these may be inferred from the fact that many pen- tameter lines
                have only four lexical stresses. Temporalist metrics: see E284 and E285. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1123">
            <bib>Cobb, Thomas D. "Wordsworth's Style and Versification in The Prelude." DA 19
                (1959): 2948A (Emory, 1954).</bib>
            <notes> Only 22% of the lines in The Prelude are regular pentameters; Wordsworth
                employed a number of metrical devices--inversions, heavy and light feet, shifts of
                caesura, occasional extra syllables, and monosyllables to slow down the rhythm--to
                achieve variety within the traditional constraints. In comparison the
                verse-paragraphing, syntax, and diction are relatively direct. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1124">
            <bib>Collins, J[ohn] Churton. "The Text and Prosody of Shakespeare." In his Studies in
                Shakespeare. Westminster: Archibald Constable, 1904. pp. 297-331.</bib>
            <notes> A review of Van Dam and Stoffel (E1136) which takes up prosody only in the last
                five pages; Collins had aquitted himself better if he had said nothing at all.
                Shakespearean harmony, he says, can no more be found by reducing metrical variations
                to rule "than the secret of life by the scalpel of the anatomist." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1125">
            <bib>Conrad, Hermann. "Metrische Untersuchungen zur Feststellung der Abfassungs- zeit
                von Shakespeare's Dramen." Shakespeare Jahrbuch 31 (1895): 318-53.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1126">
            <bib>-----. "Eine neue Methode der chronologischen Shakespeare-Forschung." GRM 1
                (1909): 232-48, 307-20.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1127">
            <bib>Cook, Albert. "Milton's Abstract Music." University of Toronto Quarterly 29
                (1960): 370-85;</bib>
            <notes> rpt in Milton: Modern Essays in Criticism. Ed. Arthur E. Barber. New York:
                Oxford University Press, 1965. pp. 398-415. Rhythmically Milton's great
                accomplishment is PL was to create "a strong- ribbed structure of accents [which]
                constantly buoys up line by line the mighty periods. . . . by assigning all [the]
                accents nearly equal value. . . . each succes- sively primary." This sustentation of
                an elevated voice is the exact opposite of the effect in PR, where the leveling of
                accents works as gradation ("the syllabic pattern keeps the accents from being
                pronounced, and the accents keep the syllabic pattern from being incantatory"),
                while in SA the equipoised accents create a "rhythmic indeterminacy" wherein every
                line has two or more possi- ble readings (and scansions) simultaneouly. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1128">
            <bib>Copeland, Thomas Arthur. "A Theory of Metrical Structure with Special Empha- sis
                on Milton's Epic Blank Verse." DAI 32 (1971): 3244A (Northwestern).</bib>
            <notes> Copeland "examines prevalent theories of meter . . . and presents a Prosody" of
                PL and PR; what these might be, we are left to wonder from the abstract. But there
                are four Appendices: a list of compound-word stressings; "a list of lines containing
                metrical inversions created by disyllabic and polysyllabic words"; a list of words
                whose stressings vary; and a list of disyllabic and poly- syllabic words showing
                "the strength of each syllable and its location in both the word and the line."
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1129">
            <bib>Crane, Milton. Shakespeare's Prose. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
                1951.</bib>
            <notes> See Appendix I, "A Note on the Printing of Prose and Verse in Shakespeare," pp.
                197-202. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1130">
            <bib>Crannell, Kenneth C. "A Metrical Analysis of Robert Frost's 'The Hill Wife.'"
                Studies in Interpretation, Volume 2. Ed. Esther M. Doyle and V. H. Floyd. Amsterdam:
                Rodopi, 1977. pp. 99-114.</bib>
            <notes> Complete line-by-line scansion and discussion, employing the Trager-Smith
                4-level numerical notation. The norm is iambic, with considerable substitu- tion;
                Crannell allows spondees and pyrrhics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1131">
            <bib>Craven, Dorothy H. "Cowper's Use of 'Slight Connection' in The Task: A Study of
                Structure and Style." Diss., University of Colorado, 1954.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1132">
            <bib>Creizenach, Wilhelm. "Verskunst und Stil." In his Geschichte des neueren Dramas. 4
                vols. Halle, 1909. Vol. 4, pp. 358-400.</bib>
            <notes> Translated by Cécile Hugon (with author's revisions) in 1916 as E1133 The
                English Drama in the Age of Shakespeare; rpt New York: Haskell House, 1964. Book
                VII, "Versification and Style," pp. 315-52, treats of metrical polish, use of rhyme,
                alliteration, use of differing verseforms to mark characters or style, use of prose,
                and rhetorical figures. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1134">
            <bib>Daiches, David. "The Opening of Paradise Lost." The Living Milton: Essays by
                Various Hands. Ed. Frank Kermode. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1960. pp.
                55-69.</bib>
            <notes> An explication--primarily prosodic in method but rather mechanical in execu-
                tion--of the first twenty-six lines. As the author himself observes, "it is not dif-
                ficult to discuss Milton's sound patterns and his handling of verbal cadence."
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1135">
            <bib>Dam, B. A. P. van, and C. Stoffel. Chapters on English Printing, Prosody, and
                Pronunciation (1550-1700). Anglistische Forschungen, vol. 9. Heidelberg, 1902;</bib>
            <notes> rpt New York: AMS Press, 1973. 206 pp. Contents: 1. "High-handed Ways of
                Elizabethan and Jacobean Printers." 2. "The Dogma of the 'Extra Syllables' in the
                Heroic and Blank Verse Line (16th and 17th Century)." 3. "An Inquiry into the Use of
                the Synizesis in Shake- spearean and Miltonic Verse." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1136">
            <bib>-----. William Shakespeare: Prosody and Text. Leyden: E. J. Brill, 1900. Rev: in
                Anglia Beiblatt 13 (1902): 322-25.</bib>
            <notes> Part One, "Prosody," has chapters on Additional Syllables, Aphaeresis, Synize-
                sis, Syncope, Dropping of Consonants, Apocope, Synalepha, Coalition, Drop- ping of
                an Entire Word, Syllabic Accent, the Heroic Line, and Structure and History of the
                Blank Verse Line (pp. 209-68). (The text is the 1895 Globe edi- tion.) Part Two is
                "Criticism of the Text of Shakespeare." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1137">
            <bib>Daniels, Edgar F. "Climactic Rhythms in 'Lycidas.'" American Notes &amp; Queries 6
                (1968): 100-1.</bib>
            <notes> The meter of the two climactic lines, 82-171, is identical. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1138">
            <bib>David, Richard. The Janus of Poets: Being an Essay on the Dramatic Value of
                Shakespeare's Poetry, Both Good and Bad. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
                1935.</bib>
            <notes> A prize-essay on Shakespeare's versecraft, arranged chronologically. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1139">
            <bib>Dawson, Benjamin. "Shakespeare's Metre." Englische Studien 11 (1888):
                174-76.</bib>
            <notes> Defends the existence of the pyrrhic foot against Elze. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1140">
            <bib>Delius, Nikolaus. "Die Prosa in Shakespeares Dramen." Shakespeare Jahrbuch 5
                (1870): 227-73.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1141">
            <bib>Diekhoff, John S. "Milton's Prosody in the Poems of the Trinity Manuscript." PMLA
                54 (1939): 153-83.</bib>
            <notes> The description of later Miltonic blank verse given by Bridges in Milton's Pros-
                ody (E491) is here confirmed for Milton's early poetry as well: it is "regularly
                iambic and decasyllabic," and Milton definitely "scanned his verse in one way and
                read it in another." Thus, throughout all his pentameter verse, whether blank or
                rhymed, Milton scrupulously insures by the strategy of elision that his lines shall
                contain ten and only ten syllables. (The tetrameter verse however is frequently
                heptasyllabic.) There is a regular inverse correlation between date of composition
                and strictness of verse design in Milton; the latest verses are the freest, the
                earliest the tightest. Rhyming and stanza in Lycidas are also exam- ined by
                Diekhoff. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1142">
            <bib>-----. "The Punctuation of Comus." PMLA 51 (1936): 757-68.</bib>
            <notes> Milton punctuated for three purposes--rhetorical/elocutionary, grammatical, and
                rhythmical--and when, in the superimposition of verse pattern on syntac- tic
                pattern, he had to make a choice, pointing (or absence thereof) for the sake of
                versification was generally given preference. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1143">
            <bib>-----. "Terminal Pause in Milton's Verse." SP 32 (1935): 235-39.</bib>
            <notes> A reply to Banks (E1091). "Milton considered the line as a more or less iso-
                lated unit of verse to be indicated as such by some sort of breath pause or lin-
                gering at the end." Diekhoff's view emphasizes the integrity of the line as op-
                posed to the "verse-paragraph" or sentence--i.e. the meter as opposed to the syntax.
                See also Treip (E1327). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1144">
            <bib>Dobrée, Bonamy. Histriophone. London: The Hogarth Press, 1925. 40 pp.</bib>
            <notes> The interlocutors in Professor Dobrée's essay on dramatic poesie survey the
                whole tradition of blank verse, interpreting its development "histriophoni-
                cally"--as a dramatic instrument, that is--rather more than "prosodically"--in terms
                of rules and permissible substitutions--though the essence of that inter- pretation
                is a theory of three principal stresses to the line and "breath-groups." More
                engaging still is the larger argument that blank verse (the dramatic effect of which
                is speed and fluidity) and dramatic prose (the effect of which is rhythmic
                deceleration and delay) were evolving, in the later Shakespeare, and could still
                evolve into a higher form of "stage-prose," more stylized than common speech, yet
                more supple than the blank-verse line, than even the dramatic medium of The Tempest,
                which was "too subtle . . . too fine for the stage." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1145">
            <bib>Doleschal, A. "Der Versbau in Thomas Kyd's Dramen: Ein Beiträg zur Geschichte der
                englischen Metrik." Programm Steyr, 1892. 23 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1146">
            <bib>Donow, Herbert S. "Linear Word Count as a Function of Rhythm: An Analysis of
                Shakespeare's Sonnets." Hephaistos 1 (1970): 1-27.</bib>
            <notes> Interested in the rhythmic effects of trivial monosyllabic function words, Donow
                sorts the 2,155 lines of the sonnets first by number of words, then also by
                function-word appearance. These 136 words represent only 4% of the total vocabulary
                used in the Sonnets (3,211 words) but account for a surprising 55 % of the actual
                words used. Since the stressing of polysyllables is relatively rigid compared to
                that of monosyllables, lines heavy in the latter will show greater metrical variety.
                The author invites further analysis of the data presented in this typology. Based on
                the Rollins variorum text. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1147">
            <bib>Draper, John W. "King James and Shakespeare's Literary Style." Archiv 171 (1937):
                36-48.</bib>
            <notes> Would a worldly-wise dramatist adapt his style to the interests of a new, lan-
                guage-conscious king? The evidence of meter, rhyme, and alliteration is dis- cussed
                on pp. 38-40. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1148">
            <bib>Dunbar, Georgia. "The Verse Rhythms of Antony and Cleopatra." Style 5 (1971):
                231-45.</bib>
            <notes> The author's tactic of working through the play citing statistics on metrical
                variation (syntactic and pausal) without a single illustration leaves the unfortu-
                nate impression that the statistics not the variations are the source of meaning in
                characterization, making the essay virtually useless to the reader and also un-
                pleasant to read. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1149">
            <bib>Eckert, Charles W. "The Poetry of Henry Howard, Earl of Surrey." DAI 21 (1961):
                1939A (Washington).</bib>
            <notes> A critical text and notes for fifty-four poems, with discussion of musical set-
                tings, which Eckert believes the poems were intended for. "Surrey's prosody . . . is
                shown to be heavily influenced by the humanist reaction against rhyme, intricate
                stanza forms, and short line, and less regular than it has been believed to be."
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1150">
            <bib>Ehrl, Charlotte. Sprachstil und Charakter bei Shakespeare. Heidelberg, 1957. 194
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> The differentiation of characters is effected by means which are linguistic, of
                course, and to a much lesser extent prosodic, as in the alternation of prose, blank
                verse, and couplets. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1151">
            <bib>Eichhorn, Traudl. Prosa und Verse im Vorshakespeareschen Drama: Ein Beitrag zum
                Formproblem des Englischen Renaissancedramas. Diss., Munich, 1949. 173 pp. Rpt in
                Shakespeare Jahrbuch 86 (1950): 140-98.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1152">
            <bib>Ekwall, Eilbert. "Die Shakespeare-Chronologie." GRM 3 (1911): 90-108.</bib>
            <notes> Bibliographical-review essay. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1153">
            <bib>Eliot, T. S. "A Note on the Verse of John Milton." Essays and Studies 21 (1936):
                32-40.</bib>
            <notes> Eliot's famous censure of Milton: his language is "artificial and conventional,"
                his verse is nothing but "mazes of sound" detached from sense: "the inner mean- ing
                is separated from the surface." Eliot here explores the Miltonic branch of the
                "dissociation of sensibility" theory he had earlier proposed. This essay, and also
                Eliot's </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1154">
            <bib>Eliot, T. S."Milton" in Proceedings of the British Academy 33 (1947): 61-79</bib>
            <notes> , were cut considerably when reprinted as "Milton I" and "Milton II" in his On
                Poetry and Poets. New York: Noonday Press, 1961. pp. 156-64, 165-83. Discussed in
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1155">
            <bib>P. F. Armin, "Eliot on Milton: Tone as Criticism." Miscellanea Anglo- Americana:
                Festschrift für Helmut Viebrock. Ed. Kuno Schuhmann et al. Munich: Karl Pressler,
                1974. pp. 184-201.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1156">
            <bib>-----. "Notes on the Blank Verse of Christopher Marlowe." In his The Sacred Wood.
                London: Methuen, 1920; rpt New York: Barnes &amp; Noble, 1960. pp. 86-94.</bib>
            <notes> Eliot develops here the earliest part of his famous thesis that blank verse
                achieved its finest form in the Renaissance but withered after Milton--which is that
                Marlowe was the first great master of the form, achieving "the melody of Spenser"
                and "a new driving power by reinforcing the sentence period against the line
                period." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1157">
            <bib>-----. "Shakespeares Verskunst." Der Monat 2 (1950): 198-207.</bib>
            <notes> In constrast to those identifying Early, Middle, and Late styles, Eliot insists
                on the irrefrangible unity of Shakespeare's development, most importantly in its
                elevation of the natural colloquial language into a more refined arena. A sur- vey
                of Shakespeare's contemporaries reveals how crude their versification was in
                comparison; Shakespeare surpassed them in writing genuine dialogue and in putting
                great art even in the mouths of mean characters. But Shakespeare only became a great
                poet by finding solutions to his dramatic problems, and it is this "inner necessity"
                in the nature of drama which led to the development of his verse, early (King John)
                to late (Pericles). The late plays achieve a profundity and musicality of language
                within dream-worlds where play and ritual are fused. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1158">
            <bib>Elste, Emil. Der Blankvers in den Dramen George Chapmans. Diss., Halle, 1892. 62
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Exemplifies Chapman's practices in syllabification (syncope, apocope, etc.),
                word-stressing, caesura-placement, trochaic substitutions, "ringing" and "glid- ing"
                (i.e. masculine and feminine) verse-endings, absent and extra syllables in the line,
                anomalous long and short line, lines split between two speakers (and the misprinting
                of such lines as prose), use of prose, rhyme, enjambement, and alliteration.
                Synopsis at the end. Texts used are the 1873 and 1874 editions (ed. R. H. Shepherd).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1159">
            <bib>Elze, Karl. Alexandrines in "The Winter's Tale" and "King Richard II." Halle: E.
                Karras, 1881. 12 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Sixty copies privately printed. A response to the Metrical Tests reprinted by
                Fleay in C. M. Ingleby's Occa- sional Papers on Shakespeare, criticizing the working
                definition of Alexandrines: Fleay allowed such lines as And leave you to your graver
                steps. Hermione as full twelve-syllabled, six-foot verses, whereas Elze takes them
                to be blank verse lines with trisyllabic feminine endings, x / |x x x /|x i.e.
                Hermi|one metrically and Hermi|ne in pronunciation. If we reduce the final syllable
                to a slack or elide the penultimate syllable then the number of Al- exandrines in
                the two plays (Fleay found their number unexpectedly high) is very much reduced.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1160">
            <bib>-----. "Falsche Versabtheilung bei Shakespeare." Englische Studien 11 (1888):
                362-63.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1161">
            <bib>Emerson, O. F. "The Development of Blank Verse: A Study of Surrey." MLN 4 (1889):
                cols. 466-72.</bib>
            <notes> Miltonic and Shakespearean forms of the line are contrasted to Surrey's.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1162">
            <bib>Evans, Robert O. Milton's Elisions. University of Florida Monographs, Humanities,
                no. 21. Gainesville: University of Florida Press, 1966. 67 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation, "The Theory and Practice of Poetic Elision From
                Chaucer to Milton with Special Emphasis on Milton," at Florida in 1954. Rev: in
                Studia Neophilologica 39 (1967): 184-86; in Seventeenth-Century News 26 (1968): 3-4;
                in South Atlantic Bulletin 32 (1967): 11-12. An analysis of Milton's command of the
                traditional practice of elision, with ta- bles and summaries. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1163">
            <bib>Fest, Otto. Über Surrey's Virgilübersetzung, nebst Neuausgabe des vierten Buches
                nach Tottel's Originaldruck und der bisher ungedruckten Hs. Hargrave 205 (Brit.
                Mus.). Palaestra, no. 34. Berlin: Mayer &amp; Müller, 1903.</bib>
            <notes> A complete study of Surrey's translation of the Fourth Book of the Aeneid, in-
                cluding text, comparison of earlier translations, sources, style, meter, diction,
                syntax, etc. Blank verse and metrical variation are discussed on pp. 3-8, 40-45, and
                91-94. See the critique by Immelmann (E1213). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1164">
            <bib>Finkenstaedt, Thomas. Die Verskunst des jungen Shakespeare: "Richard III,"
                "Richard II," "King John." Diss., Munich, 1955. 154 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1165">
            <bib>-----. "Zur Methodik der Versuntersuchungen bei Shakespeare." Shakespeare Jahrbuch
                90 (1954): 82-107.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1166">
            <bib>Flatter, Richard. Shakespeare's Producing Hand: A Study of his Marks of Expression
                to be Found in the First Folio. London: New York: W. W. Norton, 1948.</bib>
            <notes> A curious little book by a working translator on the line-structure, versifica-
                tion, and accidence of Shakespeare's plays. The main thesis seems to be that any
                supposed "irregularities" of meter or punctuation are actually intentional,
                semantically significant directives for stage-business (pauses, emphases). The
                argument rests virtually entirely on the Folio punctuation. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1167">
            <bib>-----. "Some Instances of Line-Division in the First Folio." Shakespeare Jahrbuch
                92 (1956): 184-96.</bib>
            <notes> Asserts more succinctly the author's theory that while some lines were halved or
                divided in the First Folio because they were too long for the frame (these broken
                lines will be restored as full long-lines by modern editors), other lines were
                divided in two which would have fitted as one. These must have been di- vided in
                manuscript, Flatter argues, and so the break in versification and white space on the
                page must be understood as denoting a silence on stage during some significant
                action or gesture. One wonders how verse-time could be so precisely equated with
                stage-time. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1168">
            <bib>Fleay, F[rederick] G[ard]. "On Metrical Tests as Applied to Dramatic Poetry."
                Transactions of the New Shakspere Society, Series 1, Part 1, 1874. pp. 1-50, 51-84
                (two papers).</bib>
            <notes> The first paper applies the metrical tests to Shakespeare, the second to
                Beaumont, Fletcher, and Massinger. Both include Notes, Tables, and extended
                discussion by other members present. In fact, the entire volume for 1874 (Se- ries
                1, Parts 1 and 2) is of interest, with many papers and convoluted discus- sions on
                the dating of the plays in the canon by means of linguistic and metri- cal evidence.
                Notice the extract from Roderick (E1288) and also Ingram's arti- cle (E1214). Fleay
                was the leader of the English scholars using Metrical Tests to order the
                Shakespearean plays. For further discussion of the validity of Fleay's and
                Furnivall's work on the meter and authorship of The Taming of the Shrew, see
                (E1326). The two papers cited are revised and rpt as Chapters 1 and E1170 3 of Part
                II of </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1170">
            <bib>Fleay, F[rederick] G[ard]. Shakespeare Manual. London: n.p., 1876;</bib>
            <notes> 2nd ed. 1878; rpt New York: AMS Press, 1970. Since a convenient reprint exists,
                I may reasonably say that the entire volume merits a leisurely examination: Part II,
                "Original Investigations," offers much technical information (statistics based on
                the Globe edition) on Shake- speare and others, though one would not wish to take
                the precise statistics as accurate. Part I also includes a brief chapter (5) on
                "Pronunciation and Metre" (pp. 66-72) and an even briefer one (12, pp. 106-9) "On
                the Tests By which Chronology and Authorship can be Determined." See now pp. 69-72,
                108, 135, 153, and 239 ff. in Fleay's Manual on the sequence of tests: Spedding, the
                first, tested for feminine endings. Fleay tests for that, prose, rhyme against blank
                verse, short lines. Ingram tested for weak and light endings. [König is 1888, over a
                decade later.] The first of the two chief papers, on Shakespeare alone, is revised
                and rpt as </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1172">
            <bib>Fleay, F[rederick] G[ard]. "Metrical Tests Applied to Shakespeare" in Shakespeare:
                The Man and the Book. Ed. C. M. Ingleby. 2 vols. London: n.p., 1877</bib>
            <notes>, 2nd ed. 1881. Vol. 2, p. 50 ff. See also König (E1229), Browne (E1113),
                Bayfield (E1093), and Spedding (E1311). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1173">
            <bib>Fletcher, Harris. "A Possible Origin of Milton's 'Counterpoint' or Double Rhythm."
                JEGP 54 (1955): 521-25.</bib>
            <notes> Using Hopkins’ terminology, Fletcher argues that the sources for the reversed
                stresses in Milton's verse--i.e., one rhythm counterpointed against another-- were
                Greek, Latin, and Hebrew metrics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1174">
            <bib>Fletcher, Priscilla. A Study of English Blank Verse 1558-1632. Colorado College
                Publications, Language Series, vol. 2, no. 19, pp. 41-65. Colorado Springs,
                1907.</bib>
            <notes> This Master's thesis provides a succinct literary history of the form from Sur-
                rey's Aeneid to Middleton, paying special attention to caesura placement. Ta- bles
                based on fifty-line samples from twenty major texts present the corrobo- rating
                statistical evidence on caesuras, end-stopping, and several devices of metrical
                variation. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1175">
            <bib>Forde, William. The True Spirit of Milton's Versification developed in a new
                systematic arrangement of the First Book of "Paradise Lost," with an introductory
                essay on Blank- Verse. London: Hurst, Chance, 1831.</bib>
            <notes> The "new arrangement" is to divide the pentameter lines into semantic units or
                phrases--Paradise Lost in free verse, as it were. How utterly odd, to obliter- ate
                all that grand metrical counterpoint on the grounds that "the difficulties arising
                from the complicated nature of the language, are increased by its distri- bution
                into Lines or Verses of ten syllables in each." Only unmitigated eccen- tricity--or
                ignorance--could hold that the great poem is "no more a succession of distinct
                portions of ten syllables, than if it were ordinary Prose." Forde identifies
                Metrical Verse with solely that which is rhymed. Sixty-two pages of introduction and
                thirty-six pages of sample text. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1176">
            <bib>Fowler, Roger. "Three Blank Verse Textures." Fowler (A12), pp. 184-99.</bib>
            <notes> Starting from a critique of Traditional prosody as "an extremely blunt instru-
                ment" for analyzing verse, Fowler examines very closely the metrical style--
                "texture"--of extracts from Tamburlaine, The Tempest, and The Prelude, so as to
                anatomize and discuss the immensely complex fabric of syntax-and- meter. "A
                distinctive verse texture or metrical style is created. . . where pat- terns of
                syntax and morphology are interwoven with patterns of minor metri- cal
                irregularities, and the scheme so established is repeated to give a cumulative
                effect." Fowler's exposition of "grammetrics" (i.e., syntacti-metrics) is pro-
                vocative and, in a way, traditional. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1177">
            <bib>Franz, Wilhelm. "Metrische-Grammatisches zu Shakespeares King Lear." Anglia 59
                (1935): 391-93.</bib>
            <notes> Grammarian-turned-critic, Franz opines that the great attraction of the plays
                lies in their highly sophisticated rhythms of emotion, which create uncon- scious
                movements in our souls and an atmosphere of sympathy around the subject-matter. The
                iambic verse-movement helps to convey emotion, but in Lear the common meters were
                not enough, and we note the disappearance of the caesura, the appearance of long
                runs of stresses. It is oppressive to watch grammarians rhapsodizing. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1178">
            <bib>-----. Shakespeare's Blankvers, mit Nachträgen zu des Verfasser's Shakespeare-
                Grammatik. Tübigen: Verlag des englischen Seminars in Tübigen, 1932; 2nd rev. ed.
                1935. 104 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Anglia Beiblatt 44 (1933): 113-14; 47 (1936): 108-9. Franz's monumental
                study of Shakespearean syntax (F66) led naturally to the consideration of the
                verse-frame across which the syntax is stretched; hence, this full-scale study was
                published separately though intended as ancillary to the larger work. But the whole
                study was thereafter added to the last revised edi- tion of the grammar, retitled
                Die Sprache Shakespeares (F67). Along with Chambers (E1118), Franz is still an
                authority to be consulted on the mecha- nism of the meter. Also contains a good
                bibliography. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1179">
            <bib>Freedman, Morris. "Dryden's 'Memorable Visit' to Milton." Huntington Library
                Quarterly 18 (1855): 99-108.</bib>
            <notes> Very cautious detective work here to find out precisely what is known (on whose
                authority, against what external evidence) about Dryden's visit to Mil- ton "to have
                leave to put his Paradise Lost into a Drama in Rhyme," in order to judge what
                inference may reasonably be drawn. See also: E1180 Swaim, Donna E. "Milton's
                Immediate Influence on Dryden." DAI 39 (1978): 904A (Arizona). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1181">
            <bib>-----. "Dryden's Reported Reaction to Paradise Lost." Notes &amp; Queries 203
                (1958): 14-16.</bib>
            <notes> Despite some anecdotal evidence to the contrary, Dryden seems not to have
                changed radically his views in favor of rhyme over the course of his career.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1182">
            <bib>-----. "Milton and Dryden on Rhyme." Huntington Library Quarterly 24 (1961):
                337-44.</bib>
            <notes> A suggestion that Milton's opinion of rhyme was intended to reconcile the
                contemporary dispute between Dryden (defending rhyme) and Sir Robert Howard (blank
                verse). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1183">
            <bib>Freeman, Donald C. "'Brave to Be a King': A Stylistic Analysis of Christopher
                Marlowe's Dramatic Poetry." DA 26 (1966): 5411A (Connecticut).</bib>
            <notes> Analysis of meter and syntax in the four major plays. In Tamburlaine, for ex-
                ample, Marlowe strengthens the line as metrical unit by placing major syntactic
                (constituent) cuts at line-end, and by matching metrical with linguistic stress.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1184">
            <bib>Furnivall, F. J. "The Stopped-Line Test." In New Shakspere Society Prospectus;
                also in The Leopold Shakespeare. London: Cassell, Petter &amp; Galpin, 1873. pp.
                xix- xxii, retitled "Metrical Tests."</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1185">
            <bib>-----. The Succession of Shakespeare's Works and the use of the metrical tests in
                settling it, &amp;. . . . London: Smith, Elder, 1874; rpt New York: AMS Press,
                1972.</bib>
            <notes> A useful review of the whole body of work on meter and chronology done by the
                members of the New Shakespeare Society. Originally appeared as the in- troduction to
                the English translation of Gervinus's Commentaries on Shakspere (1874). Interested
                persons will find a photograph of Furnivall in Shakespeare Jahrbuch 47 (1911).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1186">
            <bib>Goldstein, Leonard. "The Good Old Cause and Milton's Blank Verse." Zeitschrift für
                Anglistik und Amerikanistik 23 (1975): 133-42.</bib>
            <notes> Examines the connections between Milton's "bourgeois revolutionary attitude" and
                his versification. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1187">
            <bib>-----. "Some Suggestions on the Social Aspects of Changes in Dramatic Blank Verse
                in Elizabethan and Post Elizabethan Theatre." Cahiers Elisabethains, no. 12 (1977),
                pp. 59-64.</bib>
            <notes> Marxist explanation of the increasing prosiness of dramatic blank verse from
                Marlowe to Shirley; this tendency is “the result of the tendency of prose to re-
                place poetry as the characteristic form of expression or capitalist society," prose
                being "the form most suitable for secular rational analysis" by the bourgeoisie.
                E1187a Gordon, Ralph. "Shelley's Alastor: A Study in the Technique of Blank Verse."
                Diss.; Cornell University, 1924. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1188">
            <bib>Granville-Barker, Harley. "Shakespeare's Progress." On Dramatic Method. London:
                Sidgwick &amp; Jackson, 1931. pp. 63-112.</bib>
            <notes> Hardly technical, of course--the chapter traces Shakespeare's developing con-
                trol of the line. The preceding chapter sketches "The Making of Blank Verse Drama,"
                defending the necessity of "the artifice of form." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1189">
            <bib>Griffith, Hubert. "Antony, Cleopatra, and Others." New English Review 14 (1947):
                162-65.</bib>
            <notes> Brief remarks on Shakespeare's developing control of his blank-verse instru-
                ment, particularly in the late period, as a standard for judging actors' deliveries.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1190">
            <bib>Hall, William C. "Blank Verse." Manchester Quarterly 44 (1925): 151-66.</bib>
            <notes> Capsule history, Surrey to Tennyson, at the end: Hall emphasizes the flexibil-
                ity of the form. The only opinion worthy of note is Hall's remark that Surrey's
                blank-verse line is only a rhymeless heroic; the true form originated, mightily, in
                Marlowe. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1191">
            <bib>Halliday, F[rank] E. The Poetry of Shakespeare's Plays. London: Gerald Duckworth,
                1954. 193 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A readable book on an essential subject. Since it proceeds chronologically and
                discusses every play, though, its treatment is necessarily light at times. The long
                Introduction devotes considerable time to onomatopoeia, alliteration and asso-
                nance, and the development of rhythms against the iambic metrical base; Hal- liday
                uses a numerical scansion-notation of 1-5. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1192">
            <bib>Halsey, Joan. "Quantitative Meter and the Development of Blank Verse." DAI 31
                (1971): 655OA (Claremont, 1968).</bib>
            <notes> Argues, curiously, that it was Marlowe, in his translation of Book I of Lacan's
                Pharsalia (ca. 1585), who first wrote the truly "mature" (i.e. flexible, rich, var-
                ied) English blank verse, under the influence of Sidney and the hexametrists
                (imitators of classical meters). The techniques learned from Latin were "en-
                jambement, foot-substitution, syllaba anceps, variety of caesura, and avoidance of
                diaeresis." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1193">
            <bib>Hampsten, Richard F. "Studies in Milton's Blank Verse." DA 25 (1964): 1210A
                (Washington).</bib>
            <notes> A statistical analysis of pause in the Miltonic line, chiefly in Samson
                Agonistes. Extends the work of Oras (E1269) and Sprott (E1314). The conclusions dis-
                cussed in the Abstract are quite complicated. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1194">
            <bib>Hanford, James Holly. "Milton's Style and Versification." A Milton Handbook. New
                York: F. S. Crofts, 1929; 4th ed. 1946. pp. 292-326.</bib>
            <notes> Includes Bibliography. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1195">
            <bib>Hannemann, Eduard. Metrische Untersuchungen zu John Ford. Diss., Halle, 1988. 62
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1196">
            <bib>Harrison, J., J. Goodlet, and R. Boyle. "Report of the Tests Committee of the St.
                Petersburg Shakespeare Circle." Englische Studien 3 (1880): 473-504.</bib>
            <notes> Part I defines "run-on lines," gives copious examples of varieties, produces an
                analysis of Act 5 of The Tempest and one scene of Henry VIII, and rejects
                Furnivall's tallies. Part II adjusts the figures and principles of Ingram (E1214) on
                the "Light and Weak Endings" in the same manner, making very careful distinctions of
                varieties. The Committee concludes that verse-tests may never stand as primary
                arguments for chronology--only corroborative ones. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1197">
            <bib>Hart, Alfred. "The Number of Lines in Shakespeare's Plays." Review of English
                Studies 8 (1857): 22-31.</bib>
            <notes> Hart complins about the statistics which Fleay compiled on verse and prose in
                Shakespeare based on the Globe edition and shows plainly that the "line" in prose
                varies widely with editions, making such statistics problematic at best. Hart's own
                tabulations on the canon show that Shakespeare consistently used about eight words
                to the blank-verse line, and Hart recommends this figure as a standard for prose
                "lines." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1198">
            <bib>Hart, Walter M. "Shakespeare's Use of Verse and Prose." Five Gayley Lectures,
                1947-1954. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1954. pp. 1-17.</bib>
            <notes> Believes that Shakespeare used prose to indicate states of extreme mental agi-
                tation. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1199">
            <bib>Hauptvogel, Karl. Der Wechsel Zwischen Vers und Prosa in Shakespeare's Komödien.
                Diss., Innsbruck, 1923.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1200">
            <bib>Havens, Raymond D. The Influence of Milton on English Poetry. Cambridge, Mass.:
                Harvard University Press, 1922; rpt New York: Russell &amp; Russell, 1961.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in PQ 2 (1923): 75-76; in JEGP 22 (1923): 457-61; in MLR 18 (1923): 345-46;
                in The Nation 116 (1923): 575-76. Contains: "The Attitude of the Eighteenth Century
                Toward Milton" "Blank Verse and Rime" "Prosody and Diction" "The Influence of
                Paradise Lost" "The Characteristics of Paradise Lost and Their Relation to
                Eighteenth- Century Blank Verse" "Wordsworth" "Keats" "The Influence Outside of
                Blank Verse: Ossian, Blake, Shelley, Byron" "The Influence of Paradise Lost as Shown
                in the More Important Types of Blank-Verse Poetry" "Milton and the Sonnet" An
                immensely useful work: Havens surveys exhaustively the effects of Miltonic blank
                verse, themes, and forms on all the major English poetry from 1660-1837. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1201">
            <bib>Hazlitt, William. "On Milton's Versification." In The Round Table. Edinburgh:
                Archibald Constable, 1817;</bib>
            <notes> rpt in The Complete Works of William Hazlitt. Ed. P. P. Howe. 21 vols. London:
                J. M. Dent and Sons, 1930. Vol. 4, pp. 36-41. Hazlitt's encomium allows itself but a
                single restraint: "Milton's blank verse is the only blank verse in the language
                (except Shakespeare's) which is readable. . . . there are more perfect examples in
                Milton . . . of an adaptation of the sound and movement of the verse to the meaning
                of the passage, than in all our other writers, whether of rhyme or blank verse, put
                together (with the exception already mentioned)." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1202">
            <bib>Hensley, Don H. "Wordsworth and a New Mythology: A Stylistic Analysis of The
                Excursion." DAI 25 (1964): 1914A (Wisconsin). </bib>
            <notes>Though mainly on the processive rhythms of imagery, some attention is given to
                meter and syntax. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1203">
            <bib>Hertzberg, W. "Metrisches, Grammatisches, und Chronologisches zu Shakespeares
                Dramen." Shakespeare Jahrbuch 13 (1878): 248-66.</bib>
            <notes> Suggests analyzing (1) "lax" blank-verse lines, (2) feminine endings, and (3)
                Al- exandrines for determining chronology. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1204">
            <bib>Hickey, Emily. "On the Making of English Blank Verse." The Nineteenth Century and
                After 88 (1920): 1002-19.</bib>
            <notes> On the foreign sources and English users, chiefly in the Renaissance. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1205">
            <bib>Hickson, Samuel. "The Shares of Shakespeare and Fletcher in Two Noble Kinsmen."
                Westminster and Foreign Quarterly 47 (1847): 59-88;</bib>
            <notes> rpt in Transactions of the New Shakespeare Society Series 1, Part 1, 25 (1874):
                25*-61*. See also his other brief article reprinted in this latter source E1206 on
                pp. 18*-20*. Both of these articles are suffixed by metrical confirmations by Fleay
                and Furnivall. Hickson's view is that the "entire plan and general arrangement" of
                the play are Shakespeare's. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1207">
            <bib>Hilgers, Theodor J. Der dramatische Verse Shakspeare's. Programm der Realschule
                erste Ordnung in Aachen, 1868-69. 45 pp.</bib>
            <notes> (in two parts). Professor Hilgers was the distinguished scholar who translated
                all of S's plays into Latin, doubtless to spare his students the pain of having to
                read a vulgar language. (There is a jeering review in Shakespeare Jahrbuch 7 (1872):
                350-52.) The present essay discusses the nature of S's meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1208">
            <bib>Howe, M. L. "Anapestic Feet in Paradise Lost.” MLN 45 (1930): 311-12.</bib>
            <notes> Of which, he concludes, there are none: all are disyllabic feet with elision.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1209">
            <bib>Hubbard, Frank G. "A Type of Blank Verse Line Found in the Earlier Elizabethan
                Drama." PMLA 32 (1917): 68-80.</bib>
            <notes> A thorough discussion of an interesting feature in Renaissance drama, espe-
                cially in Marlowe--the "symmetrical line" (Article + Preposition + Adjective + Noun
                + Conjunction + Article + Adjective + Noun). Examples and statis- tics. The line
                apparently does not occur in nondramatic blank verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1210">
            <bib>Hungerford, Edward B. Recovering the Rhythms of Poetry: The Elements of
                Versification. Chicago: Scott, Foresman, 1964. 117 pp.</bib>
            <notes> The third word in the title should be "Metrics," the final one "Blank Verse."
                Along with McAuley, this is the best available introduction to the metrical
                structures and textures of the iambic pentameter line (chiefly in Shakespeare). The
                format is "half-worksheet, half programmed instruction," with self- correcting
                exercises. Chapters on "The Pattern," "Modulations of the Pattern," "Pauses," "Line
                Lengths." An excellent student's manual of meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1211">
            <bib>Hunter, William B., Jr. "The Sources of Milton's Prosody." PQ 28 (1849):
                125-44.</bib>
            <notes> These are two: Sylvester and the metrical psalters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1212">
            <bib>-----. "Two Milton Notes." MLR 44 (1949): 89-91.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1213">
            <bib>Imelmann, Rudolph. "Zu den Anfängen des Blankverses: Surrey's Aeneis IV in
                ursprunünglicher Gestalt." Shakespeare Jahrbuch 41 (1905): 81-123.</bib>
            <notes> A critique of Fest (E1163); section 5 treats six metrical aspects of Tottel's
                revi- sions of Surrey's pentameters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1214">
            <bib>Ingram, John K. "On the 'Weak Endings' of Shakespeare, With Some Account of the
                Verse-Tests in General." Transactions of the New Shakspere Society Series 1, Part 2,
                vol. 25 (1874): 442-64.</bib>
            <notes> The article commences with a short (and to us very useful) history of eight-
                eenth- and nineteenth-century work on metrical tests in Shakespeare; Ingram then
                presents his analysis of "light" and "weak" (lighter) endings: these bear secondary
                rather than primary stress. Table of results on p. 450. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1215">
            <bib>Johnson, Dr. Samuel. The Rambler. Vols. 3, 4, and 5 of The Yale Edition of the
                Works of Samuel Johnson. Ed. W. J. Bate and A. B. Straus. New Haven: Yale University
                Press, 1969. Vol. 4, p. 87 ff.</bib>
            <notes> Three numbers--86, 88, and 90--discuss Milton's versification, specifically in-
                versions, elision, and pause-placement (the caesura after the sixth syllable pro-
                duced in Dr. Johnson "strong emotions of delight or admiration"). Nos. 92 and 94
                treat "representative meter" or sonal-metrical mimesis, which Dr. Johnson terms
                "imagery of sound" and generally depreciates, on the grounds "that on many occasions
                we make the music which we imagine ourselves to hear; that we modulate the poem by
                our own disposition, and ascribe to the numbers the effects of the sense. . . .
                Sound can resemble nothing but sound, and time can measure nothing but motion and
                duration." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1216">
            <bib>Jones, Frederick L. "An Experiment with Massinger's Verse." PMLA 47 (1932):
                727-40.</bib>
            <notes> Notices Massinger's stylistic idiosyncrasy of frequently ending verse-lines with
                of or to, a practice which turns out to have been abhorrent to most of his con-
                temporaries (172 plays by 33 playwrights are examined). These prepositions either
                end phrases or split phrases across the line-end. Detailed analysis of Massinger's
                plays. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1217">
            <bib>Judd, William E. "The Metrics of Wallace Stevens." DAI 35 (1975): 6717A (Columbia,
                1972).</bib>
            <notes> On the "rhythms" of walking, jazz, and dance in Stevens' poetry, and also his
                exploration of the iambic pentameter. His blank verse shows "great variety" and "a
                tendency toward diversity." Computerized sorting of metrical patterns. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1218">
            <bib>Kahler, Rigobert. Das Verhältnis von Verse und Prosa in Shakespeares Schauspielen.
                Diss., Innsbruck. 1924.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1219">
            <bib>Keightley, Thomas. "The Verse." An Account of the Life, Opinions, and Writings of
                John Milton. London: Chapman and Hall, 1855, 1859. pp. 440-50.</bib>
            <notes> Criticized in Mayor (E592), pp. 76-77. See also the short chapter in "Milton As
                a Writer," pp. 382-87, which touches on rhyming. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1220">
            <bib>Kermode, Frank. "Adam Unparadised." The Living Milton: Essays by Various Hands.
                Ed. Frank Kermode. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1960. pp. 85-123.</bib>
            <notes> See "Counterlogical Elements," pp. 94-99. "Milton in the poem is not aiming
                directly at the truth, but at the perturbed senses by means of delight; the plan-
                ning of this circuitous route to the mind of the reader is an elaborate exercise in
                counterlogic." Why then eschew rhyme, the most counterlogical device of all? (1)
                Other devices were available, such as dislocation in syntax. (2) Milton does
                occasionally rhyme. (3) There is a kind of "pseudo-rhyme" as well-- semantically
                contrasting word-pairs. Milton had "more refined ideas about the way to achieve
                musical delight; his counterlogic is a vastly more subtle affair than a mere tagging
                of verses." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1221">
            <bib>-----. "Samson Agonistes and Hebrew Poetry." Durham University Journal 14 (1953):
                59-63.</bib>
            <notes> Milton's imitations of Hebrew prosodic forms. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1222">
            <bib>Kerrl, Anna. Die metrischen Unterschiede von Shakespeare's King John und Julius
                Caesar: Eine chronologische Untersuchung. Bonner Studien zur englischen Philologie,
                vo. 10. Bonn: Peter Hanstein, 1913. 189 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Anglia Beiblatt 25 (1914): 109-13. Summary table of metrical statistics,
                pp. 188-89. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1223">
            <bib>Kim, Joo-Hyon. "Reconsideration of Shakespeare's Prosody." The English Language
                and Literature 15 (1964): 111-25. (In Korean; summary in English on pp.
                167-69.)</bib>
            <notes> Claims that understanding of Shakespeare's pronunciation and use of pauses will
                regularize any seeming irregular lines. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1224">
            <bib>Kiran, Hartvig. "Ritmekunst in Macbeth." Syn og Segn 67 (1961): 418-28.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1225">
            <bib>Kirkconnel, Watson. Awake the Courteous Echo: The Themes and Prosody of 'Comus,'
                'Lycidas,' and 'Paradise Regained' in World Literature with Translations of the
                Major Analogues. Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1973.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Renaissance Quarterly 27 (1974): 601-2. Lists 166 Analogues for the
                three poems, with discussion for each and a trans- lated sample text; references to
                prosody are intermittent throughout except for a two-page "Appendix A: On Metre" at
                the end, which unfortunately dis- cusses not the character of the original meters of
                the analogues but rather the most suitable meters for translating the analogues.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1226">
            <bib>Knaut, C. Über die Metrik Robert Greenes. Diss., Halle, 1890. 63 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1227">
            <bib>Koehler, G. Stanley. "Milton on 'Numbers,' 'Quantity,' and Rime." SP 55 (1958):
                201-17.</bib>
            <notes> A search of the recorded statements of Milton's contemporaries and the Eliza-
                bethan prosodists about "number" and "quantity" in verse; Koehler concludes (though
                without any clear consensus as support) that "apt Numbers" refers to the use of the
                metrical foot (not merely the count of syllables), and "fit quan- tity" to syllabic
                length, implying thereby Milton's awareness of the available resources of syllabic
                "weight" in the line, yet without implying that he in- tended to write in a
                quantitative metric. Since the final syllable in his lines is frequently "weighted,"
                and since rhymes do occur in PL, Koehler judges that Milton objected not so much to
                the concept of rime as to the narrower, more tediously monotonous couplet rime.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1228">
            <bib>Kökeritz, Helge. "Elizabethan Prosody and Historical Phonology." Annales Academiae
                Regiae Scientiarum Upsaliensis 5 (1961): 79-102.</bib>
            <notes> A stinging rebuke to Bayfield, Saintsbury, Omond, and all those others who
                upheld the dubious doctrine of "trisyllabic substitution": "those who have written
                most extensively on Shakespeare's versification have been linguistically least
                qualified to express their views on the subtle problems involved." Their error was
                not to see that elision has been normal in both common speech and written prose as
                well as poetry since Middle English. K. cites extensive exam- ples of "doublets"
                (alternative forms of a word used to normalize the meter). Cf. Sipe (E1304).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1229">
            <bib>König, Goswin. Der Vers in Shaksperes Dramen. Quellen und Forschungen, no. 61.
                Strassburg: Karl Truübner, 1888. 138 pp. Based on his dissertation, "Zu Shaksperes
                Metrik," at Strassburg in 1888.</bib>
            <notes> This classic work devised metrical tests to apply to the verse as a tool for
                dating the plays, based on an assumption of orderly and discernible changes in
                versifi- cation. Conclusions on the chronology of the Shakespearean canon are given
                in Chapter 7, p. 130 ff. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1230">
            <bib>Kolbe, Heinrich. Metrische Untersuchungen über die Gedichte der "Uncertain
                Authors" in "Tottel's Miscellany." Diss., Marburg, 1902. 90 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1231">
            <bib>Kozlenko, Eva. [Robert Frost's Metrics]. Literatura 19,3 (1977): 79-92.</bib>
            <notes> In Russian; English summary at end. Statistical analysis of metrical style in
                both "classic" and "traditional" meters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1232">
            <bib>Kupka, P. Über den dramatischen Vers Thomas Dekkers. Diss., Halle, 1893. 37
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1233">
            <bib>Lacy, John. "A Sixth Letter to the Dramatists of the Day." London Magazine 8
                (1823): 645-52.</bib>
            <notes> Berates the author of Mirandola for using "the vicious principles of metre pa-
                tronized by Lord Byron," the versification of "Prose-poetry," i.e. blank verse. The
                first salvo had been fired in the previous number; see pp. 530-38, esp. 535 ff.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1234">
            <bib>Langworthy, Charles A. "A Verse-Sentence Analysis of Shakespeare's Plays." PMLA 46
                (1931): 738-51</bib>
            <notes>. Based on the author's dissertation work, "A Determination of the Authorship of
                Henry the Eighth and The Two Noble Kinsmen by a Comparative Study of Verse-Sentence
                Patterns." Here L. applies his method for assessing the relations of line to
                sentence (see E572) to the dating of the Shakespearean canon (earlier plays show
                congru- ence, later plays divergence), but even though he can show that the four
                commonest metrical tests are widely inconsistent, his own chronology for the canon
                is erratic too, placing Pericles too early and Macbeth too late, among other misses.
                Still, his analytic method is a useful tool for other purposes. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1235">
            <bib>Lanier, Sidney. Music and Poetry: Essays Upon Some Aspects and Inter-Relations of
                the Two Arts. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1898; rpt New York: AMS Press,
                1969.</bib>
            <notes> Despite the suggestive title, there is nothing of technical interest in this
                collec- tion of essays except a section on the development of Shakespeare's
                versecraft, pp. 171-89. There we do find this author's equivalent of Metrical Tests
                being used to date the plays. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1236">
            <bib>-----. Shakespeare and his Forerunners. 2 vols. New York: Doubleday, Page
                1902.</bib>
            <notes> Chapter 1 summarizes the main prosodic concepts of The Science of English Verse
                (E364), and Chapters 11 and 12 treat pronunciation. Chapters 20 and 21 discuss "The
                Metrical Tests." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1237">
            <bib>Larkins, G. L. "The Scansion of the Heroic Verse." The Academy 38 (1890): 616- 17
                (Abstract).</bib>
            <notes> A long report on his paper read before the Philological Society, which ex-
                plores the origin of the English iambic pentameter, finding it to be not the French
                décasyllable but the Italian endecasillabo. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1238">
            <bib>Leavis, F. R. "Milton's Verse." Scrutiny 2 (1934): 123-36; rpt in his Revaluation:
                Tradition and Development in English Poetry. London: Chatto &amp; Windus, 1936;
                1953; 1959.</bib>
            <notes> (A response to Allen Tate's essay in The New Republic, 21 (Oct. 1931, pp. 42-
                67.) Professor Leavis's famous piece of iconoclasm attacks not the myth but the
                meter of Paradise Lost, charging it with the ultimate and irredeemable fault,
                Monotony; he protests (too much) "against the routine gesture, the heavy fall of the
                verse . . . the foreseen thud that comes so inevitably, and, at last, irresistibly .
                . . in the end our resistance is worn down; we surrender at last to the inescapable
                monotony of the ritual." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1239">
            <bib>Allen Tate's essay in The New Republic, 21 (Oct. 1931, pp. 42-67.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="E1240">
            <bib>Littschwager, Felix. Alexandriner in den Dramen Shakespeares. Normannia:
                Germanische-Romanische Bücherei, vol. 11. Berlin: Emil Felber, 1912. 77 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Lists of types. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1241">
            <bib>Lloyd, W. Watkiss. "Miltoniana." Notes &amp; Queries 12 (1891): 5.</bib>
            <notes> Argues that Milton used Greek (quantitative) accent for proper names in cer-
                tain lines, so that we are to reproduce that pattern in stress accent. Very brief.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1242">
            <bib>McCutcheon, R. P. "Notes on the Occurrence of the Sonnet and Blank Verse." MLN 40
                (1925: 513-14.</bib>
            <notes> Additions of obscure periodical verse of the two forms, 1660-1700, to Ha- vens's
                The Influence of Milton (E1200). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1243">
            <bib>Marshall, Donald G. "The Development of Blank Verse Poetry from Milton to
                Wordsworth." DAI 32 (1971): 1480A (Yale).</bib>
            <notes> Blank verse poetry prefers Jakobson's "metaphoric" pole in language: its style
                is characterized "by repetition at varying intervals, by succession, and by conti-
                nuity." So, in Milton, repetition provides cohesion over clauses, and enjam- bement
                "carries the reader strongly forward" into the next line. The result is "forward
                contiguous movement." Marshall examines all of the eighteenth- century writers of
                blank verse, showing in a striking manner how each fash- ioned a prosodic instrument
                in his verse for his themes and mood. Word- sworth "re-assimilates" the Miltonic
                style. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1244">
            <bib>Masson, David. "Milton's Versification and His Place in the History of English
                Verse." In his edition of The Poetical Works of John Milton. 3 vols. London:
                Macmillan, 1874; 1877-1882; many times reprinted. Vol. 3, pp. 206-32.</bib>
            <notes> Adopting Latham's x a system of scansion (E573), Masson briefly reviews the
                versification of Milton's poems in their chronological order then takes up se-
                riatim Milton's metrical craft and rhyme craft. The meter is of course iambic and
                decasyllabic, 5 x a, but variations are "equivalent," Masson says, to the ideal
                form, and he will allow "a Trochee, a Spondee, or a Pyrrhic, for the Iambus, in
                almost any place of the line." Trisyllabic substitutions in the meter are allowed
                too, in preference to any elision in pronunciation. Alexandrines, feminine endings,
                and caesura placement are also examined. On rhymes, the most novel conclusion is
                that Milton freely used imperfect (off, near) rhymes and dialectal forms. As perhaps
                the best statement of the traditional view of Milton's prosody (on the old
                principles of equivalence and substitution), Masson's essay still bears
                examinination. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1245">
            <bib>Maveety, Stanley R. "Versification in The Steele Glas." SP 60 (1963):
                166-73.</bib>
            <notes> Gascoigne's long 1576 poem of social criticism, the first instance of non-
                dramatic blank verse, is medieval in meter as in matter, resembling very closely the
                line of Piers Plowman in regard to: four major stresses, heavy medial cae- sura,
                heavy end-stopping, absence of rhyme (of course), and overt alliteration. The author
                gauges that fully 50% of Gascoigne's 1200 lines fit one of the eight alliterative
                patterns of Piers Plowman. It seems Gascoigne did not entirely know what he was
                doing, or the nature of his metric. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1246">
            <bib>Maxwell, J. C. "Vergilian Half-Lines in Shakespeare's 'Heroic Narrative.'" Notes
                &amp; Queries 198 (1953): 100.</bib>
            <notes> Short and incomplete lines in Shakespearean blank verse, particularly in "he-
                roic" passages, seem to be modelled on a Virgilian practice in the Aeneid. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1247">
            <bib>Mayor, Joseph B. "English Metre"; "Mr. Alexander J. Ellis's Remarks on Mr. Mayor's
                Two Papers on Rhythm"; "Appendix" [by Mayor]; "Additional Observations" [by Ellis].
                Transactions of the Philological Society, 1875-76, pp. 397-469.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1248">
            <bib>-----. "English Metre." Ibid., 1877-78, pp. 257-82.</bib>
            <notes> The two principle essays, Mayor's studies of Blank verse in Shakespeare and
                Tennyson, along with his exchange with Ellis, are revised, expanded, and commented
                upon in retrospect in chapters 8-13 and 5 (respectively) of Mayor's Chapters on
                English Metre (E592). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1249">
            <bib>Meiners, J. Metrische Untersuchungen über den Dramatiker John Webster. Diss.,
                Halle, 1893. 40 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1250">
            <bib>Meyer, Paul. Metrische Untersuchungen über den Blankvers John Dryden's. Diss.,
                Halle, 1897. 84 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Merely list examples of varieties of syllabification, word-stressing, and verse
                rhythm (caesura, trochaic substitutions, extra syllables, feminine endings, missing
                syllables, Alexandrines, tetrameters and short lines, rhyme, use of prose, broken
                lines, mislineation, diaeresis, enjambement, and alliteration). Cf. Speerschneider
                (E1418). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1251">
            <bib>Milton, John. "The Verse." Preface to Paradise Lost. London. 1668, 1674.</bib>
            <notes> Many modern editions. Milton's decision to employ blank verse for his Epic seems
                based in part on the example of "both Italian and Spanish Poets of prime note" (for
                discussion of possible candidates, see E1121), and in part on his own repugnance to
                Rhyme, it being "no necessary Adjunct or Ornament of Poem or good Verse." The "true
                musical delight" consists only in "apt Numbers, fit Quantity of Syllables, and the
                sense variously drawn out from one Verse into another," not in any "jingling sound
                of like endings." The tone of this brief Preface is more strident than one might
                have expected. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1252">
            <bib>Moloney, Michael F. "The Prosody of Milton's 'Epitaph,' 'L-Allegro,' and 'Il
                Penseroso.'" MLN 72 (1957): 174-78.</bib>
            <notes> An argument that the rhythm of the "Epitaph" should be distinguished from that
                of the two later companion-pieces, as having its origin not in Shakespear- ean
                aestival songs but in Jonson, who showed that octosyllabics could be writ- ten in
                falling rhythm (Moloney thinks them iambic nevertheless) yet weighty and somber in
                effect, not light or tripping. The critical uncertainty about the meter of the
                "Epitaph's" tetrameters is natural since "Milton mingled octosylla- bles and
                heptasyllables with uncertain results." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1253">
            <bib>Mommsen, Tycho, ed. Shakespeare's Romeo und Julia. Oldenberg: G. Stalling; London:
                Williams &amp; Norgate, 1859.</bib>
            <notes> Sections 2-4 of the textual introduction (pp. 94-156) treat matters of
                versifica- tion, especially syncope and synizesis, caesura-placement, and the use of
                blank verse and rhyme by Shakespeare and his contemporaries. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1254">
            <bib>Montgomery, Lyna L. "The Prosodic Techniques of Edward Young and John Keats in
                Heroic Couplets and Blank Verse." DA 28 (1967): 199A (Arkansas).</bib>
            <notes> Keats shows a clear pattern of technical growth inot a "mature severity and
                sparseness of style," while Young shows none. Keats relies more heavily on
                enjambement and couplets, whereas Young uses caesural placement more ef- fectively
                and often. Substituted feet are more common in Keats. Trisyllabic feet, entirely
                absent in Young, occur in the early Keats but not the later. "Keats's technical
                development was toward an increasing use of monosylla- bles." Alexandrines and
                triplets occur only in Lamia. Conclusion: Young seems intent on restraining his
                verse, whereas Keats seems to enjoy rhythmic and melodic variety for its own sake.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1255">
            <bib>Moore, Charles L. "The Lost Art of Blank Verse." The Dial 33 (1902): 317-19.</bib>
            <notes> "Measured motion and ordered repetition' being the basis for all metered verse,
                blank verse has suffered greatly the loss of classical quantity. Its advan- tages
                however are "freedom and fluidity within limits." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1256">
            <bib>Morsbach, Lorenz. Shakespeares dramatische Kunst und ihre Voraussetzungen.
                Abhandlungen der Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften zu Göttingen, Philolog-
                isch-historische Klasse, vol. 3, no. 25. Göttingen: Vanderhoek &amp; Ruprecht,
                1940.</bib>
            <notes> Chapter 2, section 5 discusses the use of prose and verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1257">
            <bib>Morton, Edward P. The Technique of English Nondramatic Blank Verse. Chicago: R. R.
                Donnelley &amp; Sons, 1910;</bib>
            <notes> rpt Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1970; rpt Norwood, Pa.: Norwood
                Editions, 1975. His dissertation at Chicago in 1910. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1258">
            <bib>Mott, Emma P. "Shakespeare and Rhythm." Poet-Lore 4 (1892): 212-17.</bib>
            <notes> Insignificant. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1259">
            <bib>Munday, Mildred B. "The Influence of Shakespeare's Predecessors on his Early Blank
                Verse: A Study of Metrical Structure with Special Attention to Rhetoric and Syntax."
                Diss.; University of Wisconsin, 1953. Abstracted in Shakespeare Newsletter 6 (1956):
                2.</bib>
            <notes> Munday denies that Shakespeare learned his metrical craft from Marlowe and
                denies that early Elizabethan dramatic blank verse is in any way wooden or stiff,
                claiming that even the earliest efforts were complex, supple, and sophisti- cated.
                Analyzes six Histories and two Tragedies of Shakespeare's. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1260">
            <bib>Nearing, Homer, Jr. "Shakespeare as a Nondramatic Poet: Sonnet 29." Shakespeare
                Quarterly 13 (1952): 15-20.</bib>
            <notes> Metrical analysis and interpretation. The author scans with four markers de-
                noting stress and non-stress and ictus and non-ictus. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1261">
            <bib>Nomachi, S. "Shakespeare's Blank Verse." Shakespeare Studies (Tokyo) 1 (1962):
                33-45.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1262">
            <bib>Norpoth, Hugo. Metrisch-Chronologische Untersuchung von Shakespeare's "Two
                Gentlemen of Verona." Diss., Dülmen, 1916. 86 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1263">
            <bib>Nott, George Frederick, ed. The Works of Henry Howard Earl of Surrey and of Sir
                Thomas Wyatt the Elder. 2 vols. London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, and Brown,
                1815-16.</bib>
            <notes> See, in vol. 1, the prefatory "Dissertation on the State of English Poetry
                before the Sixteenth Century," pp. cxxxvii-cclxxxvi. Sections 1-6 (5 is misnumbered
                as 7 in the Texas copy] treat Chaucer and fifteenth-century versification; sec-
                tions 7-11 and 17 treat Surrey and Blank Verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1264">
            <bib>Nowottny, Winifred. "Some Aspects of the Style of King Lear." Shakespeare Studies
                13 (1960): 49-57.</bib>
            <notes> Ms. Nowottny faces squarely the difficulties of the plain style of Lear, and
                asks why and how "the language of Lear compensates for its apparent limitations?"
                The answer includes some incandescent remarks on prosody at the end (pp. 56-57).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1265">
            <bib>Omond, T. S. "Milton and Syllabism." MLR 4 (1909): 93-101.</bib>
            <notes> Responds to Walter Thomas on Milton's line (E1322), quarreling with his claim
                that every Miltonic line is a decasyllable. Omond will not allow extra syllables to
                be totally dropped in uttering the line--a position easily congenial with his prior
                one that only time-periods count in verse--nor will he allow them full weight: a
                light, rapid slurring is urged. He questions the historical veracity of full
                elision. Rejoinder by Thomas in "Milton's Heroic Line," 5 (1910): 107-11; Omond
                replies briefly, pp. 111-12. R. A. Williams then joins the argument, focusing on the
                definitions of "syllable" and "elision," in "Syllables of Verse and Speech," 5
                (1910): 208-10, to which Omond takes exception again at pp. 505-6. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1266">
            <bib>Oras, Ants. Blank Verse and Chronology in Milton. University of Florida
                Monographs, Humanities, no. 20. Gainesville: University of Florida Press, 1966. 81
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Studia Neophilologica 39 (1967): 184-86; in Seventeenth Century News 25
                (1967): 27-28; in South Atlantic Bulletin 32 (1967): 11-12; in Notes &amp; Queries
                212 (1967): 319-20. A study of participles, metrical pauses, word-length, and
                feminine endings. Extensive tables and charts. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1267">
            <bib>-----. "'Extra Monosyllables' in Henry VIII and the Problem of Authorship." JEGP
                52 (1953): 198-213. </bib>
            <notes> Attacking Alexander (E1087), Oras argues for a Shakespeare-Fletcher collabo-
                ration in this play, based on the high incidence of heavy monosyllables in feminine
                endings. Shakespeare's own practice in the late plays was toward fre- quent use of
                feminine endings, but the last syllable was rarely a monosyllable. The argument is
                complex and minute. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1268">
            <bib>-----. "Metre and Chronology in Milton's 'Epitaph on the Marchioness of
                Winchester,' 'L'Allegro' and 'Il Penseroso.'" Notes &amp; Queries 198 (1953):
                332-33. </bib>
            <notes> Metrical evidence from Comus, a closer scrutiny of the prosodic parallelisms
                between "L'Allegro" and "Il Penseroso," and a wider perspective on their Ge- stalt
                than the statistical suggest that Sprott's (E1314) chronology for these three poems
                is erroneous. The "Epitaph" seems clearly earlier than, and separable from, the
                companion poems. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1269">
            <bib>-----. Pause Patterns in Elizabethan and Jacobean Drama: An Experiment in Prosody.
                University of Florida Monographs, Humanities, no. 3. Gainesville: University of
                Florida Press, 1960. 90 pp. Rev: in Studia Neophilologica 33 (1962): 340-42. </bib>
            <notes> The first thirty-two pages summarize the results of the remaining tables and
                charts. Oras examines only a single metrical phenomenon--pauses denoted by some mark
                of punctuation in the line--over virtually the whole corpus of Renaissance drama,
                with selected additional authors for comparison. The graphs present the frequencies
                (in percentages) of occurrence of pause in each of the nine possible positions in
                the pentameter line; three types of pauses are distinguished: (A-pattern) all pauses
                marked by punctuation. (B-pattern) "strong pauses," marked by punctuation stronger
                than the comma; and (C-pattern) pauses created by a "line-split" between two
                characters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1270">
            <bib>Parker, William Riley. "Milton's Meter: A Note." Seventeenth Century News 2
                (1943): 6. </bib>
            <notes> "Upon the Circumcision" is perfectly regular in meter and rhyme. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1271">
            <bib>Partridge, A. C. Orthography in Shakespeare and Elizabethan Drama: A Study of
                Colloquial Constructions, Elisions, Prosody and Punctuation. Lincoln: University of
                Nebraska Press; London: Edward Arnold, 1964. </bib>
            <notes> The study of Shakespeare's meter is of course bound up with the reliability of
                the texts, printers' practices, authorial idiosyncrasies of style, and the pronun-
                ciation and orthographic conventions of the day. Chapters 9 through 11 here are
                devoted to these problems: "Shakespeare's Versification and the Editing of the First
                Folio," "Italian Prosodists and Types of Dramatic Elision in the Eng- lish Drama,"
                and "Syllabic Variation in the Quarto and Folio Texts of Shake- speare: Its Effects
                upon Prosody in Hamlet and Troilus and Cressida." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1272">
            <bib>-----. The Problem of "Henry VIII" Re-Opened: Some Linguistic Criteria for the Two
                Styles Apparent in the Play. Cambridge: Bowes &amp; Bowes, 1949. 35 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Examination of lexical and syntactic usages in the play, particularly contrac-
                tions, corroborates the metrical evidence for a collaboration with Fletcher.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1273">
            <bib>Pasternack, Boris. "Shakespeare's Imagery and Rhythm." Translated by Peter
                Meadows. Arena 1 (1950): 33-37. </bib>
            <notes> Shakespeare's rhythm, which Pasternack calls "irrepressible and gusty," is used
                (1) for characterization, (2) to "materialize in sound" various themes and moods,
                and (3) to soften, smooth out, and conjoin the weaker parts of the play to the
                stronger. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1274">
            <bib>Penner, Emil. Metrische Untersuchungen zu George Peele. Diss., Halle, 1890. 40 pp.
                Rpt in Archiv 85 (1890): 269-308. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1275">
            <bib>Perry, Jeannette B. "Is Blank Verse Lawless?" Poet-Lore 8 (1896): 528-35. </bib>
            <notes> Traces the development of the dramatic line up through Shakespeare and no- tices
                the nondramatic line of Milton, Tennyson, and Browning thereafter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1276">
            <bib>Philbin, Joan H. "A Metrical Analysis of the Blank Verse of Henry Howard, Earl of
                Surrey." Diss., Yale University, 1963. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1277">
            <bib>Price, Hereward T. "Author, Compositor, and Metre: Copy-Spellings in Titus
                Andronicus and Other Elizabethan Printings." Publications of the Bibliographical
                Society of America 53 (1959): 160-87. </bib>
            <notes> A very vigorous and extended defense of the presence of metrical spelling in
                Elizabethan texts--chiefly Orlando Furioso and T. A. No matter what vagaries of
                compositor idiosyncrasy, textual corruption, or house-styling seem to have occurred,
                there is clear evidence of spelling variations intended to denote clipped (elided)
                or full pronunciation. Copious examples. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1278">
            <bib>Price, Thomas R. "The Construction and Types of Shakespeare's Verse as Seen in the
                Othello." Papers of the New York Shakespeare Society no. 8, 1888; rpt New York: AMS
                Press, 1971. 69 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Anglia 11 (1889): 550. So far as I know, this is the only work ever to
                employ the scansion-system of Dr. Guest (E543) based on staves (hemistichs).
                Explanation, pp. 14-19; list of the twenty-two types, pp. 20-21. 1279 Prince, F. T.
                The Italian Element in Milton's Verse. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1954. 183 pp.
                Chapter 7, "Milton's Blank Verse: The Diction," is rpt in Milton: A Collection of
                Critical Essays. Ed. Louis L. Martz. Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall, 1966.
                pp. 61-76. The well-known demonstration of Milton's debt in diction and in prosody
                to the sonnets of Della Casa and the verse and dramas of Tasso, besides Spenser. For
                the versification of his great epic Milton learned to forge a weighty but seamless
                meld of diction, syntax, and meter from the sixteenth-century versi sciolti,
                especially in Tasso. But Prince disagrees sharply with Bridges (E491) over the
                mechanism of the prosody, denying that Milton thought of his verses in feet at all.
                The whole concept of the metrical foot was a product of the late Renaissance
                Humanist revival of learning; Dante and Tasso, earlier, speak only of length of line
                and rhyme as the elements of verse. The rhyme-patterns of the choruses of Samson
                Agonistes take their origin, Prince concludes, in the dramas of Tasso, Guarini, and
                Andreini, the rhythms, in elaborations and ex- tensions of analogues to the Italian
                hendecasyllable, in Spenser's November ec- logue, and in the self-confidence and
                virtuosity Milton had gained in writing Paradise Lost. Altogether the prosody of PL
                is based on rhyme even though it dispenses with rhyme, in that Milton preserves in
                the final word in the line a gravity, a full measure, a weightiness which remains
                even though the sounds no longer jingle. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1280">
            <bib>Pulling, F. S. "The 'Speech-Ending' Test Applied to Twenty of Shakespeare's
                Plays." Transactions of the New Shakespeare Society, 1879, pp. 457-58. </bib>
            <notes> The information he reports is in one large table. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1281">
            <bib>Ramsey, Paul. "The Metrical Rules of the Sonnets." The Fickle Glass: A Study of
                Shakespeare's Sonnets. New York: AMS Press, 1979. pp. 65-98. Summary on pp. 97-98;
                Tables, 209-14. </bib>
            <notes> A thorough metrical analysis of the 2155 lines of the Sonnets produces useful
                generalizations about (1) trochaic substitutions [that is what metrical variation in
                Shakespeare comes down to, finally] and (2) rhyme and sound-patterning, these
                conclusions being weakened only by some arguable scansions and a no- tation system
                deserving one more sweep of Occam's Razor. Findings: trochees (5% of the 10,761 feet
                here) occur in all five feet in the pentameter line (under constraints set by five
                Metrical Rules which Ramsey stipulates), even split across the caesura; there are 56
                "pyrrhic-spondee combinations" and 21 un- metrical feet in the Sonnets; 7-12% of the
                lines have feminine endings; both discrepancies in terminal consonants of rhyming
                syllables and also identical rhymes were quite acceptable to the age; many
                off-rhymes occur; and the sheer amount of internal rhymes and general sound
                patterning is astonishing. See also the Appendix (E1282) and Index (passim).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1282">
            <bib>-----. "The Syllables of Shakespeare's Sonnets." New Essays on Shakespeare's
                Sonnets. Ed. Hilton Landry. New York: AMS Press, 1976. pp. 193-215; rpt as the
                Appendix to his The Fickle Glass (E1281); pp. 191-208. </bib>
            <notes> Had Robert Bridges written on Shakespeare instead of Milton (E491), he would
                have produced something like this study of pronunciation, meter, and elision in the
                pentameter line. The problem is extra syllables and three posi- tions have been
                taken: (1) they count both for pronunciation and in the meter; (2) they should be
                pronounced but not counted metrically; and (3) they do not exist and deserve
                neither. Making some telling points against the prevalent second ("semielision")
                position, Ramsey concludes, from textual evidence, remarks by Puttenham and others,
                and doublets, that Shakespeare intended "a strict disyllabism" in his metrical feet.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1283">
            <bib>-----. "Shakespeare and Sir Thomas More Revisited: Or, A Mounty on the Trail."
                Papers of the Bibliographic Society of America 70 (1976): 333-46. </bib>
            <notes> The ambiguous metrical evidence for Shakespeare's authorship is examined on pp.
                343-44. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1284">
            <bib>Reeves, W. P. "The So-called Prose Version of Guy of Warwick." MLN 11 (1896):
                cols. 404-8. </bib>
            <notes> If such a version ever existed it would have a bearing on the early history of
                blank verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1285">
            <bib>Reimer, Hans. Die Vers in Shakespeare's nichtdramatischen Werken. Diss., Bonn,
                1908. 60 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Classification and illustration of syllabification, word-stressing, and
                versification in "Venus and Adonis," "Lucrece," "A Lover's Complaint," and the
                Sonnets, leading to a chronology. He follows Zitelmann (L661) in distinguishing the
                two or three essential stresses of the line a "higher rhythm." He finds single and
                double alliteration common but off-rhyme and assonance rare. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1286">
            <bib>Reinhold, Heinz. "Die metrische Verzahnung als kriterium für Fragen der
                Chronologie und Authentizität im Drama Shakespeares und einiger Zeitgenossen und
                Nachfolger." Archiv 181 (1942): 83-96; 182 (1943): 7-24. </bib>
            <notes> Follows Conrad (E1125). R. suggests the better term "dove-tailing" for the line
                split between two dramatic characters, in preference to "broken verse" or "shared
                verse." He gives a critical review of the methods of earlier workers using this
                characteristic to date the plays: Conrad's original study simply counted
                occurrences; Pulling analyzed the types of breaking without specific attention to
                this type; König was interested only in where the end of the first speech fell in
                the line; Hereford misunderstood König; and Chambers treated only the pentameter.
                Reinhold's method is to set the total number of broken verses over the number of
                dovetailings (change-in-speaker), giving a percent- age. Application to all the
                major Renaissance dramatists. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1287">
            <bib>Robertson, J. M. "The Evolution of English Blank Verse." Criterion 2 (1924): 171-
                87. </bib>
            <notes> Renaissance dramatic and nondramatic. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1288">
            <bib>Roderick, R. "The Metre of Henry VIII." In Thomas Edward's Canons of Criticism.
                6th ed. London: C. Bathurst, 1758. </bib>
            <notes> This edition is exceedingly rare, but the essay is conveniently reprinted in
                Transactions of the New Shakspere Society, Series 1, Part 1, vol. 25 (1874): 66*-
                68*. Roderick notices an exceedingly high number of feminine endings in the play,
                curious caesura-placement after the seventh syllable, and frequent clashing of
                normal stress with metrical ictus. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1289">
            <bib>Ronniger, Lisbeth. Die Kunstform der Dichtung Robert Frosts. Diss., Vienna,
                1939.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="E1290">
            <bib>Scherer, Bernhard. Vers und Prosa bei den jüngeren dramatischen Zeitgenossen
                Shakespeares: Ein Beitrag zum Studium der Formtechnik im englischen Renais-
                sancedrama. Diss., Munich, 1932. Bottrop: Postberg, 1932. </bib>
            <notes> Primarily on Jonson. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1291">
            <bib>Schipper, Jakob. De Versu Marlovii. Diss., Bonn, 1967. 43 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Analysis of metrical variety in the plays. In Latin. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1292">
            <bib>Schröer, [Michel Martin] Arnold. "Ueber die anfaenge des Blankverses in England."
                Anglia 4 (1881): 1-72. </bib>
            <notes> A study of the metrical characteristics (metrical treatment of syllables, word-
                stressing, and verse-rhythm) in the early Renaissance blank verse up to Mar- lowe
                (Surrey, Grimald, Sackville and Norton, Turberville, Spenser, Gascoigne, Rich, Lyly,
                Peele, Greene, and Hughes). Though Schröer's study appeared slightly before volume 1
                of Schipper's monumental study (A9), he had been a student of Schipper's previously.
                Apparently he subsequently had an illustrious career, to judge by the memorial essay
                in Englishe Studien 62 (1927): 1-16 (in- cludes a photograph). See also K341.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1293">
            <bib>-----. Über Titus Andronicus: Zur Kritik der neuesten Shakespereforschung.
                Marburg: N. G. Elwart, 1891. 140 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Fleay's arguments for authorship (Marlowe) and dating on the basis of metrical
                evidence are taken up on pp. 24-49 and set against Schröer's own statistical
                analysis. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1294">
            <bib>Schulz, O. Über den Blankvers in den Dramen Thomas Middletons. Diss., Hall, 1892.
                48 pp. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1295">
            <bib>Schweinbach, Berta. Syntaktisch-metrische Untersuchungen zu Milton. Diss.,
                Innsbruck, 1922. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1296">
            <bib>Sedlack, Werner. Blankversveränderungen in Shakespeares späteren Tragödien: eine
                Interpretation von "Othello," "King Lear," Macbeth," und "Antony and Cleapatra."
                Diss., Munich, 1971. 253 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Not a strict metrical analysis but rather a broader approach to rhythmic play in
                the verse. Sedlak adopts some of the terminology of Wolfgang Kayser and John Draper
                in order to differentiate between an earlier "linear style" and a later "overflowing
                style" in "flowing" and "rushing" rhythms. He also treats of the relation of meter
                to syntax (or colon to line) and of the variations of meter against the iambic
                pentameter norm for rhythmic effect: hovering stresses, overweighting, and
                endstopping retard the tempo of the verse, while slurring, extra slacks,
                enjambements, feminine endings, and short cola accelerate its tempo. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1297">
            <bib>-----. "Typen des Blankverses bei Shakespeare." Jahrbuch der Deutsche Shakespeare-
                Gesellschaft West, 1969, pp. 122-42. </bib>
            <notes> The types are: rhetorical, witty, epic, lyric, and poetic, especially in King
                Lear and Othello. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1298">
            <bib>Seigler, Milledge B. "Milton's Prosody." Diss., Duke University, 1942. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1299">
            <bib>"Shakespeare's Rhythms." Bulletin (Sydney) 69 (1948): 2. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1300">
            <bib>Shawcross, John T. "One Aspect of Milton's Spelling: Idle Final 'E.'" PMLA 78
                (1963): 501-10. </bib>
            <notes> The metrical relevance of this study of Milton's spelling practices lies in its
                conclusion that Milton did not add an extra -e to such words as he, she (i.e. hee,
                shee) in order to mark them as stressed. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1301">
            <bib>-----. "What We Can Learn from Milton's Spelling." Huntington Library Quarterly 26
                (1963): 351-61. </bib>
            <notes> See also his </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="E1302">
            <bib>-----. "Orthography and the Text of Paradise Lost." In The Language and Style of
                Milton. Ed. Ronald D. Emma and John R. Shawcross. New York: Frederick Ungar, 1967.
                pp. 120-53. </bib>
            <notes> Both of these studies conclude that Milton's orthography (spelling and punc-
                tuation) are not crucially relevant to his metrics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1303">
            <bib>Simpson, Percy. "Shakespeare's Versification: A Study of Development." Studies in
                Elizabethan Drama. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1955. pp. 64-88. </bib>
            <notes> A strictly historical progression through the plays, showing many varieties of
                verseform with very many examples. Criticized by Borinski in Shakespeare Jahrbuch
                for 1956. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1304">
            <bib>Sipe, Dorothy L. Shakespeare's Metrics. Yale Studies in English, vol. 166. New
                Haven: Yale University Press, 1968. 266 pp. [Typescript]. Based on her dissertation,
                "Meter and Word-Choice in Shakespeare's Verse," directed by Kökeritz at Yale in
                1963. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Shakespeare Studies 6 (1972): 385-87; in Yearbook of English Studies 1
                (1971): 241-43. A study somewhat narrow in scope but very, very rigorous in method,
                leading to one narrow but irrefragable conclusion and several others, by
                implication, much more important. Sipe, in an effort to discriminate purely lexical
                from metrically influenced lexical choices in Shakespeare's lines, searches the
                74,817 lines of the canon for "syllabic variants" (i.e. doublets, words
                etymologically related or synonymous, varying only in number of syllables, e.g.
                against vs. 'gainst). Such variants appear in 12,814 lines, of these only 63 % (.5%)
                show a usage in spite of the meter. Conclusion: "Shakespeare was in fact greatly
                con- cerned about preserving the regularity of his verse. . . . [and] chose
                particular word-forms with metrics in mind." Even neologism seem to have been formed
                partly so as to fit the meter. This study should be the complete anti- dote to those
                turn-of-the-century aberrations about Shakespearean trochaic meter, trisyllabic
                substitutions, and unreliable orthography. See also Kökeritz (E1228). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1305">
            <bib>Sitwell, Edith, comp. The Pleasures of Poetry: A Critical Anthology. First Series.
                Milton and the Augustan Age. London: Duckworth, 1930. </bib>
            <notes> The Introduction (pp. 3-80) has much to say of the prosody of Milton, Her- rick,
                Dryden, and Pope; on Milton, particularly, Dame Sitwell prefers the the- ory of
                "equivalence" to any "'pretended' elision" of syllables. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1306">
            <bib>Smart, George K. "English Non-dramatic Blank Verse in the Sixteenth Century."
                Anglia 61 (1937): 370-97. </bib>
            <notes> In this careful historical and conceptual survey, Smart criticizes the
                treatments of blank verse by Alden and Courthope, approving Saintsbury, E. P.
                Morton, and Symonds. There are sections here on Surrey, Grimald, Turbervile, Spen-
                ser, Higgins, Gascoigne, Mundy, Rich, Peele, Greene, Lyly, and Marlowe. And he
                insists that "dramatic blank verse is quite different from non-dramatic, and the two
                ought not to be considered as one form." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1307">
            <bib>Smith, J. C. "Feminine Endings in Milton's Blank Verse." TLS, 5 December 1936, p.
                1016. </bib>
            <notes> Statistics: from PL to SA, the incidence of feminine endings rises from 1 to 17
                %. Smith is seeking a correlation between feminine endings and particularly emotive
                passages. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1308">
            <bib>Smith, Lewis W. "Chronology and Verse in Shakespeare." English Journal [College
                Edition] 21 (1932): 58-66. </bib>
            <notes> Identifies three types of blank-verse line: a "balanced" form (having primary
                stress in ictic positions 2, 4, and 5 of the regular iambic pentameter), a "lyrical"
                form (stresses in 1, 3, and 5), and a third form (3, 5), citing frequencies of oc-
                currence in the first acts of eight plays selected at random (text not identified).
                Unfortunately the results contradict the Chambers chronology, placing All's Well and
                Troilus fairly early, between Love's Labors and Romeo and Juliet. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1309">
            <bib>-----. "Shakespeare and the Speaking Line." Poet-Lore 48 (1842): 61-70. </bib>
            <notes> In the course of this brief purview of the blank-verse line up to Shakespeare
                (note the novel quotation, top of p. 62), Smith distinguishes the "dramatic" from
                the "lyric" line in terms of stress-patterns. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1310">
            <bib>Sonnenschein, E. A. "What is 'Blank Verse'?" Contemporary Review 126 (1924):
                756-60. </bib>
            <notes> Criticism of the term as being useless for revealing the nature of this
                verseform. Suggested replacement: "the five-foot iambic." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1311">
            <bib>Spedding, James. "Who Wrote Shakespere's Henry VIII?" The Gentleman's Magazine,
                1850, pp. 115-23</bib>
            <notes>; revised and rpt as </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="E1312">
            <bib>Spedding, James. "On the Several Shares of Shakespere and Fletcher in the Play of
                Henry VIII" in the Transactions of the New Shakspere Society, Series 1, Part 1, vol.
                25 (1874): 1*-18*. </bib>
            <notes> See also his letter in the latter location on pp. 21*-22* and his letter "On the
                Pause-Test" on pp. 26-31 (Text not Appendix). This last-mentioned letter is a
                critique of the refinement of the pause-test and bears reading; the other essay
                argues for both hands in the play; the Table on p. 14* in TNSS shows his di- vision
                of authorship attributions. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1313">
            <bib>Spenser, Hazelton. "A Nice Derangement: the Irregular Verse-Lining in A Midsummer
                Night's Dream, Act 5, Scene 1, Lines 1-84." MLR 25 (1930): 23-29. Reply by J. Dover
                Wilson, pp. 29-31. </bib>
            <notes> Spenser argues--against Wilson--that the irregular lining in the passage is the
                result of reductions for stage production rather than a manifestation of author- ial
                revisions or additions. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1314">
            <bib>Sprott, S. Ernest. Milton's Art of Prosody. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1953. 147 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in TLS, 15 May 1953, p. 318; by Oras in Seventeenth Century News 11 (1953):
                30; in Études Anglaises 7 (1954): 232; by Prince in Review of English Studies 5
                (1954): 292-94; in Anglia 73 (1955): 229-39. Along with Bridges' 1921 Milton's
                Prosody (E491) (which Sprott cites in his Preface as the "archetype" of his work),
                Sprott is the standard source for Mil- ton's metrics in his blank verse. A very
                extensive survey of the metrical devices available to Milton's hand for enriching
                his verse, including "supernumerary syllables and elision," "inversion of feet,"
                "loss of speech accent," "'paragraph fingering' and the break," and couplets. Also
                included are short sections on Milton's Sonnets and Stanzas. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1315">
            <bib>Stevick, Robert D. "The Metrical Style of E. A. Robinson." Edwin Arlington
                Robinson: Centenary Essays. Ed. Ellsworth Barnard. Athens: University of Georgia
                Press, 1970. pp. 54-67. </bib>
            <notes> After an extended metrical contrast of "Eros Turranos" and "The Unforgiven,"
                Stevick argues that E. A. R.'s verse has been slighted because it has been mis-
                understood: his long blank-verse narratives have two metrical bases (norms, types)
                not one. One of these is the traditional foot-system; the other employs syntax,
                frequent feminine endings, and "bulk" (syllabicity?) as the elements of its
                metering. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1316">
            <bib>Stewart, George R. "A Note on the Sleep-Walking Scene." MLN 42 (1927): 235-37. </bib>
            <notes> Finds one dipodic long line in the prose, possibly a snatch of an old ballad,
                which perhaps ought to be set: The Thane of Fife / Had a wife. / Where is she now?
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1317">
            <bib>Stolwitzer, Thomas. Das Verhältnis zwischen Vers und Prosa in den Tragodien
                Shakespeares. Diss., Innsbruck, 1923. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1318">
            <bib>Strachey, J. St. Loe. "The Vicissitudes of Blank Verse." London Mercury 6 (1922):
                45-60. Correspondence follows, chiefly by T. S. Omond, pp. 190-92, 305-6, 423, 531. </bib>
            <notes> Noting that the greatest English measure has had only one form (the iambic
                pentameter) rather than many, Strachey looks briefly at the unsuccessful at- tempts
                to diversify: iambic blank verse lyrics, hexameters, dactylics, trochaics, and
                sapphics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1319">
            <bib>Stroheker, Friedrich. Doppelformer und Rhythmus bei Marlowe und Kyd. Diss.,
                Heidelberg, 1913. Tübigen: H. Laupp, 1913. 105 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: Anglia Beiblatt 25 (1914): 135-37; in Shakespeare Jahrbuch 50 (1914): 235.
                "Doppelformen" ("doublets" in English) are words which are syllabically am- bivalent
                and may be pronounced as either one syllable or two, or two or three, depending on
                what is required for the meter. Cf. Sipe (E1304) and Ziesenis (E1085). Stroheker
                also treats word-stress, metrical treatment of syllables, syn- tax, etc. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1320">
            <bib>Symonds, John Addington. Blank Verse. London: John C. Nimmo, New York: Charles
                Scribner's Sons, 1895; rpt Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1969; rpt New
                York: AMS Press, 1970. </bib>
            <notes> From his Sketches and Studies in Italy (Appendix), and Fortnightly Review 22
                (1874): 767-81. Contains three chapters: "Prefatory Note," "The History of Blank
                Verse," and "The Blank Verse of Milton." Symonds has been sometimes dismissed if not
                damned by later prosodists for adopting the "intuitive" approach, since prosodists,
                fanatical about precision of statement and detail, abhor anything that smacks of
                impressionism; Omond's virulent characterization of Symonds' methods as amounting,
                "practically, to a negation of prosody," is both spiteful and undeserved. In fact
                Symonds' slim little volumne has been continuously quoted and approved, due mainly I
                think to the surprisingly fresh yet acute discussion of Accent and Quantity in the
                first chapter. His critics were foolish to believe that "non-technical" means "not
                ac- curate" or even "not useful." The historical survey of B. V. extends from
                Sackville &amp; Norton to Tennyson. See Mayor (E592), Chapter 4; Omond (A5), p. 186,
                and Saintsbury (A8), vol. 3, pp. 446-47. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1321">
            <bib>Tannenbaum, Samuel A. "Shakespeare's Verse Prepared for Students." Shakespeare
                Association Bulletin 14 (1939): 60-61. </bib>
            <notes> Trivial: examples of feminine endings, enjambement, etc. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1322">
            <bib>Thomas, Walter. "Milton's Heroic Line Viewed from an Historical Viewpoint." MLR 2
                (1907): 289-315; 3 (1908): 16-39, 232-56. </bib>
            <notes> Attacking critics such as David Masson and Charles Witcomb for refusing eli-
                sions in the Miltonic line, Thomas frames an argument that Milton consis- tently
                wrote absolute decasyllabic lines on the foundations of that line in Old French,
                Italian, Middle English, and Renaissance versification and on known
                seventeeth-century conventions of pronunciation and stressing. Fixity of sylla-
                ble-count, in short, Thomas claims to be the sole inviolable law of Milton's
                versification; Milton did not conceive of his decasyllable as an iambic one, since
                he often has more than five stresses, sometimes contiguous stresses, or fre- quently
                two inversions in a line, but it was a five-stress line, since Milton also followed
                "the law of a minimum quantity of accents." The third installment takes up variation
                in pause-placement both at mid- and end-of-line, and pho- netic harmonies. See
                replies by Omond and others at E1265. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1323">
            <bib>Thompson, John. "Blank Verse." Princeton (A18), pp. 78-79. </bib>
            <notes> An informatively elegant summary, Surrey to Eliot. "Blank verse has no inher-
                ent tone. Except for free verse, it is the form closest to the form of our speech."
                The article is concluded by S. Lyngstad's "Blank Verse in Other Lan- guages," pp.
                79-81. Bibliographies. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1324">
            <bib>Till, Hermann. Metrische Untersuchungen zu Blankversdichtungen P. B. Shelley's.
                Diss., Rostocker. Frankfurt, 1902. 62 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Englische Studien 32 (1903): 249-51. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1325">
            <bib>Timberlake, Philip W. The Feminine Ending in English Blank Verse: A Study of Its
                Use by Early Writers in the Measure and Its Development in the Drama up to the Year
                1595, with Full Tables of Percentages. Menasha, Wis.: Printed for the Author by the
                George Banta Publishing Co., 1931. 131 pp. Based on his dissertation at Princeton in
                1926. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Baum in JEGP 31 (1932): 291-93; in Anglia Beiblatt 44 (1933): 73-74.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1326">
            <bib>Tolman, Albert H. "Shakespeare's Part in The Taming of the Shrew." PMLA 5 (1890):
                201-78; rpt with revisions in his The Views About Hamlet and Other Essays. Boston:
                Houghton Mifflin, 1904. pp. 205-42. </bib>
            <notes> Along the way Tolman scrutinizes critically the metrical tests and conclusions
                of assigned authorship produced by Fleay and Furnivall. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1327">
            <bib>Treip, Mindele. Milton's Punctuation and Changing English Usage 1582-1676. London:
                Methuen, 1970. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Diekhoff in JEGP 70 (1971): 553-55. "Rhythmical Punctuation," pp. 56-60,
                and "Prosody," pp. 61-64. The latter section suggests that stops and pauses may
                affect metrical scansions. Cf. Banks (E1091) and Diekhoff (E1143). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1328">
            <bib>Tschopp, Elisabeth. Zur Verteilung von Vers und Prosa in Shakespeares Dramen.
                Swiss Studies in English, no. 41. Bern: Francke, 1956. 117 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in English Studies 41 (1960): 270-72; in Anglia 78 (1960): 96-97. Worth
                being aware of, even though her interest is the distribution of verse- forms vis à
                vis the characters in ten selected plays. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1329">
            <bib>Turner, Richard M. "A Study of Robert Browning's Blank Verse Technique." DA 28
                (1968): 4650A (Colorado). </bib>
            <notes> Nondramatic blank verse in a random sample from Browning's whole canon is
                analyzed, with a method which is a "reconciliation of traditional metrical scansion
                and current linguistic techniques for analyzing prose." Conclusion: "available
                descriptions exaggerate the irregularities of Browning's metrics." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1330">
            <bib>Ulreich, John C., Jr. "By Gradual Scale Sublimed: Ideas of Form in Milton's
                Poetry." Diss., Harvard University, 1969. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1331">
            <bib>Verity, A. W. The Influence of Christopher Marlowe on Shakespeare's Earlier Style.
                Cambridge: Macmillan and Bowes, 1886. Especially pp. 53-73. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1332">
            <bib>Von Scholten, W. Metrische Untersuchungen zu John Marston's Trauerspielen. Diss.,
                Halle, 1886. 55 pp. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1333">
            <bib>Vos, Erik. "Ritmische Aspecten bij het Vertalen." De Gids 127 (1964): 420-36. </bib>
            <notes> On The Taming of the Shrew in translation. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1334">
            <bib>Wagner, Albrecht. "Metrische Bemerkungen zu Shakespeares MacBeth." Anglia 13
                (1891): 352-57. </bib>
            <notes> Instances of metrical mis-lineation, lines with one missing syllable, and lines
                with a double feminine ending (i.e. two extra syllables) resulting in apparent
                Alexandrines. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1335">
            <bib>Wagner, Max. The English Dramatic Blank Verse before Marlowe. Programm Abhandlung
                der städtischen höhren burgerschule zur Osterode in Ostpreussen, no. 15. Ostern,
                1881. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Schipper in Englische Studien 5 (1882): 457-58. Wagner's study is
                inferior to that of Schröer (E1292) in that it is narrower in scope (he fails to
                recognize Chaucer's line behind that of Sackville and Nor- ton) and takes no account
                of recent scholarship (Fleay, Furnivall, etc.). It was obsolete before it was
                published. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1346">
            <bib>Walker, William Sidney. A Critical Examination of the Text of Shakespeare with
                Remarks on his Language and That of his Contemporaries, Together with Notes on his
                Plays and Poems. 3 vols. London: John Russell Smith, 1860. </bib>
            <notes> Vols. 1 and 2 collect short notices of spelling, pronunciation, and accentuation
                (essentially the whole of vol. 2), rhyme-usage (vol. 1, nos. 14, 15, 16, 20; vol. 2,
                no. 81), and the metrical treatment of syllables (vol. 1, no. 40 on final -ion).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1337">
            <bib>-----. Shakespeare's Versification and its apparent irregularity explained by
                examples from early and late English writers. London: John Russell Smith, 1854. 296
                pp. </bib>
            <notes> Unfinished and published posthumously (edited by W. W. Lettsom). A series of
                philological notes on spelling, pronunciation, and metre. See Bathurst (E1092) and
                Walker (above). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1338">
            <bib>Waller, Frederick O. "The Use of Linguistic Criteria in Determining the Copy and
                Dates for Shakespeare's Plays." Pacific Coast Studies in Shakespeare. Ed. W. F.
                McNeir and T. N. Greenfield. Eugene: University of Oregon, 1966. pp. 1- 19. </bib>
            <notes> Should be considered augmentation of the metrical tests: lists tables of
                frequen- cies for certain verb forms, modals, and contractions. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1339">
            <bib>Watkins, Ronald. "Only Shake-Scene." PQ 54 (1975): 47-67. </bib>
            <notes> Observations on Shakespeare's evolving poetical craft in the early Henry VIII
                tetralogy, most particularly the metrical variation of the blank-verse line and the
                differentiation of verse and prose for characterization. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1340">
            <bib>Webb, Daniel. Remarks on the Beauties of Poetry. London: R. and J. Dodsley, 1762;
                rpt New York: Garland, 1970. 123 pp. </bib>
            <notes> In Dialogue 1, Eugenio upholds the advantages of blank verse over rhyme, then
                turns to censure excessive sound-patterning in verse, stopping along the way to
                praise and illustrate Shakespeare's versification, the sweetness of which lies in
                its making high artifice seem nothing but natural; yet, Shakespeare "in- tended it
                to be nothing more than a measured or musical prose; except, when he meant to rise
                to his Subject, or give a distinction to a thought; and then we shall always trace
                in his numbers the influence of his feelings." Of sound: it is a fault "to suffer
                any one letter . . . to govern entirely" a passage of verse. it is equally a fault
                to believe too literally that the sound must seem an echo to the sense: "the sounds
                should be always in accord with the sense, but they should accompany, not mimic it."
                See also E696. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1341">
            <bib>Weismiller, Edward R. "The 'Dry' and 'Rugged' Verse." In The Lyric and Dramatic
                Milton. Ed. Joseph H. Summers. New York: Columbia University Press, 1965. pp.
                115-52. </bib>
            <notes> Distinguishes between the metrical styles of PL, and PR and SA. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1342">
            <bib>-----. The Prosody of Milton's English Poems. Vol. 7 of A Variorum Commen-tary on
                the Poems of John Milton. Ed. Merritt Y. Hughes. New York: Columbia University
                Press, forthcoming. </bib>
            <notes> The final volume of the series still in preparation. Should be the successor to
                Bridges (E491). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1343">
            <bib>-----. "Studies of Verse Form in the Minor English Poems." In The Minor English
                Poems. Vol. 2 of A Variorum Commentary on the Poems of John Milton. Ed. Merritt Y.
                Hughes. London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1972. pp. 1007-87. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1344">
            <bib>-----. "The Versification of Paradise Lost and Paradise Regained: A study of
                Movement and Structure in Milton's Nondramatic Blank Verse." Diss., Oxford
                University, 1951. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1345">
            <bib>Wentersdort, Karl. "Shakespearean Chronology and the Metrical Tests."
                Shakespeare-Studien: Ecstschrift für Heinrich Mutschmann. Ed. Walther Fischer and
                Karl Wentersdort. Marburg: N. G. Elwert, 1951. pp. 161-93. </bib>
            <notes> A detailed review of the evidence on dating uncovered since Chambers, fol- lowed
                by a review (beginning on p. 182) of the four major metrical tests and their
                reception by scholars. Individually they show little validity, but the author
                demonstrates that by totalling them (no. of variations against no. of possible
                variations), a "Metrical Index" can be devised which shows a reasona- bly steady and
                smoothly curved progression over Shakespeare's career, and which agrees with the
                other types of external evidence. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1346">
            <bib>Whaler, James. Counterpoint and Symbol: An Inquiry into the Rhythm of Milton's
                Epic Style. Anglistica, vol. 6. Copenhagen: Rosenkilde and Bagger, 1956. 225 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Weismiller in MLN 72 (1957): 612-18; by R. O. Evans in JEGP 56 (1957):
                487-90; by F. T. Prince in Review of English Studies n.s. 9 (1958): 320- 22; in MLR
                53 (1958): 244-45; in Anglia 76 (1958): 329-33. "Rhythm" is here used in its widest
                sense: though Whaler speaks to enjambe- ment, his main interest is the larger
                architectonic, "mathematical" patterns cre- ated by Milton ("intensely interested in
                mathematics") across his verse. Takes "the Miltonic paragraph as a rhythmic analogue
                to a piece of contrapuntal music." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1347">
            <bib>Whiteley, M. "Verse and Its Feet." Review of English Studies n.s. 9 (1958):
                268-78. </bib>
            <notes> A critique of F. T. Prince's "Italian" scansion of Miltonic pentameters. Prince
                replies, pp. 278-79. The argument is then joined by Ernest Schanzer in 10 (1959):
                292-93; Mrs. Whiteley answers, in 11 (1960): 191-92; reply by Schan- zer, p. 192. J.
                Buxton closes the exchange, 11 (1960): 305. The original sally by Mrs. Whiteley is
                vigorous and cogent: she defends the concepts of the "foot" and "rising rhythm," and
                she rejects altogether Prince's two rules for the meter of the Miltonic line (which
                are derived from those for the Italian hen- decasyllable), but only after examining
                all the arguments on both sides and many examples very closely. Prince demurs.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1348">
            <bib>Whiting, George W. "Milton's Rules for -ed." MLN 49 (1934): 166-68. </bib>
            <notes> Milton spelled -ed to denote a metrically stressed suffix; if the syllable was
                metrically weak, he used 'd or d (without apostrophe) indiscriminately. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1349">
            <bib>Wiehl, K. Thomas Kyd und sein Vers: Ein Beiträg zur Geschichte des englischen
                Dramas. Diss., Munich, 1910. 58 pp. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1350">
            <bib>Wolff, Lucien. An Essay on Keats's Treatment of the Heroic Rhythm and Blank Verse.
                Paris: Hachette, 1909. 154 pp. </bib>
            <notes> The Table of Contents page, with summary notes at the bottom, may well be the
                most useful part of the book. Wolff examines variations of the iambic pentameter
                norm in Keats's major poems vis à vis the influences of Hunt, Dry- den, and Milton.
                But (in the German manner) over half the book is given over to tables of scansions.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1351">
            <bib>Wood, James O. "A Special Cadence in King Lear." Shakespeare Quarterly 12 (1961):
                465-67. </bib>
            <notes> Notices a metrical-stylistic idiosyncrasy of Lear's in a number of lines before
                his regeneration--four syllables at the beginning of the line, followed by a
                caesura, all of virtually equal weight (not quite spondaic but nearly so). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1352">
            <bib>Wright, B. A. "Stressing of the Preposition Without in the Verse of Paradise
                Lost." Notes and Queries 203 (1958): 202-3. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1353">
            <bib>Yardi, M. R. "A Statistical Approach to the Problem of Chronology of Shakespeare's
                Plays." Sankhya: The Indian Journal of Statistics 7 (1946): 263-67. </bib>
            <notes> Yardi tries to improve upon the nineteenth-century work on metrical tests by a
                rigorous statistical analysis, but--astoundingly--he takes his data on feminine
                endings, split lines, and pauses directly from Fleay and Chambers (and thus their
                outdated editions). The conclusions confirm the accepted order. Such work generally
                fails because the researcher must be expert in (1) Elizabethan theatrical practice;
                (2) the textual history of the Folio; (3) statistics; and (4) metrics. Work based on
                faulty texts is worthless a priori. See also: B40, B44, C3, C8-9, C17, C27, C200,
                C206-7, C236, C263, C271-72, D243, D274, D294, D304, E44, E56, E65, E72-73, E91,
                E450, E452, E524, E605, E621, E687-88, E692, E707, E753, E766, E800, E818, E912,
                E964, E1391, E1393, E1431, F2, F13, F28, F40, F43, F52-53, F66-67, F70, F74, F99,
                F137, F155, F168, F177, F197, F219, G109, G134, I32, L151, L368, L1174, N113.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1354">
            <bib>Adler, Jacob H. "Notes on the Prosody of The Vanity of Human Wishes." Studies in
                the Literary Imagination 5 (1972): 101-17. </bib>
            <notes> Comparing Johnson's actual prosodic practice in the poem to his stated opin-
                ion, Adler finds that the former is "more liberal than the more liberal side" of the
                latter. Dr. Johnson's pronouncements give the impression that he only val- ued
                Regularity in verse, but in fact Variety also counted: only 57% of the lines in this
                poem are perfectly regular pentameters, 8% have initial trochees, and 26% have only
                four prominent stresses. Other features analyzed: caesura- placement, end-of-line
                pauses and stops, "representative meter," monosyllabic lines, hiatus, alliteration,
                and rhyme. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1355">
            <bib>-----. "Pope and the Rules of Prosody." PMLA 76 (1961): 218-26. </bib>
            <notes> Compares Pope's actual practice in versification to (1) his statements on the
                matter (seven rules given in a 1710 letter to Henry Cromwell), concluding that the
                rules "cannot be accepted as anything like an accurate reflection of his own
                practice" and to (2) general eighteenth-century critical views, concluding that
                Pope's divergence from these views increased as his career advanced. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1356">
            <bib>-----. The Reach of Art: A Study in the Prosody of Pope. University of Florida
                Monographs, Humanities, no. 16. Gainesville: University of Florida Press, 1964.
                Based on his dissertation at Harvard in 1951. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in JEGP 64 (1965): 738-40; by D. I. Masson in MLR 61 (1966): 110; in
                English Studies 48 (1967): 453-60. A survey of Pope's handling of metrics,
                caesura-placement, line-structure, monosyllables, devices of repetition, inversion,
                rhyme, alliteration, and "rep- resentative meter" in the major poems throughout his
                career. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1357">
            <bib>Allison, Alexander W. "The Reform of Our Numbers." Toward an Augustan Poetic:
                Edmund Waller's "Reform" of English Poetry. Lexington: University of Kentucky Press,
                1962. pp. 62-87. </bib>
            <notes> Waller adapted the resources of the old native "two by two" line with strong
                caesura, molding from it a pentameter line with a consistent, precise "formu- lary
                balance" of caesura after the fifth syllable (see Appendix A). He "strength and
                sweetness joined," melding the Donne-Jonson school of strong lines with the
                Spenser-Fairfax school of mellifluousness, by controlling his diction (speech
                cadences disrupt meter) and employing syntactic inversion. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1358">
            <bib>Alssid, Michael W. "Rhyme the Usurper" and "Dryden's Versification." In his
                Dryden's Rhymed Heroic Tragedies: A Critical Study of the Plays and of their Place
                in Dryden's Poetry. 2 vols. Salzburg Studies in English Literature, no. 7. Salzburg:
                Universität Salzburg Institut für englische Sprache und Literatur, 1974, Vol. 2, pp.
                256-64, 315-54. </bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation at Syracuse University. In the first section Alssid
                defends Dryden's use of rhyme in drama from the criticisms of Harley
                Granville-Barker by adapting a political analogy: rhyme, as monarch, gives order and
                law to the verse and rivets ("usurps") the attention of the audience, reminding them
                of the fictiveness of the aesthetic artiface. In the second he shows how Dryden
                derived, from the early nondramatic couplets of "Upon the Death of Lord Hastings,"
                "Astrea Redux," and "Verses to Her Highness the Duchess," a dramatic couplet that
                was (1) more varied in meter, (2) simplified in syntax and rhetoric, and (3)
                mitigated in repetitiveness by triplets, Alexandrines, etc. The three poems receive
                very close analysis. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1359">
            <bib>Amis, George T. "The Structure of the Augustan Couplet." Genre 9 (1976): 37- 58. </bib>
            <notes> Statistical analysis of features in over 13,000 lines allows more precise
                descrip- tion (including frequencies of occurrence) of the structure of the "modules
                of sense" in Dryden and Pope, with The Rape of the Lock serving as model; sum- mary
                on p. 46. Of particular interest is the correlation of caesura to weighting of
                stresses. The last half of the article turns to broader implications, and sec- tions
                iii, vii, and viii discuss rhyme. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1360">
            <bib>-----. "Style and Sense in Three Augustan Satires: MacFlecknoe, Book I of The
                Dunciad Varorum, The Vanity of Human Wishes." DA 29 (1968): 558A (Yale). </bib>
            <notes> An examination of the joint effects of stress-placement, caesura-placement,
                endstopping, syntax, and rhyme in each. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1361">
            <bib>-----. "The Style of The Vanity of Human Wishes." MLQ 35 (1974): 16-29. </bib>
            <notes> Shows specific features of meter and diction responsible for the discontinuity
                of structure and compression of statement which critics have found most striking
                about the poem. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1362">
            <bib>Balliet, Conrad A. "The History and Rhetoric of the Triplet." PMLA 80 (1965):
                528-34. </bib>
            <notes> Appendix table shows frequency of occurrence in poets, Grimald through Dr.
                Johnson. The device was used chiefly by Dryden; Pope employed it only about 75 times
                in 3000 lines. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1363">
            <bib>Barron, Joseph M. "Stylistic Development in the Poetry of Charles Churchill." DAI
                30 (1970): 3900A (Case Western Reserve). </bib>
            <notes> Chapter 3 discusses meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1364">
            <bib>Beatty, J. M. "Charles Churchill's Treatment of the Couplet." PMLA 34 (1919):
                60-69. </bib>
            <notes> Churchill's position as satirist of Classicism demanded that he imitate Pope's
                verses in order to parody them, yet his verses were considerably freer: their heavy
                enjambement in consecutive couplets and variation of pause influenced later
                pre-romantic poets considerably and also seemed to return to Dryden's ampler
                verse-structure, in preference to Pope's. Churchill's run-on couplet was further
                loosened by the influence of the rhythms of Shakespearean blank verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1365">
            <bib>Beeching, Henry C. "A Note Upon Waller's Distich." An English Miscellany Presented
                to Dr. Furnivall In Honour of His 75th Birthday. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1901. pp.
                4-9. </bib>
            <notes> Some minute particulars of the Wallerian Style, mainly negative: his pauses at
                couplet-end represent no new device in English poetry; he uses aureate diction and
                polysyllables but has monosyllabic lines as well, though never in clusters so as to
                be conspicuous; the line never exceeds five accents; he matches sense- pauses to
                breath-points, often ends with strong verbs, adopts the "epithetic" style of giving
                every noun an adjective; he allows himself an "uncompensated, unemphatic accent" at
                times in the third foot (otherwise termed "pyrrhic" by some; he rarely elides
                vowels, and he frequently uses the modal do. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1366">
            <bib>Blount, Thomas P. "Concerning Rhyme, and Blank Verse." De Re Poetica: or, Remarks
                upon Poetry. London, 1964; rpt in facsimile: Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar Press, 1972; </bib>
            <notes> rpt New York: Garland, 1974. pp. 102-6. Merely repeats the opinions of Dryden on
                heroic verse as the most suitable medium for drama. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1367">
            <bib>Brown, Wallace Cable. "Churchill's Mastery of the Heroic Couplet." JEGP 44 (1945):
                12-23. </bib>
            <notes> Concentrates on inter-linear more than intra-linear devices, mainly syntactic
                and structural. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1368">
            <bib>-----. "Gay's Mastery of the Heroic Couplet." PMLA 61 (1946): 114-25; </bib>
            <notes> rpt as chapter 2 of his The Triumph of Form (below). One of the most underrated
                poets in the English language, John Gay was sec- ond only to Pope in the correctness
                of his meter, use of expressive sound, bal- ance and antithesis, verbal rhymes,
                verse paragraphing, and satire. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1369">
            <bib>-----. The Triumph of Form: A Study of the Later Masters of the Heroic Couplet.
                Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1948. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in MLQ 11 (1950): 110-12; in MLN 66 (1950): 61-62; in Review of Eng- lish
                Studies n.s. 1 (1950): 366-67. Stemming from the author's earlier studies, this work
                studies both (1) technical mastery of versecraft and (2) "synthesis of style and
                content" in Gay, Johnson, Cowper, Young, Churchill, Goldsmith, and Crabbe. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1370">
            <bib>Carruth, Hayden. "Three Notes on the Versewriting of Alexander Pope." Michigan
                Quarterly Review 15 (1976): 371-81. </bib>
            <notes> Iconoclasm: Carruth argues that Pope "did everything he could, within the strict
                couplet, to relieve the jig-jog of standard pentameter"--i.e. (1) he used the
                apostrophe for all sorts of stylistic effects, and quite inconsistently, but never
                for mere metrical elision, because hiatus does occur in Pope's verse; (2) he used
                weak syllables in ictic position and, later, runs of up to three stresses followed
                by three slacks to break the iambic drone; and (3) he considered the couplet not as
                an "artificial" verseform but as "nearest prose," hence exhibiting, more than
                anything else, naturalness and "freedom from padding." In the early Pope, as Carruth
                shows in a brilliant demonstration, pentameters can be easily "translated" into
                tetrameters, but in the mature Pope no padding is allowed at all: every word pulls
                its weight. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1371">
            <bib>Catlett, Larue S. "'An Odde Promiscuous Tone': A Study of the Prosody of
                Hudibras." DAI 32 (1971): 3244A (Wisconsin). </bib>
            <notes> Butler's satiric intent is undercut by his own metrical incompetence. He appar-
                ently accepted "the restrictions of conservative theories" of prosody for his own
                verse-making, while he "repeatedly and violently" attacked them through his
                narrator. There are clear prosodic indications that Butler was "pretending to
                metrical regularity," yet his counterpointing of the metrical and rhythmic stresses
                is consistently imcompetent. The result is "a prosodic situation that is awkward,
                grotesque, and bathetic." And thus the polarizing of readers' re- sponses to
                Hudibras is explained: readers who recognize the stumbling rhythm find it "jolting";
                those who cannot, but hear only the metrical norm under- neath, find it "jogging."
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1372">
            <bib>Chase, Lewis N. The English Heroic Play: A Critical Description of the Rhymed
                Tragedy of the Restoration. New York: Columbia University Press, 1903. </bib>
            <notes> Appendix D lists plays written partly or wholly in heroic verse, 1656-1703.
                Additions in MLN 19 (1904): 152. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1373">
            <bib>Clark, Arthur M. "Thomas Heywood's Art of Love Lost and Found." The Library, 4th
                series, 3 (1922): 210-22. </bib>
            <notes> See the final page. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1374">
            <bib>Dickinson-Brown, Roger M. "The Art of Edmund Waller: A Technical and Prosodic
                Analysis." DAI 38 (1977): 2802A (Syracuse). </bib>
            <notes> Metrical analysis shows what we expected--that Waller's regularity in meter
                increases over time. But it also shows that he assimilated and perfected a num- ber
                of other prosodic techniques besides meter, especially alliteration (having
                "accidental, musical, emphatic, and grammatical" functions), off-rhyme, grammatical
                figuration, and enjambement. His metrical range was wider than we assume. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1375">
            <bib>Diller, Hans-Jürgen. "Linguistic Observations on the Heroic Couplet in English
                Poetry." Applications of Linguistics: Papers of the Second International Congress of
                Applied Linguistics. Ed. G. E. Perren and J. L. M. Trim. London: Cambridge
                University Press, 1971. pp. 181-88. </bib>
            <notes> An optimistic prospectus for the application of generative phonology and its
                methods to the study of versification. Diller suggests a number of intriguing areas
                for further inquiry, specifically emphatic and contrastive stress, intona- tional
                nuclei, parallelism, and enjambement. Heuristic. Examples from Pope. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1376">
            <bib>Dixon, Peter. "'Talking Upon Paper'" Pope and Eighteenth Century Conversa- tion."
                English Studies 46 (1965): 36-44. </bib>
            <notes> The first two pages admire Pope's remarkable skill at capturing the cadences of
                common contemporary speech in his meters, mainly by employment of elision and
                elimination of modals (do) as metrical fillers. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1377">
            <bib>Dryden, John. Essays of John Dryden. Ed. W. P. Ker. 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon
                Press, 1900; 1926. </bib>
            <notes> The "Epistle Dedicatory of The Rival Ladies" [1664] defends the use of rhyme,
                taking Waller as authority and precedent (see vol. 1, pp. 5-8). This was an- swered
                by Sir Robert Howard, in the Preface to his Plays [1665]; Dryden countered with the
                indomitable Of Dramatick Poesie, an Essay [1668] (see vol. 1, pp. 89-107); Howard
                tried to rally in the Preface to his The Great Favorite, or, The Duke of Lerma
                [1668]; Dryden fired the final volley in "A Defense of an Essay of Dramatic Poesy,"
                prefixed to the second edition of his The Indian Em- peror [1668] (vol. 2, pp.
                113-18). Aureng-zebe [1676]; by the way, was the last play Dryden wrote in rhyme
                (couplets). From the Rival Ladies preface comes the famous remark that the verse
                must serve as the "clogs" for the "high-ranging Spaniel" of the imagination. "The
                great easiness of blank verse renders the poet too luxuriant; he is tempted to say
                many things, which might better be omitted, or at least shut up in fewer words; but
                when the difficulty of artful rhyming is interposed . . . the fancy then gives
                leisure to the judgment to come in, which, seeing so heavy a tax imposed, is ready
                to cut off all unnecessary expense." This is Dryden's reply to those who think rhyme
                "only an embroidery of sense." In the Essay of Dramatick Poesie, Crites attacks the
                use of rhyme in plays (though he will allow them in poetry) on the grounds that the
                drama follows Nature, and of course there is no natural rhyming in Speech. Neander
                (Dry- den) replies on a variety of fronts: dramatic language, he observes, is
                height- ened over that of everyday speech, so rhyme is appropriate to the stage. And
                the pressure of the formal constraints forces the verse-making poet to think ahead,
                thereby sharpening his wits. Rhyme is equally proper for plays as for poetry; it
                "might be made as natural as blank verse by the well placing of the words, etc. All
                the difference between them when they are both correct, is, the sound in one, which
                the other wants." From the Preface to Albion and Albanius [1685]: while the
                recitative part of opera "requires a more masculine beauty of expression and sound,"
                the mu- sic "must abound in the softness and variety of numbers." "And yet there are
                rules . . . and as great a certainty of quantity in our syllables, as either in the
                Greek or Latin. . . ." Double rhymes and a symtax especially formed "for the
                sweetness of the voice" are the "main hinges" on which opera turns. The 1697
                Dedication of Aeneis (vol. 2, esp. pp. 214-34) defends the use of triplets and
                Alexandrines, on the authority of Spenser and Cowley, men- tioning also diction in
                translations. The great difficulty for the imitator of Vir- gil is "his numbers, his
                choice of words, and his placing them for the sweetness of the sound." Dryden
                recommends avoidance of caesura (needed in Latin to temper the lusciousness of
                over-abundant vowels), hiatus, and monosyllabic lines. More vexingly: "I have long
                had by me the materials of an English Proso- dia, containing all the mechnical rules
                of versification, wherein I have treated, with some exactness, of the feet, the
                quantities, and the pauses." Yet, "the evil of false quantities is difficult to be
                cured in any modern language" (pp. 217- 18). In the Preface to Fables Ancient &amp;
                Modern [1700] (vol. 2, esp. pp. 258- 59), Dryden compares Homer to Virgil, then
                asserts (mistakenly) that Chau- cer's meter is often rugged: his verse "is not
                harmonius to us" (though Dryden recognizes that it was not found so in Chaucer's own
                age). See also Dryden's poem "To the Earl of Roscommon," 11. 5-25. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1378">
            <bib>English, Hubert M., Jr. "Prosody and Meaning in Ben Jonson's Poems." Diss.; Yale
                Univesity, 1955. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1379">
            <bib>Erlich, Richard D., and James Harner. "Pope's Annotations in his Copy of Dryden's
                Comedies, Tragedies, and Operas: An Exercise in Cryptography." Restoration and 18th
                Century Theatre Research 10 (1971): 14-24. </bib>
            <notes> The authors think that Pope's cryptic marginal symbols refer to aspects of Dry-
                den's versification particularly worthy of note, though they have no proof and
                indeed account for several of the symbols on other grounds. In fact, the article
                appeals for a study of the matter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1380">
            <bib>Greenblatt, Daniel. "Ben Jonson's Prosody." Rackham Literary Studies (Michi-gan),
                no. 3 (1972), pp. 77-92. </bib>
            <notes> Not broad or statistical characterization of prosodic style but rather close
                expli- cation of prosodic expressiveness in four poems. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1381">
            <bib>Grübner, Willy. Der Einfluss des Reimes auf den Satzbau der englischen "Heroic
                Plays." Diss., Königsberg, 1912. 69 pp. </bib>
            <notes> A study of the distortion which the rhyme in couplet verse wreaks upon the
                syntax, especially in the Restoration dramas of Dryden, Lee, Otway, and Crowne.
                Since rhyme words are frequently verbs, and since the most useful form of the verb
                is the infinitive, present- and past-tense verbs are often sup- planted by do/did +
                infinitive. The rhyme may also necessitate splitting an oth- erwise-integral phrase,
                dropping syllables, adding proclitics or enclitics to fill out the line, or dumping
                excess material into the beginning of the following line ("bad enjambement").
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1382">
            <bib>Haswell, Richard E. "The Heroic Couplet Before Dryden (1550-1675)." Diss.,
                University of Illinois, 1932. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1383">
            <bib>Havens, Raymond D. "Changing Taste in the Eighteenth Century: Dryden's and
                Dodsley's Miscellanies." PMLA 44 (1929): 501-36. </bib>
            <notes> The considerable variation in the content of the five complex editions of
                "Dryden's Miscellany" from 1684 to 1727 furnishes valuable and reliable in-
                formation on the hegemony of the couplet over other metrical forms, and the nine
                editions of "Dodsley's Miscellany" between 1748 and 1758 show striking contrast. See
                pp. 504-7 and 522-25. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1384">
            <bib>-----. "Romantic Aspects of the Age of Pope." PMLA 27 (1912): 297-324. Pages
                320-22 offer some useful facts on the number of non-couplets being written in the
                Age of the Couplet. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1385">
            <bib>Heuser, Julius. Der Coupletreim in Shakespeare's Dramen. Diss., Marburg, 1893. Rpt
                in Shakespeare Jahrbuch 28 (1893): 177-272; 29 (1894): 235-45. </bib>
            <notes> Lists the couplets in each of the plays (Globe Edition) with some discussion.
                Criticized by Ness (C260). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1386">
            <bib>Holder, Kenneth R. "Some Linguistic Aspects of the Heroic Couplet in the Poetry of
                Phillis Wheatley." DAI 34 (1974): 5144A (North Texas State). </bib>
            <notes> On the complexity scale established by the Halle-Keyser theory of generative
                metrics, this eighteenth-century American poet scores rather low. Only about 85% of
                her rhymes are phonetically exact. And (transformational) syntactic analysis shows
                most of her sentences to be declarative. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1387">
            <bib>Holzhausen, P. "Dryden's heroisches Drama." Englische Studien 16 (1892):
                201-29.</bib>
            <notes> See the section on "Metrik" in this concluding installment of H's serial study,
                pp. 221-26. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1388">
            <bib>Jack, Ian. "Pope and "The Weighty Bullion of Dr. Donne's Satires.'" PMLA 66
                (1951): 1009-22. </bib>
            <notes> There are observations on pp. 1011-15 on Pope's smoothing of the "harshness" of
                Donne's meters when he came to imitate his Satires. Cf. Chatman (E709). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1389">
            <bib>Jones, Evan. "Verse, Prose, and Pope: A Form of Sensibility." Melbourne Critical
                Review, no. 4 (1961), pp. 30-40. </bib>
            <notes> Admitting the well-known metrical, syntactic, and rhetorical accomplishments of
                the closed couplet, Jones suggests, radically, that in the larger context of the
                poem the couplet form accentually impoverishes the coherence of the whole, by the
                attenuations of elaboration and by reliance on only a single effective mode of
                development--logic. The "play of sensibility" in the verse is thus con- strained.
                Comparing Donne's version of his Satires to Pope's reveals how Donne was able to
                create an "interplay of verse and prose structure," the prose syntax having maximum
                play within the metrical form, whereas in Pope the verse-structure (pace Matthew
                Arnold) entirely subsumes and compels the prose statement. Extraordinary insight
                here. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1390">
            <bib>Jones, John A. Pope's Couplet Art. Athens: Ohio University Press, 1969; 217 pp.
                Based on his dissertation, "Line Structure and Sentence Form in Pope's Couplets," DA
                29 (1968): 872A (Florida). </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Style 6 (1972): 198-202; in English Studies 53 (1972): 258-63. A stylish
                non-technical study of Pope's handling of his in eight representative, major poems.
                Over the course of Pope's career his verse decreased slightly its reliance on
                balance for structure, increased slightly its use of the open couplet, and shifted
                from an early tendency to compose in terms of the line to a late tendency to compose
                by the sentence. In many respects the most distinguished example of Pope's
                versecraft is The Rape of the Lock. But balance and closure are primary concerns in
                his verse-architecture throughout. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1391">
            <bib>Kaul, R. K. "Rhyme and Blank Verse in Drama: A Note on Eliot." English 15 (1964):
                96-99. </bib>
            <notes> Contrasts the opinions of Johnson (disapproving) and Eliot (approving) on the
                suitability of rhymed verse as the medium of drama. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1392">
            <bib>Kermode, Frank, and J. C. Maxwell. "Marvell." Notes &amp; Queries 197 (1952): 136-
                37, 218 </bib>
            <notes> (see also p. 317 on the meter of the "Horatian Ode"); 206 (1961): 309. Marvell
                found a model for the meter of "The Mower Against Gardens" (pen- tameter/tetrameter
                couplets) in Randolph, and there are instances also in Jon- son (Epode II), the
                ultimate source of the meter being Horace's Epodes rather than the Latin elegiac.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1393">
            <bib>Kirsch, Arthur C. "Dryden's Theory of the Rhymed Heroic Play." In his Dryden's
                Heroic Drama. Princeton University Press, 1965. pp. 3-33. </bib>
            <notes>Based on his dissertation, DA 22 (1961): 1979A (Princeton). Section 4, "Rhyme"
                discusses Dryden's context and technique; compare this with p. 126 ff on his later
                shift to blank verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1394">
            <bib>Cf. B. J. Pendlebury, Dryden's Heroic Plays (New York: Russell &amp; Russell,
                1923; rpt 1967), p. 62 ff. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1395">
            <bib>Krischel, Violet. "Prosodic Similarities to Pope in Five of Byron's Satires." DAI
                37 (1976): 2897A (Arkansas). </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1396">
            <bib>Kulisheck, Clarence L. "Swift's Octosyllabics and the Hudibrastic Tradition." JEGP
                53 (1954): 361-68. </bib>
            <notes> "Swift's octosyllabics are to be Hudibrastic tradition as the blank verse of
                Tam- burlaine was to Gorboduc." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1397">
            <bib>Low, Anthony. "A Metrical Device in 'The Exeguy.'" MLR 63 (1968): 7-12. </bib>
            <notes> This is the device of the "extended couplet"--a couplet "relatively separate
                from what goes before, [followed by] an extra half-line, divided by a caesura from
                [the other half-line that] follows." That is, the sense-group is two-and-a- half
                lines long. The effect is one either of unexpected expansion or of unnatu- ral
                incompleteness. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1398">
            <bib>Mahony, Patrick J. "the Heroic Couplet in Donne's Anniversaries." Style 4 (1970):
                107-17. </bib>
            <notes> Donne's couplets do not show the symmetrical, balanced, antithetical style of
                the Augustans; he allows himself considerable freedom in caesura-placement,
                enjambement, feminine endings, and chiastic and punning rhymes. Perhaps the "looser
                structure and softly focused endings" of his verse were influenced by the looser
                Baroque prose. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1399">
            <bib>Mead, William Edward. The Versification of Pope in its Relation to the Seven-teeth
                Century. Diss., Leipzig. Leipzig: Frankenstein and Wagner, 1889. 143pp. </bib>
            <notes> Old, but still very useful: the study surveys the 15,000 lines of Pope's verse
                (excluding translations from Homer) and concludes that (1) Pope exercised care in
                matching verse-ictus with word-stress; (2) he was unsurpassed in use of (mainly
                end-of-line) pauses; (3) he learned from Waller what devices to avoid; (4) he
                surpassed Dryden in artistic self-control and craftsmanship in satire; (5) he
                repeated rhymes monotonously, used false rhymes, avoided polysyllables, and relied
                on conventionalized seventeenth-century rhymes too heavily, availing himself of the
                further convenience of the newer eighteenth-century changes in pronunciation. Part 1
                on verse-structure covers forty pages, Part 2 on rhymes, the re- maining hundred.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1400">
            <bib>Meyer, H. Studien zur Verkunst Alexander Popes. Diss., Göttingen,1930. 123 pp. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1401">
            <bib>Miller, Clarence H. "The Styles of 'The Hind and the Panther.'" JEGP 61 (1962):
                511-27. </bib>
            <notes> Versification on pp. 523-26. This "most flexible poem of an eminently flexible
                poet" does indeed employ three distinct styles (respectively, high, plain, and
                mixed/familiar) for its three parts. Metrically, the first part is high in medial
                caesuras and enjambement, while caesuras are more scattered and run-ons less
                frequent in the other two parts; the number of Alexandrine, triplets, com- plexes of
                both these, and "pyrrhic substitutions" declines steadily as the poem progresses.
                Sample passages of a dozen or so lines from each part are scanned and compared.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1402">
            <bib>Parfitt, George A. E. "Compromise Classicism: Language and Rhythm in Ben Jonson's
                Poetry." Studies in English Literature 1500-1900 11 (1971): 109-23. </bib>
            <notes> Analysis of meter and language shows that Jonson owed less to the Classics than
                to the contemporary "plain style" tradition. "With Jonson the tension between speech
                and verse-rhythm is unusually strong and the pattern of em- phasis very varied. . .
                the total result is that our attention is directed less to the line or couplet than
                to particular words or phrases emphasized at various points within these units."
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1403">
            <bib>Partridge, A. C. "Form and Language in English Neo-Classical Poetry." An English
                Miscellany Presented to W. S. Mackie. Ed. Brian S. Lee. Cape Town: Oxford University
                Press, 1977. pp. 131-48. </bib>
            <notes> A thick packet of remarks on nearly all the familiarly-known features of the
                Augustan "refinement of language" in poetry, including purification of syntax in
                couplets, strategic placement and weighting of verbs, appropriate and ur- bane
                diction, restraint in figures, parallelism, and metrical elision and modula- tion.
                Versification, pp. 140-46. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1404">
            <bib>Piper, William Bowman. The Heroic Couplet. Cleveland: Case Western Reserve
                University Press, 1969; 465 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Wimsatt in JEGP 70 (1971): 312-15. Part 1 gives the history and
                structure of the form; Part 2 provides forty-eight short summaries of the style of
                specific authors, Chaucer to Keats. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1405">
            <bib>-----. "The Inception of the Closed Heroic Couplet." MP 66 (1969): 306-21; rpt as
                chapter 3 of his The Heroic Couplet (above). </bib>
            <notes> A study of the two forces which led to the rise of the couplet form in the
                Renaissance--the standard iambic pentameter line with caesura which was "the staple
                of English versification by the time the history of the English closed couplet
                began," and the Renaissance interest in translating and imitating the Latin elegaic
                distich. Close study of Marlowe's translations of Ovid and Jon- son's of Martial
                show their efforts to refine devices of pausing, balance and an- tithesis, a
                dynamics between meter and speech rhythm, zeugma and other fig- ures, and a
                conversational tone, all of which they found in their Latin sources. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1406">
            <bib>Provost, Foster. "Pope's Pastorals: An Exercise in Poetical Technique."
                Contributions to the Humanities, 1954. Louisiana State University Studies,
                Humanistic Series, no. 5. Baton Rouge: LSU Press, 1954. pp. 25-37. </bib>
            <notes> See Section B, "Experiments in Versification," pp. 30-35. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1407">
            <bib>Quivey, James. "Marvell's Couplet Art: 'Last Instructions to a Painter.'" Essays
                in Literature (Western Illinois University) 1 (1974): 28-36. </bib>
            <notes> Should one speak of expressive metrical modulations when the tone created is one
                of "brash, bawdy burlesquerie"? Close prosodic analysis of a long and ob- scure
                poem. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1408">
            <bib>Riley, Joseph R. "George Crabbe's Prosodic Theory and Practice." DA 23 (1962):
                1370A (Vanderbilt). </bib>
            <notes> On the whole Crabbe's prosodic practice was conventional, conforming closely to
                Bysshe's rules, and it was liberalized only modestly over the course of his career.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1409">
            <bib>Rymer, Thomas. The Critical Works of Thomas Rymer. Ed. Curt A. Zimansky. New
                Haven: Yale University Press, 1956. </bib>
            <notes> At various times Rymer both defended (pp. 3-7, 76, 77) and castigated (p. 118)
                the use of Ryme (couplets). He used that meter for his 1677 tragedy Ed- gar--on the
                grounds that the play ended happily--but by the 1692 Short View of Tragedy could
                reject it as entirely inappropriate for Tragedy: "Our Ear shou'd not be hankering
                after the Ryme, when the business should wholly take us up, and fill our Head. The
                words must be all free, independant, and disengag'd, no entanglement of Ryme to be
                in our way." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1410">
            <bib>Sackton, Alexander H. "The Rhymed Couplet in Ben Jonson's Plays." University of
                Texas Studies in English 30 (1951): 86-106. </bib>
            <notes> A review of the uses of the couplet in each of Jonson's plays, in chronological
                order. Even more than for epigrams or for scene-ending in plays Jonson's use of
                rhyme is significant for consecutive runs of couplets in the speeches of seri- ous
                plays, as Dryden recognized. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1411">
            <bib>Schelling, Felix E. "Ben Jonson and the Classical School." PMLA 13 (1898): 221- 49 </bib>
            <notes>; also published as an offprint with an Index. See pp. 234-40. It was Jonson who
                first established the precise form of the couplet (strictly hemistichic and stopped)
                which, through Waller, Dryden, and Pope, was to dominate English poetry for the next
                century and a half, as can be seen by a statistical comparison of the metrical
                features of the couplets of the major Augustan poets. Those poets using the form
                before Jonson, together with Sandys, all adhere to the somewhat different model
                established by Spenser. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1412">
            <bib>Sentimental Fables. translated from the French with the original and notes. To
                which is prefixed, an essay on English versification by a country curate. Brentford:
                P. Norbury for the Author, 1775. </bib>
            <notes> The Preface (pp. iii-xx) defends the use of heroic measure for Fables, examines
                Pope's letter to Walsh on rhyming, criticizes imperfect rhymes and the same rhyme
                sound used (in different words) too frequently too close together, ap- proves of
                variety in caesura-placement, defends Dryden from Pope's criticism concerning
                elision, and emphasizes the virtue of making the sound "seem an echo to the sense."
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1413">
            <bib>Shannon, George P. "The Heroic Couplet in the Sixteenth and Early Seventeenth
                Centuries, with Special Reference to the Influence of Ovid and the Latin Elegaic
                Distich." Leland Stanford University Abstracts of Dissertations 2 (1926-27): 127-34. </bib>
            <notes> The argument for the Latin elegaic couplet as the source for the "classical"
                English closed couplet rests on a high degree of similarity between the two in
                end-stopping, metrical regularity, and balance/antithesis. A full survey of the
                couplets written from Chaucer to the 1630's shows that the major develop- ment began
                with Tottel (1557) in translations of Ovid and reached its zenith, in 1590-1610, in
                satire and the epigram; after 1610 the incidence of the open couplet increases under
                the influence of the Tribe of Ben and John Donne. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1414">
            <bib>-----. "Nicholas Grimald's Heroic Couplet and the Latin Elegaic Distich." PMLA 45
                (1930): 532-42. </bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation (above). Shannon proposes Grimald as the pioneer in
                the use of the couplet in the early Renaissance. Survey of his works shows that
                Grimald's couplets--his favorite meter--are used mainly for epigrams, elegies, and
                occasional verse, maintain good continuity, show a high degree of closure, employ
                balance and antithesis, and were generally scrupulous about correct rhymes, metrical
                regularity, and aureate diction. Similar statistical surveying shows these
                neoclassical features to be very close to those of Latin elegaic verse (Martial and
                Ovid). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1415">
            <bib>Shipley. Joseph T. "Spenserian Prosody: The Couplet Forms." SP 21 (1924): 594-615. </bib>
            <notes> Rejecting the view that Spenser's couplets reveal his ignorance or misunder-
                standing of the function of final -e in the Chaucerian pentameter, Shipley ar- gues
                from detailed phonological evidence that in fact Spenser must have known it; the
                mistake derives from an assumption that the Chaucerian pen- tameter rather than the
                tetrameter was Spenser's model for the couplets of the February, May, and September
                eclogues. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1416">
            <bib>Skinner, James L., III. "William Cowper's Use of the Heroic Couplet." DA 26
                (1966): 4640A (Arkansas). </bib>
            <notes> Metrically Cowper was not influenced by Churchill. His position in terms of
                metrical style lies midway between Dryden and Pope on the one hand and Churchill and
                Keats on the other. He varies caesura-placement more than Pope but his end-stopping,
                rhymes, and stress-variations are more conservative than Pope's. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1417">
            <bib>Sparling, Ivan H. "On Writing Couplets." Missouri English Bulletin 27 (1970):
                4-11. </bib>
            <notes> Cited in MHRA for 1970 but unlocated by the Library of Congress. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1418">
            <bib>Speerschneider, Otto. Metrische Untersuchungen über den heroischen Vers in John
                Dryden's Dramen. Diss., Halle, 1897. 88 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Merely lists examples of varieties of syllabification, word-stressing, and
                verse- rhythm (caesura, inversions, hovering stress, extra and missing syllables,
                femi- nine endings, Alexandrines and short verses, lineation, rhyme, other meters,
                enjambement and endstopping, alliteration, and diaeresis). Cf. Meyer (E1250).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1419">
            <bib>Stein, Arnold. "Donne and the Couplet." PMLA 57 (1942): 676-96. </bib>
            <notes> On Donne's "chief prosodic innovation," the rhyming of words with feminine and
                masculine endings, also other devices for facilitating smooth enjambement:
                stress-shifts, late caesura, line-end polysyllables, following-line anacrusis. Be-
                yond, there are the wider reaches of register and voice--Donne's austere music of
                monosyllables and consonants, his preferences for strength over smoothness and sense
                over sound. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1420">
            <bib>Swoboda, Wilhelm. "Versbau der Heywood'schen Interludes." John Heywood also
                Dramatiker. Wiener Beiträger zur deutschen und englischen Philologie, no. 3. Vienna:
                Wilhelm Braumüller, 1888. pp. 83-107. </bib>
            <notes> Heywood uses two line-forms, the iambic tetrameter (octosyllabic) and a four-
                stress long line descended from the old alliterative form. Swoboda surveys metrical
                variation, enjambement, rhyme, and position of alliterations, follow- ing Schipper's
                analysis. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1421">
            <bib>Tatlock, J. S. P. "Origin of the Closed Couplet in English." The Nation 98 (1
                April 1914): 390. </bib>
            <notes> Candidate: Thomas Heywood, in Epistle XVI and XVII of Ovid's "Heroides" in
                Heywood's Britaines Troy (1609). E1422 E. C. Knowlton replies in The Nation 99 (30
                July 1914): 134, arguing instead for Joseph Hall in his Virgideniarum (1597).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1423">
            <bib>Thompson, Elbert N. S. "The Octosyllabic Couplet." PQ 18 (1939): 257-68. </bib>
            <notes> History of the modulations of the form in a number of English poets from Chaucer
                to Milton and Waller. Oddly, though, Thompson derives the octo- syllabic couplet
                from the four-stress Old English line, and "possibly" from the French, whereas he
                derives the heroic couplet from the Latin elegaic meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1424">
            <bib>Tillotson, Geoffrey. "Correctness IV. Versification: 'Certain Niceties.'" In his
                On the Poetry of Pope. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1938, 2nd ed. 1950, 1959. pp.
                105-40. </bib>
            <notes> In comparison with Pope, Dryden was laxer, easier, allowing himself the ex-
                pansiveness of a triplet or Alexandrine whenever it was convenient; Pope however
                adopted the rule making "difficulties overcome more admirable than difficulties
                accommodated." The great advantage of the couplet as a form is its greater control
                of the reader's attention, since the reader knows the poet is re- sponsible for each
                one of the twenty syllables in every line. The early Pope concerned himself (in the
                letter to Walsh) with mimetic sound and modal verbs; the mature Pope preferred
                monosyllables--usually one of them a verb-- as rhymes, emphasized the importance of
                balance as a structural principle, and perfected the disposition of the weighty and
                unexpected polysyllable within the line. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1425">
            <bib>Wallerstein, Ruth. "The Development of the Rhetoric and Metre of the Heroic
                Couplet, Especially in 1625-1645." PMLA 50 (1935): 166-209. </bib>
            <notes> Cf. Williamson (E1437); both studies were published in the same year. The
                present one is a monograph on the metrical development of the couplet in Drayton,
                Fairfax, Jonson, the occasional verse of Sandys and his circle, Falk- land, Waller,
                and Denham. (Waller's "rhetorical and musical patterns are the perfection and
                systematization of the basically simple and formal units created by Fairfax and
                Sandys.") This is a study much richer in scope and discernment than its companion.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1426">
            <bib>Wasserman, Earl R. "Elizabethan Poetry 'Improved.'" MP 37 (1940): 357-69. </bib>
            <notes> Eighteenth-century revisionist versions of Renaissance verse, regularizing me-
                ter, diction, and syntax. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1427">
            <bib>-----. "The Return of the Emjambed Couplet." ELH 7 (1940): 239-52. </bib>
            <notes> The tide of resistance to the Popean closed couplet after the midpoint of the
                eighteenth century turned primarily to blank verse, of course, taking Milton as its
                model, but there were some vestiges of interest in the run-on couplet per- fected by
                Dryden--chiefly in the poems and essays of Churchill, William J. Mickle, William
                Belsham, Joseph Weston, Richard Mant, William Lisle Bowles, and Samuel Rogers.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1428">
            <bib>Westcott, Allan F. "Traces of Classical Style in Poetry of the Early Seventeenth
                Century." Sewanee Review 16 (1908): 257-76. </bib>
            <notes> Metrical analysis of the earlier seventeenth-century satirists--Donne, Row-
                lands, Marston, Wither, and Hall, as well as Beaumont, Drummond, and Jon-
                son--against the later couplet-writers Dryden and Pope. The "classical" design of
                the heroic couplet restricted the sense quite rigidly to the distich, strived for
                internal "smoothness" (absence of stops and pauses0, and achieved a "lightness and
                swiftness" of tempo (frequent pyrrhics). The influence of King James I's Revlis and
                Cautelis (E560) is also surveyed. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1429">
            <bib>Weston, Joseph. Philotoxi Ardenae . . . by John Morfitt . . . With a Translation
                in Blank Verse, Another in Rhyme, Attempted in the Manner of Dryden . . . and an
                Essay on the Superiority of Dryden's Versification over that of Pope and of the
                Moderns, by Joseph Weston. Birmingham, 1788; rpt in Records of the Woodmen of Arden
                from 1785. Ed. W. K. R. Bedford. Edinburgh: Privately Printed, 1885. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1430">
            <bib>Weygant, Peter S. "Oldham's Versification and the Literary Style of the English
                Enlightenment." Enlightenment Essays 3 (1972): 120-25. </bib>
            <notes> Oldham's major work, the Satyrs, is admittedly rough in meter but it is un-
                characteristic of his work as a whole: he could vary metrical style with genre when
                he wished, and his work is in general quite conventionally regular. [In fact, the
                meter of the Satyrs is much less rough than even Weygant believes.] </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1431">
            <bib>Wheeler, Thomas. "Milton's Blank Verse Couplets." JEGP 66 (1967): 359-68. </bib>
            <notes> On unrhymed couplets (two-line syntactic units) in Milton's epics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1432">
            <bib>Wikelund, Philip R. "Edmund Waller's Fit of Versifying: Deductions from a
                Holograph Fragment, Folger MS. X.d. 309." PQ 49 (1970): 68-91. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1433">
            <bib>-----. "The Fettered Muse: Aspects of the Theory of Verse Translation in Augustan
                English 1640-1750." Diss., U.C.L.A., 1948. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1434">
            <bib>Wilke, Wilhelm. Metrische Untersuchungen zu Ben Jonson. Diss., Halle, 1888. 70 pp. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1435">
            <bib>-----. "Anwendung der Rhyme-Test und Double-Endings Test auf Ben Jonson's Dramen."
                Anglia 10 (1887): 512-21. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1436">
            <bib>Williams, Aubrey L. "Alexander Pope's 'Knack' at Versifying." All These to Teach.
                Ed. Robert A. Bryan et al. Gainesville: University of Florida Press, 1965. pp.
                171-79. </bib>
            <notes> Pope's use of the word was ironic; in fact, his verse-making was nothing ex-
                cept dilligently laborious. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1437">
            <bib>Williamson, George. "The Rhetorical Pattern of Neo-Classical Wit." MP 33 (1935):
                55-81. </bib>
            <notes> A classic study in the development of the couplet form, which resulted from a
                confluence of a metrical tradition (running from Puttenham to Byssche) fa- voring
                rhyme and a rhetorical-syntactic tradition encouraging parallelism, bal- ance, and
                antithesis. The great linchpin in the line is Ben Jonson; beside him, Waller is a
                "consolidator" rather than an innovator, whose main achievement was to shift the
                matter of the couplet from the paradox of (metaphysical )wit to the sharp bite of
                out-and-out antithesis. It was the joint effort of these two men to weld the proper
                rhetorical form to its proper metrical frame in the couplet. Cf. Wallerstein
                (E1425). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1438">
            <bib>Wood, Henry. "Beginnings of the 'Classical' Heroic Couplet in England." American
                Journal of Philology 11 (1890) 55-79. </bib>
            <notes>Also published separately as an offprint. See p. 73 ff. It was Sandys rather than
                Waller who was the first English poet to write the new French-style stopped
                couplets. Wood compares the degree of stopping in these two poets particularly but
                also in Pope, Drummond, and Beaumont. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1439">
            <bib>Wyld, H. C. "Observations on Pope's Versification." MLR 25 (1930): 274-85. </bib>
            <notes> A demonstration of the nearly infinite variation of pacing or speed in Pope's
                lines by the use of consecutive weak syllables, the employment of half-stresses both
                singly and in combination with the weaks, and of course the disposition of the
                caesural pause. Wyld also examines the hypothesized retardation of the line by
                consonants and monosyllables, concluding that (1) short consonants either singly or
                in groups do not impair speed, whereas (2) long consonants, singly or in pairs,
                groups of three or more consonants, and any consonantal clusters where rapid
                shifting of the tongue is required do retard the line, though (3) two monosyllables
                are not a priori any harder (slower) to pronounce than a dissyllable--slowness
                depends not on word-boundaries but on phonetic patterns. See also: B212, C231, C236,
                C249, C260, C378, E709, E787, E1254, F155, F181-83, F213, K76. </notes>
        </item>



    </chapter>
</bibliography>
