<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="FREE VERSE">

        <item id="E1440">
            <bib>Allen, Charles. "Cadenced Free Verse." College English 9 (1948): 195-99. </bib>
            <notes> Following Patterson (D248) and Amy Lowell (E1498), Allen distinguishes between
                "accentual" and "cadenced" free verse, and (disregarding the former) shows the
                latter to comprise "reading-time units, line cadences, and strophic rhythms." That
                is, the lines tend to be built up of phrases which are perceptu- ally isochronous in
                reading and parallel syntactically, longer sequences of similiar phrases in the poem
                (hence timing) being called "strophes." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1441">
            <bib>Allen, Gay Wilson. "Biblical Analogues for Walt Whitman's Prosody." Révue
                Anglo-Américaine 10 (1933): 490-507. </bib>
            <notes> Whitman's two prosodic principles were parallelism (synonymous, antithetic,
                synthetic, and climactic; frequently in "envelopes" but sometimes internal) and
                repetition (initial, medial, or final). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1442">
            <bib>-----. A New Walt Whitman Handbook. New York: New York University Press, 1975. </bib>
            <notes> Replaces the original 1946 edition. The section on "'Organic' Rhythm" (pp.
                230-39) in Chapter 4 has scansions. See also the very useful Bibliography on pp.
                395-99. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1443">
            <bib>-----. "On the Trochaic Meter of 'O Pioneers! O Pioneers.' " American Literature
                20 (1949): 449-51. </bib>
            <notes> Whitman's poem (first published in Drum Taps) uses a relatively regular tro-
                chaic meter to represent the forceful cadences of marching-rhythm. The problems of
                "organic" versification also pertain. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1444">
            <bib>Andrews, C. E. "The Rhythm of Prose and Free Verse." Sewanee Review 26 (1918):
                183-94. </bib>
            <notes> Of interest here is the author's recognition that a prose rhythm must be trans-
                muted to become a verse-rhythm. Of more interest are the exhibits of rhyth- mically
                identical but semantically different passages of prose, which, though they are
                parallel, cannot be read the same way; Andrews draws the inference that rhythm as an
                objective or abstract entity is much less important than con- tent for determining
                the overall effect (contour) of the passage. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1445">
            <bib>Archer, William. Poets of the Younger Generation. London: John Lane, 1902. </bib>
            <notes> Chapters on thirty-three poets; a great many of the remarks on the verse sam-
                ples throughout the book are on metrics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1446">
            <bib>Austin, Mrs. Mary. "Native Rhythms." Literary Review, 1 July 1922, pp. 769-70. </bib>
            <notes> Comment by S. T. Byington, July 22, p. 831, and by H. M. Watts, August 12, pp.
                878-80; reply by Mrs. Austin, Sept. 2, p. 926. Further discussion in the issue for
                October 14, pp. 101-2, by Charles S. Baldwin: "Which Verse Is Free?" </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1447">
            <bib>Barber, Virginia P. "The Poetics of William Carlos Williams." DAI 33 (1972): 301A
                (Duke, 1970). </bib>
            <notes> Only passing attention to versification. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1448">
            <bib>Barry, Sister M. Martin. An Analysis of the Prosodic Structure of Selected Poems
                of T. S. Eliot. Rev. ed. Washington, D.C.: Catholic University of America Press,
                1969. Based on her dissertation at C.U.A. in 1948. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Baum in South Atlantic Quarterly 48 (1949): 155-56. A study of fourteen
                representative poems in order to discern signs and direc- tions of development,
                based on the system of La Drière (E570). Thus, Barry devotes separate chapters to
                analyses of "group cadence" [rhythmic groupings of syllables based on stress and
                syntax], "general cadence" [meter, in effect], and "measure" [balance within the
                line and correspondence between lines]. This method will not distinguish
                stress-verse very well, however. The reader should go straight to the concluding
                (fourth) chapter, since the system is so bulky as effectively to obscure any
                discoveries made in the earlier chapters. Appendices of tabular data, Bibliography.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1449">
            <bib>Bennett, Florence M. "A Laboratory Experiment in Poetry." Poet-Lore 33 (1922):
                537-52. </bib>
            <notes> Scans some free-verse lines for both quantity and accent; she seems to think
                them lagaoedic, as in Greek, while saying that her intent is "to show that it is
                possible to measure this mysterious thing, the 'cadence,' by the foot or the musical
                bar." Eccentric and prolix. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1450">
            <bib>Binyon, Laurence. Tradition and Reaction in Modern Poetry. English Association
                Pamphlet no. 63. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1926. </bib>
            <notes> "Some element of resistance stimulates and fortifies." "Free verse is a soft me-
                dium." "To write successfully without metre needs . . . more mastery of rhythm, and
                a severer sense of form" than to write verse that is metered. Binyon concludes
                against free verse. Much here on the functions of meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1451">
            <bib>Bowering, George. "The New American Prosody." Kulchur 4, 15 (Autumn 1964): 3-15. </bib>
            <notes> Tracing the free-verse tradition through Poe, Hopkins, Dickinson, Williams, and
                Olson, the author emphasizes as the crux of free-verse the precise notation of the
                poet's oral delivery of his lines. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1452">
            <bib>Bradley, Sculley. "The Fundamental Metrical Principle in Whitman's Poetry.'
                American Literature 10 (1939): 437-59. </bib>
            <notes> Whitman's conception of verse was derived through the Transcendentalists from
                Coleridge (organic form) and the German Romantics. His practice, his meter, is
                derived through the ballads from the old native stress-meter of Old English poetry;
                it is thus a nonsyllabic meter characterized by a principle of pe- riodicity and by
                hovering accent, which demarcate equal intervals of time. Fur- ther, Whitman's poems
                reveal a tightly unified pyramidal structure of line- lengths and line-groupings.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1453">
            <bib>Bridges, Robert. "Humdrum and Harum-Scarum: A Lecture on Free Verse." North
                American Review 216 (1922): 647-58. Also in London Mercury 7 (1922): 54-63 (see
                following correspondence on pp. 306-7). </bib>
            <notes> Rpt in his Collected Essays, Papers, &amp;. London: Oxford University Press,
                1927-36. Vol. 2, no. 2, pp. 35-55. Counterpoises free verse to prose: in giving up
                fixed meter, the poet is forced to rely even more heavily on rhythm, and the rhythms
                of free verse are simply more regular than those of prose. Cites four distinct
                disadvantages of the loss of meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1454">
            <bib>Brooke-Rose, Christine. A Structural Analysis of Pound's "Usura Canto": Jakobson's
                Method Extended and Applied to Free Verse. The Hague: Mouton, 1976. 76 pp. </bib>
            <notes> The analysis finds that the canto is kinetic rather than static, enacting its
                mes- sage rather than merely asserting it. The prosodist will be interested in
                "Level 3: Phonic and Prosodic" (pp. 59-65) and the table in Appendix B (pp. 71-72).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1455">
            <bib>Burdett, Osbert. "Vers Libre." The New Statesman 20 (1923): 453-54. </bib>
            <notes> Recognizes 3 types of rhythmical speech: meter, cadenced prose, and prose.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1456">
            <bib>Byrd, Don. "The Possibility of Measure in Olson's Maximus." Boundary 2 (1973):
                39-54. </bib>
            <notes> Olson's verse is quantitative, not in the classical sense but in its attention
                to the duration and the "weight" of syllables; Olson was interested in these, in
                mod- ern atonal music, in classical Greek ontological concepts. . . . </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1457">
            <bib>Catel, Jean. Rythme et Langage dans Première Édition des "Leaves of Grass" (1855). </bib>
            <notes> Diss., Paris, 1930. Montpellier: Causse, Graille et Castelnau, 1930. 195 pp.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1458">
            <bib>Ciardi, John. "How Free Is Free Verse?" Saturday Review, 11 October 1958, p. 38. </bib>
            <notes> Argues that the verse-line of William Carlos Williams is "a series of variations
                on an iambic-pentameter line divided into three equal units by the careful control
                of caesuras." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1459">
            <bib>Clare, John. "Form in Vers Libre." English 27 (1978): 150-70. </bib>
            <notes> Relying on a notion of "loops" or "return" in poetry created by reiterated
                sounds or syntax, Clare distinguishes six types of free verse: "spherical" (using
                such circular devices frequently), "rhythmical" (loose iambics), "cadenced" (heavy
                endstopping and parallelism), "musical" (in counterpointed rhythms), "balanced," and
                "vernacular." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1460">
            <bib>Cone, Eddie G. "The Free Verse Controversy in American Magazines, 1912- 1922." DAI
                32 (1972): 4605A (Duke). </bib>
            <notes> The "disintegration of one poetic tradition" and concomitant search for an-
                other was not much expedited or clarified by the periodical criticism of the time;
                au contraire, it mainly mirrored the confusions and polemics of the times. A
                detailed historical study, demonstrating strikingly the process by which spe- cific
                attacks and rebuttals broadened into larger, deeper theoretical issues in prosody.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1461">
            <bib>Cook, Albert. "Rhythm and Person in The Cantos." New Approaches to Ezra Pound. Ed.
                Eva Hesse. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1969. pp. 349-64. </bib>
            <notes> In the first section Cook argues that "three mutual possibilities of design-
                scansion [i.e. major metrical systems]--Greek dipodies, or else iambs, or else
                trochees and dactyls--are not superimposed on each other . . . because they are only
                possibilities; no one emerges as a main design. . . . The effect is of great
                modulation (multiple design) and of great freedom (masterly instance) . . . The
                instances are so diverse we attend to each one: instance becomes design." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1462">
            <bib>Corke, Hillary. "Is Metre a Dirty Word? and other observations on the present
                state of poetry." London Magazine, vol. 7, no. 4 (1960): 52-62. </bib>
            <notes> Interim report on the modern malady, "metre-deafness," now nearing epi- demic
                proportions, with specimens of some of the more grievously afflicted cases. See the
                ensuing controversy in TLS (E1513). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1463">
            <bib>Cory, Robrt E. "The Prosody of Walt Whitman." North Dakota Quarterly 28 (1960):
                74-79. </bib>
            <notes> From a great mass of jargon here we may extract the fact that Whitman's lines
                are written in phrasal units, but little else. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1464">
            <bib>Biehl, Paul B. "The Renewal of Abstraction: E. E. Cummings' Sentiment, Sonnets,
                and Meters." DAI 37 (1976): 2869A (Texas). </bib>
            <notes> A stout defense of cummings' critically sagging reputation by showing that (1)
                sentiment is one thing, sentimentality another; (2) Cummings wrote a very surprising
                number of sonnets and other traditional forms--his poems are not predominantly
                "gimmicks"; and (3) he mastered a variety of meters, both vis- ual and aural,
                especially in syllabic-, stress-, and foot-verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1465">
            <bib>Dudek, Louis. "A Note of Metrics." Delta (Montreal), no. 5 (Oct. 1958), pp. 15-17. </bib>
            <notes> The most distinctive, melodic poetry will abandon the "repetitive rhythmical
                beat" of iambic/rhymed verse--i.e. meter--in favor of an utterly unique form. "Metre
                makes it easy to counterfeit poetry." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1466">
            <bib>Eliot, T. S. Ezra Pound: His Metric and Poetry. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1917.
                31 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Rpt in his To Criticize the Critic. London: Faber and Faber, 1965. pp. 162-82.
                Tracing Pound's formal development and the critical reactions in the English
                literary review, Eliot emphasizes the erudition, "temperance," virtuosity, and
                consistency of Pound's work. He was most indebted to Yeats and Browning, he mastered
                "the adaptability of metre to mood" he had "a tendency toward quantitative measure,"
                and he created a free verse whose "freedom" derived solely from working "tirelessly
                with rigid forms and different systems of metric." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1467">
            <bib>-----. "Reflections on Verse Libre." The New Statesman 9 (3 March 1917): 518-19; </bib>
            <notes> rpt in his To Criticize the Critic. London: Faber and Faber, 1965. pp. 183-89.
                Eliot's famous, brilliant argument that Vers Libre does not exist," since it has no
                positive definition, only "absence of pattern, absence of rhyme, absence of meter."
                It is "a battlecry of freedom, and there is no freedom in art. . . . There is no
                escape from metre; there is only mastery. . . . the ghost of some simple metre
                should lurk behind the arras in even the 'freest' verse; to advance men- acingly as
                we doze, and withdraw as we rouse. . . . The rejection of rhyme is not a leap at
                facility; it imposes a much severer strain upon the language." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1468">
            <bib>Engel, Bernard F. "The Verse Line of Dr. Williams: A Fact of the Thing Itself."
                Papers of the Michigan Academy of Sciences, Arts, and Letters 46 (1961): 665-70. </bib>
            <notes> Argues that Williams' line is measured in phrases containing one major stress.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1469">
            <bib>Ern, Lothar. Freivers und Metrik: Zur Problematik der englischen Verswissenschaft.
                Diss., Darmstadt: Blaeschke, 1970. Freiburg, 1968. </bib>
            <notes> A doubly valuable study: between two chapters on the development and met- rical
                structure of free verse (with a sample analysis of Pound's second Canto) lies a long
                second chapter categorizing the major theoretical approaches his- torically taken in
                English metrics. Five such approaches are recognized: (1) Non-Temporal Metrical
                Theory (Gascoigne et al., Guest, Mayor, Hopkins, Bridges, Abercrombie, Young, Hamer,
                and G. W. Allen); (2) Rhythm-analysis (Corson, C. M. Lewis; psychological
                experiments and theories). (3) Experi- mental Phonetics (Scripture, Verrier, C. F.
                Jacob, Stetson, De Groot); (4) Temporal Theories of Meter (the Musical-Analogy
                Theory of Patmore and Lanier; the Length Theory of Saintsbury, Alden, Omond,
                Bayfield, Sonnen- schein; and the Interval Theory of Thomson, E. Smith, and J. C.
                Anderson); and (4) Recent Trends in Metrics (Russian Formalism, New Criticism, and
                Trager-Smith). A very substantial study both in theory and application. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1470">
            <bib>Ficke, Arthur D. "Metrical Freedom and the Contemporary Poet." The Dial 58 (1915):
                11-13. </bib>
            <notes> Lamentation over the paucity of adroitness in the verbal abuse of the free-verse
                controversy. A review of four volumes. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1471">
            <bib>Fowler, Roger. "Linguistics and the Analysis of Poetry." The Critical Survey 3
                (1967): 78-89. </bib>
            <notes> This model analysis, mainly lexical, of a Cummings poem includes a metrical
                analysis on pp. 86-87; the lines divide into hemistichs fairly evidently and seem to
                be in a four-stress meter, but Fowler describes them as being in Sprung Rhythm.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1472">
            <bib>Freedman, Morris. "Jazz Rhythms and T. S. Eliot." South Atalantic Quarterly 51
                (1952): 419-35. </bib>
            <notes> Characteristic of these are pause, repetition, nonsense syllables, and rhyme.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1473">
            <bib>Fussell, Paul, Jr. "Free Verse." Antaeus 30/31 (1978): 296-308; </bib>
            <notes> rpt as chapter 5 of the 2nd ed. of his Poetic Meter &amp; Poetic Form (E537). An
                introduction to the poetic form of our time, with many examples of tech- nique,
                particularly the enumerative catalogue or syntactic parallelism so preva- lent in
                this mode. Auden knew acutely how much harder fine free verse is to write than
                metered, and Fussell too rightly insists on "the principle of excel- lence"--the
                principle of economy: no element without a purpose--in every form of verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1474">
            <bib>Gall, Sally M. "Pound and the Modern Melic Tradition: Towards a Demystifica- tion
                of 'Absolute Rhythm.'" Paideuma 8 (1979): 35-47. </bib>
            <notes> Scans six poems by Pound and one by Whitman in musical notation. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1475">
            <bib>Gardner, Helen. The Art of T. S. Eliot. London: The Cresset Press, 1949. </bib>
            <notes> The first chapter ("Auditory Imagination"), esp. pp. 15-35, traces Eliot's crea-
                tion of a new meter for the verse after The Waste Land. Dame Gardner's expo- sition
                is here, as always, lucid and limpid, conveying great understanding in the force of
                few words. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1476">
            <bib>Guiliani, Alfredo. "Le Ragioni Metriche di Ezra Pound (Il Problema della cetra)."
                Nuova Corrente, nos. 5-6 (1956), pp. 105-11. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1477">
            <bib>Gunderson, Keith. "What Is Projective Verse?" Burning Water, Fall 1964, pp. 21-26. </bib>
            <notes> Some very sensible unpacking of Olson's terms and concepts in the "Projective
                Verse" essay shows the contents of the package to be in a shambles. To take Olson
                literally is to conclude that "it is in principle impossible to write Projec- tive
                Verse" and to answer the title question with "No one really knows." Ol- son cannot
                mean what he says. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1478">
            <bib>Hills, E. C. "Meter in Anglo-American Free Verse." University of California
                Chronicle 26 (1924): 299-310. </bib>
            <notes> Only the first three or four pages warrant interest. Hills distinguishes between
                poetry (content), rhythm (repetition), and verse ("unless there be meter--or
                measure--there is no verse"), so that he finds much modern free verse to be poetry
                but not verse, giving the latter term considerably more weight and value than the
                former. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1479">
            <bib>Hindus, Milton. "Notes Toward the Definition of a Typical Poetic Line in Whitman."
                Walt Whitman Review 9 (1963): 75-81. </bib>
            <notes> After considerably circumlocution the author suggests that Whitman's verse is
                constructed of measures of three stresses. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1480">
            <bib>Hollander, John. "Experimental and Pseudo-Experimental Metrics in Recent American
                Poetry." Poetics I (A16), pp. 127-36. </bib>
            <notes> Includes a long digression on the limited value of theories made by practicing
                poets. Those poets publishing their first volumes between 1960 and 1965 comprise two
                camps, those of the Pound-Williams free-verse tradition and those willing to work in
                strict forms. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1481">
            <bib>-----. "Observations on the Experimental." In his Vision and Resonance (A13), pp.
                227-44. </bib>
            <notes> Beyond question the American free-verse poets have shown a persistent, sometimes
                intense interest in matters of metrical form, regardless of whether they knew more,
                less, or other than they actually said in their poems, meta- poems, statements,
                meta-statements, or manifestoes. Behind it all there is "the power of an ideology
                about experiment which descends, in successive mis- readings, from Emerson." But the
                truer form of experimentalism, evident in Pound's archaizing, makes explicit "the
                internalization of other prior models, that they may be incorporated into the new
                poetic being." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1482">
            <bib>Hope, A. D. "Free Verse: A Post Mortem." Quadrant (Sydney) 4 (1960): 49-58. </bib>
            <notes> Denies that free verse allows more rhythmic variety than metered verse: free
                verse suffers the immense loss of metrical counterpoint and cannot find neces- sary
                restraints in the welter of possibilities. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1483">
            <bib>Hough, Graham. "Free Verse." Proceedings of the British Academy 43 (1957): 157-77. </bib>
            <notes> Charts three varieties of free verse: (1) a type which begins, as it were, in a
                standard meter but consciously moves away from it, (2) a type which begins in no
                formal pattern at all but seems repeatedly to approach a strict form, and (3) a type
                which is not recognizably iambic yet is obviously highly formal in other ways. The
                respective types are exemplified in Eliot, Lawrence, and Pound. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1484">
            <bib>Howarth, Robert G. Notes on Modern Poetic Technique, English and Australian.
                Sydney: Angus and Robertson, 1949. 64 pp. </bib>
            <notes> A thin primer in paper covers: chapter 6 treats "Rhythm and Cadence," chap- ter
                8 "Sound." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1485">
            <bib>J., W. H. "Free Verse: Description and Origin." Notes and Queries 172 (1937):
                443-44. </bib>
            <notes> Finds perhaps the earliest description in an 1863 letter of E. B. Browning's re-
                peating a remark of Disraeli's. Notes the influence of Goethe and Arnold. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1486">
            <bib>Jannaccone, P. La Poesia di Walt Whitman e Évoluzione delle Forme Ritmiche.
                Torino, 1898. Tr. by Peter Mitilineos. Washington, D. C.: Microcard Editions, 1973. </bib>
            <notes> Finds regular meters underlying Whitman's rhythms. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1487">
            <bib>Jones, Llewellyn. "Free Verse and Its Propoganda." Sewanee Review 28 (1920):
                384-95; rpt in his First Impressions: Essays on Poetry, Criticism, and Prosody. New
                York: Knopf, 1925. pp. 231-49. </bib>
            <notes> As the saying goes, "Beware the wrath of a patient man." Finally exasperated
                with the intense propaganda (as opposed to accomplishment) of the free-verse school,
                Jones deftly dispatches Amy Lowell (E1499) making her understanding of metrics look
                puerile. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1488">
            <bib>Kenner, Hugh. "Blood for the Ghosts." Texas Quarterly 10 (1967): 67-79; rpt in New
                Approaches to Ezra Pound. Ed. Eva Hesse. Berkeley: University of California Press,
                1969. pp. 331-48. </bib>
            <notes> By the time Pound came to the Pisan Cantos, his grasp of the whole tradition of
                Western metrical forms--decasyllable, pentameter, Imagist cadence--was so firm that
                it is less hyperbolic than literal to say that he was possessed of the spirits of
                the Old Masters. Kenner's explication of a portion of those verses dis- entangles
                skillfully all the voices of the dead, now become instrumentalities of the living.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1489">
            <bib>-----. "Plea for Metrics." Poetry 86 (1955): 41-45. </bib>
            <notes> Most directly a review of three new works of poetry (by Pound, Eliot, and Peter
                Russell), but Kenner takes the occasion for some incisive remarks on three varieties
                of modern metrical divagations: Pound's metric without un- stressed syllables,
                Eliot's self-conscious effort to sever subject from treatment--a metric of craft if
                not substance--and Russell's translation of Greek into English lines of
                hyperwordical metric. Kenner engages, and performs, with his expect- edly
                unexpected, ionized prose. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1490">
            <bib>Kmetzo, Thomas. "Notes Toward a Prosody of Free-Verse." Twenty-Seven to One. Ed.
                Bradford B. Broughton. Ogdensburg N. Y.: Ryan Press, 1970. pp. 85-95. </bib>
            <notes> The author (confusedly) identifies the four types of metrical theory as Graphic,
                Musical, Acoustic, and Mixed, then argues that none of these will scan free verse;
                he therefore appropriates the Trager-Smith system, modifies its symbols, then
                (confusedly) identifies its dimensions as stress, pitch, terminal contour, pause,
                and duration. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1491">
            <bib>Kunitz, Stanley. "Action and Incantation." Antaeus 30/31 (1978): 283-95. </bib>
            <notes> An interview with Kunitz by Harvey Gross which focuses on his views about
                versification and especially on his technical development from strictly metrical
                verse to freer rhythms. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1492">
            <bib>Kwan-Terry, John W. "Free Verse: A Prosodic Description of Its Development from
                Browning to T. S. Eliot.: Diss., Cambridge University, 1970. </bib>
            <notes> Cited in McNamee (q.v. in Appendix D) but not listed in CDI. Not seen. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1493">
            <bib>-----. "The Prosodic Theories of Ezra Pound." Papers on Language and Literature 9
                (1973): 48-64. </bib>
            <notes> Any effort to bring Pound's pronouncements and practices into order and sense
                will be a great struggle: this one succeeds tolerably well at explicating Pound's
                interests in traditional prosodic principles, his confusions and analogies of music
                with poetry, the interplay of the fixed and variable, syntax as struc- ture, melodic
                cadence, the "lengthened foot," the value of meter, the quanti- ties of words, and
                tone-color. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1494">
            <bib>LaFerrière, Daniel. "Free and Non-Free Verse: A Response to Howard McCord's
                'Breaking and Entering.'" Language and Style 10 (1977): 79-85. </bib>
            <notes> Reflectively, the author counterpoises the unscholarly approach of McCord
                (E1503) to the wasteland of Halle-Keyser metrics (E775), deploring the latter for an
                abandonment of the necessary concept of rhythm. He then offers a con- cise
                formulation of McCord's observations: a line-break either (a) falls at the natural
                end of a syntactic period (phrase, clause), or (b) emphasizes some word or element
                not at the end of a phrase or clause. But in order to buy the latter, LaFerrière
                shows, free verse (with its visual prosody) must pay the great price of losing much
                of the auditory dimension of accentual-syllabic verse. The con- clusions reached
                here have extensive range and implication. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1495">
            <bib>Lee, Charlotte, I. "The Line as a Rhythmic Unit in the Poetry of Theodore
                Roethke." Speech Monographs 30 (1963): 15-22. </bib>
            <notes> Detailed metrical analysis of "The Lost Son," focusing on stress-distribution,
                line length, and types of endings. Lee does not seem to differentiate stress- verse
                from foot-verse very clearly, however. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1496">
            <bib>Lieberman, Marcia R. and Philip. "The Breath-Group as a Constructive Element in
                Charles Olson's 'Projective Verse.'" Proceedings of the Seventh International
                Congress of Phonetic Sciences. Ed. André Rigault and R. Charbonneau. The Hague:
                Mouton, 1972. pp. 949-56. </bib>
            <notes> Slightly revised and expanded as E1497 "Olson's Projective Verse and the Use of
                Breath Control as a Structural Element." Language and Style 5 (1972): 287-98.
                Laboratory measurements of breathing while reading poetry generally confirm that
                Olson did in fact use breath-groups as a "structural prosodic element" to point up
                (underscore, demarcate) the line or rhythmic group rather than the syntactic group
                (though one breath-group does not always equal one line). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1498">
            <bib>Lowell, Amy. "The Rhythms of Free Verse." The Dial 64 (1918): 51-56. </bib>
            <notes> Responding to Patterson (D248), Miss Lowell reports experiments they con- ducted
                together in search of a distinctive rhythm ("cadence") of free verse between those
                of prose and metered verse. Patterson eventually identified seven discrete states on
                the continuum between Verse and Prose. See Sapir (E390). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1499">
            <bib>-----. "Some Musical Analogies in Modern Poetry." Musical Quarterly 6 (1920):
                127-57. </bib>
            <notes> Free verse in English should be termed "cadenced verse," since it depends upon
                the cadence not upon meter, since it is nonsyllabic, and since the num- ber of
                syllables within the equal time-units varies widely. Many examples. Miss Lowell
                mentions the resemblance of modern poetry to music frequently, speaks again of her
                experimental intercourse with Patterson (D248), and turns at the end to "polyphonic
                prose." E1500 See also William C. Bedford's "A Musical Apprentice: Amy Lowell to
                Carl Engel." Musical Quarterly 58 (1972): 519-42. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1501">
            <bib>-----. "Vers libre and Metrical Prose." Poetry 3 (1914): 213-20. </bib>
            <notes> Establishes "metrical prose" and verse libre on a continuum between "pure prose"
                and "pure poetry," the "rhythmic wave length" of vers libre being slightly shorter
                and sharper than that of the metered prose. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1502">
            <bib>Lowes, John Livingston. Convention and Revolt in Poetry. Boston and New York:
                Houghton Mifflin, 1919. </bib>
            <notes> See especially chapter five, "The Diction of Poetry Versus Poetic Diction," and
                chapter six, "Rhyme, Metre, and Verse Libre." In the latter, he tena- ciously
                defends the value of the tension--and resultant harmony--of meter and natural
                speech-rhythm (read, restraint and liberty) in metrical verse, as against free
                verse, which abandons the meter for cadence, and "is at its best essentially
                strophic." Though we may feel Professor Lowe's book to be behind us now, and though
                it often seems tediously discursive, still it "supports familiarity"; in grace,
                clarity, and cool sense it remains undimmed. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1503">
            <bib>McCord, Howard. "Breaking and Entering: Words on Line-Lengths in Poems." Language
                and Style 10 (1977): 73-79. </bib>
            <notes> Not a rigorous or categorical analysis but rather the insights and contempla-
                tions of a practicing poet. "Perception provides information. A poem is the ordered
                memory, in language, of perception." See the ambivalent response by LaFerrière
                (E1494). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1504">
            <bib>MacNaughten, Hugh. "Free Verse: A Parallel and a Warning." The National Review
                [National and English Review] 90 (1927): 88-96. </bib>
            <notes> The parallel is with classical Greece, where poetry also altered course
                radically after a total war (Peloponnesian); the warning is that the result, in
                Greece, was the total collapse of lyric poetry. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1505">
            <bib>McNaughton, William. "Ezra Pound's Meters and Rhythms." PMLA 78 (1963): 136-46. </bib>
            <notes> To break the magnetism of the iamb, to stay close to music, to masure the to-
                tal sound of a poem in the meter--these are Pound's three central metrical im-
                pulses. McNaughton collects what must surely be everything Pound ever said on the
                subject, along with a great many examples of metrical experiments. There is more
                than enough material here for a book-length study. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1506">
            <bib>-----. "Pound's Translations and Chinese Melopoeia." Texas Quarterly 10 (1967):
                52-56. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1507">
            <bib>MacNeice, Louis. "Rhythm and Rhyme." In his Modern Poetry: A Personal Essay.
                Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1938; 2nd ed. 1968. pp. 114-35. </bib>
            <notes> Though MacNeice himself favors the more regular verseforms and rhyme, he defends
                free verse from the criticism of G. M. Young; the problem with free verse is only
                that "the poet's matter tends in this form to appear insufficiently digested or
                distilled." The crucial element in any poetry however is rhythmical variation, or
                varied patterns of stresses which MacNeice demonstrates in a de- tailed scansion of
                a lyric by Nashe, remarks by Coleridge, poems by Hopkins, Anglo-Saxon imitations by
                Pound, Auden, and Day Lewis, and Skeltonics by Graves. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1508">
            <bib>Maynard, Theodore. "The Fallacy of Free Verse." Yale Review n.s. 11 (1922):
                354-66. </bib>
            <notes> "The point at issue is not whether free verse has form, but whether it has po-
                etic form; whether it is a satisfactory medium for poetry." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1509">
            <bib>Meyerstein, E. H. W. "You Might Have Rimed." Essays and Studies n.s. 2 (1949):
                64-74. </bib>
            <notes> It is not easy to say with confidence that the subject of this opaque essay is
                free verse. Along the way, he nominates James Macpherson as the originator of free
                verse and discusses the meter of The Testament of Beauty. He expects "the re- turn
                of stanza, of strophe." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1510">
            <bib>Mitchell, Roger. "A Prosody for Whitman?" PMLA 84 (1969): 1606-12. </bib>
            <notes> The key to scanning Whitman's verse is not metrical but syntactic--it is the
                caesura. Whitman constructs his lines so that the stress-counts of the half-lines
                form recognizable patterns of repetition over a run of lines, the chief pattern
                being the "parabola." Also, Whitman establishes a principle of opposition be- tween
                the number of syntactic groups per line and the number of stresses per group.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1511">
            <bib>Monroe, Harriet. "The Free-Verse Movement in America." English Journal 13 (1924):
                691-705; </bib>
            <notes> rpt in her Poets &amp; Their Art (E374), pp. 291-301. A historical survey of the
                vers libre movement in the early part of the century and its general metrical
                backgrounds, with a musical scansion of Richard Ald- ington's "Choricus," "the first
                Imagist poem ever printed." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1512">
            <bib>Morgan, Frederick. "William Carlos Williams: Imagery, Rhythm, Form." Sewanee
                Review 55 (1947): 675-90. </bib>
            <notes> Section II treats rhythm in Williams' verse: its chief characteristics are "a
                con- tinuous movement and adroit timing of the beats." The use of the short line
                isolates and sharpens images, allows variations of tempo, and permits expressive use
                of indentation, sudden break-off, and white space. Morgan takes issue with Yvor
                Winters on the possibility of a free-verse meter, finding "in all true free verse .
                . . rhythm doing its work unsupported by meter." But that view forces a concession:
                "free-verse rhythm is but an intensification of prose rhythm." So, by his mode
                Williams has severely constricted his range of expression, since "the elimination of
                meter entails the abandonment of metrical effects, which are far richer and more
                various than free-verse effects." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1513">
            <bib>"The Muse in Chains." TLS, 13 May 1960, p. 305. </bib>
            <notes> Correspondence follows, from 27 May - 5 August, pp. 337, 353, 385, 401, 417,
                433, 456, 481, 497. The original article above follows an earlier by Hilary Corke;
                see E1462. The TLS reviewer raps Mr. Corke lightly on the knuckles for insisting on
                strict adherence to regularity in form, especially in an age of metrical con- fusion
                and transition. Mr. Corke replies that he actually insisted on metrical control.
                Thereafter the correspondents quarrel over the "cadence-scansion" of one case and
                the entailed issues of stress-assignment and semantics. At pp. 417 and 456, Terence
                Hawkes interecedes to promote linguistic metrics as the only precise descriptive
                instrument. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1514">
            <bib>Olson, Charles. Projective Verse. First printed in Poetry New York, no. 3, 1950. </bib>
            <notes> Thereafter published as a pamphlet, New York: Totem Press, 1959. Rpt in his
                Selected Writings. New York: New Directions, 1966. Rpt in Perkins (A25), pp. 336-42.
                Olson's famous manifesto on the "laws and possibilities of the breath" and
                COMPOSITION BY FIELD posits as the twin premises of its metric the syl- lable and
                the line. "It would do us no harm . . . if both rime and meter, and, in the quantity
                words, both sense and sound, were less in the forefront of the mind than the
                syllable, if the syllable, that fine creature, were more allowed to lead the harmony
                on. . . . it is from the union of the mind and the ear that the syllable is born. .
                . . And the line comes (I swear it) from the breath, from the breathing of the man
                who writes, at the moment that he writes . . . for only he, the man who writes, can
                declare, at every moment, the line, its metric and its ending--where its breathings
                shall come to, termination." See the scathing criticisms by Perloff (next entry).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1515">
            <bib>Perloff, Marjorie G. "Charles Olson and the 'Inferior Predecessors': 'Projective
                Verse' Revisited." ELH 40 (1973): 285-306. </bib>
            <notes> Inquiry into the argument and sources (Pound and Williams) of Projective Verse
                with a more-than-skeptical (indeed, hostile) attitude yields the conclusion that
                Olson's manifesto is "hardly the break-through in literary theory it is reputed to
                be. It is essentially a scissors-and-paste job, a clever but confused collage."
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1516">
            <bib>Pound, Ezra. "A Few Dont's by an Imagiste." Poetry 1 (1913): 200-6. Rpt as "A
                Retrospect." The Literary Essays. New York: New Directions, 1918. </bib>
            <notes> Rpt in Perkins (A25). Pound's familiar laconic advice to would-be poets. See
                esp. the section "Rhythm and Rhyme": "behave as a musician, a good musician, when
                dealing with that phase of your art which has exact parallels in music. The same
                laws govern, and you are bound by no others. . . . your rhythmic structure should
                not destroy the shape of your words, or their natural sound, or their meaning. . . .
                The term harmony is misapplied in poetry; it refers to simultaneous sounds of
                different pitch. There is, however, in the best verse a sort of residue of sound
                which remains in the ear of the hearer and acts more or less as an organ- base. . .
                . As regarding rhythm, compose in the sequence of the musical phrase, not in
                sequence of a metronome." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1517">
            <bib>Powell, Grosvenor E. "Two Essays: I. Quantity and the Meters of Yvor Winters; II.
                Being, Poetry, and Yvor Winters' Poetry." University of Denver Quarterly 10 (1975):
                38-66. </bib>
            <notes> A subtle yet penetrating essay which suggests that in contrast to the
                traditional metrical theory of the twentieth century, derived from Hopkins and
                positing his conception of metrical pattern counterpointed against rhythmical
                realiza- tion, Winters devised--or discovered--another metrical system having two
                levels of counterpointing: (1) the meter (actually "heard," for Winters, and not an
                abstraction) against the rhythm of actual stresses, and (2) the rhythm against
                variations in (a) degrees of accent and (b) syllabic length. That is, several sam-
                ples of verse may have identical meter and rhythm but vary considerably in secondary
                stressing and deployment of syllabic quantity, producing markedly different textural
                effects. It was this latter aspect--a patterning of syllable length which was
                neither entirely random nor fixedly repetitive--which Winters de- veloped in his
                verse. The result is a dipodic or hierarchic structure where two levels of
                counterpointing are evident--the one (accentual) setting the primary stresses
                against all others, the other (accentual-syllabic) setting primary and sec- ondary
                stresses against all others. In his verse, therefore, Winters sought to minimize
                variations of meter and rhythm so as to allow the subtler free-quanti- tative
                patterns to shine through. He also experimented in blank verse, cou- plets,
                quatrains, sonnets, and the seven-syllable tetrameter line so dear to Her- rick.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1518">
            <bib>Powell, James A. "The Light of Vers Libre." Paideuma 8 (1979): 3-34. </bib>
            <notes> Propounds the problematic thesis that the rhythmic patterns of Pound's verse can
                best be discovered by marking the stresses, then grouping them into the longer and
                more arcane feet of Greek metrics (Powell calls them "rhythmic phrases larger and
                more articulate than the iamb"). This, because "as early as 1912 [Pound] began to
                evolve from a synthesis of Greek quantitative prosody and English accentual potency
                a new rhythmic basis for English verse." But it is surely untrue that "in Pound's
                mature poetry there is no metre. Rhythm is all." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1519">
            <bib>Rambo, Dorothy E. "An Analysis of Four Quartets by T. S. Eliot with Particular
                Respect to its Prosody." DA 19 (1958): 1476A (Northwestern). </bib>
            <notes> Only the sixth chapter provides analysis, but the study seems to be mainly
                concerned with the structural integration of the individual movements of the poem
                into a unified whole. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1520">
            <bib>Ramsey, Paul. "Free Verse: Some Steps Toward Definition." SP 65 (1968): 98-108. </bib>
            <notes> Should we have had to have waited years for some sense on this muddled sub-
                ject? Ramsey examines ten possible conceptions of free verse, concluding that the
                tenth, "All of the Above," is correct: free verse is not so much a single rhythmic
                form as a range of closely related forms. Wonderfully stylish. See also this
                author's </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1521">
            <bib>-----. The Lively and the Just: An Argument for Propriety. University of Alabama
                Studies, no. 15. Tuscaloosa: University of Alabama Press, 1962. </bib>
            <notes> There is a discussion of free verse and poetic prose (denigrating Eliot in the
                Four Quartets) on pp. 125-32; note also pp. 57-58, 63-64, and 86-90. For some years
                Professor Ramsey has also been writing a regular review col- umn on recent poetry
                for the Sewanee Review; the reviews generally include at least a few pages of
                commentary on versification. See vols. 74 (1966): 930-45; 82 (1974): 393-406; 85
                (1977): 532-40. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1522">
            <bib>-----. "Some American Poetry of 1974: Three Traditions." Sewanee Review 83 (1975):
                348-56. </bib>
            <notes> The traditions being metrical--"short-line free verse," strict iambics," and
                "loosened iambics." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1523">
            <bib>-----. "William Carlos Williams as Metrist: Theory and Practice." Journal of
                Modern Literature 1 (1971): 578-92. </bib>
            <notes> The "variable foot," Ramsey concludes, is nothing very clear and nothing very
                new. However, as another poet said, there are moments, points, spheres of co-
                herence, as this poet elucidates in two of Williams' poems, abundantly. Wil- liams'
                verse runs to a medley of musics, it seems. Yet consider: we must say either tht he
                knew not what he was about or that he could not speak what he knew. Which is it?
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1524">
            <bib>Ramsom, John Crowe. "Gerontion." In T. S. Eliot: The Man and His Work. Ed. Allen
                Tate. New York: Delacorte Press, 1966. pp. 133-58. </bib>
            <notes> A close explication of rhythmic analysis of each of the five movements of the
                poem in which Eliot "first worked out to his own satisfaction that brisk pros- ody
                which was to be his staple thereafter." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1525">
            <bib>Ranta, Jerrald L. "William Carlos Williams' Prosody to 1940." DAI 31 (1970): 400A
                (Kent State, 1968). </bib>
            <notes> Williams' prosody depends on counting, as do all others, but in his early verse
                he counts and measures many more features than conventional meters do. What he
                achieved is less "free verse" than "a new poetic order" altogether, based on the
                principles of variability and relativity. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1526">
            <bib>Ross, E. C. "Whitman's Verse." MLN 45 (1930): 363-64. </bib>
            <notes> Propounds the unlikely thesis that because traditional verse is "but metered
                prose" Whitman's verse is even further removed from prose than are tradi- tional
                forms. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1527">
            <bib>Savage, D. S. "Form in Modern Poetry." Poetry 65 (1944): 30-43. </bib>
            <notes> "Form is always the effect of rhythm. . . ." But form cannot be identified
                strictly with meter. "Free Verse" should be re-termed "Loose Verse." Discus- sion
                chiefly of M. Moore, Pound, and Hardy. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1528">
            <bib>Schafer, R. Murray. "The Developing Theories of Absolute Rhythm and Great Bass."
                Paideuma 2 (1973): 23-35; rpt in Ezra Pound and Music: The Complete Criticism. New
                York: New Directions, 1977. pp. 467-80. </bib>
            <notes> An effort to explicate these two troublesome concepts by collecting, ordering,
                and examining Pound's known statements about them. Summary in penulti- mate
                paragraph. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1529">
            <bib>Schiller, Andrew. "An Approach to Whitman's Metrics." Emerson Society Quarterly
                no. 22 (1961), pp. 23-25. </bib>
            <notes> Despite the image of "the natural poet, the bardic savage . . . [of] the
                barbaric yawp" that Whitman cultivated, his verse was carefully crafted. Though the
                lines are not isosyllabic or isoaccentual, they are isosyntactic, Schiller shows,
                and probably also isochronic. Specimen: "I Sit and Look Out." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1530">
            <bib>Schilling, Dorothy C. "The Form of Free Verse." Leland Stanford University
                Abstracts of Dissertations 2 (1928): 125-26. </bib>
            <notes> Defining the metrical foot as "primary" rhythm (the line and the stanza being
                secondary and tertiary), the author distinguishes types of free verse where pri-
                mary rhythm is (1) absent, (2) potential, (3) irregular, or (4) regular. It is this
                rhythm which she finds the only one comparable to that of regular verse; the other
                two are only "vaguely suggested." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1531">
            <bib>Schramm, Richard. "The Line Unit: Studies in the Later Poetry of W. B. Yeats."
                Ohio University Review 3 (1961): 32-41. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1532">
            <bib>Schulte, Edvige. "Ritmi vecchi e neovi nella poesia inglese moderna." Annali
                Instituto Universitario Orientale, Napoli, Sezione Germanica 2 (1959): 191-236. </bib>
            <notes> On the meters of Pound, Eliot, and Auden. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1533">
            <bib>Scott, Fred Newton. "A Note on Whitman's Prosody.: JEGP vol. 7, no. 2 (1907- 8):
                134-53. </bib>
            <notes> See also the brief abstract of his paper entitled "The Prosody of Walt Whit-
                man" in PMLA 21 (1906): xix (Proceedings). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1534">
            <bib>Sienicka, Marta. "William Carlos Williams' Theory and Practice of Poetic Measure."
                Studia Anglica Posnaniensia 3 (1971): 121-29. </bib>
            <notes> On the genesis of the concept of the "variable foot." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1535">
            <bib>Sutton, Walter. American Free Verse: The Modern Revolution in Poetry. New York:
                New Directions, 1973. </bib>
            <notes> Not technical, unfortunately; it would have been a far better book had it been
                so. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1536">
            <bib>-----. "The Analysis of Free Verse Form, Illustrated by a Reading of Whitman."
                JAAC 18 (1959): 241-54. </bib>
            <notes> General remarks on the four aspects of poetic structure--sound, syntax, image,
                and meaning. Schematized on pp. 249-50. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1537">
            <bib>Swett, Margery. "Free Verse Again." Poetry 25 (1924): 153-59. </bib>
            <notes> The author acknowledges the utility of rhyme and meter but thinks free verse
                provides greater "cohesion." The greatest artists command both media. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1538">
            <bib>Teele, Roy E. "The Japanese Translations." Texas Quarterly 10 (1967): 61-66. </bib>
            <notes> Metrical problems--and accomplishments--besetting Ezra Pound in translating
                haiku and lyrics in the Noh plays. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1539">
            <bib>Van Doorn, Willem. "Vers Libre in Theory and Practice." English Studies 3 (1921):
                1-7. </bib>
            <notes> Observations on rhythm in the course of a long review of F. S. Flint's Other-
                world: Cadences (1920). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1540">
            <bib>Ware, Lois. "Poetic Conventions in Leaves of Grass." SP 26 (1929): 47-57. </bib>
            <notes> Instances of those conventions Whitman professed to eschew--meter, rhyme scheme,
                poetic diction, sound patterns--repeatedly used by him in his poetry. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1541">
            <bib>Warfel, Harry R. "A Rationale of Free Verse." Jahrbuch für Amerikanstudien 13
                (1968): 228-35. </bib>
            <notes> A close history of the early free-verse movement in America and a short view of
                some of its principles. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1542">
            <bib>Warner, H. E. "Verse--free or confined?" The Dial 61 (1916): 572. </bib>
            <notes> A letter. Vers libre is free but is not verse because it lacks consistently
                organized rhythm. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1543">
            <bib>Weatherhead, A. Kingsley. "William Carlos Williams: Prose, Form, and Measure." ELH
                33 (1966): 118-31. </bib>
            <notes> Even though Williams' own dicta on versification are, on the whole, erratic and
                unreliable, his poetry is certainly something other than prose cleverly de- ployed
                on the page. The typography is functional, and the three-part lines seem to be
                measured into temporally equal rhythmic units. Still, "looseness" or
                "incompleteness" of form as of statement does seem to be central to the Wil- liams
                poetics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1544">
            <bib>Weeks, Ruth M. "Phrasal Prosody." English Journal 10 (1921): 11-19. </bib>
            <notes> An entirely nontechnical essay on Whitman: the author believes English
                speech-rhythm to comprise stress, pitch, time, and pause, the stress being of two
                sorts: "syllabic stress, or accent, and phrasal stress, or emphasis." Whatever this
                means, Weeks divides lines into phrase-groupings or "feet." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1545">
            <bib>Wesling, Donald. "The Prosodies of Free Verse." In Twentieth Century Literature in
                Retrospect. Ed. Reuben A. Brower. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1971.
                pp. 155-87. </bib>
            <notes> An articulate apologia for the "far wider variety" of rhythmic patterns
                available in free verse. Drawing on P. J. Wexler's notion of "grammetrics" (L1000-1)
                and emphasizing the virtues of uncertainty where the metrical unit is the line,
                Wesling points out the tracers of the complimentarities--continuity and dis-
                continuity--in modern verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1546">
            <bib>West, Paul. "Poetic Form Today." English 13 (1960): 8-12. </bib>
            <notes> Some salient observations on the form and effects of free verse here--effects
                "of making the reader wait, of spreading weight upon a single word by making it a
                line in itself," even though free verse in "essence is a disposition of type," and
                hence makes "vocalization less necessary" since it gives, in silent reading, "an
                effect of vocal light and shade." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1547">
            <bib>Whitman, Walt. "Preface to Leaves of Grass [1855]. In The Collected Writings of
                Walt Whitman. Ed. Gay Wilson Allen and Sculley Bradley. 9 vols. New York: New York
                University Press, 1965. Vol. 5, pp. 708-29. </bib>
            <notes> "The poetic quality is not marshalled in rhyme or uniformity . . . but is the
                life of these and much else and is in the soul. The profit of rhyme is that it drops
                seeds of a sweeter and more luxuriant rhyme, and of uniformity that it conveys
                itself into its won roots in the ground out of sight. The rhyme and uniformity of
                perfect poems show the free growth of metrical laws and bud from them as unerringly
                and loosely as lilacs or roses on a bush, and take shapes as compact as the shapes
                of chestnuts and oranges and melons and pears, and shed the perfume impalpable to
                form." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1548">
            <bib>Williams, William Carlos. "On Measure--Statement for Cid Corman." In his Selected
                Essays New York: New Directions, 1948; rpt in Perkins (A25), pp. 259-62. </bib>
            <notes> Probably the poet's best-known pronouncement on metrics: modern verse cannot
                take the form of the older verse because "the very grounds of our be- liefs have
                altered"; Whitman is to be chided for being "the cause of our going astray. . . . No
                verse can be free, it must be governed by some measure, but not by the old measure."
                The solution is "a relatively stable foot, not a rigid one." This is the famous
                "variable foot." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1549">
            <bib>-----. "Some Hints Toward the Enjoyment of Modern Verse." Quarterly Review of
                Literature 7 (1953): 171-75. </bib>
            <notes> In the fascinating symposium on "Experimental and Formal Verse." Williams
                reiterates his interest in "the search of the modern world for a new measure, a new
                way of measuring." See B16 and B230. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1550">
            <bib>-----. "Some Simple Measures in the American Idiom and the Variable Foot." Poetry
                93 (1959): 386-91. </bib>
            <notes> Not to be deceived: these are poems. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1551">
            <bib>Winters, Yvor. "The Influence of Meter on Poetic Convention." Primitivism and
                Decadence: A Study in American Experimental Poetry. New York: Arrow Editions, 1937.
                Rpt in his In Defense of Reason. Chicago: Swallow Press, 1947. pp. 103-50. </bib>
            <notes> Winters, managing to set aside for a space his moral objections to modern verse,
                turns to consider its achievements, limitations, and possibilities from a strictly
                technical point of view. For this he will (1) sketch out his general the- ory of
                verse-structure, (2) examine free verse of his own, his models, and his
                contemporaries, (3) contrast these achievements with those of the poets working
                within the great metrical tradition of the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, and
                (4) sharpen the focus of the contrast by examining the tradi- tional meter developed
                with the greatest refinement, the heroic couplet. Summary at the end. Four metrical
                systems are recognized--quantitative, accentual, syllabic, and
                accentual-syllabic--with the permissible variations in English (accentual- syllabic)
                verse being four: substitution, secondary control of quantity, variety in degree of
                accent (Winters recognizes the Relative Stress Principle and argues for
                pyrrhic-spondee combinations), and contiguous stresses (Sprung Rhythm). Free Verse
                Winters views as being organized metrically on two levels at once, as a kind of
                "dipodic" verse (as Stewart would say): the patterning of both primary and secondary
                stresses is basically iambic meter, but the pattern- ing of primary stresses alone
                is the free-verse meter. But "if the ambiguity, in free verse, ceases to be a
                hesitation between alternatives. . . . [or] if the heavy beats cannot be heard as
                distinct from the light, then the free verse scheme vanishes and one has left only a
                fragmentary blank verse, badly arranged." The technical weakness of free verse are
                that the devices for variation in traditional verse--substitution and shading of
                accent--are not available, and that "the free- verse foot is very long, or is likely
                to be," so that "the only norm, so far as the structure of the foot is concerned, is
                perpetual variation." These deficiencies may be offset by "the use of lines of
                irregular length" and "the approximate repetition of a foot or of a series of feet."
                But Winters concludes that free verse cannot achieve the complexity and subtlety of
                tone, the range and profundity of emotion, possible in metered verse. Traditional
                meter "tends to exploit the full possibilities of language; experimental meter . . .
                is incomplete." It is only by hovering near the steadying norm that the poet can
                "vary his feelings in opposite or even in many directions." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1552">
            <bib>-----. "Mr. Winters' Metrics." Saturday Review of Literature 7 (1930): 188. </bib>
            <notes> Prof. Winters explains the "loose foot" he employs in his free verse; "it
                consists of a single heavily-accented syllable, placed usually toward the fore, an
                unlim- ited number of secondarily-accented syllables, and an unlimited number of un-
                accented syllables." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="E1553">
            <bib>Wood, Clement. "Poetry's New Tools." English Journal 22 (1933): 615-27. </bib>
            <notes> Examines rhythm, line-structure, rhyme, and vocabulary in American poetry of the
                Teens and Twenties. See also: B197, B220, D333, E28, E135, E461, E486, E634, I5,
                I24, I33, L24, L64, L77, L360, L803-4, L821, L858-59; L903, L984, L1626, L1629.
            </notes>
        </item>
    </chapter>
</bibliography>
