<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="SYNTAX AND GRAMMAR">

        <item id="F1">
            <bib>Aarts, Jan. "A Note on the Interpretation of 'he danced his did.'" Journal of
                Linguistics 7 (1971): 71–73. </bib>
            <notes> Contrary to Fowler's view (F63), Aarts believes that readers interpret deviant
                sentences by searching for "well-formed parts" rather than any "new structure in
                general." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F2">
            <bib>Abbott, E[dwin] A. A Shakespearean Grammar. London: Macmillan and Co., 1869; 3rd
                ed. "revised and enlarged," 1870; rpt New York: Dover Publications, 1966. </bib>
            <notes> Part 1 treats Grammar, Part 2 (sections 452–515) Prosody. Abbott's textbook
                gives the standard account of the structure of Elizabethan English as well as the
                traditional foot-verse description of the iambic pentameter. But N.B.: Abbott's
                "rules" are supple enough to yield to almost any construing of the meter one might
                make, and his scansions are exceedingly unreliable. He allows monosyl- labic and
                trisyllabic feet, and feet composed of a rest (sec. 508), and he will ex- pand or
                contract syllables shamelessly to fill up a foot. Superseded by Franz (F66, F67).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F3">
            <bib>Adams, John J. "A Syntactic Approach to Yeats." DAI 36 (1976): 8068A (Columbia). </bib>
            <notes> Mainly on determiners and verb tense. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F4">
            <bib>Alexis, Gerhard R. "A Keen Nose for Taylor's Syntax." Early American Literature 4
                (1970): 97–101. </bib>
            <notes> Explication of the knotty eighth stanza of "Christs Reply." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F5">
            <bib>Alford, John A. "Wordsworth's Use of the Present Perfect." MLQ 33 (1972): 119–29. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F6">
            <bib>Ando, Sadao. A Descriptive Syntax of Christopher Marlowe's Language. Tokyo:
                University of Tokyo Press, 1976. 704 pp. </bib>
            <notes> A compendious tome, organized by grammatical element; it seems to examine verb
                constructions almost exclusively. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F7">
            <bib>Arakelian, Paul G. "Evaluative Stylistic: A Non-Programmatic Study of ‘The
                Windhover.’” Language and Style 9 (1976): 118–29. </bib>
            <notes> Argues that stylistics should evaluate literary texts in terms of structure
                rather than meaning. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F8">
            <bib>Araki, Kazuo. "A Study of Shakespeare's Use of Simple Relative Pronouns." Studies
                in English Literature (Tokyo), English Number, 1965, pp. 59–76. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F9">
            <bib>Austin, Frances O. "Time, Experience, and Syntax in Wordsworth's Poetry."
                Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 70 (1969): 724–38. </bib>
            <notes> Wordsworth had "a tendency to use full or expanded forms of syntax," the chief
                of which is of + noun phrase, to express possession, instead of apostrophe + s. This
                form tends to slow down the tempo of a passage and provide psychic distancing,
                effects which are jointly the principal determiners of that mood of "reflectiveness"
                so frequent and so central in Wordsworth. In other passages, such as those of direct
                narration or excitement, the form practically disappears. For metrical reasons, the
                form frequently occurs at the beginning of the line. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F10">
            <bib>Austin, Timothy R. "Constraints on Syntactic Rules and the Style of Shelley's
                'Adonais': An Exercise in Stylistic Criticism." PTL 4 (1979): 315–43. </bib>
            <notes> Passages in the critically admired "Adonais" show the same three types of vio-
                lations of syntactic constraints (the Tensed S Condition, Up-to-Ambiguity
                Constraint, and Center-Embedding), producing convoluted, awkward, even ungrammatical
                lines, that passages in the critically denigrated Laon and Cythna show, the
                difference being that in the latter case the violations are "repeated and
                consistent," whereas in the former they appear solely in the first twenty stanzas of
                the fifty-five stanza poem, i.e. precisely in the passage where Shelley portrays the
                world that is "untransmuted by poetic vision." In "Adonais" he controlled and turned
                to expressive use a technique hitherto uncontrolled. This essay is too long by half,
                but the section on the ambiguity of NP-NP-V constructions as lines of verse is
                enlightening. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F11">
            <bib>-----. "A Linguistic Approach to the Style of the Early Romantic Poets." DAI 38
                (1977): 3441A (Massachusetts). </bib>
            <notes> A search for dominant linguistic features as specific characteristics of style:
                a "mirror-image" syntactic feature in Coleridge, triads and syntactic "contortion"
                in Shelley, and deletions in the couplets of Byron. These syntactic devices are then
                correlated to particular thematic elements in the passages in which they occur:
                symbolic landscape in Coleridge, elegiac adoration in Shelley, and satire in Byron.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F12">
            <bib>Baker, William E. "Syntax in English Poetry 1870–1930. Berkeley: University of
                California Press, 1967. Based on his dissertation, DA 25 (1965): 4123A. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Review of English Studies n.s. 20 (1969): 241–43; in Criticism 11
                (1969): 384–89. A study of a selected corpus of 500 lines from each of thirty poets,
                divided into two groups roughly sixty years apart, reveals that the characteristic
                late- Victorian modes of syntactic articulation are dislocation and elaboration,
                while the characteristic early-twentieth-century mode is fragmentation. A closer
                scrutiny is given to the contrastive styles of Hopkins and Yeats and the com-
                parable ones of Browning and Eliot. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F13">
            <bib>Banfield, Ann M. "Stylistic Transformations: A Study Based on the Syntax of
                Paradise Lost." DAI 34 (1973): 1265A (Wisconsin). </bib>
            <notes> Proposes two transformational rules to account for Miltonic deviance in word-
                order and in deletions. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F14">
            <bib>Barfoot, C. C. "Key Perspective, The Tonality of Tense in Some Poems of
                Wordsworth." English Studies 54 (1973): 22–37. </bib>
            <notes> Draws an extended analogy between the poet's use of verb tense in a poem and the
                tonality of key in a musical composition: both allow construction of a sense of
                perspective, a spatial and hierarchical deployment, a figure, via depar- tures from
                and return to a major key, tensions, contrasts, subordinations, etc. Demonstrated in
                "Elegiac Stanzas," "The Solitary Reaper," and "Resolution and Independence."
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F15">
            <bib>-----. "A Partial Grammar of Autumn." Dutch Quarterly Review of Anglo-American
                Letters 2 (1972): 73–81. </bib>
            <notes> The "union of process and stasis" which W. J. Bate and other critics have found
                in the poem may be verified in the tenses of its verbs and the forms of its syntax.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F16">
            <bib>Barton, Ruth P. "'The Natural Words in the Natural Order': A Study of W. B.
                Yeats's Verse Syntax." DAI 30 (1970): 5438A (Wisconsin). </bib>
            <notes> Yeats was "not a syntactic innovator, he was a master of syntax," as Barton
                shows, moving through an analysis that is "grammatical rather than linguistic" and
                that keeps close to the individual poems themselves. A traditional method
                appropriate for a poet traditional in syntax. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F17">
            <bib>Berry, Francis. Poet's Grammar: Person, Time, and Mood in Poetry. London:
                Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1958. 190 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in TLS, 16 May 1958, p. 270; in English 12 (1959): 147; in Review of
                English Studies n.s. 11 (1960): 343; in Anglia 80 (1962): 136–37. A miscellany of
                studies of verb tense and mood (mainly the interesting Sub- junctive), pronouns
                (mainly the second-person familiar form), and prepositions in English poetry from
                medieval drama to T. S. Eliot, with full-chapter studies on Shakespeare, Keats, and
                Shelley. In contrast to the many later linguistic studies of poetic grammar--highly
                technical, very narrow, self-conscious of theory and method--Berry's approach is
                best termed speculative: his forte is his delicate yet incisive thinking into the
                implications and the assumptions behind grammatical forms and specific grammatical
                usages. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F18">
            <bib>-----. "'Thou' and 'You' in Shakespeare's Sonnets." Essays in Criticism 8 (1958):
                138– 46. Reply by Thomas Finkenstaedt, pp. 456–57 </bib>
            <notes>; rejoinder by Berry in 9 (1959): 196–97. See also Archer's remarks on the same
                topic in TLS, 27 June 1936, p. 544. Berry is searching for a persuasive motivation
                for the distribution of the inti- mate form vs. the formal form of the pronoun in
                the sonnets. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F19">
            <bib>Berutti, Betty R. "A Grammatical Analysis of the Poetry of E. E. Cummings." DAI 31
                (1971): 3530A (Texas). </bib>
            <notes> Results are compared to current critical estimations of cummings. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F20">
            <bib>Bivens, William P., III. "Noun Phrase Case Schemes in the Deep Structure of
                Poems." Style 8 (1974): 305–21. </bib>
            <notes> Explicates Yeats's "A Prayer for My Daughter" in terms of the underlying case-
                schemes of change-of-state verbs vs. surface-contact verbs: the former require
                agent, instrument, and object, the latter agent or object, and goal. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F21">
            <bib>-----. "Parameters of Poetic Inversion in English." Language and Style 12 (1979):
                13–25. </bib>
            <notes> Poetic inversions are of two types--stanzaic inversions for metrical compliance
                and displacement inversions for foregrounding--for two purposes--order and
                marking--and via two means--verb or auxiliary shift, or noun-phrase inversion.
                Bivens shows that "the extent to which poetic inversion obeys the rules of or-
                dinary language . . . is not generally appreciated" by mapping out the trans- forms.
                But more importantly, his study avoids the gaudy, ephemeral, and idiosyncratic in a
                steady and patient search for basic principles, such as "the larger question of how
                new and old information is distributed within the sen- tence" [this has applications
                in scansion] and the rather amazing effects of the Traces Convention proposed by
                Selkirk. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F22">
            <bib>Bliss, Frank W., and Earl R. MacCormac. "Deep Structures in Poetry." PTL 2 (1977):
                227–40. </bib>
            <notes> Tries to show that the deep structure of Shakespeare's Sonnet 116 is "reasona-
                bly standard." A line by Dylan Thomas is also derived by tree-diagrams in or- der to
                point up the relations of semantics to syntax in interpretation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F23">
            <bib>Bloomfield, Morton W. "The Syncategorematic in Poetry: From Semantics to
                Syntactics." In To Honor Roman Jakobson. 3 vols. The Hague: Mouton, 1967. Vol. 1,
                pp. 309–17. </bib>
            <notes> On poetic "foregrounding." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F24">
            <bib>Bouquet, Robert L. "Obscure Syntax in Shelley's Visionary Poetry." Diss., Columbia
                University, 1972. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F25">
            <bib>Bowley, C. C. "Robert Graves's 'Language of the Seasons': A Linguistic Approach to
                Poetic Analysis." Te Reo (Proceedings of the Linguistic Society of New Zealand)
                10–11 (1967–69): 9–26. </bib>
            <notes> Analyzes syntax and meter. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F26">
            <bib>Boyd, Julian and Zelda. "The Perfect of Experience." Studies in Romanticism 16
                (1977): 3–13. </bib>
            <notes> Explores Wordsworth's affinity for the present perfect tense of verbs and con-
                siders, more generally, what aspects of situations tense can most effectively or
                subtly denote. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F27">
            <bib>Bozek, Philip. "Hugh MacDiarmid's Early Lyrics: A Syntactic Examination." Language
                and Style 9 (1976): 29–41. </bib>
            <notes> Interpretive analysis of five poems by this Scottish poet. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F28">
            <bib>Brisman, Leslie. "'More Glorious to Return': Miltonic Repetition." Yearbook of
                English Studies 1 (1971): 78–87. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F29">
            <bib>Burton, Dolores M. "Aspects of Word Order in Two Plays of Shakespeare." Computer
                Studies in the Humanities and Verbal Behavior 3 (1970): 34–39. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F30">
            <bib>-----. "'To Keep Decorum': A Stylistic Analysis of Shakespeare's Richard II and
                Antony and Cleopatra." Diss., Harvard University, 1968. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F31">
            <bib>Chatman, Seymour. "Milton's Participial Style." PMLA 83 (1968): 1386–99. </bib>
            <notes> One important aspect of the phrasal style in English poetry identified by Jose-
                phine Miles is the poets' "disposition to convert verbs into noun-modifying parti-
                ciples," thereby gaining themselves the compression and ambiguity inherent in such
                constructions. Milton's practice is here compared to that of the other major English
                poets in a nearly model study which demonstrates again how much can be shown about
                poetic effects by attention to only a single device. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F32">
            <bib>Cherubini, William. "The 'Goldenness' of Sidney's Astrophel and Stella: Test of a
                Quantitative Stylistics Routine." Language and Style 8 (1975): 47–59. </bib>
            <notes> The first section of the analysis concerns grammar. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F33">
            <bib>Chisholm, William S., Jr. "An Exercise in Syntactic Stylistics." Linguistics no.
                33 (1967), pp. 24–36. </bib>
            <notes> Extended analysis of cummings' "what if a much of a which of a wind." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F34">
            <bib>Clark, Virginia P. "The Syntax of John Berryman's Homage to Mistress Bradstreet."
                DA 29 (1969): 2703A (Connecticut). </bib>
            <notes> A structural approach is compared with a transformational. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F35">
            <bib>Cluysenaar, Anne. Aspects of Literary Stylistics: A Discussion of the Dominant
                Structures in Verse and Prose. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1976. </bib>
            <notes> Chapter 3 is on poetic syntax. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F36">
            <bib>Coppay, Frank L. "The Internal Analysis of Compression in Poetry." Style 11
                (1977): 19–38. </bib>
            <notes> A rebuttal of Levin's argument (F124) that nonrecoverable deletion rules in
                poetry create an effect of "compression": Coppay argues that the rules do not exist,
                that the cause of the stated effect is semantic not syntactic, and that Levin's
                method is "a gloss, pure and simple" of the Dickinson poem. The pre- ferred method
                is that of Riffaterre. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F37">
            <bib>Cox, Keith. "A Syntactic Comparison of Robert Frost's '. . . Snowy Evening' and
                'Desert Places.'" Ball State University Forum (Robert Frost No.) 11 (1970): 25–28. </bib>
            <notes> Actually a Contrast. Syntactically, Frost's lines tend to be balanced between
                two parts, and they are often relatively end-stopped. He has some single- sentence
                poems and some poems where grammatical elements are packaged in separate stanzas.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F38">
            <bib>Cuddy, Lois S. "The Latin Imprint on Emily Dickinson's Poetry: Theory and
                Practice." American Literature 50 (1978): 74–84. </bib>
            <notes> The irregularities in the poet's syntax are attributable to rules learned from a
                Latin grammar. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F39">
            <bib>Dahl, Liisa. Nominal Style in the Shakespearean Soliloquy. Turku: Turun Yliopisto,
                1969. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in English Studies 53 (1972): 357–58; in Notes &amp; Queries 18 (1971):
                158– 59; in Studia Neophilologica 43 (1971): 310–12. Analyzes "nominal
                sentences"--sentences with a missing verb--in Shakespeare, on the assumption that
                they more readily suggest emotional intensity. Shake- speare is then compared to his
                predecessors and contemporaries (Kyd, Mar- lowe, Lyly, Peele, and Greene). Long
                bibliography. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F40">
            <bib>Darbishire, Helen. "Milton's Poetic Language." Essays and Studies n.s. 10 (1957):
                31– 52. </bib>
            <notes> In syntax and lexical matters, Milton "holds to the idiom and vocabulary of our
                common speech as the groundwork of his diction." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F41">
            <bib>Davie, Donald. Articulate Energy: An Enquiry into the Syntax of English Poetry.
                London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1955 </bib>
            <notes>; 2nd ed. 1976. Pages 106–16 are rpt as "Syntax in Wordsworth's Prelude" in
                Literary English Since Shakespeare. Ed. George Watson. London: Oxford University
                Press, 1970. pp. 308–18. Rev: In Études Anglaises 10 (1957): 175–76; in Essays in
                Criticism 8 (1958): 79– 87; in Review of English Studies n.s. 8 (1957): 212–14; in
                TLS, 4 November 1955, p. 658; in Yale Review 47 (1957–58): 617–23; by John Thompson
                in Po- etry 93 (1959): 325–28. There is a review article on the second edition in
                Critical Quarterly 19 (1977): 31–39. In the first full-length monograph on the
                subject, Davie examines the views of T. E. Hulme (syntax is unnecessary in poetry),
                Susanne Langer (syntax like music traces the form of experience), and Fendlosa
                (syntax symbolizes action), finding them all unsatisfactory; he then produces a
                typology of his own: syntax may be subjective (it shows us the form of the author's
                thought), dramatic (the form of someone else's thought), objective (the form of an
                experience or emo- tion), like music (showing us the form of a thought without
                defining it), or like mathematics (it can give pleasure in and of itself).
                Applications follow in several very short and eclectic studies. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F42">
            <bib>-----. "The Relation Between Syntax and Music in Some Modern Poems in English."
                Poetics I (A16), pp. 203–14. </bib>
            <notes> The Symbolist interest in the "music" of poetry was in fact a concern with
                "linked sweetness long drawn out," as is the case with Milton, Spenser, and Yeats.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F43">
            <bib>-----. "Syntax and Music in Paradise Lost." The Living Milton: Essays by Various
                Hands. Ed. Frank Kermode. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1960. pp. 70– 84. </bib>
            <notes> In an intrepid performance, Davie shows that although Miltonic syntax is ca-
                pable of spectacular mimesis on occasion, leading the reader to a meaning by
                enacting it, in general neither the syntax nor the narrative structure itself in PL
                is designed to propel the reader forward or sustain his interest; indeed, "the
                splendidly elaborate syntax . . . in fact is employed characteristically to check
                narrative impetus and frustrate musical pleasure." Hence the "unifying struc- ture"
                of the poem is neither syntactic nor narrative, nor can it be "musical" in the sense
                of music as a structure of expectation and resolution--i.e. sustained
                progression--in time; rather, "it is a matter of vocal colouring and skillful reso-
                nance. . . . the 'music delight' is all in sonority." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F44">
            <bib>Dillon, George L. "Inversions and Deletions in English Poetry." Language and Style
                8 (1975): 220–37. </bib>
            <notes> Gives modern transformational descriptions (or equivalents) for some of the
                traditional rhetorical schemes, drawing the conclusion therefrom that no sharp line
                can be drawn between "poetic" and "ordinary" transformations. Three motives or
                functions of inversion or deletion in the poetic line are identified: presentational
                (deployment of a word for effect), imitative (the syntax forcing the reader to enact
                what is being described), and prosodic (to effect a rhyme, con- form to meter, or
                place a caesura). This last is given some further attention. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F45">
            <bib>-----. "Literary Transformations and Poetic Word Order." Poetics n.s. 5 (1976):
                1–22. </bib>
            <notes> A demonstration that the traditional rhetorical schemes for deletion (the zeugma
                group) and re-ordering (anastrophe, hyperbaton, etc.) may be ac- counted for by
                optional transformational rules, thereby accounting for many constructions in
                Spenser, Shakespeare, and Milton. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F46">
            <bib>Doherty, Paul C., and E. Dennis Taylor. "Syntax in Hardy's 'Neutral Tones.'"
                Victorian Poetry 12 (1974): 285–91. </bib>
            <notes> The difficult lines seven and eight may be infelicitous but they are not un-
                grammatical; the sense is: "And some words (were) played on between us to and fro
                which (words) lost the more by our love." The odd use of the preposition on is
                defended historically and contextually. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F47">
            <bib>Douds, J. B. "George Herbert's Use of the Transferred Verb: A Study in the
                Structure of Poetic Imagery." MLQ 5 (1944): 163–74. </bib>
            <notes> A study of the means by which a poet can deploy syntactic features (here, the
                verb) in order to control the sense of his metaphors and images. The verb fuses the
                subject and predicate terms in a metaphor and thus "transfers" sense, often
                forcefully, since verbs by nature express energy of action. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F48">
            <bib>Dunlap, Elizabeth D. "The Wreck of the Deutschland" A Study of Its Lexical,
                Syntactical, and Critical Problems." DAI 34 (1974): 5907A (South Carolina). </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F49">
            <bib>Dyboski, Roman. Tennysons Sprache und Stil. Wiener Beiträge zur englischen
                Philologie, no. 25. Vienna and Leipzig; Wilhelm Braumüller, 1907. 544 pp. His
                dissertation at Vienna in 1905. </bib>
            <notes> Part I treats Syntax. Note also sections 221–31 on sound-patterns. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F50">
            <bib>Edelson, Phyllis M. F. "The Millenial Vision in Shelley's Poetry: A Study of Motif
                and Syntax." DAI 35 (1975): 7901A (C.U.N.Y.). </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F51">
            <bib>Elgin, Suzette H. "A Transformational View of the Concepts of Compression and
                Closure in the Analysis of Poetry." English Record 20 (1970): 87–94. </bib>
            <notes> A full-scale demonstration of the process wherein a complete set of underlying
                "poem-constituents" is cut, elided, and compressed into a final ("surface") poem,
                wherein certain constituents are absent but referred to. "Closure" is the reader's
                ability to supply missing parts to complete a pattern. Text: the author's own poem.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F52">
            <bib>Emma, Ronald D. "Grammar and Milton's English Style." Language and Style in
                Milton. Ed. Ronald D. Emma and John T. Shawcross. New York: Frederick Ungar, 1967.
                pp. 233–51. </bib>
            <notes> Milton's grammatical style is less Latinate, less aureate than critics commonly
                think. He is not expressly imitating Virgil in his syntax; on the contrary, his
                usages are native English and relatively conservative, showing only the amount of
                Latinate influence one would expect in any cultivated English style. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F53">
            <bib>-----. Milton's Grammar. The Hague: Mouton, 1964. 164 pp. Based on his
                dissertation of the same title, DA 21 (1961): 2286A (Duke). </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in TLS, 31 December 1964, p. 1182; in Language 41 (1965): 674–76; in
                Linguistics 22 (1966): 121–34; in Anglia 84 (1966): 429–32. A close study of
                Milton's grammatical usages in both poetry and prose, based on eight thousand-word
                samples, one each from his four most important po- etic and prose works. Seven
                chapters treat each part of speech separately, fol- lowed by an eighth on larger
                syntactic patterns. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F54">
            <bib>Epstein, E. L. "Yeats' Experiments with Syntax in the Treatment of Time." Modern
                Irish Literature. Ed. Raymond J. Porter and James D. Brophy. New York: Twayne, 1972.
                pp. 171–84. </bib>
            <notes> Explicates some "detemporalizing techniques" which Yeats and other Symbol- ists
                used to try to neutralize or freeze the naturally kinetic temporal-succession built
                into the verbs of English syntax. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F55">
            <bib>Erich, Otto. Die Syntax Spensers. Diss., Vienna, 1913. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F56">
            <bib>Erikson, Fred W. "Literary Style as Dialect: An Empirical Study of Syntactic
                Distinctions Between Neoclassic and Romantic Poetry." DAI 36 (1975): 2777a
                (Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute). </bib>
            <notes> Analyzing poetic syntax at the kernel level rather than at the surface level
                will show that the Neoclassic and Romantic period-styles can be clearly distin-
                guished even though individual poets cannot be differentiated within each pe- riod.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F57">
            <bib>Fairley, Irene R. E. E. Cummings and Ungrammar: A Study of Syntactic Deviance in
                His Poems. New York: Watermill Publishers, 1975. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in PTL 3 (1978): 180–84. Applies the methods of transformational syntax to
                Cummings (who better, and who easier?) in order to approach the issue of whether
                (and how) poetic lan- guage is "deviant" from standard language, and if so, whether
                a workable grammar for poetry is possible. Examines morphology and word-formation,
                orthography, and the syntactic features of deletion, repetition, and displace- ment.
                Based on her dissertation at Harvard in 1971, "Syntactic Deviance in the F58 Poetry
                of E. E. Cummings: A Stylistic Investigation," and on the following published
                essays: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F59">
            <bib>-----. "Meaning and Syntax in e e cummings' 'quick i the death of thing.'" The
                Ph.D in English and Foreign Languages: A Conference Report. New York: MLA, 1973. </bib>
            <notes> pp. 42–49; rpt in Meaning: A Common Ground of Linguistics and Literature. Ed.
                Don I. F. Nilsen. Cedar Falls, Iowa: University of Iowa, 1973. pp. 42–49. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F60">
            <bib>-----. "Syntactic Deviation and Cohesion." Language and Style 6 (1973): 216–29. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F61">
            <bib>-----. "Syntax as Style: An Analysis of Three Cummings Poems." Studies Presented
                to Professor Roman Jakobson By his Students. Ed. Charles E. Gribble. Cambridge,
                Mass.: Slavica Publishers, 1968. pp. 105–11. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F62">
            <bib>Fallis, Richard. "Language and Rhythm in Poetry: A Previously Unpublished Essay by
                W. B. Yeats." Shenandoah 26, no. 4 (1975): 77–79. </bib>
            <notes> Yeats wonders to himself why he prefers "a lyric that sings" to one that merely
                "talks," which leads him to reflections on "passionate syntax"; a little historical
                review shows how very few major English poets have preserved normal word- order and
                the authentic tone of an active man speaking intensely. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F63">
            <bib>Fowler, Roger. "On the Interpretation of Nonsense Strings." Fowler (A12), pp.
                238–51. </bib>
            <notes> Against Levin and in support of Thorne (F210), Fowler argues that a grammar
                should not be expected to include or account for deviant sentences found in poems;
                rather, the competence which speakers show in interpreting poetic lines is "like
                learning a language," or better, like learning "an unfamiliar dialect of one's own
                language": "one seeks to discover regularities which imply rules which one has not
                yet internalized as a part of one's linguistic competence." This heuristic skill is
                thus simply a capacity to "LOOK FOR NEW STRUC- TURE in general." Cf. Aarts (F1).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F64">
            <bib>Francis, Henry E. "The Adjectives of Donne and Wordsworth: The Key to a Poetic
                Quality." DAI 25 (1964): 1891A (University of Southern California). </bib>
            <notes> Donne's adjectives tend to emphasize temporality, absolute value, and concre-
                tion; Wordsworth's, timelessness, subjective value, emotion, and sensation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F65">
            <bib>Francis, W. Nelson. "Syntax and Literary Interpretation." Monograph Studies on
                Language and Literature 13 (1962): 83–92 </bib>
            <notes>; rpt in Chatman and Levin (A21): pp. 209–16; in Readings in Applied English
                Linguistics. Ed. Harold B. Allen. New York: Appleton-Century Crofts, 1958; 2nd ed.
                1964. pp. 515–22. Francis observes that when readers of poetry confront a difficult
                passage, they usually try to surmount it by paying attention to lexical meanings or
                logical structure, but rarely by paying attention simply to syntax. He catches
                Kenneth Burke at this, and then gauges the skills of several other critics of
                Thomas's "Altarwise by Owl-light," giving a close reading himself. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F66">
            <bib>Franz, Wilhelm. Shakespeare-Grammatik. Halle, 1898–1900; 2nd ed. 1909; 3rd ed.
                Heidelberg, 1924; 4th ed. expanded and retitled Die Sprache Shakespeares in Vers und
                Prosa. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1939. 730 pp. </bib>
            <notes> There are many reviews of the successive editions, i.e.: in Englische Studien 29
                (1901): 81–106; in MLR 20 (1925): 345–47; in Shakespeare Jahrbuch 35 (1899): 316–20
                and 38 (1902): 248–49; in Shakespeare Jahrbuch 75 (1939): 154–56; in Études
                Anglaises 4 (1940): 58; in Anglia Beiblatt 51 (1940): 73–75; in Archiv 177 (1940):
                54; in MLR 35 (1940): 129–30; in MLN 35 (1920): 460; in JEGP 39 (1940): 577; in
                Studia Neophilologica 13 (1940–41): 158–59. Franz's compendious, seemingly
                exhaustive study of Shakespeare's grammar is the successor to Abbott (F2) and
                remains a standard reference despite many later studies. The fourth edition adds
                Franz's Shakespeare's Blankvers (E1178) as Part 2, "Metrik und Rhythmik." The
                prosodist will also be interested in the section on "Rhythmus und Sprachform," pp.
                588–99. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F68">
            <bib>Freeman, Donald C. "Keats's 'To Autumn': Poetry as Process and Pattern." Language
                and Style 11 (1978): 3–17. </bib>
            <notes> Deep-structure analysis of the poem discloses "syntactic mimesis": the poem's
                language establishes and enacts "the agency of an abstraction" (the poem's theme) by
                creating "instruments from non-instruments [causative construc- tions] . . .
                processes from states . . . and transitivity from inchoateness [transi- tive verb
                forms]." Cf. F169. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F69">
            <bib>-----. "The Strategy of Fusion: Dylan Thomas's Syntax." Style and Structure in
                Literature. Ed. Roger Fowler. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1975. pp. 19–39. </bib>
            <notes> Not microgrammar but rather a discernment of the more general--even fun-
                damental--syntactic strategies by which the poet embodies his vision. Thomas
                expresses his central concerns with fusion, continuity, and process via the yoking
                of contradictory constituents, by intensification of relative construc- tions, and
                by preposing transforms. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F70">
            <bib>Fridén, Georg. Studies in the Tenses of the English Verb, Chaucer to Shakespeare,
                with Special Reference to the Late Sixteenth Century. Uppsala: Almqvist &amp;
                Wiksells, 1948 </bib>
            <notes>; rpt in Essays and Studies on English Language and Literature, II. Ed. S. B.
                Liljegren. Uppsala, 1948; Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1949. 222 pp.
                Rev: in JEGP 49 (1950): 104–6; in MLR 45 (1950): 77–78. by Sledd in MP 47 (1949):
                208–9; in Studies in Linguistics 9 (1951): 98–99; by Mossé in Études Anglaises 5
                (1952): 69–70; in Studia Neophilologica 31 (1949): 300–2. Principally a treatise in
                historical syntax, but relies heavily on poetic and dra- matic texts for
                source-material. Tables for Shakespearean plays on pp. 65, 73, 80, 110, etc.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F71">
            <bib>Fujii, Takeo. "Verb-Adverb Combinations in Shakespeare's Language: An Approach to
                the Interpretations of Shakespeare's Language and Expression." Anglica (Osaka) 5
                (1965): 54–91. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F72">
            <bib>Gallagher, Michael P. "Yeats, Syntax, and the Self." Arizona Quarterly 26 (1970):
                5– 16. </bib>
            <notes> It was by crossing the limen, from "words alone" as "certain good" to a search
                for "the syntax of passionate speech," that Yeats elevated his work above that of
                every other poet of his generation. "Among School Children" is a poem which
                "explores a set of dualities in search of some fruitful and integrating vi- sion."
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F73">
            <bib>Gardiner, Judith K. "Syntax and the Platonic Ladder: Jonson's "though Beautie be
                the Mark of Praise.'" Concerning Poetry 8 (1975): 35–40. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F74">
            <bib>Gearreald, Karen L. "Milton's Majestic Style: Studies in the Diction and Syntax of
                'Paradise Regained.'" Diss., Harvard University, 1969. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F75">
            <bib>Greenfield, Stanley B. "Ellipsis and Meaning in Poetry." Texas Studies in
                Literature and Language 13 (1971): 137–47. </bib>
            <notes> Complaining that Geoffrey Leech (F123) is short-sighted in refusing to allow
                semantics and context to affect judgments of grammaticality (deviance), Greenfield
                cites examples to show that the (syntactic) ellipsis of one element in a sentence
                can generate the possibility of ambiguity in other elements, which, lacking such a
                deletion, would otherwise not be open to multiple meaning. So the deletion of on in
                Hopkins' "fastened [on] me flesh" creates such an ambi- guity, a "phonological
                ellipsis," namely "fashioned me flesh." In effect syntactic compression allows
                phonological expansion which enhances semantic richness. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F76">
            <bib>-----. "Grammar and Meaning in Poetry." PMLA 82 (1967): 377–87. </bib>
            <notes> A review essay surveying two major grammatical analyses of poetry made by
                linguists since 1960, those of S. R. Levin (B129) and J. McH. Sinclair (F197).
                Greenfield wishes to show that pure linguistic description is useless without
                critical selectivity, and that grammatical analysis cannot produce meaning in the
                absence of lexical-contextual-semantic analysis as well. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F77">
            <bib>Grennen, Joseph E. "Grammar as Thaumaturgy: Hopkins' 'Heraclitean Fire.'"
                Renascence 15 (1963): 208–11. </bib>
            <notes> The final verb Is, entailing predication, represents claiming that the latter
                fails the criterion of coherence. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F79">
            <bib>-----. "Structure and Style in Poems: A Paradox." Style 1 (1967): 93–106. </bib>
            <notes> Concludes that the theory of "style is choice" is severely weakened by the
                formal constraints which restrict choices in the composing of a poem. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F80">
            <bib>Hagopian, John V. "The Morphology of John Donne, Including a Pun Index, a Rhyme
                Index, and Studies in the Relation Between Linguistics and Literature." Diss., Case
                Western Reserve University, 1956. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F81">
            <bib>Halpern, Martin. "Keats's Grecian Urn and the Singular "Ye.'" College English 24
                (1963): 284–88. </bib>
            <notes> See also the ensuing correspondence in TLS for February-March 1964. Argues that
                the 'ye' was chosen for the sake of euphony, at the expense of syntactic
                consistency, and was intended to be singular: the poet speaks the final lines to the
                urn (not the figures on the urn). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F82">
            <bib>Hamilton, G. Rostrevor. The Tell-Tale Article. New York: Oxford University Press,
                1950. </bib>
            <notes> A curiosity--he argues that the frequency of the definite article in this
                century has produced a "degenerate syntax" in modern poetry. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F83">
            <bib>Hammond, Mac. "On the Grammar of Wallace Stevens." The Art of the Mind: Essays on
                the Poetry of Wallace Stevens. Ed. Roy Harvey Pearce and J. Hillis Miller.
                Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1965. pp. 179–84. </bib>
            <notes> Argues that Stevens' poetry is in fact metapoetry (poetry about poetry), and
                hence it must consist primarily of "concepts about poetic language itself, of which
                grammar makes up a large part of the story." That is why Stevens' later poetry is so
                incredibly dense in nouns and adjectives--reifiers and descriptors--and nearly
                devoid of strong verbs. His close repetitions of a word or phrase can usually be
                explicated if we assume a shift in meaning in the second instance. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F84">
            <bib>-----. "Poetic Syntax." Poetics I (A16), pp. 475–82. </bib>
            <notes> Illustration of the author's thesis that "syntax is poetic when grammatically
                equivalent constituents in connected speech are juxtaposed by coordination or
                parataxis, or are otherwise prominently accumulated" in the ninth stanza of The Man
                with the Blue Guitar and one other poem. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F85">
            <bib>-----. "Sound and Grammar in Wallace Stevens' 'The Man With the Blue Guitar.'"
                Diss;, Harvard University, 1962. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F86">
            <bib>Harrison, James. "Syntax in Donne's 'The Dream.'" Humanities Association Review 25
                (1974): 141–45. </bib>
            <notes> The equivocal ending to this both-affirming-and-doubting-love poem is achieved
                by particular deployment of personal pronouns, object complements, and repetition.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F87">
            <bib>Hedges, James S. "William Carlos Williams: Language About Language." DAI 31
                (1970): 5403A (Nebraska). </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F88">
            <bib>Hendricks, W. O. "Three Models for the Description of Poetry." Journal of
                Linguistics 5 (1969): 1–22. </bib>
            <notes> The grammatical approach of Thorne (F210) and the lexical approach of Rif-
                faterre are criticized; Hendricks urges that they be supplanted with a "textual"
                approach, mainly lexical but grammatical in part, and focused on text not on any
                hypothesized "poetic language." Thorne replies on pp. 147–52. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F89">
            <bib>Herrmann, Albert. A Grammatical Inquiry into the Language of Lord Byron. Berlin,
                1902. 33 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Not seen; cited in C. G. Kayser's Bücher-Lexicon for 1899–1902. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F90">
            <bib>Hill, Archibald A. "Some Further Thoughts on Grammaticality and Poetic Language."
                Style 1 (1967): 81–92 </bib>
            <notes>. Revised and condensed as </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F91">
            <bib>-----. "Two Views of Poetic Language and Meaning: The Poem as Cryptogram and as
                Example of Deviant Grammar." In his Constituent and Pattern in Poetry. Austin:
                University of Texas Press, 1976. pp. 115–22. </bib>
            <notes> Proposes two types of syntactic deviation in poetry, both of them relatively
                slight in terms of distortion of the normal grammar yet capable of considerable
                range and also capable of differentiating for us coherent poetic strategies from
                random and unintelligible poetic "cryptograms": in the one type, normal syn- tactic
                processes are simply carried to an unexpected extreme; in the other, an unexpected
                word has been substituted for a familiar one. Both types may be explicated by
                searching for the underlying "immediate source sentence"--i.e., the normal
                nondeviant form. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F92">
            <bib>Hirshfield, Susan E., and Ruth Portner. "A Voyage Through Two Voyages: A Study of
                Hart Crane's Voyages IV and V." Language and Style 1 (1968): 115–28. </bib>
            <notes> Syntactic analysis, to verify that the first of the two poems is "less
                successful" than the second, the second being more "complex" and "economical."
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F93">
            <bib>Hollander, John. "'Sense Variously Drawn out': Some Observations on English
                Enjambement." Literary Theory and Structure: Essays in Honor of W. K. Wimsatt, Jr.
                Ed. Frank Brady, John Palmer, and Martin Price. New Haven: Yale University Press,
                1973. pp. 201–25; rpt in his Vision and Resonance (A13), pp. 91–116. </bib>
            <notes> The iconic text for illustration of the full array of effects possible in
                enjambe- ment is of course Paradise Lost. Hollander formalizes some earlier
                suggestions by devising a graded continuum of the cuts into syntax made by
                enjambment, ranked from "hardest" (worst dislocation, as between determiner and
                noun) to "softest," (respectively) six to one numerically. Determinations of
                hardness, however, are complex matters, given the syntactic ambiguities which Milton
                systematically exploits at line-end: we have learned very well how a following line
                can force a revision of the semantic construal tentatively made at the end of the
                previous line. Such "revisionist" cuts are other than what they seem. Behind this
                article there is a very good book waiting to be written. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F94">
            <bib>Holloway, John. "Poetic Analysis and the Idea of the Transformational-Rule: Some
                Examples from Herbert, Wordsworth, Pope, and Shakespeare." Miscellanea
                Anglo-Americana: Festschrift für Helmut Viebrock. Ed. Kuno Schuhmann et al. Munich:
                Karl Pressler, 1974. pp. 279–96. </bib>
            <notes> A lucid and reflective critique of linguistics applied to literature: phrase-
                structure rules are useless, but transformational rules, and indeed "the idea of the
                rule itself," are not. "Transformations" (inversions) considered: rhyme, word-order,
                metaphor, antithesis, diction. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F95">
            <bib>Hudea, Ana M. "'Peter Quince at the Clavier' by Wallace Stevens--a Linguistic
                Analysis." Analele Universitatii Bucaresti, Limbe Germanice 22 (1973): 43–50. </bib>
            <notes> Rather mechanical analysis of syntax and structural grouping. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F96">
            <bib>Ives, Sumner. "Grammatical Analysis and Literary Criticism." Monograph Series on
                Language and Linguistics 13 (1962): 99–117. </bib>
            <notes> Some non-technical observations followed by an analysis of an MacLeish poem and
                panel discussion. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F97">
            <bib>Jakobson, Roman. "The Grammatical Texture of a Sonnet from Sir Philip Sidney's
                Arcadia." Studies in Literature and Language in Honor of Margaret Schlauch. Ed. M.
                Brahmer et al. Warsaw: Polish Scientific Publishers, 1966. pp. 165–73. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F98">
            <bib>Jindra, V. A Syntactical Analysis of the Language of Ben Jonson's Plays. Prague,
                1930. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F99">
            <bib>Jones, Myrl G. "Word-Repetition as a Technique Emphasizing Characterization and
                Theme in Paradise Lost." DAI 34 (1973): 1860A (Houston). </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F100">
            <bib>Jungnell, Tore. "Notes on the Language of Ben Jonson." Studier i Modern
                Sprakvetenskap (Stockholm), n.s. 1 (1960): 86–110. </bib>
            <notes> A list of syntactic idiosyncrasies and first known occurrences. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F101">
            <bib>Katz, Elaine S. "Sector Analysis and the Study of Poetry: A Paradigmatic
                Explication of Syntactic Structures in John Donne's 'Goodfriday, 1613. Riding
                Westward.'" DAI 39 (1978): 2224A (Alabama). </bib>
            <notes> An effective pedagogical technique for teaching the importance of syntax in
                poetry is sector analysis, wherein "written English is perceived as a system of
                visual signals which overlaps rather than replicates the system of spoken Eng- lish.
                . . . During analysis each unit (filling sector or slot) is identified on each
                successive layer of structure in terms of a correlation between its positional
                function and form." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F102">
            <bib>Kenner, Hugh. "Some Post-Symbolist Structures." In Literary Theory and Structure:
                Essays in Honor of W. K. Wimsatt. Ed. Martin Price. New Haven: Yale University
                Press, 1973. pp. 379–93. </bib>
            <notes> Varieties of Syntax as structure: • Tennyson: gorgeous words displayed within a
                plain syntax; • Jonson: his verse structure as indispensable as the diction; •
                Mallarmé: the complex unfolding of subordinations ordering and routing our
                perceptions; • Yeats: calculated syntactic deceptions and feints. But the relevant
                facts or images of the poem may be held in place also by meter, or by the repetition
                and variation of "musical" motifs. With these examples in co-ordination, Kenner
                constructs his marvelously instructive and graceful sketch of Post-Symbolist poetic
                ordering. Closes emphasizing Eliot. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F103">
            <bib>Keyser, Samuel Jay. "Wallace Stevens: Form and Meaning in Four Poems." College
                English 37 (1976): 578–98. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F104">
            <bib>Killingley, Siew-yue. "Lexical, Semantic, and Grammatical Patterning in Dylan
                Thomas (Collected Poems 1934–1952)." Orbis 23 (1974): 285–99. </bib>
            <notes> Thomas prefers unusual lexical collocations within normal syntactic order.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F105">
            <bib>Kintgen, Eugene R. "Is Transformational Stylistics Useful?" College English 35
                (1974): 799–824. </bib>
            <notes> A general review article on the published work of Levin and Ohmann. Sur- veying
                closely Levin's book and seven articles on poetic grammar, Kintgen dis- counts both
                the theoretical validity and literary applicability of transformational grammar: it
                can ask good questions, but "has no answers: at best it can parrot back our
                intuitions, expressing them without explaining them; the danger is that the
                expression, formal as it is, looks like an explanation an is likely to be taken for
                one." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F106">
            <bib>-----. "Perceiving Poetic Syntax." College English 40 (1978): 17–27. </bib>
            <notes> An experimental inquiry (sixteen subjects) into the reader's "syntactic
                glossing" of a poem, and also into types of strategies for resolving cruces.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F107">
            <bib>Klimenko, E. "Zu Shelley's Syntax." Archiv 158 (1930): 55–59; 159 (1931): 19–35. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F108">
            <bib>Korg, Jacob. "Hopkins' Linguistic Deviations." PMLA 92 (1977): 977–86. </bib>
            <notes> Students of sonal mimesis, recognizing Hopkins as a prime source, will be in-
                terested in the philosophical assumptions underlying the whole concept that language
                "represents" reality. Korg argues that "language that is occupied with the
                self-conscious investigation of its own properties cannot also be referen- tial";
                indeed, "the most referential language is that which adheres to conven- tion," and
                in as much as the poet "amplifies the corporeality of his language, he actively
                pursues the dissociation of words and things" (Gerald Bruns). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F109">
            <bib>Krause, Florence P. "The Grammatical Aspect of Browning's Style." DAI 32 (1971):
                412A (Tennessee). </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F110">
            <bib>Kroeber, A. L. "Parts of Speech in Periods of Poetry." PMLA 73 (1958): 309–14. </bib>
            <notes> Appraisal, extension, and refinement of the methods and findings of Miles
                (F147), with speculations on the cultural and literary causes of the phenomena she
                discerns. Kroeber accepts her conceptions and finds her method "poten- tially
                productive" though he is more dubious about her conclusion that such changes occur
                cyclically. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F111">
            <bib>Kuhns, Richard. "Deletion and Compression in Poetry." Foundations of Language 11
                (1974): 401–7. </bib>
            <notes> Further argument and interpretation of Dickinson's poem #1146, following Kintgen
                (F125): and Levin; Kuhns appeals to evidence from other of her po- ems. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F112">
            <bib>Kusakabe, Hiroko. "Syntactic and Rhetoric in Milton's Poems." Diss., Doshisha
                Women's College, 1966. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F113">
            <bib>Kypriotaki, Lyn R. "A Linguistic Analysis of Poetic Style." DAI 32 (1971): 949A
                (Berkeley). </bib>
            <notes> A purely linguistic analysis of the 1805 and 1850 versions of The Prelude, which
                concludes that the later version produces a "less personal, less immedi- ate, less
                direct style." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F114">
            <bib>Lair, Robert L. "Emily Dickinson's Fracture of Grammar." DA 27 (1967): 3052A (Ohio
                State). </bib>
            <notes> General types of syntactic ambiguity in Dickinson's poetry are distinguished
                from specific syntactic idiosyncrasies in an effort to characterize her attitude
                toward grammar. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F115">
            <bib>Landon, George M. "The Contribution of Grammar to the Poetic Style of Wilfred
                Owen." DA 25 (1965): 6610A (Indiana). </bib>
            <notes> Transformational analysis uncovers 8% syntactic deviance and 10% lexical de-
                viance. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F116">
            <bib>-----. "The Grammatical Description of Poetic Word-Order in English Verse."
                Language and Style 1 (1968): 194–200. </bib>
            <notes> Responding to Levin (B128), Landon suggests that the sequential ordering of
                elements in the production of a grammatical sentence takes place very late, and to
                say that deviations in word-order "violate a rule" of English grammar is too simple:
                in one case that is too strong to a claim, in another too weak. A better strategy
                would be to introduce into the grammar a device which "scrambles" the elements of
                the sentence. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F117">
            <bib>Lasher, William E. "A Grammar of the Auxiliary Component in the Faerie Queene."
                DAI 32 (1971): 949A (North Carolina). </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F118">
            <bib>Lauvrière, Émile. Repetition and Parallelism in Tennyson. London: Oxford
                University Press, 1910. 107 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Part I catalogues the repetitions analytically, Part 2 chronologically. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F119">
            <bib>Lawler, Justus George. "Enjambement: A Structure of Transcendence." College
                English 39 (1978): 725–37 </bib>
            <notes>; rpt in revised form as chapter 4 of his Celestial Pantomime. New Haven: Yale
                University Press, 1979. pp. 73–103. As a demurrer to Hollander's view that
                enjambement is a device infinitely flexible, Lawler suggests in this richly allusive
                and elegant essay that its princi- pal purpose is to stand as the emblem of the
                larger spiritual and sexual union in transcendence, in overflowing, in going over
                into the other. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F121">
            <bib>Lebedeva, N. V. "Certain Syntagmatic Features of Poetic Speech." Linguistics 141
                (1974): 35–42. Originally in Voprosy jazykoznanija 4 (1972): 112–17. </bib>
            <notes> The work surveyed is Russian though the examples are English. Highly tech-
                nical. The author recognizes that the verse-line is the irreplaceable requirement
                for all poetry but insists that it "can be defined only within the bounds of the
                semiotics of poetic speech." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F122">
            <bib>Le Comte, Edward S. Yet Once More: Verbal and Psychological Patterns in Milton.
                New York: Liberal Arts Press, 1953. </bib>
            <notes> Primarily on lexical and rhetorical repetitions, both in the poetry and the
                prose. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F123">
            <bib>Leech, Geoffrey N. "'This Break I Break'--Language and Interpretation." Review of
                English Literature 6 (19654): 66–75 </bib>
            <notes>; rpt in Freeman (A22), pp. 119–28. Discusses grammatical and lexical cohesion in
                a Dylan Thomas poem. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F124">
            <bib>Levin, Samuel R. "The Analysis of Compression in Poetry." Foundations of Language
                7 (1971): 38–55 </bib>
            <notes>. Reply by Eugene Kintgen, </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F125">
            <bib>"Nonrecoverable Deletion and Compression in Poetry," 9 (1972): 98–104; rejoinder
                by Levin, pp. 105–12 </bib>
            <notes>. Translated into German in Versprache: Zeitschrift für Literaturwissenschaft und
                Linguistik 1, 3 (1971). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F126">
            <bib>-----. "Deviation-Statistical and Determinate--in Poetic Language." Lingua 12
                (1963): 276–90. Reply by Robert Scholes in 13 f(1965): 189–92; rejoinder by Levin,
                pp. 193–95. </bib>
            <notes> Syntactic deviations in poetry are of two types: "those produced against the
                conventions of the poem." The first type, which Riffaterre has treated in terms of
                microcontext and macrocontext, is not a satisfactory concept, nor is the second if
                it approached purely statistically, since statistical norms for syntax in the lan-
                guage as a whole are simply impracticable. "But not all ungrammatical se- quences
                are poetically deviant . . . poetic deviation is in some sense controlled." Hence
                the standard for deviation should be the determinate norm of a genera- tive grammar
                of the language. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F127">
            <bib>-----. "On Automatic Production of Poetic Sequences." Texas Studies in Literature
                and Language 5 (1963): 138–46. </bib>
            <notes> A computer programmed with a complete English grammar could indeed pro- duce
                "poetic" (i.e. deviant) strings if it were given one additional directive to relax
                lexical co-occurrence restrictions. Such restrictions normally prohibit unrelated
                word-classes from appearing together, as in a hungry dance. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F128">
            <bib>-----. "Poetry and Grammaticalness." Proceedings of the Ninth International
                Congress of Linguists. Ed. Horace G. Lunt. The Hague: Mouton: 1964. pp. 308–14. </bib>
            <notes> Discussion follows on pp. 314–15. Rpt in Chatman and Levin (A21), pp. 224– 30.
                Confronts the general question of the adequacy of grammar for generating se- quences
                in poetry such as "he danced his did" or "a grief ago." See Thorne (F210). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F129">
            <bib>-----. "Some Uses of the Grammar in Poetic Analysis." Problèmes de l'analyse
                textuelle. Ed. Pierre R. Léon et al. Paris: Didier, 1971. pp. 19–27. </bib>
            <notes> Restatement of the problems involved in writing grammatical rules for deviant
                expressions such as in poetry, with sample analysis of recoverable deletions in some
                lines from Emily Dickinson. Questions by Riffaterre follow. N.B.: "A fundamental
                problem exists here, the problem of how to correlate statements of poetic value with
                statements of linguistic description." It is so everywhere in aesthetics. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F130">
            <bib>Limaye, Mohan R. "The Sentential Syntax of Edmund Spenser's Minor Poetry." DAI 38
                (1978): 4138A (Wisconsin). </bib>
            <notes> An effort to specifically correlate seven aspects of syntax with the traditional
                categories of "low," "middle," and "grand" style. Six conclusions: (1) pas-
                toral/non-pastoral is Spenser's primary distinction for genre; (2) the social rank
                of characters in the poems virtually always correlates with syntactic complex- ity;
                (3) the most syntactically complex poems are the celebratory ones; (4) the satires
                are nearly all in the middle style; (5) in poems where lament suffuses joy, joy
                dominates at least in terms of syntactic complexity; and (6) Spenser shows a
                remarkable range of complexity in syntax. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F131">
            <bib>Lint, Robert G. "Structural Sources for Symbol and Meaning in 'The Red
                Wheelbarrow.'" Language and Style 4 (1971): 297–300. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F132">
            <bib>-----. "Syntax in Browning's 'Sordello.'" DA 28 (1968): 4617A (Ohio). </bib>
            <notes> Having previously sorted out critical objections to types of "obscurity" having
                nothing to do with poetic texture, Lint applies T-unit analysis in order to gauge
                the relative degree of syntactic complexity in "Sordello," which turns out to be
                "not uniform, nor even major in the poem." In quantitative density, specific
                features do not occur so very frequently compared to other stylists such as Gibbon,
                Johnson, or Swift, though in the relationships among specific features, some
                passages in the poem do score highly. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F133">
            <bib>Lipski, John M. "Poetic Deviance and Generative Grammar." PTL 2 (1977): 241– 56. </bib>
            <notes> A review of the whole issue of grammatical deviance in poetry. "In the realm of
                highly deviant expression . . . given the idiosyncratic and non-formalizable nature
                of poetic deviance, it is likely that generative grammars will be at best
                irrelevant, and at worst misleading. . . . Additional models . . . are called for .
                . . ." The crux of the problem, Lipski concludes, is that "when faced with an
                instance of severe grammatical deviance, the listener makes use of a set of pre-
                grammatical strategies for arriving at the basic semantic structure." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F134">
            <bib>Lord, John B. "Apposite Grammatical Patterns in Spencer's Epithalamion." Pacific
                Coast Philology 3 (1968): 73–77. </bib>
            <notes> A full model of the seventeen variants of the refrain line in the twenty-three
                stanzas of the poem shows that over 28,00 variants were possible, but that Spencer
                chose his to indicate (syntactic) attachment and affirmation in the first sixteen
                stanzas (when guests are present at the wedding-feast) and detachment and negativity
                in the last seven (when the two lovers are alone and value their privacy). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F135">
            <bib>-----. "Para-grammatical Structure in a Poem of E. E. Cummings." Pacific Coast
                Philology 1 (19660: 66–73. </bib>
            <notes> The "recursive" structures in "anyone lived in a pretty how town" (e.g. "all in
                all and deep by deep") suggest steady incremental motion toward a "remote whole";
                the "non-recursive" structures (e.g. "if by yes") imply a "complemen- tary
                oscillation." There is a splendid observation on "pushing through" on p. 66.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F136">
            <bib>Luthy, Melvin. "The Case of Prufrock's Grammar." College English 39 (1978): 841–
                43. </bib>
            <notes> Argues that the first line of the poem is grammatical. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F137">
            <bib>Lyford, Roland H. "Grammatical Categories in Robert Frost's Blank Verse: A
                Quantitative Analysis." DA 29 (1969): 4475A (California at Davis). </bib>
            <notes> Structural-linguistic analysis of grammatical patterning in forty-six
                blank-verse poems. The chief stylistic features in Frost are "contradictions and
                com- pounds." The use of blank verse enables Frost to present conversation while
                retaining the coherence usually absent in actual speech. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F138">
            <bib>McIntosh, Margaret M. "Emily Dickinson's Poems About Pain: A Study of Interrelated
                Moral, Theological, and Linguistic Freedoms." Diss., Harvard University, 1967. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F139">
            <bib>Martin, Loy D. "The Literary Style of Robert Browning and Ezra Pound." DAI 35
                (1974): 2947A (Virginia). </bib>
            <notes> Some attention to syntax. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F140">
            <bib>Maxwell, J. C. "Peele and Shakespeare: A Stylometric Test." JEGP 49 (1950):
                557–61. </bib>
            <notes> Proposes as a stylistic criterion of authorship the use of a possessive
                adjective or pronoun as the antecedent of a relative clause. It is not a very
                effective indica- tor. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F141">
            <bib>Messing, Gordon M. "The Impact of Transformational Grammar upon Stylistics and
                Literary Analysis." Linguistics 66 (1971): 56–73. </bib>
            <notes> A review article, the first half of which surveys the work so far done on poetry
                and "grammaticality" in a spirit of healthy skepticism. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F142">
            <bib>Miles, Josephine. The Continuity of Poetic Language. Berkeley: University of
                California Press, 1951; rpt New York: Octagon Books, 1965. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in JEGP 51 (1952): 426–28; in the Saturday Review of Literature, 13 Oc-
                tober 1951, p. 46; in JAAC 10 (1951–52): 80–82. A synthesis of the work in her
                earlier studies: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F143">
            <bib>-----. The Primary Language of Poetry in the 1940's. University of California
                Publications in English, vol. 19, no. 3. Berkeley: University of California Press,
                1951. pp. 385–542. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F144">
            <bib>-----. The Primary Language of Poetry in the 1640's. University of California
                Publications in English, vol. 19, no. 1. Berkeley: University of California Press,
                1948. pp. 1–160. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in MP 47 (1949) 140–43; in Sewanee Review 57 (1949): 709–14; in MLN 65
                (1950): 60–62; in MLR 47 (1952): 101–2. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F146">
            <bib>-----. "Eras in English Poetry." PMLA 70 (1955): 853–75; rpt in Chatman and Levin
                (A21):, pp. 175–96 </bib>
            <notes>. Expanded into: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F147">
            <bib>-----. Eras &amp; Modes in English Poetry. Berkeley: University of California
                Press, 1957; 2nd rev. ed. 1964. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Kenner in Poetry 92 (1958): 121–26; in TLS, 12 September 1958, p. 512;
                in MLR 53 (1958): 621; in Review of English Studies n.s. 10 (1959): 323– 25. See
                F110. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F148">
            <bib>-----. Renaissance, Eighteenth-Century, and Modern Language in English Poetry: A
                Tabular View. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1960. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F149">
            <bib>Miller, Helena F. "The Use of the Third Person Singular of Have and Do in the
                Works of Shakespeare and Massinger." PQ 9 (1930): 373–78. </bib>
            <notes> Shakespeare's usage is surprisingly uniform: hath and doth are forms generally
                confined to his early career, while has and does mainly appear late, with
                Shakespeare' rarely mixing forms (e.g. has and doth) at any time. Massinger's usage
                is different, and some the non-Fletcherian scenes in Henry VIII, when tested for
                this feature, show his patterns somewhat more than Shakespeare's. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F150">
            <bib>Mitchell, Roger. "Toward a System of Grammatical Scansion." Language and Style 3
                (1970): 3–28. </bib>
            <notes> Implicitly or explicitly syntax has always been a part of English verse-theory,
                especially for Old English, but even "where a metrical principle is not percep-
                tible, as in most modern verse, the description and definition of rhythms be- comes
                impossible unless we take grammar into consideration." Earlier proso- dists offer
                little help, though Scripture's "centroid" captures the idea of the
                phrase-coalescing stress. Probably enjambement is only a matter of degree, every
                line having at least some minimal pause at its end. Mitchell gives a ten- tative
                sketch of a taxonomy for English verse (pp. 18–19), with illustrations. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F151">
            <bib>Morenberg, Max. "The Syntax of Robert Browning's Poetry." DAI 33 (1973): 4391A
                (Florida State). </bib>
            <notes> T-unit analysis of six Browning poems reveals that his syntax is "additive in
                nature, composed of relatively large numbers of tenuously related small clauses"
                which give the impression of "minds in motion, thinking." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F152">
            <bib>Morris, Jessie F. "Thomas Hardy's Style: A Syntactic Approach to the Poetry." DA
                29 (1968): 875A (New Mexico). </bib>
            <notes> A comparison of the syntax in Hardy's poetry to that in his letters shows very
                little difference; his poetry preserves most of the features of conversational
                prose. Nor is there significant variation between the early verse and the late.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F153">
            <bib>Mulholland, Joan. "Thou and You in Shakespeare: A Study in the Second Person
                Pronoun." English Studies 48 (1967): 34–43, 163. </bib>
            <notes> Analyzes the distribution in Much Ado and Lear, with lengthy discussion and
                useful footnote-references. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F154">
            <bib>Musacchio, George L. "Milton's Feminine Pronouns with Neuter Antecedents." Journal
                of English Linguistics 2 (1968): 23–28. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F155">
            <bib>Musser, Joseph F., Jr. "William Cowper's Syntax as an Indication of his Relation-
                ship to the Augustans." Style 11 (1977): 284–302. </bib>
            <notes> In their metrical pattern, Cowper's heroic couplets "imply the analytic mode [of
                conceiving experience] while his syntax implies the constructive." (In comparison
                with Pope, Cowper tends to modify the whole assertion rather than merely the
                subject.) It was this uncongeniality of the couplet to Cowper's modi cogitandi which
                impelled his toward blank verse. (In comparison with Wordsworth, Cowper's blank
                verse is much more argumentative and dialectic.) F156 See also this author's
                dissertation, "William Cowper's Poetry: A Comparison with Pope and Wordsworth." DAI
                32 (1971): 4573A (Virginia). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F157">
            <bib>Nelson, Thomas Edward. "The Syntax of Sidney's Poetry." DAI 36 (1976): 6710A
                (Ohio). </bib>
            <notes> The basis for structure in Astrophel and Stella is the clause rather than the
                line. Sidney's syntax (and prosody) differs markedly from that of his contemporaries
                in being "plainer," "more idiomatic," and "tending toward dramatic narration and
                elaborate argument, instead of elaborate description." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F158">
            <bib>Neuner, Karl. Untersuchungen zur Stilistik des Adjektivs in Tennysons epischen
                Dichtungen. Diss., Innsbruck, 1911. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F159">
            <bib>Nims, Irene D. "Tone in the Poetry of Emily Dickinson: A Linguistic Analysis with
                Pedagogical Reflections." DAI 32 (1972): 4594A (Indiana). </bib>
            <notes> Transformational-syntactic analysis of eleven poems generally confirms previ-
                ous critical judgments on their complex or mixed tones. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F160">
            <bib>Noël, J. "A Critique of S. R. Levin's 'Analysis of Compression in Poetry.'" Revue
                des langues vivantes (Brussels) 39 (1973): 231–38. </bib>
            <notes> Rebutting Levin's arguments, Noël denies that the linguistic "nonrecoverable
                deletion" rule is in fact operating in the ellipses in Emily Dickinson, and that the
                rule "could serve to characterize a distinctive aspect of poetic language." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F161">
            <bib>Nordan, Lewis A. "Shakespeare's Dramatic Poetry: Its Development (1591–1601): and
                Its Specialization in Cymbeline and The Tempest." DAI 34 (1974): 7199A (Auburn). </bib>
            <notes> On Shakespeare's use of grammar in the late Romances (1597–1601): to "ef- fect
                regular structural rhythms of speeches" and hence differentiate characters. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F162">
            <bib>Nowakowska, Nina. Language of Poetry and Generative Grammar: Toward Generative
                Poetics? (With Sample Analyses of T. S. Eliot's Poems). Series Filologia Angielska,
                no. 10. Pozanan: Uniwersytet im Adama Mickiewicza w. Poznaniu, 1977. 137 pp.See also
                her essay of the same title in </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F163">
            <bib>Nowakowska, Nina. "......" Studia Anglica Posnaniensia 9 (1977): 71– 77. </bib>
            <notes> The main thrust of the study falls on the formal elaboration of the theory and a
                defense of the generative method; the analysis of Eliot is incidental. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F164">
            <bib>O'Neal, Michael J. "A Linguistic Examination of the Syntactic Style of Three
                English Decadent Poets: Arthur Symons, Ernest Dowson, and Lionel Johnson." DAI 39
                (1978): 854A (Bowling Green State). </bib>
            <notes> Analyzes the proportion of phrases to clauses, varieties of verbals, and
                varieties of sentence-types (regular, elaborated, dislocated, or fragmented). Symons
                and Dowson wrote verse that is mainly clausal, while Johnson's is mainly phrasal.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F165">
            <bib>Oomen, Ursula. "On Some Elements of Poetic Communication." Georgetown University
                Working Papers on Languages and Linguistics 11 (1975): 60–68. </bib>
            <notes> A more fruitful approach to the grammar of poetry than the one which views
                poetic phrases as deviations is a broader view of the function of such phrases in
                the total (fictive) communication situation of the poem. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F166">
            <bib>Parker, David. "Verbal Moods in Shakespeare's Sonnets." MLQ 30 (1969): 331–39. </bib>
            <notes> Suggests that it is profitable to view the sonnets as written in the imperative
                mood rather than as indicative assertions. The dynamics of fact, hypothesis,
                question, demand, wish, and threat in the sonnets is complex and subtle. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F167">
            <bib>Partridge, A. C. Studies in the Syntax of Ben Jonson's Plays. Cambridge: Bowes and
                Bowes, 1953. 104 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in MLR 49 (1954): 368–69; in Review of English Studies 6 (1954): 197– 201;
                in Shakespeare Jahrbuch 90 (1954): 345–47. Treats the auxiliary verb do, nouns,
                pronouns, and articles. No summary. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F168">
            <bib>-----. A Substantive Grammar of Shakespeare's Nondramatic Texts. Charlottesville:
                University of Virginia Press, 1976. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F169">
            <bib>Patterson, Annabel M. "'How to load and . . . bend': Syntax and Interpretation in
                Keats's To Autumn." PMLA 94 (1979): 449–58. </bib>
            <notes> Recent analyses of the syntax of the poem by Donald Freeman (F68) and Geoffrey
                Hartmann find what they set out to find, as does the present analysis offered as a
                counter-view. The trouble with Freeman's analysis is that is de- taches parallel
                grammatical constructions from the stanza in order to point up their equivalence in
                the grammatical deep structure, thereby obliterating the fact that "the parallel
                phrases present themselves in various positions upon a material [metrical] field,"
                i.e. the stanza. "A viable concept of poetic syntax must, in other words, include
                metrical information." Patterson's own reading of the Ode is a negative, ironic
                reading. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F170">
            <bib>Payne, Michael. "Syntactical Analysis and 'The Windhover.'" Renascence 19 (1967):
                88–92. </bib>
            <notes> Linguistic/rhetorical analysis based on the method of Francis Christiansen.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F171">
            <bib>Peltola, Niilo. The Compound Epithet and Its Use in American Poetry from
                Bradstreet through Whitman. Annales Academiae Scientiarum Feenicae, Series B, no.
                105. Helsinki, 1956. 299 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Archivum Linguisticum 10 (1958): 147–49; in Études Anglaises 12 (1959):
                183. Part I is organized by author, historically, Part II by grammatical
                classification and author. Tables and lists at the end, including analysis of
                alliterating com- pounds (p. 276). Though modern poets have not exploited the device
                of the lexical compound as extensively as Old English poets did, still they have
                recognized its effectiveness for creating new combinations of terms, for the
                simultaneous yoking of opposites (discordia concors), and for the conveyance of
                emotion in elevated language. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F172">
            <bib>Piche, Sister Robert L. "A Study of Certain Syntactic Elements in the 'Songs and
                Sonets' of John Donne." Diss., Catholic University of America, 1952. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F173">
            <bib>Price, Hereward T. "Shakespeare's Parts of Speech." San Francisco Quarterly 18
                (1952): 19–28. </bib>
            <notes> Actually on the functional shifts in grammatical categories which Shakespeare
                devised as part of his fertile verbal inventiveness: verbs made out of adjectives,
                adjectives made into nouns, etc. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F174">
            <bib>Pryse, Marjorie. " 'The Stonecarver's Poem': A Linguistic Interpretation."
                Language and Style 7 (1974): 62–71. </bib>
            <notes> Three hypotheses in syntactic analysis--Filmore on case-grammar, Ross on
                constituent-gapping, and Halliday on deictic modifiers--will provide an expli-
                cation of the deep structure of Levertov's poem. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F175">
            <bib>Redin, Mats. Word-Order in English Verse from Pope to Sassoon. Uppsala
                Universitets Arsskrift, 1925, no. 2. Uppsala: Almqvist &amp; Wiksells, 1925. 225 pp.
                Rev: in Anglia Beiblatt 38 (1927): 293–95. </bib>
            <notes> Analyzing some 50,000 lines from 1709–1919, mainly in Pope, Wordsworth, and the
                Georgians, Redin compares syntactic deviations in verse against a hy- pothetical
                norm in prose. Part 1 arrays the evidence in categories by nine parts of speech;
                Part 2 presents the statistical analyses. The general conclusion seems to be that
                deviations steadily decrease in this period, though more clearly so in rhymed verse
                than in blank. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F176">
            <bib>Reiss, Edmund. "Whitman's Poetic Grammar: Style and Meaning in 'Children of
                Adam.'" American Transcendental Quarterly (Special Whitman Issue0 12 (1971): 32–41. </bib>
            <notes> Whitman employs paratactic structures in order to suggest the identification of
                man with Man and Nature, since hypotaxis would have implied subordination. The poem
                also consists of only a single sentence, furthering the effect of iden- tification.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F177">
            <bib>Ricks, Christopher. Milton's Grand Style. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1963. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: Review of English Studies n.s. 16 (1965): 313–14; English Studies 48
                (1967): 553–55; in MLR 60 (1965): 594–98; in JEGP 63 (1964): 521–24; in Archiv 201
                (1964): 376–78; in English 15 (1964): 24–25; in TLS, 20 September 1963, p. 706; by
                Kermode in Encounter 21 (1963): 84–85; by Gardner in The Listener 70 (1963): 575; by
                Muir in Critical Quarterly 5 (1963): 275–76. An elegantly stylish discourse; Ricks
                defends Milton against his twentieth- century critics (Leavis, Eliot) with a method
                which counterposes observations by Milton's eighteenth-century editors (Bentley,
                Hume, Richardson, Newton) against sensitive and minute readings of the verse.
                Subjects: "rhythm or music, syntax, metaphor, and word-play"--above all, the
                "suggestiveness" of syntax. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F178">
            <bib>-----. "Wordsworth: 'A Pure Organic Pleasure from the Lines.'" Essays in Criticism
                21 (1971): 1–32. </bib>
            <notes> A luminous piece which begins with a brief review of the questions of how verse
                is related to poetry, then examines "the kinds of effect, subtle and vari- ous, that
                Wordsworth achieves with line-endings," taking the white-space at line-end as some
                sort of pause or punctuation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F179">
            <bib>Robinson, Fred C. "Verb Tense in Blake's 'The Tyger.'" PMLA 79 (1964): 666–69. </bib>
            <notes> The verb form dare in the poem is not an anomalous present tense but a rare,
                "poetical" preterite form, making it perfectly consistent with all the other verbs
                in the poem. There is a subsequent exchange between Robinson and John E. Grant on
                the issue, </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F180">
            <bib>Robinson, Fred C. "???" PMLA 81 (1966): 596–603 </bib>
            <notes>, Grant conceding Robinson's point in a flurry of contentiousness, defensiveness,
                and aggression. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F181">
            <bib>Rodway, Allen. "By Algebra to Augustanism." Fowler (A14), pp. 53–67. </bib>
            <notes> It is the road to syntax which leads to the palace of Augustan poetry. The
                methods of New Criticism have proved much less efficacious for Augustan poetry than
                for Romantic and Modern, perhaps because the former is with states. With a sharper
                instrument the critic can effect, Rodway demonstrates, some very fine
                discriminations even on very small samples: what emerges to the eye is the
                (syntactic) neural lattice of the Augustan "aesthetic of the intel- lection."
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F182">
            <bib>Rogers, J. P. W. "Pope and the Syntax of Satire." Literary English Since
                Shakespeare. Ed. George Watson. London: Oxford University Press, 1970. pp. 236–65. </bib>
            <notes> Elegantly, Robert contravenes most of our easy assumptions about the syntax of
                the couplet. Since structures of identity (stasis) such as repetition, parallel-
                ism, balance, and antithesis are inherent in the mode, Pope often works against the
                easier effects, creating for example "pseudo-parallelism" and "pseudo- antithesis,"
                structures whose actual effect is exactly the opposite of what it seems. The essence
                of the couplet is a "serial form" with "constant progres- sion." More generally, two
                modes of poetic organization may be defined, "open syntax" and "closed syntax," the
                open form emphasizing objects, things, quiddities, nouns, the closed form conversely
                attentive to connections, change, process (this the Augustan mode). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F183">
            <bib>Rogers, Pat. "Wit and Grammar in The Rape of the Lock." JEGP 72 (1973): 17–31. </bib>
            <notes> Pope's masterful control of tense, mood, and number for comic and ironic effect.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F184">
            <bib>Rose, Edward J. "Visual Forms Dramatic: Grammatical and Iconographical Movement in
                Blake's Verse and Designs." Criticism 8 (1966): 111–25. </bib>
            <notes> Does epistemology determine grammar in Blake? There is visual direction, and
                then there is grammatical direction. But directionality in both cases is anything
                but simple: an engraver might be expected to be sensitive to visual reversals, and
                images can be "read" in several configurations, but a word can be modified in
                several directions simultaneously, and in fact words often have "an internal order
                of meaning independent of the horizontal flow of the sentence." Lan- guage too is
                susceptible of reversal, and of multiple directionality. Finally, neither syntax nor
                image partakes of "single vision" in Blake: "The design of vision has no natural
                setting any more than it has anything to do with natural religion." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F185">
            <bib>Ross, Donald, Jr. "Stylistics and the Testing of Literary Hypotheses." Poetics
                n.s. (1978): 389–416. </bib>
            <notes> Further computerized stylistic analysis of syntax and lexis confirms the tradi-
                tional alignment of Coleridge with Keats against Blake, relations which are also
                borne out in Wordsworth's "Preface." Comparison of Keats's sonnets with those of the
                Elizabethans shows his technique radically unlike theirs, which is relatively
                homogeneous within the group. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F186">
            <bib>-----. "The Use of Word-Class Distribution Data for Stylistics: Keats's Sonnets
                and Chicken Soup." Poetics n.s. 6 (1977): 169–95. </bib>
            <notes> Describes a computer algorithm which parses verse by word-class, giving a more
                precise descriptive instruments for the weight or strength of verbal, ad- jectival
                or nominal style. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F187">
            <bib>Ruwet, Nicholas. "L'Analyse structurale de la poésie." Linguistics 2 (1963):
                38–59. </bib>
            <notes> An extended review of Levin's Linguistic Structures in Poetry (B129), within an
                even broader survey of the problem of a grammar for poetry vis à vis the gen- eral
                grammar of the language. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F188">
            <bib>Sarang, Vilas. "Articles in the Poetry of W. H. Auden." Language and Style 7
                (1974): 77–90. </bib>
            <notes> Auden disliked them--the definite ones--and systematically removed them both in
                his early work and in the incessant late revisions. It is astonishing what
                significant shifts in articulations can be effected by changing the specificity of
                mere articles. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F189">
            <bib>-----. "Syntactic Nuances in the Poetry of W. H. Auden." Journal of the University
                of Bombay 39 (1970): 66–101. </bib>
            <notes> A maundering survey of the uses of syntax for mimesis (in "1929"); musicality,
                structuring, and crescendo; change of tempo; inversion and changes of mood and tense
                (subjunctive, imperative, and interrogative); typographic connection; the
                ejaculatory "O"; definite and indefinite articles; and four types of deviation
                (lexical shifts and collocations, syntactic compressions, anthimeria, and syntac-
                tic distortion). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F190">
            <bib>Sasaki, Tatsu. On the Language of Robert Bridges' Poetry. Tokyo: Kenkyusha, 1930;
                106 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Englische Studien 66 (1931): 295–97; in MLR 27 (1932): 115–16; in
                English Studies 14 (1932): 236–28. A syntax study, focusing on adjectives,
                intensified nouns, infinitives, and ger- unds, and concluding that Bridges' syntax
                was determined primarily by archa- ism, meter, and rhetoric. This study has an
                advantage over all others of its kind in explicitly recognizing and examining the
                role (constraints) of meter and rhyme on any supposed irregularities in syntax (see
                pp. 20–25; 58–59, and 78–79). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F191">
            <bib>Schap, Keith. "A Syntactic Figure in Two Poems by Theodore Roethke." Language and
                Style 11 (1978): 238–46. </bib>
            <notes> Readings of Roethke's poems will be enhanced by realizing that the gram- matical
                relation subject-object may be underpinning by a more fundamental re- lation,
                predicate-role-role or predicate-patient-instrument-agent. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F192">
            <bib>Scott, F. S. "Some Observations on the Syntax of Paradise Lost." Australasian
                Universities Language and Literature Association Proceedings and Papers of the
                Twelfth Congress. Ed. A. P. Treweek. Sydney: AULLA, 1970. pp. 211–23. </bib>
            <notes> Poetic syntax may deviate from the normal, established patterns for the pur-
                poses of (1) meter, (2) emphasis, or (3) variety. Examining these deviations in
                Milton generates a forcible impression of "experienced professional control, of
                scope and variety, rather than of pedantic stiffness," Eliot and Leavis notwith-
                standing. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F193">
            <bib>Scott, Janis M. M. "The Stubborn Structure of the Language: A Study of the Syntax
                of William Blake." DAI 34 (1973): 5148A (Mississippi). </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F194">
            <bib>Scott, William O. "Structure and Repetition in Elizabethan Verse." DA 20 (1960):
                3752A (Princeton). </bib>
            <notes> Four poets examined: Wyatt's use of syntactic repetition is simple and direct;
                Sidney learned to vary syntax with speaker and context; Spenser deploys his
                repetitions strategically for transition and modulation; and Donne anatomizes and
                intellectualizes the repetition itself. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F195">
            <bib>Seright, Orin D. "Syntactic Structures in Keats' Poetry." DA 26 (1965): 1033A
                (Indiana). </bib>
            <notes> Keats's syntax contains predominantly phrases and noun modifiers as opposed to
                clauses and verbs. This feature of his style remains constant over time even though
                the types of nominal modifiers and their placements vary. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F196">
            <bib>Sheehen, Donald. "The Whole of Harmonium: Poetic Technique in Wallace Stevens."
                The Fifties: Fiction, Poetry, Drama. Ed. Warren French. DeLand, Fla.:
                Everett/Edwards, 1970. pp. 175–86. </bib>
            <notes> "The characteristic sound in Stevens' poetry depends to a surprising extent upon
                a single thing: the capacity for complex syntax . . . . The phenomenon is a matter
                of the most exquisite balances, for the parts are at once immediate yet surprising,
                while the whole is simultaneously complex and satisfying. This dramatic balance
                gives Stevens a superb aesthetic instrument, for he can vary its effect almost
                endlessly by shifting complexity from design to detail and sim- plicity from detail
                to design . . . . Since the balances in a poem are sequential rather than causal,
                and so can only be momentarily achieved, the poem's pros- ody must not offer the
                slightest resistance to reaching them . . . the prosodic resonance is all outward
                and discontinuous since what there is of it in itself is wholly implicit in the
                momentary balances between detail and design." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F197">
            <bib>Sinclair, John McH. "Lines about 'Lines.'" Current Trends in Stylistics. Ed. B. B.
                Kachru and H. F. W. Stahlke. Edmonton (Canada): Linguistic Research, Inc., 1972. pp.
                251–61. </bib>
            <notes> Close syntactic analysis of "Tintern Abbey": the poem is generally "loose" in
                its grammatical structure, a result of frequent use of co-ordination. Meter (the
                line) is also balanced against grammar (the sentence), which makes for constant
                frustration of reader expectation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F198">
            <bib>-----. "Taking a Poem to Pieces." Fowler (A14), pp. 68–81; rpt in Freeman (A22),
                pp. 129–42. </bib>
            <notes> Uses Halliday's approach for analyzing grammatical patterns in a Philip Larkin
                lyric, "First Sight." This is the classic example of an immense linguistic super-
                structure being brought to bear on a single tiny poem, resulting in a great number
                of charts and tables and nothing whatsoever that a sensitive reader would not have
                realized, on reflection, soon enough. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F199">
            <bib>-----. "A Technique of Stylistic Description." Language and Style 1 (1968):
                215–42.</bib>
            <notes> Very extended stylistic analysis, primarily of grammar, in a Robert Graves poem,
                which focuses ultimately on "clause-to-line fit." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F200">
            <bib>Smith, C[harles] Alphonso. Repetition and Parallelism in English Poetry: A Study
                in the Technique of Poetry. New York and New Orleans: University Publishing Co.,
                1894. 76 pp. </bib>
            <notes> Though Smith never mentions syntax but often mentions meter, his subject is
                clearly the former: "in prose, a word or group of words is repeated for empha- sis;
                whereas in verse, repetition is chiefly employed not for emphasis . . . but for
                melody or rhythm . . . for banding lines or stanzas . . . ." Many examples but
                virtually no analysis. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F201">
            <bib>Stalker, James C. "The Stylistic and Interpretive Function of Relative Clauses in
                Dylan Thomas's Poetry: A Transformational Analysis." DAI 31 (1970): 1815A
                (Wisconsin). </bib>
            <notes> The analysis leads to the novel conclusion that Thomas uses the relative clause
                idiosyncratically. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F202">
            <bib>Stanley, Julia P. "The Problem of Unity in Poetry: A Linguistic Approach." DAI 32
                (1972): 6407A (Texas). </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F203">
            <bib>Stewart, Ann H. "The One Less Travelled by: Grammaticality and the Poetry of
                Gerard Manley Hopkins." Language and Style 8 (1975): 189–210. </bib>
            <notes> Contrary to what we might expect, syntactic repetition in Hopkins functions not
                as complication but as a device of simplification" it "smooths out" the sur- face
                structure and pulls up, frequently, the most essential threads of the com- plexly
                elaborated pattern. Repetition reinforces continuity and offsets com- plexity.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F204">
            <bib>Sugden, Herbert W. The Grammar of Spenser's "Faerie Queene." Language
                Dissertations Published by the Linguistic Society of America, no. 22; Philadelphia:
                L.S.A., 1936; 228 pp. </bib>
            <notes>, incl. long Bibliography. Organized by parts of speech. Though Spenser's diction
                is of course unusual, his grammar is in fact very similar to that of his
                contemporaries, and not particu- larly distinguishable from Shakespeare's. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F205">
            <bib>Sunderman, Paula. "Dylan Thomas' 'A Refusal to Mourn': A Syntactic and Semantic
                Interpretation." Language and Style 7 (1974): 20–35. </bib>
            <notes> Levin's theory of coupling (B129) and A. A. Hill's theory of analogy are ap-
                plied to yield a line-by-line interpretation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F206">
            <bib>Swieczkowski, Walerien. "On the Margin of Syntax and Style (A Quantitative
                Study)." Poetics I (A16), pp. 463–70. </bib>
            <notes> On pronominal constructions in four English prose writers; not on poetry.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F207">
            <bib>Tanner, James E., Jr. "The Grammar of Poetry: An Introduction to the Analysis of
                Style in Literature." DAI 33 (1973): 4367A (North Carolina). </bib>
            <notes> Argues for the superiority of a transformational analysis and proposes some de-
                letion rules for Cummings. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F208">
            <bib>Taylor, George C. "Marlowe's 'Now.'" Elizabethan Studies . . . in Honor or G. F.
                Reynolds. University of Colorado Studies in the Humanities, vol. 4, no. 2, Boulder:
                University of Colorado, 1945. pp. 93–100. </bib>
            <notes> The word appears very frequently at the beginnings of lines and speeches and
                stands as Marlowe's most obvious stylistic idiosyncrasy. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F209">
            <bib>Thorne, James P. "Generative Grammar and Stylistic Analysis." New Horizons in
                Linguistics. Ed. John Lyons. Baltimore: Penguin, 1970. pp. 185–97. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F210">
            <bib>-----. "Stylistics and Generative Grammars." Journal of Linguistics 1 (1965):
                49–59. </bib>
            <notes> Following Levin (F128), Thorne argues that the stylistic analyst should treat a
                literary text as a sample of an unknown language in constructing its grammar.
                Criticized by Hendricks (F88). Cf. Fowler (F63). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F211">
            <bib>Tuttle, Siri. "The Stopping of the Battle: Syntactic Deviation in 3 Poems by
                Charles Olson." Io 22 (1976): 37–47. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F212">
            <bib>Walker, Francis C. "Syntax of the Infinitive in Shakespeare." Diss., Harvard
                University, 1911. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F213">
            <bib>Walsh, Sister Mary Margaret. "Deep and Surface Structure in Five Poems of
                Alexander Pope." DA 29 (1969): 4477A (Syracuse). </bib>
            <notes> Five poems are compared to their germinal texts (classical antecedents) or
                contemporaneous verse for syntactic devices and variations: "Eloisa to Abe- lard,"
                "The Wife of Bath's Tale," "The First Satire, Second Book of Horace Imitated," The
                Dunciad, and The Rape of the Lock. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F214">
            <bib>Warfel, Harry R. "Language Patterns and Literature: A Note on Roethke's Poetry."
                Topic 6 (1966): 21–29. </bib>
            <notes> Bemoans the general lack of critical awareness of the importance of poetic
                syntax: examples from Roethke. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F215">
            <bib>-----. "Syntax Makes Literature." College English 21 (1960): 251–55. </bib>
            <notes> Otto Jesperson's tunnel vision for morphology has hindered the understanding of
                poetic syntax: analyses of Whitman poems and Hamlet may help correct this situation.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F216">
            <bib>Weinig, Mary A. "Syntax and Rhetoric in T. S. Eliot's Four Quartets." Diss;,
                Fordham University, 1957. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F217">
            <bib>Weiser, David K. "'I' and 'Thou' in Shakespeare's Sonnet's." JEGP 76 (1977):
                506–24. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F218">
            <bib>Whaler, James. "Grammatical nexus of the Miltonic Simile." JEGP 30 (1931): 327–34. </bib>
            <notes> The typical long simile in Milton (S) is both preceded and succeeded by a
                grammatical linkage (A--giving the formula ASA); it is rare when the succes- sive
                nexus is dropped. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F219">
            <bib>Wiley, Bowman G. The Clear Synthesis: A Study of William Wordsworth's Stylistic
                Development as a Descriptive Poet from 1793–1808. Salzburg: University of Salzburg
                Institute for English Language and Literature, 1974. </bib>
            <notes> cf. his dissertation, DA 28 (1967): 2224A (Michigan). Considerable discussion of
                syntax passim. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F220">
            <bib>Wilson, Milton. "Definite and Indefinite: Wyatt's Pronouns." Familiar Colloquy.
                Ed. Patricia Brückmann. Ontario: Oberon Press, 1978. pp. 25–36. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F221">
            <bib>Wolff, George. "Syntactic and Imagistic Distortion in Roethke's Greenhouse Poems."
                Language and Style 6 (1973): 281–88. </bib>
            <notes> Mainly interpretation and explication. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F222">
            <bib>"Words Divided at End of Line." Notes and Queries 170(1936): 246–47, 284, 319– 20,
                448; 171 (1936): 70, 87, 124, 212–13; 172 (1937): 157–58. </bib>
            <notes> See also 9th series, 10 (1902): 238–39. Instances in English, French, and German
                poetry, mostly minor, though the original query was about Ben Jonson. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F223">
            <bib>Wright, George T. "The Lyric Present" Simple Present Verbs in English Poems." PMLA
                89 (1974): 563–79. </bib>
            <notes> A study of the functions, overtones, and history of the simple present (in con-
                trast to the progressive present) tense in English poetry. The history is one of
                erratic increase, suggestive of the shift in Western sensibility from authority to
                experience. The overtones range from eternity to provisionality. An Appendix
                provides data on use of the progressive tense in fifty-nine poets. See the later
                exchange by Donald Ross and Wright: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F224">
            <bib>Wright, George T. "Frequency of Progressive Forms in Poetry in English." PMLA 92
                (1977): 132–34. </bib>
            <notes> Ross's analysis of the statistical data implies that the variances Wright
                notices are normal effects of changes in the language, not any indication of
                particular poet's styles; Wright disagrees. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F225">
            <bib>Wright, Keith. "Word-Repetition in T. S. Eliot's Early Verse." Essays in Criticism
                16 (1966)F: 201–6.</bib>
            <notes>See also his</notes>
        </item>
        <item id="F226">
            <bib>-----. "Rhetorical Repetition in T. S. Eliot's Early Verse." Review of English
                Literature 6 (1965): 93–100. </bib>
            <notes> See also: B121, B128–29, D317, D335–36, E92, E416, E572, E716, E801, E825, E946,
                E1039, E1162, E1178, E1183, E1234, E1381, G135, G137, H17, H22, H39, J4, J108–11,
                J136, J186, J205–10, J235, J259–60, K61, K174, K183, K187, K198, K207, K287, K391,
                L6, L44, L71, L156, L778, L864, L1000–1, L1307, L1310, L1313, L1401, L1460, N60.
            </notes>
        </item>
    </chapter>
</bibliography>
