<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="STANZA STRUCTURES">

        <item id="G1">
            <bib> Adams, Stephen J. "T. S. Eliot's So-called Sestina: A Note on The Dry Salvages,
                II." ELN 15 (1978): 203–8.</bib>
            <notes> Therein Eliot is attempting not the sestina but a related Provençal lyric form,
                the coblas estrampas (isolated stanzas) with rimas cars (scarce rhymes), which he
                apparently learned from Pound. The meter is still stress-verse. Cf. G9 and
                G20.</notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G2">
            <bib> Allen, James L., Jr. "Stanza Pattern in the Poetry of Poe." Tennessee Studies in
                Literature 12 (1967): 111–20.</bib>
            <notes> Convinced that Poe was a consummate technical craftsman, Allen reacts in-
                dignantly to the influential view of W. L. Werner (B228) that Poe's stanzas are
                mainly loose verse paragraphs. To reject everything but perfect identity of form as
                formless is to ignore Poe's allegiance to Variety Within Uniformity and to be blind
                to his expressive variations. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G3">
            <bib> Beum, Robert. "Yeats's Octaves." Texas Studies in Literature and Language 3
                (1961): 89–96</bib>
            <notes>; rpt as chapter 10 of his The Poetic Art of William Butler Yeats (B12). An
                admirably elegant defense of Yeats's stature as a poet of the very first order,
                argued on the basis of his individuality and his mastery of the ottava rima stanza.
                Coming after his earlier use of the quatrain, the octave was a moderate not a
                radical change for Yeats; it represented Tradition yet had been seldom em- ployed
                and--best of all--allowed ampler room for an ampler exposition. Cf. G39. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G4">
            <bib> Binyon, Laurence. "'Terza Rima' in English Poetry." English 3 (1940):
                113–17.</bib>
            <notes> Curious why Dante's great meter has never taken deep root in English, Binyon
                concludes that when English poets fail to respect the integrity of each stanza,
                allowing run-on of sense, they "change the metre into something else. . . . In terza
                rima, the rhymes being not coupled but interwoven, there is not the dan- ger, always
                present in the closed couplet, of the verse becoming mechanical and monotonous in
                its beat: the form is ampler, more flexible, and allows of varied cadences. But with
                a loose treatment the same thing happens in both cases: the rhyme tends to lose its
                functional value." Binyon collects as many instances in English as he can find. Cf.
                G60. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G5">
            <bib> Brewster, Paul G. "The Influence of the Popular Ballad on Wordsworth's Poetry." SP
                35 (1938): 588–612.</bib>
            <notes> Esp. pp. 597–601, for a survey of the various ballad stanzas Wordsworth ex-
                perimented with. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G6">
            <bib> Coffin, Tristram P. "Coleridge's Use of the Ballad Stanza in The Rime of the
                Ancient Mariner." MLQ 12 (1951): 437–45.</bib>
            <notes> Coleridge's variations and expansions of the abcb stanza occur most often in the
                middle of the poem, where the supernatural forces are most prevalent; the principle
                of expansion seems to be incremental repetition. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G7">
            <bib> Cohane, J. J. "Cowley and Yeats." TLS, 10 May 1957, p. 289.</bib>
            <notes> Yeats used the stanza of Cowley's "On the Death of Mr. William Hervey" for many
                of his best poems. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G8">
            <bib> Collins, Ben L. "The Stanzaic Pattern in Shelley's 'Ode to the West Wind.'" Keats-
                Shelley Journal 19 (1970): 7–8.</bib>
            <notes> Tenders the opinion that each section of the poem is a sonnet based on terza
                rima. Cf. Haworth (G103) and Wilcox (G64). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G9">
            <bib> Cummins, Paul. "The Sestina in the 20th Century." Concerning Poetry 11 (1978): 15–
                23.</bib>
            <notes> A defense of the importance of the form, against the view that it is merely a
                technical exercise, with examination of some of the best. Bibliography of sesti- nas
                by twenty-five modern poets. Cf. G1 and G20. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G10">
            <bib> Damico, Helen. "Sources of Stanza Forms Used by Burns." Studies in Scottish
                Literature 12 (1975): 207–19.</bib>
            <notes> Traces the long genealogy of the six-line stanza, the form of which is aaa 4 b 2
                a 4 b 2 , from its first appearance in the Middle Ages through fairly common usage
                by such poets as Allan Ramsey and Robert Sempill down to Burns, who turned its light
                tone into "a markedly lyric character with a dying fall" suitable for se- rious
                subjects. Also traced: rime couée, the septenary, the cauda, the bob-and- wheel, and
                other related and compound forms. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G11">
            <bib> Davies, H. Neville. "Laid Artfully Together: Stanzaic Design in Milton's 'On the
                Morning of Christ's Nativity.'" Fair Forms: Essays in English Literature from
                Spenser to Jane Austen. Ed. Maren-Sofie Rostvig. Totowa, N.J.: Rowman and
                Littlefield, 1975. pp. 85–117, 213–19.</bib>
            <notes> Argues that the stanzaic structure has four sections--a four-stanza Proem and a
                Hymn in sections of 15, 11, and 1 stanzas. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G12">
            <bib> Dechert, Peter. "'He Shouts to See Them Scamper So': E. A. Robinson and the French
                Forms." Colby Library Quarterly 8 (1969): 386–98.</bib>
            <notes> Robinson's interest in strict metrical forms borrowed from the French (ron-
                deau, rondel, ballade, triolet, villanelle) was limited to his early period, under
                the influence of his mentor A. T. Schumann; he wrote no more of them after 1895. The
                villanelle "The House on the Hill" is the best of the lot. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G13">
            <bib> Dickson, Margarette Ball. Patterns and Poems. Minneapolis: Argus, 1938. 103
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> A pocket primer of stanza forms with the author's original poems as examples.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G14">
            <bib> Fisher, J. "James Hammond and the Quatrain of Gray's Elegy." MP 32 (1935): 301–
                10.</bib>
            <notes> Hammond was the first, though not the most important, influence in fixing the
                quatrain as the staple--indeed, obligatory--stanza for the elegy in the eight- eenth
                century. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G15">
            <bib> Fletcher, Robert H. "The Metrical Forms Used by Certain Victorian Poets." JEGP 7
                (1907–8): 87–91.</bib>
            <notes> A very brief statement of the sum totals of metrical (i.e. stanzaic) forms used
                by Browning (200), Tennyson (240), and Swinburne (420), with discussion of problems
                of categorization and usefulness of results. Given the present exposi- tion, I
                cannot see but that the former is exceedingly large and the latter very small,
                though the question is an interesting one. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G16">
            <bib> Françon, Marcel. "Wyatt et le Rondeau." Renaissance Quarterly 24 (1971):
                340–43.</bib>
            <notes> Confirms the traditional judgments about Wyatt's nine triple-strophic ron-
                deaus. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G17">
            <bib> Gosse, Edmund. "A Plea for Certain Exotic Forms of Verse." Cornhill Magazine 36
                (1877): 53–71.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G18">
            <bib> Häublein, Ernst. Strophe und Struktur in der Lyrik Sir Philip Sidneys. Bern:
                Herbert Lang, 1971.</bib>
            <notes> A current, critically informed, and "fully systematic" analysis of the structure
                and internal dynamics of the stanza, taking Sidney's poems and those of the major
                Renaissance miscellanies as texts. The author anatomizes (1) structural (or logical)
                relations between stanzas in a poem, grading the connectedness as "unfixed,"
                "light-stimulus," or "strong-stimulus," with a notation for marking these; (2)
                reiteration of key words or phrases in and across stanzas; and (3) the structure
                within a stanza, especially vis à vis the problem of rhyme. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G19">
            <bib>Häublein, Ernst. The Stanza. The Critical Idiom Series, vol. 38. London: Methuen, 1978. 125
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> A companion-work to Turco (G59), yet of considerably greater range and
                penetration. Häublein reviews the major critical opinions on stanza-form from
                Puttenham (E614) to the present and surveys the characteristics of the major forms,
                but his principal interest throughout is the functions and effects--the dynamics--of
                stanzas, a province virtually unexplored to date. He examines modes of unification,
                varieties of openings and endings, structural repetition, and the "framing" effect
                within the stanza, and forms of linkage and develop- ment between stanzas in a poem.
                Well informed; extensive examples. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G20">
            <bib> Haselmayer, Louis A. "Sestina Revival." Iowa English Bulletin Yearbook, no. 8
                (1963), pp. 37–45.</bib>
            <notes> A splendidly succinct, informative, synoptic history of sestinas written from
                the twelfth century (Arnaut Daniel) to the twentieth, along with notes on twenty-
                one sestinas written by poets in our time and a Bibliography. Cf. G1 and G9.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G21">
            <bib> Havens, Raymond D. "The Meter of Collins's Ode to Evening." MLN 25 (1910):
                30–31.</bib>
            <notes> The stanza form of the ode is that of Milton's translation of the fifth ode of
                the first book of Horace, but it was suggested to Collins by Joseph Warton, who also
                has a poem in the same form. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G22">
            <bib> Hayes, Albert M. "Counterpoint in Herbert." SP 35 (1938): 43–60.</bib>
            <notes> Herbert devised a strategy of counterpointing his stanzas (abstract patterns of
                line-lengths, e.g. abab) to his rhymes (also abstract patterns, e.g. abba). As a re-
                sult, "this clash of patterns, this countrapuntal music" seems designed to pro- mote
                the sense before the pleasing sounds of the poem, thereby insuring the alertness of
                the reader. The sources: Puttenham's theory and Donne's practice. Hayes identifies
                twenty-seven varieties of stanza in The Temple, concluding, from an examination of
                twelve other major poets, that Herbert's contrapuntal stanza-structure is nearly
                nonexistent in the rest of English poetry. Compare this study with that by Kiparsky
                on abstract patterns (B117). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G23">
            <bib> Hinnant, Charles H. "Freedom and Form in Milton's Lycidas." Papers of the Michigan
                Academy of Sciences, Arts, and Letters 53 (1968): 321–28.</bib>
            <notes> Promotes two explanations for the unrhymed lines and intricate stanza-
                arrangements in the poem, basing both on extensive English literary tradition: (1)
                they denote the "formless agitation" of grief; (2) they are appropriate to the
                rustic diction and manners of an "uncouth swain." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G24">
            <bib> Huttar, Charles A. "A 'Sixain' of Four-Line Stanzas." Renaissance News 18 (1965):
                7–8.</bib>
            <notes> Finds an instance of a poem having six syllables to the line (four lines per
                stanza and twenty-six stanzas, in this case) in 1561, fourteen years before the
                first use of the term "sixain" recorded in the OED (by Gascoigne) and differing in
                sense. Gascoigne used the term to mean stanzas of six lines, which seems to have
                been the generally accepted definition. The 1561 usage--six syllables to the
                line--is an anomaly. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G25">
            <bib> Jackson, Elizabeth. "The Stanza of Rossetti's 'The Blessed Damozel.'" PMLA 58
                (1943): 1050–56.</bib>
            <notes> The six-line form (metrically 4-3-4-3-4-3; rhyme-scheme xaxaxa) Rossetti thought
                of as a ballad stanza and seems to have found in Coleridge, but by the time of "The
                Blessed Damozel" it had lost the ballad meter entirely and taken on a "shifting,
                hesitant rhythm" created by back-to-back stresses. Longfellow and Holmes also
                employed the form. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G26">
            <bib> Jason, Philip K. "Stanzas and Anti-Stanzas." College English 39 (1978):
                738–44.</bib>
            <notes> A very salient point: apparent units should be real units. Stanzaic divisions on
                the page ought to correspond to divisions in thought or organization in the struc-
                ture of the poem. Plath's "Ariel" is taken to task. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G27">
            <bib> Keating, John E. "'A Continuous Structural Parallelism': Stanzaic Pattern in The
                Wreck." Readings of The Wreck: Essays in Commemoration. Ed. Peter Milward and
                Raymond J. Schoder. Chicago: Loyola University Press, 1976. pp. 154– 61.</bib>
            <notes> Drawing some suggestions from Hopkins' undergraduate essay "On the Origin of
                Beauty" (on symmetry and variation), Keating notices that the first four lines of
                Hopkins' stanza are separated (and unified) metrically and thematically from the
                last four. This diremption creates effects of (1) balanced antithesis, (2)
                particularization, (3) incremental addition, or (4) reflectiveness, and altogether
                the stanzaic pattern of The Wreck is "basically antiphonal." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G28">
            <bib> King, Terrance J. "An Effect of Ease: Stanzaic Structure in the Early Poetry of
                Wallace Stevens." DAI 31 (1970): 6615A (Michigan).</bib>
            <notes> A visual approach to stanzaic design, emphasizing the "geography" or contour of
                the poem on the page, whether it be in monomorphic, polymorphic, paratactic, or
                radial-design (pivoting on a central line or word--the fulcrum in "Thirteen Ways of
                Looking at a Blackbird" is the word "see") construction. Rhyme, too, can serve
                visual as well as aural effects. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G29">
            <bib> Kronenfield, Judy Z. "The Asymmetrical Arrangement of Donne's 'Love's Growth' as
                an Emblem of Its Meaning." Concerning Poetry 9 (1976): 53–58.</bib>
            <notes> Stanza-breaks at lines 6 and 14 are both indispensable, even though the rhyme
                scheme does not seem to concur: two stanzas must seem to be three, since the-
                matically love has not inherently changed, it has simply become more mani- fest.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G30">
            <bib> Lawlor, Nancy K. "Eliot's Use of Rhyming Quatrains in The Waste Land." Poet and
                Critic 4 (1967): 29–37.</bib>
            <notes> The abcb quatrain seems to be distinctly associated, in Eliot's mind, with the
                theme of love-degraded-into-lust, i.e. sex. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G31">
            <bib> McGhee, Richard D. "'Blank Misgivings': Arthur Hugh Clough's Search for Poetic
                Form." Victorian Poetry 7 (1969): 105–15.</bib>
            <notes> The changes in the poem's stanza-pattern "reflect the ironic paradox of discov-
                ering aesthetic form while trying to escape from it." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G32">
            <bib> McGill, Josephine. "Old Ballad Burthens." Musical Quarterly 4 (1918):
                293–306.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G33">
            <bib> McKeehan, Irene P. "A Neglected Example of the In Memoriam Stanza." MLN 41 (1926):
                531–32.</bib>
            <notes> Addendum to Morton (G40). The example is a poem of Mrs. Katherine Phil- lips
                called "A Translation of Thomas à Kempis into verse," first published in 1667.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G34">
            <bib> MacLaine, Allan H. "New Light on the Genesis of the Burns Stanza." Notes &amp;
                Queries 198 (1953): 349–51.</bib>
            <notes> Additions to the genealogy of this six-line stanza-form (aaabab): Robert Sem-
                pill used it in 1640, taking the form from a collection of lyrics, The Gude and
                Godlie Ballatis. Some earlier instances are here identified ca. 1500; the form has
                been traced back to thirteenth-century France by T. F. Henderson. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G35">
            <bib> Marcotte, Paul J. "An Introduction to the Triolet." Inscape 5 (1966): 18–31.</bib>
            <notes> Patrick Cary seems to have transported the form, ca. 1651, though his work
                remained unknown until Scott reprinted it in 1819; Bridges revived it in 1873.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G36">
            <bib> -----. "More Late-Victorian Triolet Makers." Inscape 6, no. 2 (1968): 1–18.</bib>
            <notes> Namely Lang, Gosse, Henley, Hardy, and Symons. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G37">
            <bib> -----. "A Victorian Trio of Triolet Turners." Inscape 6, no. 1 (1968): 1–19.</bib>
            <notes> Bridges, Dobson, and Hopkins. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G38">
            <bib> "Modern Stanzas and Meters of Fixed Forms Originating under the Influence of the
                Renascence, or Introduced Later." Schipper (A11), Book II, Part 3. pp. 348–90.</bib>
            <notes> Five chapters on forms, including one on the Spenserian and one on the Son- net
                (Italian origins through the nineteenth century). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G39">
            <bib> Moran, Ronald. "The Octaves of E. A. Robinson." Colby Library Quarterly, Series 8,
                no. 7 (1969), pp. 363–70.</bib>
            <notes> Robinson wrote forty Octaves, twenty-eight of which are extant. Has anyone else
                written in this stanza as an isolate? Cf. G3. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G40">
            <bib> Morton, Edward P. "Poems in the Stanza of In Memoriam." MLN 24 (1909):
                67–70.</bib>
            <notes> Though Tennyson was unaware of any predecessors in the use of the abba te-
                trameter stanza, Morton locates twenty-five examples by seventeen poets in the
                seventeenth through nineteenth centuries, most notably by Jonson, Lord Herbert of
                Cherbury, and Clough, but only Lord Herbert used it at all fre- quently. See
                McKeehan (G33) and the next entry. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G41">
            <bib> -----. "The Stanza of In Memoriam." MLN 21 (1906): 229–31.</bib>
            <notes> The rarity of the form is perhaps due to its metrical compactness and enve-
                lope-rhymes; the former reduces variety and encourages prolixity, while the latter
                weaken the ends of the contiguous stanzas. Stanzaic comparison with the other
                well-known elegies in English is revealing. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G42">
            <bib> [Nature and Structure of the Stanza.] Schipper (A11), Book II, Part 1. pp.
                270–87.</bib>
            <notes> Definitions of stanza- and rhyme-forms. Classifies rhyme by number, quality, and
                position of rhyming syllables. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G43">
            <bib> Omans, Glen A. "Medieval French Poetic Forms in Victorian Poetry." DAI 24 (1963):
                1173A (Minnesota).</bib>
            <notes> A history of the revival begun in 1871 with Swinburne's translations of Villon
                and fortified by the discovery of de Banville's work in France after 1874, so that
                the English poets too--Swinburne, Lang, Gosse, Payne, Henley, and Dobson--began to
                call themselves "Parnassians." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G44">
            <bib> Power, Sister Alacoque. The Refrain in Nineteenth Century English Poetry.
                Washington, D. C.: Catholic University of America Press, 1960. 24 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A condensation of her dissertation of the same title. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G45">
            <bib> R., J. F. "Refrains." The Spectator 110 (1913): 875–76.</bib>
            <notes> Finds the origin and power of the refrain in the wider rhythmical patterns of
                repetition and variation, as also seen in meter and rhyme. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G46">
            <bib> Robinson, James K. "Austin Dobson and the Rondeliers." MLQ 14 (1953): 31–42.</bib>
            <notes> Very useful information (and notes) on Victorian poems in foreign forms.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G47">
            <bib> Ruhrmann, Friedrich G. Studien zur Geschichte und Charakteristik des Refrains in
                der englischen Literatur. Anglistische Forschungen, vol. 64. Heidelberg: Carl
                Winter, 1927. 179 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in English Studies 10 (1928): 88–89; by Baum in JEGP 28 (1929): 591– 92; in
                Englische Studien 63 (1929): 415–17; in LGRP 50 (1929): 349. Organized historically,
                from early folk ballads to the Edwardians; nearly half the book is devoted to the
                Victorians--Tennyson, Poe, Browning, Rossetti, Morris, and Swinburne. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G48">
            <bib> Schliebs, Gisela. Die Funktion der Strophenformen in George Herbert's "The Temple"
                im Rahmen des literarhistorischen sowie des musik- und dichtungstheoretischen
                Kontexte. Diss., Giessen, 1970. 643 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G49">
            <bib> Shuster, George N. The English Ode from Milton to Keats. Columbia University
                Studies in English and Comparative Literature, no. 150. New York: Columbia
                University Press, 1940.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation of the same title at Columbia University, 1940. Rev:
                in JEGP 40 (1941): 304–7; in MLN 57 (1942): 158–59. The scope is actually Early
                Renaissance to just after Keats, and the method in- cludes a very close attention to
                the prosodic aspects of the ode (as essential criteria for definition of that form)
                throughout. A much more satisfactory treatment than in Maddison (L97). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G50">
            <bib> Simonds, W. E. "The Three Rondeaux of Sir Thomas Wyatt." MLN 6 (1891): cols.
                178–84.</bib>
            <notes> Demonstrates the metrical regularization suffered by the three rondeaux cho- sen
                for inclusion in Tottel's Miscellany. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G51">
            <bib> "Stanzas Common to Middle and Modern English and Others Formed on the Analogy of
                These." Schipper (A11), Book II, Part 2. pp. 288–347.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G52">
            <bib> Stein, Arnold. "The Stanza of Lovers Infinitenesse." In his John Donne's Lyrics:
                The Eloquence of Action. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1962. pp.
                213–16.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G53">
            <bib> Stratton, Clarence. "The Italian Lyrics of Sidney's Arcadia." Sewanee Review 25
                (1917): 305–26.</bib>
            <notes> A very detailed examination of the Italian metrical forms--terza rima, ottava
                rima, sesta rima, sestina, madrigal, strambotto, canzone, and sonnet--and then the
                forms of the lyrics in the Arcadia's of Sannazaro (Italian, 1504), Montemayor
                (Portuguese, 1558), and Sidney. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G54">
            <bib> Thomas, C. T. "The Metrical Structure of Keats's Odes of 1819." Literary Studies:
                Homage to Dr. A. S. Aiyer. Ed. K. P. K. Menon et al. Trivandrum: St. Joseph's Press,
                1973. pp. 163–72.</bib>
            <notes> Follows Garrod in explicating the stanzaic form of the six Odes of 1819, be-
                ginning with the "Ode to Psyche"; their form seems to be a fusion of the Petrarchan
                sonnet and the Pindaric ode. Rejects N. S. Bushnell's conclusions G55 in MLN 44
                (1929): 287–96. See also G70. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G56">
            <bib> Tierney, Frank M. "The Causes of the Revival of the Rondeau in Nineteenth- Century
                England." Revue de l'Université d'Ottawa 43 (1973): 96–113.</bib>
            <notes> They are: the degeneration of blank verse written by minor poets imitating
                Tennyson and Browning, didacticism in poetry, a revived interest in medie- valism,
                and most importantly, the l'art pour l'art movement begun in France in the Thirties
                headed by Gautier. See Gosse (G17). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G57">
            <bib> -----. "The Development of the Rondeau in England from its Origin in the Middle
                Ages to its Revival in the Years Following 1860." Revue de l'Université d'Ottawa 41
                (1971): 25–46.</bib>
            <notes> Discusses the form as used by Chaucer, Hoccleve, Lydgate, Wyatt, Charles Cotton,
                and the authors of The Rolliad (1784). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G58">
            <bib> -----. "Sir Edmund Gosse and the Revival of French Fixed Forms in the Age of
                Transition." English Literature in Transition 14 (1971): 191–99.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G59">
            <bib> Turco, Lewis. The Book of Forms: A Handbook of Poetics. New York: E. P. Dutton, nd
                1968. Pp.; 2 ed. 198x. pp.</bib>
            <notes> A little handbook of metrical/stanzaic forms in English poetry, including many
                forms or analogues from French, Irish, Welsh, Spanish, Italian, Arabic, Greek, and
                Japanese, organized alphabetically, with abstract symbolizations of the form. Three
                introductory chapters on metrics, sound, and figures; bibliogra- phies of sources
                and examples; glossary. Many of the forms are however ex- tremely rare in English or
                else only assayed in the author’s own work. Not scholarly. Cf. Häublein (G19).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G60">
            <bib> Wain, John. "Terza Rima: A Foot Note on English Prosody." Rivista di letterature
                moderne n.s. 1 (1950): 44–48.</bib>
            <notes> Earlier English poets seem to have thought this form uncongenial, since it ap-
                pears but briefly in Chaucer, Wyatt, Surrey, and Sidney, but anything before 1800 is
                antediluvian. Diluvian: Shelley, Byron, Browning, Morris, Hardy, Hopkins, Dixon,
                Bridges, Empson, Auden, Eliot, Binyon, and the too- neglected E. H. W. Meyerstein.
                Cf. G4. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G61">
            <bib> Weiss, Wolfgang. Der Refrain in der elisabethanischen Lyrik. Diss., Munich,
                1964.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G62">
            <bib> White, J[oseph William] Gleeson. Ballades and Rondeaus, Chants Royal, Sestinas,
                Villanelles, &amp;, selected, with a chapter on the various forms. In the Canterbury
                Poets series. London: Walter Scott, 1887.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G63">
            <bib> White, William. "Housman's Five-Line Stanza." Notes &amp; Queries 198 (1953):
                217–18.</bib>
            <notes> Instances of the ababb stanza before Housman. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G64">
            <bib> Wilcox, Stewart C. "The Prosodic Structure of 'Ode to the West Wind.'" Notes &amp;
                Queries 195 (1950): 77–78.</bib>
            <notes> Elaborates on the synthesis of sonnet form and terza rima in the West-Wind
                stanza, and the parallel of the triple metrical form with the tripartite thematic
                divisions. Cf. Collins (G8) and Haworth (G103). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G65">
            <bib> Woolley, Arthur P. "Stanzaic Patterns in the Short Poems of Thomas Hardy." DAI 32
                (1972): 4584A (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> A fully rounded study of the prosodic structures which jointly give a stanza its
                shape, along with the effects Hardy could achieve in each of his several stan- zaic
                modes, couplets to octains and irregular forms. See also: C278–80, E964, J211, K45,
                K56, K70, K78, K84, K92–93, K165, K169, K182, K191, K206, K232, K245, K252–53, K257,
                K260, K338, K346, K353, K374, K378, K408, K413, K416–18, K428, K431, L21, L72, L97,
                L122, L139–40, L315, L574, L782, L786–87, L812, L835, L891, L1007, L1358, L1643,
                M305, M307. SPENSERIAN </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G66">
            <bib> Alpers, Paul J. The Poetry of "The Faerie Queene." Princeton: Princeton University
                Press, 1967.</bib>
            <notes> Chapter 2 is very good on Spenser's handling of his stanza-form; chapter 3
                treats his "poetic language." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G67">
            <bib> Botting, Roland B. "A New Spenserian Rhyme Scheme?" JEGP 36 (1937): 384– 86.</bib>
            <notes> Spenser employed in Colin Clouts Come Home Againe a rhyme-scheme in- tended to
                be continuous--one wherein the fourth rhyme in every group of four lines is
                reiterated as the second in the following four, i. e. ababcbcdedegfgfh, etc.--rather
                than divided into discrete elegiac quatrains. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G68">
            <bib> Bradner, Leicester. "Forerunners of the Spenserian Stanza." Review of English
                Studies 4 (1928): 207–8.</bib>
            <notes> On the three crucial characteristics of the form: the nine-line stanza Spenser
                might have noticed in two poems in Tottel, and the medial bb couplet he must have
                learned from Chaucerian rhyme royal (it appears in the June and No- vember
                eclogues); the sixth-line c-rhyme, however, which links the final cou- plet to the
                body of the stanza, he must have found in the Italian madrigal. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G69">
            <bib> Brooke, Tucker, "Stanza-Connections in the Fairy Queen." MLN 37 (1922):
                223–27.</bib>
            <notes> Spenser used four devices to effect some continuity across stanza-breaks: repe-
                tition of a rhyme, a key word, or a whole line, or beginning a stanza with a
                relative pronoun. See Stein (G84), Owen (G76), and Schoeck (G81). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G70">
            <bib> Bushnell, Nelson S. "The Style of the Spenserian Stanzas, Sonnets, and Odes of
                Keats." Diss., Harvard University, 1928. Cf. G54.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G71">
            <bib> Corse, Larry B. "'A Straunge Kind of Harmony': The Influence of Lyric Poetry and
                Music on Prosodic Techniques in the Spenserian Stanza." DAI 33 (1973): 4404A (North
                Texas State).</bib>
            <notes> Spenser devised an aural structure equally as distinctive and important as, yet
                in counterpoint and tension to, the visual structure of his stanza: against the so-
                lidity and uniformity of the structure of line-lengths, he set in opposition ir-
                regularities of stressing, caesura placement, and enjambment to create variety.
                Another device: the repetition of short metrical "motifs" to link stanzas; this
                device Spenser learned from music, since the strophic poem set to music re- quires
                metrical repetition to correspond to the repeated phrasings in the mel- ody. Seems
                to be a study of metrical variation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G72">
            <bib> Davies, Phillips G. "A Check List of Poems, 1595 to 1833, Entirely or Partly
                Written in the Spenserian Stanza." Bulletin of the New York Public Library 77
                (1974): 314–28.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G73">
            <bib> Mahony, Patrick J. "An Analysis of Shelley's Craftsmanship in Adonais." Studies in
                English Literature 1500–1900 4 (1964): 555–68.</bib>
            <notes> Detailed technical analysis of Shelley's handling of the Spenserian stanza in
                matters of tempo and pacing, rhyme, feminine endings, caesura, trisyllabic feet with
                elision, spondees, pyrrhics, alliteration, and assonance. Stanzas 1, 4, and 21 are
                anatomized. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G74">
            <bib> Morton, Edward P. "The Spenserian Before 1700." MP 4 (1907): 639–54.</bib>
            <notes> A valuable examination of the predecessors and successors of Spenser's metrical
                hallmark. Of the former the most important and least understood is the Mirrour for
                Magistrates. Of the latter, only eighteen examples by five authors may be found in
                the seventeenth century. But aside from the full form of the stanza, its principal
                characteristics are the linking of quatrains and a final Alexandrine: the linking
                has not been much followed, but the final long-line "is the most cer- tain mark of
                Spenserian influence, even where that influence is at second or even third hand."
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G75">
            <bib> -----. "The Spenserian Stanza in the Eighteenth Century." MP 10 (1913):
                365–91.</bib>
            <notes> Continuing his historical researches, Morton finds fifty-six instances by
                thirty- eight known and eight anonymous authors in the eighteenth century, includ-
                ing a few early attempts by Pope. But the immediate public response to Thomson's
                "Castle of Indolence" shows that Spenser's influence was unexpect- edly strong in
                the Age of Reason. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G76">
            <bib> Owen, W. J. B. "Orlando Furioso and Stanza-Connection in The Faerie Queene." MLN
                67 (1952): 5–8.</bib>
            <notes> Tucker Brooke (G69) was wrong to think Virgil the source for Spenser's de- vice
                of linking stanzas by verbal repetition; Ariosto is the more obvious source. See
                also Schoeck (G81) and Stein (G84). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G77">
            <bib> Pope, Emma F. "The Critical Background of the Spenserian Stanza." MP 24 (1926):
                31–53.</bib>
            <notes> Drawing on a very extensive knowledge of early Italian poetics, Pope argues that
                Spenser derived his stanza form from the terza rima in Dante, a stately epic meter,
                regularizing syllable-count and line-length, and adapting the final Alex- andrine
                from the sdrucciolo; "for stanzaic form his direct model was the nine- line madrigal
                recognized by all critics as a stanzaic form of terza rima." Addi- tionally, Section
                1 of the essay surveys the course of quantitative measures in Italy, France, and
                England up to 1600. Repetitive but very highly informed. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G78">
            <bib> Prausuhn, Klaus-Ulrich. Zur Erfüllung der Spenserstanze bei Edmund Spenser, Lord
                Byron und John Keats. Diss., Göttingen, 1974.</bib>
            <notes> Historical development. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G79">
            <bib> Reeve, Frederic E. "The Stanza of The Faerie Queene." DA 12 (1952): 307A
                (Princeton).</bib>
            <notes> Applies Elder Olson's theory of prosody (B158) to the analysis of the Spense-
                rian stanza, isolating rhythmic, metric, and harmonic. Matter and diction also ex-
                amined. In terms of metrical structure the stanza generally sets four lines against
                five or vice versa. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G80">
            <bib> Reschke, Hedwig. Die Spenserstanza bei den Spensernachahmern des neunzehnten
                Jahrhunderts. Anglistische Forschungen, vol. 54. Heidelberg: Carl Winter, 1918. 198
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> His dissertation at Heidelberg in 1918. Rev: in Literaturblatt 44 (1923): 103–4;
                in Englische Studien 53 (1919–20): 430– 32. This is still the most extensive study
                of the later use of the form. Organized by author, with chapters on Wordsworth,
                Coleridge, Shelley, Byron, Keats, Hunt, and Tennyson, and shorter chapters on many
                other lesser figures. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G81">
            <bib> Schoeck, R. J. "Alliteration as a Means of Stanza Connection in The Faerie
                Queene." MLN 64 (1949): 90–93.</bib>
            <notes> Addenda to Stein (G84) and Brooke (G69). Schoeck distinguishes regular or
                primary alliteration from subordinate or secondary (more subtly and closely em-
                bedded). See also Owen (G76). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G82">
            <bib> Skeat, W. W. "The Origin of the Spenserian Stanza." The Athenaeum, 6 May 1893, p.
                574.</bib>
            <notes> Spenser formed his stanza from the ottava rima stanza he found in Chaucer and
                the Alexandrines he saw in Tottel's Miscellany. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G83">
            <bib> Steadman, John M. "Stanzaic Patterns in the English Wagner Book." Notes &amp;
                Queries 202 (1957): 376–77.</bib>
            <notes> Some odd seven-line stanzas (six pentameters plus a hexameter) in this early
                (1594) version of Faust seem to be a conflation of the Spenserian stanza and rhyme
                royal, the final Alexandrine of the former being appended to the latter, the older
                form. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G84">
            <bib> Stein, Arnold. "Stanza Continuity in The Faerie Queene." MLN 59 (1944):
                114–18.</bib>
            <notes> Addenda to Brooke (G69). Continuity is preserved also by repetition of key
                sounds or sound-patterns, by rhyme-sounds repeated outside of the rhyme po- sition,
                and by preservation of rhythmic flow. See Schoeck (G81) and Owen (G76). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G85">
            <bib> Taboreux, Etienne. "The Spenserian Stanza." Revue de l'enseignement des langues
                vivantes 15 (1899): 499–505; 16 (1899): 14–21, 112–18, 163–72.</bib>
            <notes> The source of the form is not the Chaucerian ottava rima but the stanza of The
                Monk's Tale and the A.B.C. Surveys rhyme, (syntactic) pause, (metrical) cae- sura,
                enjambment, metrical variety, metrical and sonal mimesis ("word- painting"), melody
                (assonance, consonance, alliteration), and the use of the Al- exandrine. Concluding
                list of poets who have used the form. See also: B40, C264, C296, C299, K250. SONNET
                The fourteen lines of the sonnet constitute that narrow cell where English poets
                have fretted most, and most accurately gauged their skill and invention in
                comparison with their predecessors, the great poets of the past--in the tightest
                forms, the set pieces, the obligatory routines. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G86">
            <bib> Blank, Philip E., Jr. Lyric Forms in the Sonnet Sequences of Barnabe Barnes. The
                Hague: Mouton, 1974. 162 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation at North Carolina in 1966. After Spenser and Sidney,
                Barnes was the most prolific and versatile innovator of stanzaic forms in the
                Renaissance. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G87">
            <bib> Bray, Sir Denys. "The Art-Form of the Elizabethan Sonnet Sequence and
                Shakespeare's Sonnets." Shakespeare Jahrbuch 63 (1927): 159–82.</bib>
            <notes> Then see his </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G88">
            <bib> Bray, Sir Denys. Shakespeare's Sonnet Sequence (London, 1938).</bib>
            <notes> In support of his argument that the sequence not the individual sonnet was the
                aesthetic whole for the Elizabethans, Sir Denys demonstrates varieties of link- age
                between sonnets, i.e. the whole line, the half line, rhyme words, rhyme sounds,
                composite rhyming (both whole words and sounds), and more com- plex patterns of
                rhymes and other key words elsewhere in the lines, both in consecutive and separated
                sonnets. Detailed analysis of rhyme-linkages in Shakespeare's sonnets allows
                reconstruction of their chronology. Bray's results are disputed by Bullitt (G91).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G89">
            <bib> Brewer, Wilmon. Sonnets and Sestinas. Boston: Cornhill, 1937. 245 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Original poems in both forms followed by a history of each. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G90">
            <bib> Brownlow, E. G. "Wyatt's Sonnets and Their Sources." Poet-Lore 3 (1891): 44–45,
                127–34.</bib>
            <notes> Addenda and corrigenda, pp. 97–98, 595. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G91">
            <bib> Bullitt, John M. "The Use of Rhyme Link in the Sonnets of Sidney, Drayton, and
                Spenser." JEGP 49 (1950): 14–32.</bib>
            <notes> Sir Denys Bray's (G88) somewhat excessive claim for rhyme-linking as an im-
                portant and common device in Renaissance sonnets is repudiated in this analysis:
                Sidney and Drayton show no particular enthusiasm for the device, though Spenser
                employs it at times. Without a doubt some of the sonnets of these poets were
                intended to be linked, but on the other hand the paucity of rhymes in English
                entails the unfortunate fact that many seeming links will ap- pear which may or may
                not have been intended, even beyond those that ap- pear in sonnets that are
                unquestionably not meant to be linked. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G92">
            <bib> Bullock, Walter L. "The Genesis of the English Sonnet Form." PMLA 38 (1923):
                729–44.</bib>
            <notes> Rebuts the argument of Lathrop (G113) and insists on the simpler, traditional,
                consensus view that Wyatt learned the forms of both octave and sestet from an
                anthology he read while on a trip to Italy in 1527. Surrey, then, "relaxed and
                simplified" the forms he learned from Wyatt. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G93">
            <bib> Cermak, Mary M. "Terminal Structures in the Sonnets of Wyatt and Surrey." DA 30
                (1969): 2522A (Catholic University of America).</bib>
            <notes> A study in Poetic Closure; also a study in The Sense of an Ending. Most of
                Wyatt's and Surrey's sonnets end with a couplet, but (surprisingly) this terminal
                structure does not correlate with 12–2 division of the sonnet as a whole, quat-
                rains, serial progression, and syntactic isolability of the couplet. The conclud-
                ing couplet is usually attached syntactically only to the closest preceding lines,
                and the rhyme form is clearly 8–6, so that in both poets the sonnets show both
                Italian and English characteristics. Their sonnets have, on the most general level,
                beginnings, middles, and ends, though the form is not indelibly Shake- spearean.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G94">
            <bib> Chandler, Patricia A. "Gerard Manley Hopkins and Dylan Thomas: A Study in
                Computational Stylistics." DAI 31 (1971): 4747A (L.S.U.).</bib>
            <notes> Computerized comparison of thirty variables in ten sonnets by each. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G95">
            <bib> Clinard, Turner N. "A Critical History of the Pre-Elizabethan English Sonnet."
                Diss., Vanderbilt University, 1956.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G96">
            <bib> Cook, Wister J. "The Sonnets of Christina Rossetti: A Comparative Prosodic
                Analysis." DAI 32 (1972): 6419A (Auburn).</bib>
            <notes> Examines metrical variation and pause-placement in her sonnets as compared with
                those of Dante Gabriel Rossetti, Swinburne, and Meredith. Rossetti was not
                especially adroit at meter: her lines tend to oscillate between the extremes of
                regularity and irregularity, and she rarely uses enjambment. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G97">
            <bib> Cooper, Sherod M., Jr. The Sonnets of "Astrophel and Stella": A Stylistic Study.
                The Hague: Mouton, 1966.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation, "A Stylistic Study of the Sonnets of Astrophel and
                Stella." DA 24 (1964): 1612A (Pennsylvania). Chapter 3 treats versification, chapter
                4 rhyming, chapter 5 lexis. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G98">
            <bib> Cygan, Jan. "English Sonnet Structure." Germanica Wratislaviensia 14 (1971): 103–
                18.</bib>
            <notes> A pedestrian literary history of the "external form" of the sonnet in England
                from its twelfth-century Provençal origins to the present, but particularly in the
                Renaissance. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G99">
            <bib> Ellis, Patrick. "Wordsworth's 'Ode: Intimations of Immortality' and the Italian
                Sonnet." CEA Critic 34, 3 (1972): 26–29.</bib>
            <notes> The rhyme-scheme of the "Ode" shows discernible lineaments of the Italian
                sonnet, the close proximity of which in ancestry is not immediately evident because
                of line-lengths in typography. But in the aural mode the kinship is more evident.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G100">
            <bib> Flower, Timothy F. "3. Making It New: Problems of Meaningful Form in the Sonnets
                of Sidney and Keats" (Three-part dissertation). DAI 32 (1972): 6927A
                (Rutgers).</bib>
            <notes> Astrophel's unease with the Petrarchan conventions is reflected in the Sidneyan
                prosodic strategy of using a two-tercet sestet against the quatrained octave.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G101">
            <bib> Gibson, William M. "Sonnets in T. S. Eliot's The Waste Land." American Literature
                32 (1961): 465–66.</bib>
            <notes> A double Shakespearean sonnet is embedded in ll. 236–62 of "The Fire Ser- mon."
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G102">
            <bib> Hanscom, Elizabeth D. "The Sonnet Forms of Wyatt and Surrey." MLN 16 (1901): cols.
                274–80.</bib>
            <notes> Detailed comparison and contrast of meters and rhymes. The single most sig-
                nificant difference between the Petrarchan sonnet and its English imitations is the
                adoption in the latter of a couplet to close the sestet. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G103">
            <bib> Haworth, Helen E. "'Ode to the West Wind' and the Sonnet Form." Keats-Shelley
                Journal 20 (1971): 71–77.</bib>
            <notes> More successful than any of Shelley's seventeen experiments in the sonnet form
                is the fusion of terza rima and the sonnet in each of this poem's sections: "the
                sonnet restrains the speed of the terza rima, terza rima, in turn, loosens the
                sometimes ponderous sonnet, giving it flexibility and speed." Cf. Collins (G8) and
                Wilcox (G64). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G104">
            <bib> Jacobs, Elijah L. "The Sonnet on the Sonnet." South Atlantic Quarterly 42 (1943):
                282–88.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G105">
            <bib> Jakobson, Roman, and Lawrence G. Jones. Shakespeare's Verbal Art in "Th'Expense of
                Spirit." The Hague: Mouton, 1970.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: by I. A. Richards in TLS, 28 May 1970, pp. 589–90, an essay G106
                subsequently revised and expanded into "Linguistics and Poetics" in his Poetries:
                Their Media and Ends. Ed. Trevor Eaton. The Hague: Mouton, 1974. pp. 39–49. A
                seemingly exhaustive structural analysis of the linguistic features of the son- net,
                apparently intended as a model of the method. See also: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G107">
            <bib> Fowler, Roger. "Language and the Reader: Shakespeare's Sonnet 73." In Style and
                Structure in Literature: Essays in the New Stylistics. Ed. Roger Fowler. Oxford:
                Basil Blackwell, 1975. pp. 79–122.</bib>
            <notes> And: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G108">
            <bib> Vendler, Helen. "Jakobson, Richards, and Shakespeare's Sonnet CXXIX." In I. A.
                Richards: Essays in His Honor. Ed. Reuben Brower et al. New York: Oxford University
                Press, 1973. pp. 179–98.</bib>
            <notes> also see C162. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G109">
            <bib> Johnson, Lee M. "Milton's Blank Verse Sonnets." Milton Studies 5 (1973):
                129–53.</bib>
            <notes> Johnson suggests the existence of sonnet-like units in Milton's three epics,
                dis- tinguished not by rhyme but by approximate syntax and by the fact that these
                "sonnets" regularly appear "at points of resolution in the destinies of the char-
                acters who speak them." He identifies about two dozen in PL, nearly a dozen in PR,
                and a half-dozen in SA, but nowhere are these catalogued in this essay, so the
                reader will have to pick his way through for examples, which is irritat- ing. Cf.
                Arnold Stein (G134). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G110">
            <bib> Kallsen, T. J. "W. H. Auden's Supersonnet." Genre 4 (1971): 329–34.</bib>
            <notes> Surveys the various alterations of sonnet form which English poets have ex-
                perimented with, then focuses on one such by Auden: a 21-line expanded sonnet, in
                three stanzas of 6, 6, and 9 lines, rhyming aabcbc, ddefef, and ghijghjhi. Example:
                "The Crossroads." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G111">
            <bib> Kelley, Tracy R. "Studies in the Development of the Prosody of the Elizabethan
                Sonnet." Diss., University of California, 1937.</bib>
            <notes> Basing his discussion on six very large statistical tables, Kelley draws conclu-
                sions on the evolution of technique in the sonnet from Wyatt to Donne, but with
                chief interest in the sonneteers of the 1580s and '90s. He examines (1) non-metrical
                pause placement, both intralinear and end-of-line; (2) stress variations on the
                iamb; and (3) consonant alliteration and vowel harmony (see also Appendix A). The
                author uses Mayor's (E592) 0-1-2 scansion system, yet Saintsbury is the authority
                most cited and approved. Conclusion: the sonnet- eers purposefully aimed for
                variation both in meter and internal caesura place- ment, while line-end pauses
                decreased in number yet were more effectively employed. The data here is reliable
                and worth consultation, though it is not conveniently accessible. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G112">
            <bib> Kocher, Paul H. "A Marlowe Sonnet." PQ 24 (1945): 39–45.</bib>
            <notes> Embedded in the blank verse of Act V of Tamburlaine. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G113">
            <bib> Lathrop, H. B. "The Sonnet Forms of Wyatt and Surrey." MP 2 (1904–5):
                463–70.</bib>
            <notes> A modification of the traditional view. Wyatt's sestets divide evenly into ter-
                cets as often as not; his sources were the French poet Saint Gelais and the Ital-
                ian sonneteers. Surrey's sonnet, however, is a new fourteen-line form derived from
                the strambotto not an imitation of Wyatt. See G92. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G114">
            <bib> Lentzner, Karl. Über das Sonett und seine Gestaltung in der englischen Dichtung
                bis Milton. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1886. 81 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Mainly literary history, though of course on this subject nothing much can be
                said without frequent reference to form. Indexes of sonneteers, first lines,
                Milton's sonnets in chronological order, and Milton's rhyme-schemes. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G115">
            <bib> Lever, J. W. The Elizabethan Love Sonnet. London: Methuen, 1956</bib>
            <notes>; 2nd ed. 1965; rpt 1978. Thompson (E91) gives a more direct and successful
                account of the metrical development of the early sonneteers, but it is hard--very
                hard--to draw away from Lever's refulgent book. The first chapter, on Wyatt, is
                devoted largely to versification; thereafter, mainly pp. 86–87, 134–35, and 145.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G116">
            <bib> Levý, Jirí. "The Development of Rhyme-Scheme and of Syntactic Pattern in the
                English Renaissance Sonnet." Acta Universitatis Palackianae Olomucensis, Philologica
                4 (1961): 167–85</bib>
            <notes>; rpt in his Paralipomena. Brünn: J. E. Purkyne University Philosophical Faculty,
                1971. pp. 22–42. Mere analysis of rhyme-patterns and positioning of the volta is far
                less revealing than analysis (such as this) of the deployment of syntactic and
                semantic material within the frames of rhyme and stanza. Levý examines the "internal
                morphol- ogy" of the sonnets of the eleven major Renaissance sonneteers, then com-
                pares their practices with those of three later English poets and six Continental
                ones. No radically new conclusions emerge, but a number of significant ones do, and
                in general the article synthesizes, concisely and accessibly, a wealth of
                information--far more than most English critics put into whole books. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G117">
            <bib> -----. "On the Relations of Language and Stanza Pattern in the English Sonnet."
                Worte und Werte. Ed. Gustav Erdmann and Alfons Eichstaedt. Berlin: De Gruyter, 1961.
                pp. 214–31</bib>
            <notes>; rpt in Paralipomena. Brünn: J. E. Purkyne University, 1971. pp. 43–61. A fine
                technical analysis of this case-in-point of "the transformation of a [po- etic] form
                when taken over by a foreign nation." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G118">
            <bib> Mollenkott, Virginia R. "Experimental Freedom in Herbert's Sonnets." Christian
                Scholar's Review 1 (1971): 109–16.</bib>
            <notes> Argues the "original, varied technical inventiveness" of Herbert's seventeen
                sonnets. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G119">
            <bib> Mumford, Ivy L. "Italian Aspects of Surrey's Lyrics." English Miscellany 16
                (1905): 19–36.</bib>
            <notes> A very close examination of Surrey at the hands of his successive editors dis-
                closes some modifications of traditional views on the respective importance of his
                blank verse and his sonnets: Surrey shows "rather less direct acquaintance with
                Italy than might have been expected" when his sonnets are set against Wyatt's and
                Petrarch's. Against about 600 lines of sonnets Surrey wrote over 2000 lines of
                heroic verse, and though his Aeneid was not reprinted, the intro- duction of blank
                verse is his most notable achievement. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G120">
            <bib> Nardo, A. K. "The Submerged Sonnet as Lyric Moment in Miltonic Epic." Genre 9
                (1976): 21–35.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G121">
            <bib> Nowottny, Winifred. "Some Features of Form and Style in Sonnets 97–126." New
                Essays on Shakespeare's Sonnets. Ed. Hilton Landry. New York: AMS Press, 1976. pp.
                65–107.</bib>
            <notes> Metrical virtuosity is discussed on pp. 82–88, 92–93, and 98–100. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G122">
            <bib> Oliphant, E. H. C. "The Sonnet Form: A Determination of the Rules." Poetry Review
                21 (1930): 337–51.</bib>
            <notes> Subsumed in and therefore superseded by the following study. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G123">
            <bib> -----. "Sonnet Structure: An Analysis." PQ 11 (1932): 135–48.</bib>
            <notes> Guaranteed to boggle the minds of all readers except statisticians. Working his
                way through a considerable number of the literally thousands of possible per-
                mutations of sonnet form, Oliphant stipulates ten minimal-compliance rules for a
                poem to be deemed a sonnet, and fifteen rules for it to achieve "perfec- tion" in
                that form. The permutation-analysis produces "21 forms in 46 varie- ties of unlinked
                and 170 varieties of linked" structure which meet the stipula- tions, as opposed to
                the mere eight forms now commonly in use. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G124">
            <bib> Ordeman, D. Thomas. "How Many Rhyme Schemes Has the Sonnet?" College English 1
                (1939): 171–73.</bib>
            <notes> Mathematically, 51,300 "without destroying the sonnet as a recognizable form."
                With up to 7 rhymes in alphabetical order, the English form will yield 55 types, the
                Italian 32. If the alphabetical order is discarded, the Italian sestet alone may
                yield 25 two-rhyme types and 90 three-rhyme types. How could anyone think this a
                "scanty plot of ground"? </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G125">
            <bib> Parker, William R. "The Sonnets in Tottel's Miscellany." PMLA 54 (1939): 669–
                77.</bib>
            <notes> In Tottel 54 of the 310 poems are sonnets, and these show 14 different rhyme-
                schemes, an index of the milieu of experimentation in the early development of the
                form. Parker argues that sonnets 218, 219, and 241 in the Rollins edition are by
                Wyatt. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G126">
            <bib> Pitchford, Lois W. "The Curtal Sonnets of Gerard Manley Hopkins." MLN 67 (1952):
                165–69.</bib>
            <notes> Hopkins' three "bob-tailed" sonnets ("Pied Beauty," "Peace," and "Ash Boughs")
                have a structure derived from a careful and calculated reduction of the standard
                sonnet form by 1/4, the 14 lines thus cut to 10.5, on the basis of the poet's belief
                that the English form had too expansive a structure for the compression of its
                thought. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G127">
            <bib> Potter, James L. "The Development of Sonnet-Patterns in the Sixteenth Century."
                Diss., Harvard University, 1954.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G128">
            <bib> Reader, Willie D. "Dramatic Structure and Prosodic Form in Milton's Sonnet "On His
                Deceased Wife.'" Language Quarterly 11 (1972): 21–25, 28.</bib>
            <notes> Very close explication of sound-patterning (the vowels of the octave and sestet
                rhymes seem particularly important in controlling the total sonal texture) and meter
                (variations and inversions, syllabic length) reveals the internal dynamics of the
                quickening emotional crescendo in lines 1–13 of Milton's sonnet. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G129">
            <bib> Rich, Morton D. "The Dynamics of Tonal Shift in the Sonnet." DAI 36 (1975): 2179A
                (New York University).</bib>
            <notes> Devises "an objective means of locating, describing, and finding" the volta of a
                sonnet by comparing performances of the sonnet with syntactic and supraseg- mental
                analysis. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G130">
            <bib> Rood, Karen L. "Robert Frost's 'Sentence Sounds': Wildness Opposing the Sonnet
                Form." Frost: Centennial Essays II. Ed. Jac L. Thorpe. Jackson: University of
                Mississippi Press, 1976. pp. 196–210.</bib>
            <notes> Explores "the shifting equilibrium between the freedom of spoken language and
                the restrictions of poetic form," particularly in rhyme-scheme, where Frost used
                more than the conventional number of rhymes for thematic effect. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G131">
            <bib> Ross, Ian. "Sonneteering in Sixteenth-Century Scotland." Texas Studies in
                Literature and Language 6 (1964): 255–68.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G132">
            <bib> Schirmer, Walter F. "Das Sonett in der englischen Literatur." Anglia 49 (1925): 1–
                31.</bib>
            <notes> General discussion of the form, Wyatt through the Rossettis. Useful notes.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G133">
            <bib> Stageberg, Norman C. "The Aesthetics of the Petrarchan Sonnet." JAAC 7 (1948):
                132–37.</bib>
            <notes> The longevity of the sonnet's form is explained by the fact that it (1) controls
                and (2) enriches the experience being presented. The control resides in order; the
                form evokes a unified response, based on numerous sub-levels of organiza- tion. Each
                level groups fewer than six of its units, which is in fact the maximum number of
                units perceptible in the human attention span. The Gestalt criteria of nearness,
                likeness, sequence, and closure are also met in the rhyme scheme. The enrichment
                resides in the pleasure of perceiving "equipollence," the series of "internal
                balances" the sonnet maintains both within and among its levels of organization.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G134">
            <bib> Stein, Arnold. "Sonnet Structure in Chapman's Blank Verse." MLN 59 (1944):
                397–403.</bib>
            <notes> Subliminal influence of sonnet-structure as an embedded form in Elizabethan
                dramatic blank verse. Cf. L. M. Johnson (G109). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G135">
            <bib> Stoehr, Taylor. "Syntax and Poetic Form in Milton's Sonnets." English Studies 45
                (1964): 298–301.</bib>
            <notes> Very close analysis of the "tension between energy and control" in five son-
                nets, demonstrating how Milton hammered out a unity of syntactic form, me- ter, and
                stanza form (by yoking the quatrain and sestet through enjambment) within which his
                powerfully emotional subjects could be brought under order. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G136">
            <bib> Stout, Janis P. "Convention and Variation in Frost's Sonnets." Concerning Poetry
                11 (1978): 27–36.</bib>
            <notes> Frost wrote twenty-eight sonnets, of which it can be said that "the sonnets in
                which Frost least varies the conventions tend to be his weakest." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G137">
            <bib> Strzetelski, Jerzy. The English Sonnet: Syntax and Style. Cracow: Jagiell
                University, 1970. 146 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Analysis of 278 sonnets by 55 authors over 400 years using the method mapped out
                by Reszkiewicz for The Book of Margery Kempe (a graphic notation of the dimensions
                of momentum and modification in the sentence, analogous to Jakobson's axes of
                selection and combination). The resultant summary graphs and tables provide an
                enormous amount of compressed information still to be mined. Tentative conclusion:
                the centripetal force of tradition on authors construing the syntax of sonnets has
                held much greater sway than the centrifu- gal force of the individual talent.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G138">
            <bib> Svendsen, Kester. "Milton's Sonnet on the Massacre in Piedmont." Shakespeare
                Association Bulletin 20 (1945): 147–55.</bib>
            <notes> Technical analysis of sound and meter in section 2. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G139">
            <bib> Sweeney, Kevin M. "The Structural Importance of the First Quatrain in the Sequence
                of Sonnets of Michael Drayton: A Study of the 4–10 Sonnet." DAI 38 (1977): 2147A
                (Catholic University of America).</bib>
            <notes> The study of sonnet structure is one study of the ways in which meaning can be
                structured. The 4–10 pattern is very unusual--though about a third of Drayton's 106
                sonnets are either clearly or ambiguously of this pattern--and it appears in two
                types: either the dizaine will develop the meaning embryonic in the quatrain, or it
                will provide contrast, taking the quatrain material simply as "a point of
                departure." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G140">
            <bib> Tomlinson, Charles. The Sonnet, Its Origin, Structure, and Place in Poetry.
                London: John Murray, 1974. 227 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Worth consulting: wide European scope. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G141">
            <bib> Turpin, Elizabeth R. "Rhetoric and Rhythm in Twentieth-Century Sonnets by Hopkins,
                Auden, Frost, Cummings, Thomas, and Merrill Moore." DAI 33 (1973): 4368A (Texas
                A&amp;M).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G142">
            <bib> Vabalens, D. Y. [Poetical Prosody and Poetical Translation: Shakespeare's Sonnets
                Analysed.] Vilnius, 1976. 22 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Abstract of a thesis at Vilnius University on statistical analysis of metrical
                pat- terns of the sonnets in translation. In Russian. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G143">
            <bib> Vanderbok, Judith A. "Growth Patterns in E. E. Cumming's Sonnets: A Quantitative
                Approach." Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing Bulletin 6 (1978):
                42–52</bib>
            <notes>. Based on her dissertation, </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G144">
            <bib> Vanderbok, Judith A. "E. E. Cummings and His Sonnets: A Quantitative Approach," in
                1976.</bib>
            <notes> Statistical changes in seventy-six variables are tabulated for four phases of
                Cummings' career; 99% of these elements were present in his work from the very
                beginning. If indeed Cummings did "grow" artistically it was only very modestly.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G145">
            <bib> Weeks, L. T. "The Order of Rimes of the English Sonnet." MLN 25 (1910): 176– 80.
                Addendum by H. M. Belden on p. 231.</bib>
            <notes> On p. 179 the author presents a large table showing quatrain rhyme-schemes
                listed down one axis and sestet rhymes along the other, with frequency of oc-
                currence tabulated for each variety in the sonnets of "the entire body of Eng- lish
                sonnet writers." If this last claim be true, the table should be of consider- able
                utility. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G146">
            <bib> Wendel, Karl-Heinz. Sonettstrukturen in Shakespeares Dramen. Bad Hamburg: H.
                Gehlen, 1968. 192 pp.</bib>
            <notes> An extensive exercise in triviality: "sonnet" is differentiated from "sonnet-
                structure" only on the basis of manifestation: sonnets appear separately, while
                sonnet-structures are embedded in longer runs of verse, as in the drama. There their
                purpose is dramatically, or contextually, motivated. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G147">
            <bib> Whigam, R. G., and O. F. Emerson. "Sonnet Structure in Sidney's Astrophel and
                Stella." SP 18 (1921): 347–52.</bib>
            <notes> Catalogues rhyme-schemes. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G148">
            <bib> Withim, Philip M. "A Prosodic Analysis of Milton's Seventh Sonnet." Bucknell
                Review 6, no. 4 (1957): 29–34.</bib>
            <notes> A justification of the metrical irregularities as semantically expressive, and
                an interesting observation on the grouping of sounds in the octave versus the ses-
                tet. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="G149">
            <bib> Zillman, Lawrence J. John Keats and the Sonnet Tradition: A Critical and
                Comparative Study. Los Angeles: Lymanhouse, 1939. Based on his dissertation work at
                the University of Washington in 1936, "The Sonnets of John Keats: A Critical and
                Comparative Study in Versecraft.</bib>
            <notes> A tripartite work: the first section discusses the sonnet tradition in general,
                while the second (about 75 pages) focuses on a close analysis of Keats's han- dling
                of the sonnet, and the third (Appendix) prints the texts of the 67 sonnets Keats
                wrote. There are also incidental observations on the sonnet techniques of Hunt,
                Bowles, Wordsworth, Milton, Shakespeare, and Spenser in Appendix II. Keats at
                sonnets was relatively conservative, following the views of the age- -and especially
                Hunt--pretty closely. It is not generally known that he only turned to the
                Shakespearean form after writing nearly 40 of his 67 or so son- nets in the Italian
                form. Zillman's study of Keats's prosody is narrower in focus and less stylish but
                more detailed than Bate's (B7), often providing tables of information on sound
                patterning, alliteration and assonance, rhyming, metrical variation, end-stopping,
                pauses, and phrasing. See also: B20, B40, C68, C78, C152, C374, C377, E464, E1146,
                E1242, E1260, E1281–82, H33, I27, L10, L12, L73–74, L109, L126, L304, L459, L646,
                L766, L997, L1168, L1190, L1635. </notes>
        </item>
    </chapter>
</bibliography>
