<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="VISUAL (TYPOGRAPHIC) STRUCTURES">
        <item id="H1">
            <bib> Babcock, Sister Mary D. "Cummings' Typography: An Ideogrammic Style." Renascence
                15 (1963): 115–23.</bib>
            <notes> Draws an extended analogy to the Chinese written character as a profitable
                approach to Cummings' poetic structure. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H2">
            <bib> Babula, William. "The Shaped Sound of Faith: George Herbert's 'Easter Wings.'"
                Oral English 2 (1976): 13–14.</bib>
            <notes> Six paragraphs explain how the (heard) metrical pattern and the "visual emblem"
                of this poem interact thematically to "twice indicate fall and rise." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H3">
            <bib> Beloof, Robert L. "E. E. Cummings: The Prosodic Shape of His Poems." DA 14 (1954):
                2342A (Northwestern).</bib>
            <notes> With his customary cogency Beloof identifies seven prosodic modes in Cummings'
                work: stress verse, free verse, pictograms, syllabic verse, oral verse in visual
                form, dramatic free verse, and foot verse. The typographical poetry is found to be
                both oral and visual. Three periods in Cummings' prosodic development are
                postulated. The useful Appendix III classifies the poetry by prosodic type. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H4">
            <bib> Brown, C. C., and W. P. Ingoldsby. "George Herbert's 'Easter Wings.'" Huntington
                Library Quarterly 35 (1972): 130–42.</bib>
            <notes> Since "the general shape of his stanzas is Greek, the precise dimensions
                Hebrew," Herbert set for himself in the construction of the poem the problem of
                synthesizing his Hellenic and Hebraic sources and their traditions. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H5">
            <bib> Burton, D. "The Exploitation of the Word in Concrete Poetry." Thesis, University
                of Birmingham, 1974.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H6">
            <bib> Butler, Michael. "Concrete Poetry and the Crisis of Language." New German Studies
                1 (1973): 99–115.</bib>
            <notes> H7 </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H8">
            <bib> Church, Margaret. "The First English Pattern Poems." PMLA 61 (1946): 636–50.</bib>
            <notes> Based on her dissertation, "The Pattern Poem," at Radcliffe in 1945. The
                rediscovery of the Greek Anthology at the end of the Middle Ages resulted in, among
                other things, a considerable number of imitations of pattern poems- -in England, in
                the sixteenth century, by Stephen Hawes, Richard Wills, and Puttenham, and on the
                continent, by Scalinger, Jean Crispin, and Joannes Pierius Valerianus. N.B.:
                Puttenham's mistaken attribution of the egg form to Anacreon proves he had not seen
                an authentic text. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H9">
            <bib> Conrad, Philip. "Visual Poetry." Poetry 32 (1928): 112–14.</bib>
            <notes> Lucid argumentation that the chief merit of poetry as seen lies in the near-
                instantaneous impression we gain, as opposed to the strictly sequential ordering of
                meaning in sounds. See H31. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H10">
            <bib> Crowley, John W. "Visual-Aural Poetry: The Typography of E. E. Cummings."
                Concerning Poetry 5, 2 (1972): 51–54.</bib>
            <notes> Argues that even in Cummings' most heavily typographical poems the oral- aural
                dimension is not dispensed with. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H11">
            <bib> Doyle, Mike. "Notes on Concrete Poetry." Canadian Literature, no. 46 (1970), pp.
                91–95.</bib>
            <notes> A freeform discussion of trends as an ostensible review of Oberon Press's
                collection of concretism, The Cosmic Chef. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H12">
            <bib> Draper, R. P. "Concrete Poetry." New Literary History 2 (1971): 329–40.</bib>
            <notes> Having its roots in Elizabethan rhetorical patterning and Herbert's "Easter
                Wings," concrete poetry is still a young and playfully inventive art; it will have
                to become "visual not merely graphic," absorbing the dimension of space into a set
                of rational and functional principles of meaning, as traditional poetry has done.
                Three such principles are vertical-horizontal, axial, and circular. Many examples.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H13">
            <bib> Dust, Philip C. "George Herbert's Two Alter Poems." Humanistica Lovaniensia 24
                (1975): 278–87.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H14">
            <bib> Finch, Peter. "Concrete Poetry: A Brief Outline." The Anglo-Welsh Review 43
                (1970): 207–12.</bib>
            <notes> Historical outline, that is, of the international movement in this century
                (mainly Switzerland and Brazil), with examples. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H15">
            <bib> Gray, Paul H. "American Concrete: New Poetics, New Performance." Studies in
                Interpretation Vol. 2. Ed. Esther M. Doyle and V. H. Floyd. Amsterdam: Rodopi, 1977.
                pp. 77–98.</bib>
            <notes> History, trends, and possibilities for oral performance. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H16">
            <bib> Hastings, Robert. "'Easter Wings' as a Model of Herbert's Method." Thoth 4 (1963):
                15–23.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H17">
            <bib> Hedges, James S. "Correlation of Line and Syntax in Shaped Poems." Papers from the
                1977 Mid-America Linguistics Conference. Ed. Donald M. Lance et al. Columbia:
                University of Missouri Linguistics Program, 1978. pp. 445–51.</bib>
            <notes> Random sampling of such a correlation in a large number of poets produces an
                average: 95% in non-shaped poetry vs. 68% in shaped poetry. Conclusion: "when the
                poet becomes preoccupied with the visual image of the poem upon the page, the
                correlation between line and syntax is substantially lower than when the visual
                shape of the poem on the page is dictated by nonvisual criteria, i.e. by the number
                of syllables in the line, by phrasal units, by notions of rhythm analogous to
                "isochronous units," etc. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H18">
            <bib> Helms, Alan E. "I: Visual Prosody and the Sound of Punctuation." (Three-part
                dissertation.) DAI 32 (1971): 3305A (Rutgers).</bib>
            <notes> If prosody comprises the "total rhythmic form" of a poem then everything which
                affects that form is by definition prosodic, including white space, lineation,
                paragraphing, spatial deployment of lines, and--especially-- punctuation, since the
                pointing controls both the temporal positioning and pacing of elements and also the
                sense. "To alter the poem's punctuation is to alter the poem's prosody, and, hence,
                its meaning," as can be shown by constructing twin dummy models of poems which
                differ only in punctuation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H19">
            <bib> Higgins, Dick. George Herbert's Pattern Poems: In Their Tradition. West Glover,
                Vermont: Unpublished Editions, 1977. 79 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A twenty-page introductory essay followed by examples of Greek, Latin, and other
                pattern poems. Islamic deserved much more attention. Bibliography. The traditions
                for visual poetry are much older and wider than we think they are. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H20">
            <bib> Hollander, John. "The Poem in the Eye." Shenandoah 23 (1972): 3–32</bib>
            <notes>; rpt in revised form as chapter 12 of his Vision and Resonance (A13), pp.
                245–87. There is melos, and then there is opsis. There is, as correlate to the
                reading of poems, the "reading" of the shape of poems (in the sense in which art
                critics talk about "reading" or "scanning" a painting) which is so crucial for our
                determinations of meter and genre. There is the long tradition of poems picturing
                things--the pattern poems of the Renaissance, the concrete poetry of our own
                century--but then again there is the central visuality of syllabic verse and free
                verse, the importance of which far surpasses mere picturing by form in its deep
                access to the structure and nature--both quidditas and haecceitas--of the poem.
                After all, "a poem's shape may be a frame for itself as it may be a frame for its
                picture of the world." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H21">
            <bib> Horn, Peter. "Poetical Set Theory and the Technocratic Consciousness." Theoria 40
                (1973): 19–32.</bib>
            <notes> Concrete poetry betrays a surprising degree of mysticism and irrationality,
                given its fundamental ordering principle, permutation, and in the end seems more
                advertisement than poetry. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H22">
            <bib> Kell, Richard. "A Note on Versification." British Journal of Aesthetics 3 (1963):
                341– 45.</bib>
            <notes> A short but exceptionally illuminating exposition of how the texture and timing
                of the line "Two stones dropping in a silent chasm" A B C D vary when the line is
                broken, syntactically/typographically, into various vertical linear arrangements,
                e.g.: A BCD A BC D AB CD A B CD A B C D ABC D </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H23">
            <bib> Kiyokawa, Shoichi. "Concrete Poetry." New York Quarterly, no. 14 (1973), pp.
                176–81.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H24">
            <bib> Korn, A. L. "Puttenham and the Oriental Pattern-Poem." Comparative Literature 6
                (1954): 289–303.</bib>
            <notes> Research into the history of shaped poems, especially Persian and Turkish, shows
                that Puttenham's four pattern poems in the Arte, purported to be translations, "owe
                nothing demonstrable to any direct contact with Eastern patterns." Probably the form
                was known to him only by word of mouth (from his trip to Italy?), and he seems to
                have relied mainly on the Occidental geometrical tradition. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H25">
            <bib> Kostelanitz, Richard, ed. Imaged Words &amp; Worded Images. New York: Outerbridge
                and Dientsfrey, 1970.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H26">
            <bib> Lipski, John. "Connectedness in Poetry: Toward a Topological Analysis of E. E.
                Cummings." Language and Style 9 (1976): 143–63.</bib>
            <notes> Since the typography of a poem is a spatial structure, it has a geography, and a
                topological analysis becomes possible: Lipski maps out rules for continuity in such
                a text and then synthesizes them into a formal model. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H27">
            <bib> McHughes, Janet L. "The Poesis of Space: Prosodic Structures in Concrete Poetry."
                Quarterly Journal of Speech 63 (1977): 168–79.</bib>
            <notes> Identifies three characteristics of concrete poetry: foregrounding of spatial
                ordering, "reduction of language," and "functional repetition"; distinguishes three
                varieties of concrete poetry: poems retaining elements of traditional prosody, poems
                relying on sound for their "controlling structure," and poems employing space
                exclusively. Concludes that concrete poetry is open to analysis and interpretation.
                The examples are pleasing. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H28">
            <bib> Marcus, Aaron. "An Introduction to the Visual Syntax of Concrete Poetry." Visible
                Language 8 (1974): 333–60.</bib>
            <notes> An adequate understanding of the possibilities inherent in this verseform rests
                on an adequate typology of the basic modes of visual organization, or a "visual
                syntax." Marcus postulates four types of relationships as syntactic constituents:
                figure-field, depth, structure, and movement; these four types are illustrated by
                fifty- seven subtypes with examples on pp. 356–60. This is the most valuable
                treatment of the subject yet produced. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H29">
            <bib> Merritt, Francine. “Concrete Poetry--Verbivocovisual.” Speech Teacher 18 (1969):
                109–14.</bib>
            <notes> An apologia. Some representative types of this verse: code poem, picture poem,
                text poem, anagram, node, circle, constellation, emergent poem, computer-generated
                lines, and the chance poem. Serious and judicious. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H30">
            <bib> Mooij, J. J. A. "On the 'Foregrounding' of Graphic Elements in Poetry."
                Comparative Poetics. Ed. D. W. Fokkema et al. Amsterdam: Rodopi, 1976. pp.
                89–102.</bib>
            <notes> The author's review of international works on Poetics reveals a surprising
                reluctance to admit the graphic dimension of poetry as central to the theory. His
                arguments for the primacy of the printed poem in the Western cultural tradition
                include elements such as punctuation, lineation, and eye-rhyme, and forms such as
                pattern poems and concrete poetry. Adapts Mukarovskij. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H31">
            <bib> North, J. N. "Visual Poetry." Poetry 31 (1928): 3.</bib>
            <notes> Quaintly, North considers it a "quaint delusion" that a poem "may be taken in
                with the eye." See response by Conrad, H9. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H32">
            <bib> Ostriker, Alicia. "Poem Objects." Partisan Review 40 (1973): 95–107.</bib>
            <notes> A survey of concrete poetry. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H33">
            <bib> Potter, James L. "Sylvester's Shaped Sonnets." Notes &amp; Queries 202 (1957):
                405–6.</bib>
            <notes> Notes eleven typographical poems that are also variant sonnets at the beginning
                of Sylvester's Divine Weekes and Workes. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H34">
            <bib> Ranta, Jerrald. "Geometry, Vision, and Poetic Form." College English 39 (1978):
                707–24.</bib>
            <notes> Though George Puttenham (E614) apparently had the last word on strictly
                geometrical form in poetry, Ranta identifies two forms in modern poetry--a "rising"
                and a "diminishing" design--which may be combined into a third, composite form, and
                which also operate both visually and aurally--spatially and temporally. These
                designs are conventional strategies of structure, not particularly connected to
                Concretism; they entail adding, repeating, or deleting lines from stanzas. And
                naturally the structural principle is displaced into imagery as well. The psychology
                of perception offers corroboration. Turgid beyond endurance, this essay is too long
                by half. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H35">
            <bib> -----. "Palindromes, Poems, and Geometric Form." College English 36 (1974): 161–
                72; also in Visible Language 10 (1976): 157–72.</bib>
            <notes> Shows that three poems--by William Carlos Williams, E. E. Cummings, and Marianne
                Moore--have a vertical, typographic, palindromic form, showing axial symmetry of
                meter, sound, and syntax. None of them is as interesting as: "Lewd did I live, and
                evil I did dwel" or "A man, a plan, a canal--Panama!" </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H36">
            <bib> Robbins, R. H. "Punctuation Poems--A Further Note." Review of English Studies 15
                (1939): 206–7.</bib>
            <notes> Poems capable of double interpretation depending on ambiguity of punctuation.
                See James R. Kreuzer's earlier examples in H37 Review of English Studies 14 (1938):
                321–23. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H38">
            <bib> Sousa, R. "Concrete Poetry: A Contrastive Approach." Kentucky Romance Quarterly
                [formerly KFLQ] 23 (1976): 199–212.</bib>
            <notes> Contrasts a Pignatari concrete poem to Yeats's "The Magi" in order to point up
                what devices, functions, and effects are available in each mode. Traditional poetry
                allows patterning of sound, sense, rhythm, image, and ambiguity, whereas in concrete
                poetry the signs take on added substance beyond their purely referential linguistic
                nature, detaching themselves from the usual code if not establishing an entirely new
                code, and representing the simplest (most fundamental) conceptual categories by the
                strategy of spatialization. The two poems exemplify two entirely different "modes of
                language use in poetry." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H39">
            <bib> Stanley, Julia P. "The Escape from Syntax: or the Aesthetics of Dissolution."
                Bucknell Review 22 (1976): 152–63.</bib>
            <notes> A fusillade against concrete poetry for its goal of "removing language from its
                role in the creation of poetry" or "the abrogation of language." Concrete poetry
                "might be another art, but it is not poetry. . . . it is the content, the feeling,
                the emotion that distinguishes poetry as an art." Value judgments masquerade as
                premises in this completely muddled polemic. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H40">
            <bib> Waldrop, Rosemarie. "A Basis of Concrete Poetry." Bucknell Review 22 (1976):
                141–51.</bib>
            <notes> Demonstration through numerous examples of the centrality of the principle of
                reduction in concrete poetry; since a concrete poem is "a structure which explores
                elements of language itself rather than one which uses language to explore something
                else. . . . the real concrete text only represents itself and is identical with what
                it shows." Jakobson's notion of equivalence and Levin's notion of coupling are also
                turned to use. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="H41">
            <bib> Weaver, Mike. "Concrete Poetry." The Lugano Review 1 (1966): 100–25</bib>
            <notes>; rpt in The Journal of Typographic Research [later Visible Language] 1 (1967):
                293–326. Traces part of the early history of the Concretist movement then elaborates
                a typology of concrete poems as (1) optic, (2) kinetic, or (3) phonetic. Many
                examples. See also: L7, L15, L26, L78, L114, L132, L134–36, L160, L364, L878,
                L950–51, N15, N25. </notes>
        </item>
    </chapter>
</bibliography>
