<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="THE POEM IN PERFORMANCE">

        <item id="I1">
            <bib> Ayer, James R. "Dylan Thomas in the Aural Dimension." Computer Studies in the
                Humanities and Verbal Behavior 1 (1968): 6–9.</bib>
            <notes> Ayer suggests that Thomas's style changed significantly after 1938, the year he
                began his readings over the BBC. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I2">
            <bib> Baker, George P. "Rhythm in Recent Dramatic Dialogue." Yale Review n.s. 19 (1929):
                116–33.</bib>
            <notes> Especially Yeats's. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I3">
            <bib> Barnhill, Viron L. "Poetic Context in the Collected Poems (1909–1935) of T. S.
                Eliot: A Linguistic Investigation of Poetic Context." DA 21 (1960): 2284A
                (Michigan).</bib>
            <notes> Uses the distribution-analysis methods of Charles C. Fries. Chapters on "The
                Elements of Phonological Context," "The Role of the Suprasegmental Pho- nemes in
                Phonological Context," "The Role of the Segmental Phonemes and Voice Qualifiers in
                Phonological Context," and "The Special Effects of Unus- ual Syntax." Takes the
                written form of the poem as secondary to the oral form, and insists that
                interpretation must rest on the possibilities allowed by the phonological facts. The
                emphasis throughout is on theory and methodology, not on Eliot. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I4">
            <bib> Berleant, Arnold. "The Verbal Presence: An Aesthetic of Literary Performance."
                JAAC 31 (1973): 339–46.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I5">
            <bib> Bessinger, J. B. "The Oral Text of Ezra Pound's 'The Seafarer.'" Quarterly Journal
                of Speech 47 (1961): 173–77.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I6">
            <bib> Birkinshaw, P. C. "Speaking Shelley's Ode to the West Wind." English Studies in
                Africa 2 (1959): 179–89.</bib>
            <notes> The best performances are based on extensive preparations which examine, in
                depth, speaker, medium, listener, situation, and subject, all of which are ex-
                amined here for Shelley. Shelley, by the way, had a voice that Hogg said was
                "excruciating"; it "excoriated the ears." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I7">
            <bib> Boas, Guy. "The Speaking of Shakespeare's Verse." Essays and Studies n.s. 17
                (1964): 78–87.</bib>
            <notes> Begins on p. 82. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I8">
            <bib> Breen, Robert S. "Symbolic Action in the Oral Interpretation of Robinson Jeffers'
                'Roan Stallion.'" Diss., Northwestern University, 1951.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I9">
            <bib> Burklund, Carl E. "On the Oral Reading of Poetry." Quarterly Journal of Speech 31
                (1945): 344–50.</bib>
            <notes> Identifies two faults ("sing-song" and "matter-of-fact" voicing) and four neces-
                sities (poetry should be read (1) qua poetry, (2) with honesty, (3) with aesthetic
                distance, and (4) so as to give a unified impression) of performance. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I10">
            <bib> Burniston, Christabel. "The Rendering of English Verse." In Poetic Technique.
                Altrincham: John Sherratt &amp; Son, 1949; pp. 121–84.</bib>
            <notes> Observations on oral performance based on the scansion-system of O. C. de C.
                Ellis (E349). Noteworthy sections here on Rhythm, Sprung Rhythm, Use of Pause, and
                Cadence. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I11">
            <bib> Cannon, Garland. "Linguistics and the Performance of Poetry." College Composition
                and Communication 16 (1965): 20–26.</bib>
            <notes> A ranging review of the work of structural and transformational linguists
                (Trager &amp; Smith, Chomsky, et al.) on poetry with reference to the implica- tions
                for oral performance. Cannon, disappointed at the impact of the former school on
                American criticism in general, notes three shortcomings of the Structural treatment
                of poetry: (1) fragments rather than whole texts are taped and analyzed; (2)
                intentional ambiguities in the poem-in-print must be re- solved in performance; and
                (3) no one reading of a poem can supersede all the rest as authoritative or perfect.
                Still, he encourages familiarity with transcrip- tion and a linguistic understanding
                of poetic grammar. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I12">
            <bib> Chatman, Seymour. "Linguistic Analysis: A Study of James Mason's Interpretation of
                'The Bishop Orders His Tomb.'" The Oral Study of Literature. Ed. Thomas O. Sloan.
                New York: Random House, 1966. pp. 94–133.</bib>
            <notes> Simple elucidation of the semantics of intonation, followed by a line-by-line
                commentary on the recording of the poem. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I13">
            <bib> -----. "Linguistic Style, Literary Style, and Performance: Some Distinctions."
                Monograph Series on Languages and Linguistics 13 (1962): 73–81.</bib>
            <notes> As a companion to his comparative anatomy of metrical styles (E709), Chat- man
                offers here a tentative schematization of the kinds of information con- veyed in
                performance, using Beardsley's categories of General, Emotive, and Cognitive Import,
                with application to The Waste Land. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I14">
            <bib> Church, Richard. "The English Poets from Chaucer to Yeats." Review of English
                Literature 6 (1965): 100–6.</bib>
            <notes> Deploring the "diminishing contact" between poet and audience since the ad- vent
                of the printing press, Church applauds a recent series of recordings of English
                poetry on phonograph records, and he examines specially the records first released
                (on the Romantics) and the quality of the performances. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I15">
            <bib> Clinton-Baddeley, V. C. "The Written and the Spoken Word." Essays and Studies n.s.
                18 (1965): 73–82.</bib>
            <notes> A retrospective on the history of recorded poetry, with special emphasis on the
                extensive editing and splicing by sound engineers in search of the perfect per-
                formance. Sample observation: "All Yeats's poetry demands that the reader should
                acknowledge the line endings." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I16">
            <bib> Colson, Ted D. "An Analysis of Selected Poems of Gerard Manley Hopkins for Oral
                Interpretation and a Study of His Poetic Theories." DAI 24 (1964): 5604A
                (Oklahoma).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I17">
            <bib> Corman, Cid. "The Structure of Poetic Rhythms in relation to an oral poetry." In
                his Word for Word: Essays on the Arts of Language. Santa Barbara: Black Sparrow
                Press, 1977. Vol. 1, pp. 65–76.</bib>
            <notes> The entire section of eight essays on "Oral Poetry" is important; Corman dis-
                cusses the rhythms and meters of oral compositions, taking the "breath-unit" as the
                crucial element, each breath-unit being composed of various feet. "It is ac- cent
                that creates the basic rhythm and quantity (timing and sound-values) that creates
                the melodic line; but both must cohere in a true poem. Accent is the dance; quantity
                is the song." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I18">
            <bib> Cunningham, Cornelius C. "The Rhythm of Robinson Jeffers' Poetry as Revealed by
                Oral Reading." Quarterly Journal of Speech 32 (1946): 351-57.</bib>
            <notes> On the premise that the rhythm (meter) can only be determined correctly by
                marking the stresses heard in an oral interpretation, the author collected thirty
                such transcriptions of three poems, concluding from them (in spite of himself) that
                Jeffers' metric is not stress verse or free verse but "iambic-anapestic duple
                meter." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I19">
            <bib> Dickinson, Patric. "The Spoken Word." Encounter 34 (1970): 54–62.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I20">
            <bib> Finnegan, Ruth. Oral Poetry: Its Nature, Significance, and Social Context.
                Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1977.</bib>
            <notes> Finnegan is the single most valuable source available on the social manifesta-
                tions of performed poetry. And though the scope of the book--its forte--is immense,
                providing for the first time a genuinely global perspective on the subject,
                nevertheless her judgment on each of the various specific problems in the theory is
                remarkably well-informed. See section 4.2 on "Prosodic Sys- tems," pp. 90–102, for
                examples of the wide variety of metrical and sonal pat- terns in the world's
                poetries. Also section 4.3 on structural repetition, 4.4 on diction, and 4.5 on
                performance. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I21">
            <bib> Fleischmann, Wolfgang B. "Poetry Reading." Princeton (A18), pp. 967–70.</bib>
            <notes> See also s.v. "Oral Poetry." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I22">
            <bib> Fogerty, Elsie. The Speaking of English Verse. London and Toronto, J. M. Dent; New
                York: E. P. Dutton, 1923; 4th ed. rev. and enlarged, 1937.</bib>
            <notes> Based on a musical theory of meter. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I23">
            <bib> Forrest, William C. "The Poem as a Summons to Performance." British Journal of
                Aesthetics 9 (1969): 298–305.</bib>
            <notes> Critical of the Ingarden-Wellek "objectivist" view of the poem as linguistic
                object, as a mere "set of linguistic norms," Forrest counters with a defense of the
                priority of performance both in poetic composition and in critical inter- pretation,
                developing brilliantly a concept of "homorganic alliteration" and also an analogy of
                fetal development in utero to the poem prior to performance. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I24">
            <bib> Fulsom, Ralph E. "An Investigation of the Structural Aspects of Free Verse as They
                Affect the Oral Reader." DA 17 (1957): 3120A (Northwestern).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I25">
            <bib> Goldstein, Bernard J. "The Comprehension of Poetry from Recordings." DA 12 (1952):
                434 (Columbia).</bib>
            <notes> An experiment to gauge the comprehension of oral against written modes of poems,
                with skilled and unskilled oral interpreters. Conclusion: comprehen- sion was
                greatest when subjects had a written text of the poem before them while it was being
                read aloud at the same time. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I26">
            <bib> Goring, Marius. "The Sound of Poetry." Essays by Divers Hands (Transactions of the
                Royal Society of Literature) n.s. 39 (1977): 1–23.</bib>
            <notes> A nostalgic lecture on the virtues of poetry heard in the ear: the many long
                examples suggest that the speaker was conveying his message performatively rather
                than discursively. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I27">
            <bib> Haas, Charles E. "A Structural Analysis of Selected Sonnets of Gerard Manley
                Hopkins." DA 25 (1965): 5443A (Denver).</bib>
            <notes> Seven sonnets are analyzed for oral interpretation, recorded, then transcribed,
                noting stress, pitch, and juncture via the Trager-Smith system. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I28">
            <bib> Hein, Hilde. "Performance as an Aesthetic Category." JAAC 28 (1970): 381–86.</bib>
            <notes> It is interesting to contemplate its denigration as a primary category through-
                out the history of Western aesthetics, particularly since performance entails
                interpretation in music, poetry, drama, and dance, and perhaps also in paint- ing,
                scupture, and film. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I29">
            <bib> Hillyer, Robert. "On Reading Verse Aloud." Atlantic Monthly 164 (1939):
                91–95.</bib>
            <notes> Hillyer finds the cardinal rule of verse to be that every line is divided into
                "two equal time units." His performance-directive scansions mark syllabic length,
                stresses, and pauses. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I30">
            <bib> Holmes, Oliver Wendell. "Physiology of Versification and the Harmonies of Organic
                and Animal Life." Boston Medical and Surgical Journal, 7 January 1875;</bib>
            <notes> rpt in his Pages from an Old Volume of Life. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1883. pp.
                315–21. An early study of what we would now term "breath-groups." The great rhythmic
                activities of the body are the breath and the heartbeat, four of the latter for each
                of the former. Reading octosyllabic verse, one takes about 20 breaths per minute to
                read about 20 lines per minute, thus making, by equiva- lence of the breath and
                line, such verse very easy to read. Iambic pentameter verse goes more slowly, since
                longer, and is thereby more fatiguing, but cae- suras are available as
                compensations. Ballad meters are hemistichic and easy; the duodecasyllabic line is
                rarely used because it is too long for one breath but too short for two. Finally, as
                line corresponds to breath, so accent may corre- spond to pulse--four pulses to the
                breath equal four stresses to the octosyllable. Certainly it is true that in the
                oral delivery of verse one must accomo- date the phrasal contours to one's breath;
                the question is whether such biologi- cal rhythms were the primal origins of meter.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I31">
            <bib> Hopkins, Mary Francis. "Linguistic Analysis as a Tool for the Oral Interpreter."
                Speech Teacher 18 (1969): 200–3.</bib>
            <notes> Approves of the value of phonetic transcription for clarifying (1) meter, (2)
                sound patterns, (3) lexical ambiguities, (4) structure, and (5) problems of se-
                mantic interpretation. Sample analysis of Levertov's "One A.M." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I32">
            <bib> Howarth, Herbert. "Metre and Emphasis: A Conservative Note." Essays on
                Shakespeare. Ed. Gordon Ross Smith. University Park: Penn State University Press,
                1965. pp. 211–27.</bib>
            <notes> Actors will keep closer to Shakespeare's intent in his lines the closer they
                keep to the metrical pattern in their delivery. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I33">
            <bib> Hudson, Lee. "Poetics in Performance: The Beat Generation." Studies in
                Interpretation Volume 2. Ed. Esther M. Doyle and V. H. Floyd. Amsterdam: Rodopi,
                1977. pp. 59–76.</bib>
            <notes> Includes a section on "Psychological Metrics" discussing Williams, Ginsberg,
                Olson, and Pound. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I34">
            <bib> Levertov, Denise. "An Approach to Public Poetry Listenings." Virginia Quarterly
                Review 41 (1965): 422–33.</bib>
            <notes> "The poetry . . . in which the sounds--the vowels and consonants, the tone
                patterns, the currents of rhythm--are the chief carriers of content . . . [is the]
                poetry which is most inaccessible to readers trained to bring, not the whole of
                themselves, but their wits, to a reading." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I35">
            <bib> Levin, Samuel R. "Suprasegmentals and the Performance of Poetry." Quarterly
                Journal of Speech 48 (1962): 366–72</bib>
            <notes>; rpt in The Practice of Modern Literary Scholarship. Ed. Sheldon P. Zitner.
                Glenview, Illinois: Scott, Foresman, 1966. pp. 344–51. At the outset, Levin cites
                Seymour Chatman from the 1956 Kenyon Review symposium (E712) as a examplar of the
                new interest by structural linguists in metrics. These linguists, armed with the
                Trager-Smith inventory of supraseg- mentals, believe that the meter was to be
                discovered by reading the poem aloud, and Chatman himself insists that ambiguity
                exists only on paper and is instantly resolved in oral performance. Levin's response
                is to distinguish lexical ambiguity (which no performance will disambiguate) from
                syntactic ambiguity (which is resolved in reading). Thereafter, he can only plead
                that ambiguity is an intentional device of intensification in poetry, and that
                insofar as oral per- formance reduces ambiguity, it performs "a real disservice to
                the poem." Am- biguity is preserved in "visual performance . . . a silent reading."
                The latter half of the essay demonstrates syntactic ambiguities in a Dylan Thomas
                poem. Cf. Loesch (I39). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I36">
            <bib> Lightfoot, Marjorie J. "Prosody and Performance." Quarterly Journal of Speech 53
                (1967): 61–66.</bib>
            <notes> This rather amorphous summary of the variety of conflicting prosodic opinions
                about the meter of Old, Middle, and Modern English verse leads to no clear
                commitments or conclusions about the authority of the text, performance, or
                expectation for determining scansion save one: the reader must try to identify the
                prosodic pattern intended by the author, since that is by implication the best one
                the author could conceive. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I37">
            <bib> Lipton, Lawrence. "Have You Heard Any Good Poems Lately? A Study of the Functions
                of Sight and Sound in Modern Poetry." Arizona Quarterly 13 (1957): 133–43. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I38">
            <bib> Loesch, Katharine T. "Empirical Studies in Oral Interpretation: The Text." Western
                Speech 38 (1969): 250–68.</bib>
            <notes> Part of a symposium. Acutely aware of the difficult problem of poetic ontol- ogy
                which underlies problems in both prosody and oral interpretation, Loesch charts some
                eminently tough-minded and pragmatic courses toward a solution. The indispensable
                core of such a solution is an adequate description of the poem both as text and as
                performance. Such adequacy we do not have at present; hence Loesch sets about to
                review all the important linguistic work done since Trager and Smith (D32) on
                phonology and metrics, showing clearly the nature of what has been accomplished, and
                also what has been ignored or slighted. Her grasp of the larger architecture of the
                theory is synoptic and firm. Sample phonetic transcription (i.e. a complete text) of
                "In My Craft or Sullen Art" at the end. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I39">
            <bib> -----. "Literary Ambiguity and Oral Performance." Quarterly Journal of Speech 51
                (1965): 258–67.</bib>
            <notes> A very important counterargument to the structural metrists' claim (see I35)
                that in the performance of poetry all semantic ambiguities created by alterna- tive
                intonational patterns for a line must be resolved ("disambiguated") by the performer
                (since he can only utter the line one way one time). Loesch shows that "it is
                rarely, if ever, the case that only disambiguating intonations are avail- able. A
                non-disambiguating intonation is always available as well." This seems plain sense:
                unless we had heard ambiguous statements uttered, in the past, how would we know
                they existed? </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I40">
            <bib> Long, Chester, C. "The Poem's Text as a Technique of Performance in Public Group
                Readings of Poetry." Journal of Western Speech 31 (1967): 16–29.</bib>
            <notes> In the midst of a discussion of group (but non-choral) performances of poems by
                two to three interpreters appears a discussion, on a much higher level, of the
                ontological situs of the poem, with Long differentiating text, performance, and form
                of poetry. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I41">
            <bib> Martin, Howard R., and Kenneth L. Pike. "Analysis of the Vocal Performance of a
                Poem: A Classification of Intonational Features." Language and Style 7 (1974):
                209–18.</bib>
            <notes> Not very useful; generalizations and conclusions are not easily accessible, and
                the essay seems excessively concerned with the distinction of analogic vs. digital.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I42">
            <bib> Nichols, Wallace B. The Speaking of Poetry. Boston: Expression Co., 1937. 110
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> A first chapter treats prosody in a surprisingly sure-handed manner; thereafter,
                eight chapters explore the "speaking" of various genres of poetry. Altogether the
                book is considerably more intelligently written than one expects, and it altogether
                avoids the bombast, cant, and vacuity of most works on "oral inter- pretation."
                Nichols shows sophistication in the principles of his craft. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I43">
            <bib> Orr, Peter. "Poetry and the Human Voice." English 22 (1973): 18–23.</bib>
            <notes> The aural manifestation of poetry is more central to its nature than the textual
                manifestation. The poem is a sounding and therefore must be heard. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I44">
            <bib> Payzant, Geoffrey. "Performance and the Existence of Art." Dalhousie Review 44
                (1964): 83–95.</bib>
            <notes> A philosophical treatment of the issues. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I45">
            <bib> Pike, Kenneth L. "Implications of the Patterning of an Oral Reading of a Set of
                Poems." Poetics 1 (1971): 38–45.</bib>
            <notes> Exhortation that we learn to read, write (via simple contour markers), and
                perform poetry with a heightened awareness of voice-quality and intonation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I46">
            <bib> Ready, William. "The Sound of Poetry." Bulletin of the American Library
                Association 56 (1962): 153–54.</bib>
            <notes> Praises the variety of recordings available, mainly from Caedmon. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I47">
            <bib> Rickert, William E. "Structural Functions of Rhyme and the Performance of Poetry."
                Quarterly Journal of Speech 62 (1976): 250–55.</bib>
            <notes> Isolates four functions: Formality, Organization, Expectation, Closure. Per-
                formers are to emphasize formal aspects. (Nothing new here.) </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I48">
            <bib> Robinson, Sybil C. F. "The Speaking of Shakespeare." DAI 32 (1971): 3471A
                (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I49">
            <bib> Salper, Donald R. "A Study of an Oral Approach to the Appreciation of Poetry." DA
                27 (1967): 2218A (Minnesota, 1964).</bib>
            <notes> Concerns the "transposition of sound into letter" and the reification of print.
                Examines the validity and assumptions of oral interpretation. Much on sound in
                poetry. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I50">
            <bib> Storey, Barbara. "Phonetics and Its Relation to the Aesthetic Use of Speech."
                Proceedings of the Second International Congress of Phonetic Sciences. Ed. Daniel
                Jones and D. B. Fry. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1936. pp. 99– 102.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I51">
            <bib> Winters, Ivor. "The Audible Reading of Poetry." Hudson Review 4 (1951): 433–47;
                rpt in his The Function of Criticism. Denver: Alan Swallow, 1957. pp. 79–100; rpt in
                Gross (A23), pp. 131–49.</bib>
            <notes> Winters with his odd blunt way insists on the distinction between meter and
                rhythm, arguing that therefore "adequate audible reading will be reading in which
                the rhythm of the poem is rendered intact," formally, the reader inton- ing the
                words in a style very close to chant. Illustrations of rhythmic varieties of the
                iambic pentameter, analyses, and general animadversions follow. Win- ters recognizes
                the Relative Stress Principle. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="I52">
            <bib> Yeats, W. B. "Literature and the Living Voice." The Contemporary Review 90 (1906):
                472–82.</bib>
            <notes> Esp. pp. 480–81. </notes>
        </item>
    </chapter>
</bibliography>
