<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="OLD ENGLISH">
        <item id="J1">
            <bib> Abegg, Daniel. Zur Entwicklung der historischen Dichtung bei den Angelsächsen.
                Quellen und Forschungen, no. 73. Strassburg: Karl. J. Trübner, 1894.</bib>
            <notes> A study of The Battle of Maldon and The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle poems; meter is
                treated passim, especially on pp. 9–14, 34, 41, 47, 55, 63, 65, 70, and 75. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J2">
            <bib> Andrew, S. O. The Old English Alliterative Measure. Croyden: H. R. Grubb, Ltd.,
                1931. 82 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev. by Malone in JEGP 31 (1932): 639; in MP 29 (1932): 376–77; in Review of
                English Studies 9 (1933): 85–87; in Anglia Beiblatt 44 (1933): 71–73; in Archiv 161
                (1932): 145–46. Calling the Five-Types system of Sievers "almost incredible . . .
                absurd . . . a false metrical theory," Andrew claims that Sievers' Type E is in fact
                B "with the first foot 'weighted,'" Type D is in fact A (for the same reason), and
                the C and "extended" D and E Types are varieties of the longer A Type. Thereupon he
                "reclassifies" a great many lines cited by Sievers. Also a chapter on word- stress
                in Old English. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J3">
            <bib> -----. Postscript on "Beowulf". Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1948. 158
                pp. Rev: by Malone in English Studies 32 (1951): 116–19; in Review of English
                Studies n.s. 1 (1950): 353–56.</bib>
            <notes> Further evidence to support the theses proposed in the author's two earlier
                monographs (J2, J4) on OE syntax (here, the first seven chapters) and meter (the
                following three), concluded by a chapter on the varieties of scribal error. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J4">
            <bib> -----. Syntax and Style in Old English. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
                1940; rpt New York: Russell and Russell, 1966. 112 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in TLS, 14 December 1940, p. 635; in Medium Ævum 12 (1943): 104–6; in MLR
                36 (1941): 252–55; in MP 39 (1946): 99–100; in Review of English Studies 17 (1941):
                499–501; in JEGP 41 (1942): 85–88. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J5">
            <bib> Baker, Carole F. "The Rags and Bones of Fictive Worlds: Ontological Implications
                of Syntax in Early English Prose and Poetry." DAI 36 (1976): 6109A (Bryn
                Mawr).</bib>
            <notes> Applies the hypotaxis-parataxis method of Auerbach's Mimesis to ten OE and ME
                works. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J6">
            <bib> Ball, Evelyn R. "Music and English Poetry in the Middle Ages." DAI 36 (1976):
                6666A (Missouri).</bib>
            <notes> Inter alia, Ball finds a correlation between certain types of verse and the
                three branches of medieval music--monody, antiphony, polyphony, speculates on the
                musical accompaniment to verse recitation, and discusses the metrical and stanzaic
                influences of the chanson de geste and the chante-fable on the ME metri- cal
                romances. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J7">
            <bib> Bartlett, Helen. The Metrical Division of the Paris Psalter. Baltimore:
                Friedenwald, 1896. 419 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Diss., New York University. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J8">
            <bib> Baum, P. F. "The Character of Anglo-Saxon Verse." MP 28 (1930): 143–56.</bib>
            <notes> Critical of Sievers for classifying the OE metrical types--an activity Baum
                considers both inherently "futile" (given the considerable range of variations) and
                also inferior to the truly important work of explanation (which Sievers of course
                did not attempt)--Baum undertakes "a fresh examination of the data" (very limited
                data, one must add); on the assumptions that the verse was (1) spoken not sung, (2)
                based on 2 stresses per verse, with (3) emphasis on the al- literation, he concludes
                that (1) the half-line is in every respect the unit of meter--the long line is not
                one line but a couplet; (2) the promotion and sup- pression of secondary accents is
                the very heart of the whole metrical system; (3) Sievers erred in confusing meter
                with rhythm--the Five Types are varieties of rhythm, not meter, meter being a much
                more simplified pattern; (4) the meter of OE is simply a verse of 2 stresses in up
                to 5 syllables, everything else being variable; and (5) the two most distinctive
                qualities of OE verse are "its freedom or elasticity and its heavy pounding."
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J9">
            <bib> -----. "The Meter of the Beowulf." MP 46 (1948–49): 73–91, 145–62.</bib>
            <notes> A "brief survey" by one who believes that "detailed examination can properly be
                left to the scientists." Thus our modern-day Saintsbury gives here an analy- sis
                that like his others is based on representative samples and indeed goes that far
                only in order to satisfy "those who wish everything neat and tidy" (Sievers'
                typology is disparaged thus throughout.) Everything is really very simple. In
                Beowulf we find "not a rigid meter but a rather loose and easy manner"; "the basic
                pattern of the verse is generally two-stress trochaic," i.e. "verses with two
                stresses and a varying number of unstressed syllables." But there are many
                variations. It is unlikely that the scop "used his harp as a metronome," since
                Gregorian chant uses non-isochronic measures. Baum notes the common pat- terns of
                normal, double, triple, transverse, and plurilinear alliteration but rejects the
                rule (from Rieger) that it is the first stave of the second verse which de- termines
                the alliteration, citing fifty examples. Similarly he rejects the idea of resolution
                and behind it any attention to syllabic quantity in scansion. The hy- permetrical
                lines he thinks vestiges of the oldest Proto-Germanic line of eight beats. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J10">
            <bib> Bazell, Charles E. "Notes on Old English Metre and Morphology." Wortbildung,
                Syntax und Morphologie. Ed. Herbert E. Brekle and Leonhard Lipka. The Hague: Mouton,
                1968. pp. 17–19.</bib>
            <notes> The first of these two notes suggests that in the Battle of Maldon the rule
                whereby st- and similar consonantal clusters are treated as single consonants is
                extended to all such clusters beginning with s-. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J11">
            <bib> Beale, Walter H. "Rhetoric in the Old English Verse-Paragraph." Neuphilologische
                Mitteilungen 80 (1979): 133–42.</bib>
            <notes> Actually a study of rhythmic patterning--a demonstration of the process whereby
                rhetorical motifs or schemes are embedded or, mutatis mutandis, dis- played in
                verse-paragraphs, especially through the use of metrical matching and contrast--e.g.
                a sequence of B-Type verses in second half-lines, for parallelism, or alternation of
                short A's with long E's for contrast. "Rhetoric" cannot coher- ently be explained in
                verse without reference to "Metric," and conversely, dis- plays of metrical
                virtuosity are nearly always rhetorically intensified as well. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J12">
            <bib> Beaty, John O. "The Echo-Word in Beowulf." PMLA 49 (1934): 365–73.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J13">
            <bib> Benson, Larry D. "The Literary Character of Anglo-Saxon Formulaic Poetry." PMLA 81
                (1966): 334–41.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J14">
            <bib> Bessinger, Jess B., Jr. "Alliterative Meter." Princeton (A18), pp. 16–18.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J15">
            <bib> -----. "Beowulf and the Harp at Sutton Hoo." University of Toronto Quarterly 27
                (1958): 148–68.</bib>
            <notes> A ranging essay: poetic style and ornamentation are discussed on pp. 152–55,
                methods of playing the harp on 159–61, and the implications for metrical the- ory on
                163. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J16">
            <bib> -----. "The Sutton Hoo Harp Replica and Old English Musical Verse." Old English
                Poetry: Fifteen Essays. Ed. Robert P. Creed. Providence, R.I.: Brown University
                Press, 1967. pp. 3–26.</bib>
            <notes> The best available discussion of the nature of the reconstructed Anglo-Saxon
                harps, their possible uses, and the general nature of music in Anglo-Saxon England.
                Applications to prosody are treated on pp. 14–15, where Bessinger suggests that harp
                accompaniment to the chanting of the verse could have been a percussive, monotonal
                rhythmic base, a full melody or tune sung along with the words, or, more likely,
                some "vestigial melodic and rhythmic aid to the singer"; Cable (J42) has explored
                this last possibility the most fully. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J17">
            <bib> Björkman, Erik. "Zum alliterierenden Morte Arthure." Anglia 39 (1915):
                253–67.</bib>
            <notes> Mainly on alliteration patterns. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J18">
            <bib> Bliss, A. J. "The Appreciation of Old English Metre." English and Medieval Studies
                Presented to J. R. R. Tolkien. Ed. Norman Davis and C. L. Wrenn. London: George
                Allen &amp; Unwin, 1962. pp. 27–40.</bib>
            <notes> On one of the most beguiling questions in English versification. Bliss, assum-
                ing that the difference between Old and Modern English meter lies in the fact that
                the former achieves variety "not in the more or less exact accommodation of the
                speech-material to the metrical pattern, but in the variation of the met- rical
                pattern itself," that pattern being not an artificial, abstract form but a re-
                production of the pattern of actual speech itself [Bliss agrees with Daunt], pro-
                ceeds to argue that, in fact, Old English and Modern English meters are not really
                dissimilar, since both rely au fond on the natural rhythms of the language, which in
                this respect have not changed significantly since before the Conquest, and also,
                since many combinations of OE verse-types can be scanned as pass- able iambic
                pentameters and vice versa. After all, Chaucer can hardly have learned the regular
                alternation of stresses and slacks from French verse, where no such principle
                exists; a much more likely source is the regular alternation inherent in OE verse
                itself, as when resolution occurs in the C and D types. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J19">
            <bib> -----. An Introduction to Old English Metre. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1962. 33
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> This typewriter-print pamphlet in paper covers condenses the arguments of
                Bliss's major work (below): here he partitions then discusses Rhythm (consist- ing
                of Stress, both sentence-stress and word-stress, and Quantity), Phrasing
                (breath-groups divided by caesuras, usually two groups to the verse (or half- line),
                and Alliteration. On Metre, he takes as the Rhythm Sievers' Five Types and as the
                Phrasing (one stress to each breath-group) three possibilities for placement of the
                caesura inside the verse. Of the fifteen possible combinations of these two systems,
                Bliss finds eight in actuality. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J20">
            <bib> -----. The Meter of "Beowulf". Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1958</bib>
            <notes>; 2nd ed. 1967. 170 pp. Rev: in Review of English Studies n.s. 11 (1960): 414–16;
                in Zeitschrift für Anglistik und Amerikanistik 8 (1960): 77–80; by W. P. Lehmann in
                JEGP 59 (1960): 137–42; by E. G. Stanley in English Philological Studies 8 (1963):
                47–53; in English Studies 46 (1965): 418–22. See also critiques by Cable (J45),
                Willard and Clemons (J338), and Lewis (J172). A "triumphant vindication" and
                revision of Sievers. Bliss reclassifies the verses (half-lines) in Beowulf as being
                comprised of 1, 2, or 3 principal stresses and terms them (respectively) Light,
                Normal, and Heavy. He also argues that the loss of a stress in Light verses entails
                an increase in the number of syllables in the verse "if the average interval between
                stresses is to remain constant." But in notation Bliss uses the vertical bar (oddly
                termed the "caesura," which is nothing but unhelpful) not to divide metrical units
                (Sievers called them "feet") but to mark the "breath-groups" (roughly corresponding
                to word-boundaries). He prefixes the numbers 1, 2, and 3 to the Five Types
                designations to indicate (respectively) that the first breath-group is shorter than,
                equal to, or longer than the second. This procedure yields eight major varieties:
                1A, 2A, 2B, 3B, 2C, 1D, 2E, and 3E. For the hypermetrical verses, Bliss suggests
                that the final syllables of ordinary verses are replaced by a wide variety of
                extensions. The 2nd edition adds an Appendix (E) in which Bliss reaffirms that the
                base or norm of OE verse is the normal, falling-rhythm Type A, very common, and that
                the scop deliberately counterpoised it against the other types for the sake of
                variety, repeating the A type often enough to keep the norm visible. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J21">
            <bib> -----. "The Origin and Structure of the Old English Hypermetric Line." Notes &amp;
                Queries 217 (1972): 242–48.</bib>
            <notes> Extending his earlier hypothesis (J22) of an Old Norse origin (the ljóðaháttr
                meter) for the single half-lines which occasionally appear in OE poetry, Bliss
                suggests further that "there is sufficient likeness between the Old English hy-
                permetric long line and the Old Norse ljóðaháttr couplet to make it possible that
                both are derived from one and the same prehistoric Germanic metre," which Bliss
                reconstructs hypothetically as: / (X) / | (X) / X / X || (X) / X / X . Since OE
                hypermetric alliteration is continued but that for the ON ljóðaháttr - couplet is
                double, two types must have been equally preferable in the proto- meter: three
                staves (one on the first stress of each section of the line) or four (two sets of
                pairs). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J22">
            <bib> -----. "Single Half-Lines in Old English Poetry." Notes &amp; Queries 216 (1971):
                442– 49.</bib>
            <notes> In OE poetry short lines (i.e. single verses) are much more frequent than most
                editors recognize, Bliss argues; they are especially frequent in the Maxims. The
                source for this device may well be the Old Norse ljóðaháttr meter, where short lines
                are very common; the distribution of alliteration in the OE lines also matches that
                in the ON. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J23">
            <bib> Boer, R. C. Studiën over de Metriek van het Alliteratievers. Amsterdam: Johannes
                Müller, 1916. 268 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J24">
            <bib> Bognitz, Alfred. Doppelt-steigende Alliterationsverse (Sievers' Typus B) im
                Angelsächsischen. Diss., Berlin, 1920. 48 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J25">
            <bib> Bohlen, Adolf. Zusammengehörige Wortgruppen, getrennt durch Cäsur oder
                Versschluss, in der angelsächsischen Epik. Diss., Berlin, 1908. 56 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Englische Studien 40 (1908–9): 90. A study of the connections--and
                diremptions--between meter and syntax, spe- cifically the metrical caesura and
                syntactic juncture: Bohlen examines word- groups divided by the mid-line caesura and
                the end of the line and discovers two distinct types of usage; these serve as the
                basis for classifying the style of the various Anglo-Saxon epics as either secular
                (rarely separating closely related words or phrases) or religious (more frequently
                splitting cohesive constructions). He follows the metrical rules as defined by
                Rieger. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J26">
            <bib> Bonner, Joshua H. "Toward a Unified Critical Approach to Old English Poetic
                Composition." MP 73 (1976): 219–28.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J27">
            <bib> Bosworth, Joseph. The Elements of Anglo-Saxon Grammar, with copious notes. . . .
                London: Harding, Mavor, and Leopard, 1823.</bib>
            <notes> Thereafter Bosworth published a redaction of the book: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J28">
            <bib> -----. A Compendious Grammar of the Primitive English or Anglo-Saxon Language . .
                . being chiefly a Selection of What is Most Valuable and Practical in "The Elements
                of the Anglo-Saxon Grammar," with Some Additional Observations. London: Simpkin and
                Marshall, 1826.</bib>
            <notes> Here the "Prosody" selection covers pp. 69–73. Bosworth follows Rask in basing
                OE meter on stress rather than quantity (as did Hickes). He finds gener- ally two
                stresses and a variable number of non-stresses in each verse, an inter- mittent
                anacrusis ("metrical complement"), and alliteration (the first stave of the second
                verse being the "Chief letter," the others the "Assistants"). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J29">
            <bib> Bradshaw, Margaret R. "The Meter of The Christ." Diss., Yale University,
                1902.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J30">
            <bib> -----. "The Versification of the Old English Poem 'Phoenix.'" American Journal of
                Philology 15 (1894): 454–68.</bib>
            <notes> Lists of examples of Sievers' Five Types. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J31">
            <bib> Brandeis, Arthur. Die Alliteration in Ælfric's metrischen Homilien. Diss., Vienna,
                1891. 32 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J32">
            <bib> Breitzer, Robert S. "A Stylistic Study of the Old English Metrical Psalms." DAI 31
                (1970): 2867A (Iowa).</bib>
            <notes> Since the OE metrical psalms of the Paris Psalter represent a versified close
                translation of their Latin source, close attention to repeated passages and to al-
                literation (of b in 180 lines) should reveal the poet's characteristic process of
                verse-composition. If a literal rendering of the Latin text did not yield an ac-
                ceptable alliteration, the poet would search for an alliterant adjective or adverb
                which would not change the meaning significantly, or else a cognate synonym,
                compound, or phrase; he would then add the necessary additional alliterants, or
                stresses, to fill out the meter. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J33">
            <bib> Brenner, Oscar. "Zur Verteilung der Reimstäbe in der alliterierende Langzeile."
                PBB 19 (1894): 462–66.</bib>
            <notes> On the correlation of semantic/syntactic breaks with the metrical units.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J34">
            <bib> Bright, James W. "Appendix II: Anglo-Saxon Versification." In his An Anglo-Saxon
                Reader. New York: Henry Holt and Company, 1891</bib>
            <notes>; 2nd ed. 1894; 4th ed. 1917; rev. and enlarged by J. R. Hulbert, 1935. pp.
                229–40. J35 See also "Versification" in Bright's Old English Grammar and Reader. Ed.
                Frederic G. Cassidy and Richard N. Ringler. 3rd ed. New York: Holt, Rinehart and
                Winston, Inc., 1971. pp. 274–88. The most recent version gives a very useful and
                extensive account of Sievers' system (with copious examples) and a brief sketch of
                Pope's. By the way, it may be of interest to know that Professor Bright's large
                collec- tion of German dissertations and other pamphlet publications on Old English
                metrics was posthumously acquired by Duke University, where it is listed as
                Collection Monographs (408 C697). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J36">
            <bib> -----. "Proper Names in Old English Verse." PMLA 14 (1899): 347–68.</bib>
            <notes> The first statement of Bright's theory of "pitch accent"--i.e., that ictus in
                Eng- lish verse, when not created by normal word-stress, is created by increased
                duration (quantity) and sometimes also by pitch. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J37">
            <bib> Bruce, J. Douglas. The Anglo-Saxon Version of the Book of Psalms, Commonly Known
                as the Paris Psalter. Baltimore, 1894.</bib>
            <notes> Textual and literary history; little on versification. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J38">
            <bib> Brüning, E. Die altenglischen metrischen Psalmen in ihren Verhaltnis zur latein
                Vorlage. Diss., Königsberg, 1921.</bib>
            <notes> Cf. Bartlett (J7) and Bruce (J32). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J39">
            <bib> Burchfield, R. W. "The Prosodic Terminology of Anglo-Saxon Scholars." Old English
                Studies in Honour of John C. Pope. Ed. Robert B. Burlin and Edward B. Irving, Jr.
                Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1974. pp. 171–202.</bib>
            <notes> Compilation of OED-style entries for 101 technical terms common to the field of
                Old English versification; the list should be of wider utility, though, since the
                OED was largely finished before the great flood of prosodic work appeared just at
                the turn of the century. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J40">
            <bib> Cable, Thomas. "Clashing Stress in the Meter of Beowulf." Neuphilologische
                Mitteilungen 72 (1971): 42–50</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt in revised form as chapter 5 of his The Meter and Melody of "Beowulf"
                (J42), q.v. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J41">
            <bib> -----. "Constraints on Anacrusis in Old English Meter." MP 69 (1971): 97–104</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt in revised form as chapter 3 of his The Meter and Melody of "Beowulf"
                (J42), q.v. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J42">
            <bib> -----. The Meter and Melody of "Beowulf". Urbana: University of Illinois Press,
                1974. 122 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation at Texas in 1969, "Old English Meter: Problems,
                Principles, and Abstract Form in Beowulf." DAI 30 (1970): 5401A. The heir-apparent
                to Sievers' title, Cable reaffirms then extends the work of the master, accepting
                (initially) the Five Types theory as "real," but also ac- cepting the older view of
                the viergliedrige [four-member] Vers (which Kaluza, Sievers, and other before them
                held). Cable presents a series of six preliminary, discrete arguments refining
                Sievers' Types to a final synthesis of them which attempts to explain what Sievers
                could only describe with his typology, through a single principle which will both
                (1) generate the Five Types and (2) exclude all other possibilities. This principle
                is the postulate that in a four-member verse the first of two clashing stresses must
                always be heavier. Cable is able to show, then, by this and by applying Jespersen's
                notation to the Five Types, that five and only five "contours" are produced: A 1 \ 2
                / 3 \ 4 B 1 / 2 \ 3 / 4 C 1 / 2 \ 3 \ 4 D 1 \ 2 \ 3 \ 4 E 1 \ 2 \ 3 / 4. These
                contours are a refinement of the Five Types, which "are not the meter but the
                inevitable result of the meter, which is a four-unit pattern." Ca- ble hypothesizes
                further that these gradations in the meter must have been sig- naled not by stress
                or timing or length but by pitch; the meter, that is, corre- lates with melody
                rather than rhythm, and the five contours were in fact me- lodic formulae used by
                the scop as accompaniment to his words. This is an in- trepid thesis, backed by an
                argument that is short in length but very incisive. The resolution of its focus is
                remarkable. For critique, however (the only one to appear so far), see Hoover
                (J131). The six arguments which Cable executes in his first six chapters (re-
                spectively) as "minor surgery" to the Five-Types Theory are: (1) OE is not a simple
                stress-meter; the number of weak syllables is not unconstrained; (2) Every verse
                (half-line) must have at least two stresses (Bliss's "light" verses are rejected
                entirely); (3) The most crucial observation about OE meter, preceding even the
                formulation of the Five Types, is that the scop avoided utterly the pattern X / X /
                X ; the meter must screen out this pattern, therefore, since it is very common in OE
                prose; (4) Secondary stress is metrically relevant, espe- cially for a distinction
                between Type E and certain subtypes of Type A; (5) As a general rule, the first of
                two clashing stresses must always be the stronger, es- pecially for Types C and D;
                and (6) Types D2 and E are metrically indistin- guishable and should be combined,
                leading to the wider inference that the verse consists of four and only four glieder
                (members or positions, not syllables). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J43">
            <bib> -----. "Metrical Simplicity and Sievers' Five Types." SP 69 (1972): 280–88</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt in revised form as chapter 6 of his The Meter and Melody of "Beowulf"
                (J42), q.v. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J44">
            <bib> -----. "Parallels to the Melodic Formulas of Beowulf." MP 73 (1975): 1–14.</bib>
            <notes> An interim report from the site of excavation--the tomb of the boy-king?-- where
                the search continues for the historical artifact, treatise, or statement which will
                serve as the linchpin, the unequivocal proof of the theory of me- lodic patterns
                which Cable has hypothesized for Old English verse. No harp has yet been found
                unshattered. But there are certain historical analogues to point to: Gregorian and
                Byzantine chant, Ancient Greek music, Vedic chant. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J45">
            <bib> -----. "Rules for Syntax and Metrics in Beowulf." JEGP 69 (1970): 81–88.</bib>
            <notes> Cable objects to the general principle that the metrical value of a word can al-
                ways be determined by its grammatical category. More specifically, he quarrels with
                S. O. Andrew for believing that adverbs are always metrically stressed and with A.
                J. Bliss, on the other hand, for the converse assumption, which pro- duces his
                "light" lines (also questioned here). As a medial corrective, Cable proposes two
                rules for syntactic structures containing the word þa as adverb and conjunction,
                such that the word may be metrically variable--either stressed or
                unstressed--according to its syntactic context. Thus the absolutism of each extreme
                is avoided, and the rules turn out to have greater conceptual elegance in terms of
                simplicity, consistency, and scope. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J46">
            <bib> Campbell, Jackson J. "Oral Poetry in The Seafarer." Speculum 35 (1960):
                87–96.</bib>
            <notes> Oral-formulaic studies: reply by O'Neil (J226). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J47">
            <bib> Cassidy, Frederic G. "How Free Was the Anglo-Saxon Scop?" Franciplegius: Medieval
                and Linguistic Studies in Honor of F. P. Magoun, Jr. Ed. Jess B. Bessinger and R. P.
                Creed. New York: New York University Press, 1965. pp. 75–85.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J48">
            <bib> Charitius, Franz. "über die angelsächsischen Gedichte vom heiligen Guthlac."
                Anglia 2 (1879): 265–308.</bib>
            <notes> Deriving his metrical typology from Horn (L400), Charitius examines the na- ture
                (simple or compound) and position of alliterants for evidence as to authorship.
                Criticized by Lefèvre (J159). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J49">
            <bib> Christiani, Brigitte. Zwillingsverbindungen in der altenglischen Dichtung. Diss.,
                Königs- berg, 1938. Würzburg: Konrad Triltsch, 1938. 75 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Chapter 3 discusses the metrical aspects of the variation-technique in word-
                pairing. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J50">
            <bib> Clemoes, Peter. Rhythm and Cosmic Order in Old English Christian Literature.
                London: Cambridge University Press, 1970. 28 pp.</bib>
            <notes> In his inaugural lecture the author touches upon the mirroring or enactment in
                rhythm of (1) inner truths, via "memorable synthesis," in the Dream of the Rood, (2)
                "outward pattern" or logical structure in Christ II, and (3) a funda- mental
                principle of analogy (form to thought, human orderings to divine Or- der) in the
                prose of Ælfric and Wulfstan. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J51">
            <bib> Clemons, Elinor D. "A Metrical Analysis of the Old English Poem Exodus." DA 22
                (1962): 3652A (Texas).</bib>
            <notes> A metrical index, based on Bliss (J20), with some slight modifications of his
                procedure for placing the caesura, the result of which is reformulation of some of
                his subtypes. Discussion of problem scansions, tables of distribution of types.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J52">
            <bib> Coffey, Jerome E. "The Evolution of an Oral-Formulaic Tradition in Old and Middle
                English Alliterative Verse." DAI 30 (1969): 2477A (S.U.N.Y. at Buffalo).</bib>
            <notes> Positing "the intonational contour and its metrical equivalent the cadence
                foot," as the basic unit of OE versification and a correlate to the lexical for-
                mula, Coffey analyzes "Caedmon's Hymn" and parts of Beowulf, Fates of the Apostles,
                The Battle of Maldon, Sir Gawain, and the Morte Arthure both metrically and
                formulaically, concluding therefrom that the Parry-Lord thesis that fea- tures of
                both oral and literate composition cannot appear in the same text is disproved by
                these transitional, mixed texts in Old and Middle English. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J53">
            <bib> Conlee, John W. "A Note on Verse Composition in the Meters of Boethius."
                Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 71 (1970): 576–85.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J54">
            <bib> Conner, Patrick W. "Schematization of Oral-Formulaic Processes in Old English
                Poetry." Language and Style 5 (1972): 204–20.</bib>
            <notes> The "filtering" effect (my term not Conner's) of the alliterative meter on the
                selection of lexical collocations is discussed on p. 215 ff. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J55">
            <bib> Conybeare, John Josias. "Introductory Essay on the Metre of Anglo-Saxon Poetry."
                Archaeologia 17 (1814): 257–74</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt in his Illustrations of Anglo-Saxon Poetry. Ed. W. D. Conybeare. London:
                Harding and Lepard, 1826. pp. iii–lxxv. The first three papers are reprinted from
                Archaeologia; the last four are additions by the author's brother William.
                Conybeare's view is essentially that Old English verse is written in a meter based
                on emphasis rather than quantity, a meter which measures the line in feet which
                begin with stresses--i.e., a trochaic- dactylic meter. He also recognizes the
                importance of alliteration and parallelism as indispensable structural elements. The
                verse is set as hemistichs, though, rather than as the full lines familiar to us,
                Conybeare thinking the question merely one of typography. In the four essays added
                posthumously, William sur- veys Icelandic, Scandinavian, Germanic, and Celtic meters
                (this latter receives the fullest treatment), finding them congruent with
                Anglo-Saxon; he concludes with a chapter on Middle English alliterative verse up to
                Piers Plowman. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J56">
            <bib> Cook, Albert S. "Beowulf 1422." MLN 39 (1924): 77–82.</bib>
            <notes> The practice of rhyming, both within and between lines, the Beowulf-poet seems
                to have derived from contemporary Latin poetry, particularly Aldhelm's De
                Virginitate. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J57">
            <bib> Cosmos, Spencer J. "The Evolution of Old English Meter." DAI 32 (1972): 4589A
                (Illinois).</bib>
            <notes> Old English meter, unlike Modern English, must be defined "in terms of other
                phonological levels than the phonetic," levels such as the syntactic and seman- tic,
                to be fully intelligible. Its "output," to speak in Cosmos's transformational terms,
                was simultaneously the formulae of oral composition and the stress- schemata of the
                meter. Syllable-counting, which is so evident in Eddic and Scaldic verse, in Otfrid,
                and in the medieval Latin hymn-meters, is alien to the native Old English metrical
                system and only appears in the later OE poetic monuments under the influence of
                Latin. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J58">
            <bib> -----. "Kuhn's Law and the Unstressed Verbs in Beowulf." Texas Studies in
                Literature and Language 18 (1976): 306–28.</bib>
            <notes> A major re-assessment of the validity and adequacy of Kuhn's Law of Sentence
                Particles in the terms of modern linguistic theory shows convincingly that the
                problem of unstressed finite verbs is much more adequately accounted for in terms of
                utterance analysis and "communicative dynamism" [i.e., the extent to which a given
                word "propels" the sense of the sentence forward partly deter- mines the
                phonological prominence of that word] than via the older gram- matical (word-class)
                approach, which is finally not very helpful. Distinguishing between "lexical and
                nonlexical verb roots," Cosmos shows that "the finite forms of lexical verbs
                normally occur in positions of metrical ictus in Beowulf, that nonlexical verbs, on
                the other hand, occur in metrically stressed positions only under very specific
                circumstances, and finally that unstressed lexical verbs occur as a function of very
                general principles of utterance organization." An outstanding study. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J59">
            <bib> Creed, Robert P. "The andswarode-System in Old English Poetry." Speculum 32
                (1957): 523–28.</bib>
            <notes> On the formula for "answered (him)." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J60">
            <bib> -----. "The Making of an Anglo-Saxon Poem." ELH 26 (1959): 445–54.</bib>
            <notes> An anatomy of four lines from Beowulf reveals those components of the for-
                mulaic phrase which propel us forward, syntactically and semantically, as op- posed
                to the other components, which fill the alliterative requirements. Com- parison with
                similar formulae shows just how supple the system was for the scop. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J61">
            <bib> -----. "A New Approach to the Rhythm of Beowulf." PMLA 81 (1966): 23–33.</bib>
            <notes> Repeated attempts to find a metrical system sufficiently simple as to be work-
                able for schoolroom use lead the author to devise a more (conceptually) ele- gant
                codification of Pope's obstreperous system (J242), in fact a model with only six
                types of measures: alpha: / X gamma: / \ X epsilon: (/) X beta: / X \ delta: / (X)
                alpha prime: / \ . These correspond to the Sievers Types thus: Creed Sievers alpha +
                alpha A1 epsilon + beta B epsilon + gamma C delta + gamma Da delta + beta Db gamma +
                delta E epsilon + alpha A3. Creed can give four relatively simple rules for finding
                the primary stresses and measure boundaries, and a fifth for resolution. Two
                measures make a verse. Notice that the delta type is actually an alpha with the weak
                syllable re- placed by a rest or harpbeat; similarly, the epsilon is an alpha with a
                harpbeat for the stress. The six types may then be classed into two groups, beta and
                gamma comprising Group II and the other four Group I. The possibility of trisyllabic
                substitution in each position can then be shown to obtain in the measures of Group
                I, but not of Group II. A simple and efficient account of the conditions for
                anacrusis is also then possible. See also L744. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J62">
            <bib> -----. "On the Possibility of Criticizing Old English Poetry." Texas Studies in
                Literature and Language 3 (1961): 97–106.</bib>
            <notes> A prominent student of oral-formulaic composition in Old English verse con-
                fronts the ultimate question in such studies: how can "a tissue of formulas" be
                judged a great work of art? Or, better: "what kinds of excellence are possible in an
                art built on formulas?" The answer may lie in the fact that no two instances of use
                of the same formula are ever precisely the same: the real effect is one of
                similarity-within-difference, and we may expect that at the point where the audience
                recognized the appearance of a distinctive formula they set it, more or less
                instantaneously, within the context of all the other instances of the same theme in
                other stories, hearing the echoes, seeing the differentia. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J63">
            <bib> Cremer, Matthias. Metrische und sprachliche Untersuchung der altenglischen
                Gedichte "Andreas," "Guthlac," "Phoenix" ("Elene," "Judith," "Christ"): Ein Beiträg
                zur Cynewulfrage. Diss., Bonn, 1888. 51 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Follows Frucht (J90) and Luick (J180) in extending the Sievers analysis to the
                remaining OE poems in order to affirm its validity. Cremer concludes on metrical
                grounds that Guthlac A and Phoenix are definitely not by Cynewulf, and on linguistic
                grounds against Andreas also; Guthlac B he concludes is defi- nitely Cynewulf's
                work. See Mather (J201). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J64">
            <bib> Cygan, Jan. "A Critique of the Sieversian Theory of Old Germanic Alliterative
                Verse." Germanica Wratislaviensia 12 (1968): 147–60.</bib>
            <notes> Foolish enough to describe the Sieversian Five Types typology as "complicated .
                . . not too clear . . . difficult to grasp . . . inconsistent," Cygan merely lauds
                the alternative formula devised by Jerzy Kurylowicz (L451), the fully expanded form
                of the hemistich, denoted X / X / X . Neither alliteration nor secon- dary stresses
                is relevant to the metrical formula of the hemistich, Cygan argues, and Sievers'
                "expanded" types may be eliminated if one additional type (F), having the formula X
                / / , is added to the typology; Kurylowicz's fully ex- panded model produces six
                species of half-line. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J65">
            <bib> Dahlstedt, August. Rhythm and Word Order in Anglo-Saxon and Semi-Saxon. Diss.,
                Lund, 1901. 246 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J66">
            <bib> Dailey, Virginia L. "A Metrical Analysis of the Old English Poem Juliana." DA 24
                (1964): 2898A (Texas).</bib>
            <notes> A metrical index, based on Bliss (J20), and Clemon's (J51) modifications of
                Bliss, along with discussion and tables showing the distribution of verse-types.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J67">
            <bib> Daunt, Marjorie. "Old English Verse and English Speech Rhythm." Transactions of
                the Philological Society, 1946, pp. 56–72</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt in Essential Articles for the Study of Old English Poetry. Ed. Jess B.
                Bessinger and Stanley J. Kahrl. Hamden, Conn.: Archon Books, 1968. pp. 289–304. Of
                all the theories about OE meter Daunt's--that it isn't meter--is the most radical.
                Her claim is that "Old English verse is really conditioned prose," so that Sievers'
                Five Types are "language patterns, not metrical patterns." That is, the types
                correspond to natural OE phrasal-stress patterns and, in fact, to Mod- ern English
                ones as well; the types can be found easily in OE prose, in Shake- speare, in Modern
                English speech, and in jingles. [But to say that OE poetry "was made with pieces of
                language" is one thing, and to say that such making is therefore not metering is
                quite another. It would be strange if a meter were not intimately engaged
                with--embedded in--its language. No meter the order or elements of which is alien to
                the language survives for long.] </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J68">
            <bib> -----. "Some Modes of Anglo-Saxon Meaning." In Memory of J. R. Firth. Ed. C. E.
                Bazell et al. London: Longmans, Green and Co., 1966. pp. 66–78.</bib>
            <notes> Some observations in sections 3 and 4 worthy of further research: the distinc-
                tion between verse and prose (their ends, uses) was radically different for the
                Anglo-Saxons from what it is for us; we ought to pay attention to the sense- group
                not the half-line or line; if we classify verse-types and then note their
                distribution in sense-groups, significant patterns appear; different OE poems show
                idiosyncratic preferences in alliteration; there is a tendency to continue
                alliteration into groups longer than the line; the Anglian characteristics of Beo-
                wulf merit further study; the last non-alliterating stress in a line sometimes
                "picks up" the alliteration in the next full line; and sometimes the non-
                alliterating stresses of two lines also happen to alliterate. Preliminary statistics
                for most of these features. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J69">
            <bib> Derolez, René. "Anglo-Saxon Literature: 'Attic' or 'Asiatic'? Old English Poetry
                and Its Latin Background." English Studies Today: Second Series. Ed. G. A. Bonnard.
                Bern: Francke, 1961. pp. 93–105.</bib>
            <notes> Includes a discussion of rhyme (also alliteration) in Aldhelm, Aethewald, and
                Cynewulf (pp. 98–103). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J70">
            <bib> Deutschbein, Max. Zur Entwicklung des englischen Alliterationsverses. Diss.,
                Leipzig. Halle: Ehrhardt Karras, 1902.</bib>
            <notes> 42 pp. of text + 10 pp. of Appendix and 17 pp. of Tables. A student of Luick's,
                Deutschbein determines to follow his views "in every particular." His analysis of
                prosodic patterns is designed to prove the essential continuity of the alliterative
                tradition from early OE into ME even despite significant changes in structure. He
                identifies several principles of metrical style in AV, e.g. a close connection
                between meter and sound (enjambment and plurilinear alliteration (Sievers'
                "hakenstil") and a "Crescendo-Descrescendo" pattern of sound over the line. A long
                Appendix gives statistical tables showing the distribution of Sievers' Types in the
                first and second verses of four representative alliterative poems. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J71">
            <bib> Diamond, Celia B. "Alliterative Figurations, Syntax, and Meaning in Old English
                Poetry." DAI 31 (1971): 5395A (Pennsylvania).</bib>
            <notes> Discriminates nine varieties of alliterative patterning (repeated, alternating,
                en- jambed, and six others, including "rhythmic linking") and four stylistic func-
                tions (structure marking, theme marking, rhetorical heightening and poetic
                heightening). And five specific features of sound-patterning which create a
                distinctive style in Genesis A are noted. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J72">
            <bib> Diamond, Robert E. "The Diction of the Old English Christ." Anglo-Saxon Poetry:
                Essays in Appreciation for John C. McGalliard. Ed. Lewis E. Nicholson and D. E.
                Frese. Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame Press, 1975. pp. 301–11.</bib>
            <notes> A very salient and emphatic reminder that the study of formulaic diction has
                legitimacy only when it gives "scrupulous attention to metrics" as well. Such a
                joint analysis, brought to bear on the question of the authorship of Christ, pro-
                duces evidence for believing that Cynewulf wrote the second part but not parts one
                and three. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J73">
            <bib> Douglas-Lithgow, R. A. "Anglo-Saxon Alliterative Poetry: (A.D. 449 to A.D. 1150)."
                Transactions of the Royal Society of Literature, series 2, vol. 15 (1893), pp.
                178–220.</bib>
            <notes> Mainly literary history: all the examples are the author's translations. His
                allit- eration rules are from Guest (E543) and Conybeare (J55). See K91 and C136.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J74">
            <bib> Dubs, Kathleen E. "Genesis B: A Stylistic Analysis." DAI 35 (1975): 7863A
                (Iowa).</bib>
            <notes> Some notes on versification (hypermetric lines and alliteration) appear near the
                end. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J75">
            <bib> Ehrstine, John W. "Patterns of Sound in Anglo-Saxon Poetry." Research Studies of
                the State College of Washington 33 (1965): 151–62.</bib>
            <notes> It is astounding to realize how little work has been done on sonal patterning
                other than structural alliteration in Old English poetry. Clearly such patterns are
                significant. Ehrstine identifies (not very clearly) six varieties of "sub-
                alliteration": (1) repetition of weak prefixes, and "crossed alliteration"; (2) as-
                sonantal and consonantal repetition within the line; (3) a minor sound is pat-
                terned then (noticed? and) picked up as the main alliteration; (4) larger pat-
                terns; (5) very similar sounds (e.g. m-n) in adjacent lines; and (6) ornamental
                clustering of a non-structural alliteration within a half-line. Cf. Conner (J54).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J76">
            <bib> Einenkel, E[ugen]. "Sermo Lupi ad Anglos: Ein Gedicht." Anglia Anzeiger 7 (1884):
                200–3.</bib>
            <notes> Also: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J77">
            <bib> -----. "Die metrische Frage." Anglia 17 (1894–95): 407–8.</bib>
            <notes> See J317. Einenkel, a follower of Trautmann, argues in these essays that Wulf-
                stan's work is in Otfrid's verseform--four-beat half-line couplets. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J78">
            <bib> Emerson, Oliver F. "Transverse Alliteration in Teutonic Poetry." Journal of
                Germanic Philology [after 1902, JEGP] 3 (1900): 127–37.</bib>
            <notes> Criticized by C. M. Lewis (J170). The received opinion that transverse allit-
                eration (abab rather than the usual aaax) was not an intentional device in OE verse
                composition was promulgated by Sievers, who took it from Frucht, who based his
                rejection on analysis of the mathematical probabilities. But Emerson shows that
                analysis to be not only incorrectly done but in fact wholly inappli- cable by its
                nature to the problem at hand. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J79">
            <bib> Evans, Patricia M. "Oral Interpretation in Anglo-Saxon England." DA 18 (1958):
                1145A (Northwestern).</bib>
            <notes> Useful for background information. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J80">
            <bib> Fakundiny, Lydia. "The Art of Old English Verse Composition." Review of English
                Studies n.s. 21 (1970): 129–43, 257–66.</bib>
            <notes> When Sievers set about to give a general account of the relation of metrical
                stressing to syntax in OE verse he sorted the various parts of speech into three
                classes--always-stressed (substantives, etc.), variable (verbs, adverbs), and
                rarely- stressed (prolitics, pronouns, etc.). Kuhn's Law of Sentence Particles also
                treated these latter two classes. But a much more systematic and detailed ex-
                amination of Class III-forms than that given by either Sievers or Kuhn reveals that
                their rules are not only unreasonably rigid but also "in part erroneous and
                genuinely misleading." These lesser sentential elements "offer so much range in
                position and metrical value as to impart that variety and liveliness of expression
                which raise mere versification to compositional art." Cf. Stanley (J300). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J81">
            <bib> Fijn van Draat, P. "The Authorship of the Old English Bede: A Study in Rhythm."
                Anglia 39 (1915): 319–46.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J82">
            <bib> -----. "The Cursus in Old English Poetry." Anglia 38 (1914): 377–404.</bib>
            <notes> Opposing the views of Shelly (D260) and Clark (D206), the author undertakes to
                show that the medieval cursus exerted a distinct influence on the rhythmical
                groupings of Old English poetry. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J83">
            <bib> Foley, John M. "A Computer Analysis of Metrical Patterns in Beowulf." Computers
                and the Humanities 12 (1978): 71–80.</bib>
            <notes> A revised and expanded version of J84. Foley and Creed's programmed search for
                metrical formulas underlying lexical formulas produces a set of three Para- digms
                which account for 94% of the lines in Beowulf and represent only "sim- ple
                variations on a single metrical idea." The scansion is based on Creed's (J61) system
                of six metrical types, four measures to the line: PASTE IN TABLE All the Paradigms
                are reversible. The first one alone accounts for 52% of the lines in Beowulf. The
                analysis also suggests strongly that the line not the half-line was the unit of
                metrical composition for the Beowulf-poet. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J84">
            <bib> ----. "Formula and Theme in Old English Poetry." Oral Literature and the Formula.
                Ed. Benjamin A. Stolz and R. S. Shannon. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Center
                for the Coordination of Ancient and Modern Studies, 1976. pp. 207–32.</bib>
            <notes> Response and discussion follow, pp. 233–38. Adopting the scansion-system of
                Creed (J61)--three degrees of stress, seven types of measure, four measures to the
                line--Foley formulates three general Paradigms for line-construction. Computer
                analysis shows high frequencies of one or the other of these in certain passages.
                Similar analysis applies to the- matic structures. But more important is Foley's
                argument that the metrical frame precedes, both logically and empirically, the
                formulaic-phrase linking the construction of the narrative. Note Kuhn's metrical
                criticisms, p. 233. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J85">
            <bib> Foster, T[homas] Gregory. "Judith": Studies in Metre, Language and Style, With a
                View to Determining the Date of the Old English Fragment and the Home of Its Author.
                Quellen Und Forschungen, no. 71. Strassburg: Karl J. Trübner, 1892. 103 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Pages 13–48 of Part I treat (1) alliteration, (2) rhyme, (3) hypermetrical
                verses, and (4) miscellaneous metrical matters (caesura-placement, stress-shifts,
                defec- tive lines), giving analysis of varieties, frequencies of occurrence,
                comparison with most of the other major OE poems, and general discussion. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J86">
            <bib> Fowler, Roger. "The Rhythm of Beowulf--A Review." In Fowler (A12), pp.
                178–83.</bib>
            <notes> A very incisive critique of Pope (J242): his musical notation is not a system
                available to a harp-player, so the appended hypothesis of the harp should be ignored
                as "speculation" in evaluating the theory; Pope also fails to distinguish verse
                design from verse instance--his system of types is far too "delicate." However, "it
                would be possible now to overhaul the whole theory and make it more powerful without
                destroying the spirit of the original reading." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J87">
            <bib> -----. "Some Stylistic Patterns of the Sermo Lupi." JEGP 65 (1966): 1–18</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt in Fowler (A12), pp. 200–18. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J88">
            <bib> Frey, Charles. "Lyric in Epic: Hrothgar's Depiction of the Haunted Mere (Beowulf
                1357b–76a)." English Studies 58 (1977): 296–303.</bib>
            <notes> To show significant connections between meter and syntax, and sound and sense,
                Frey (1) scans the entire passage by Pope's system, which reveals the startling
                existence of four C-A-C type patterns (off-verse / on-verse / off- verse) marking
                the four descents into the water, and (2) discerns a kind of se- mantic end-rhyme,
                some alliterative intensification, and sonal mimesis in the passage. Translation
                follows. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J89">
            <bib> Fritzsche, Arthur. "Das angelsächsische Gedicht Andreas und Cynewulf." Anglia 2
                (1879): 441–96.</bib>
            <notes> Meter is discussed on pp. 468–72. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J90">
            <bib> Frucht, Philipp. Metrisches und Sprachliches zu Cynewulfs "Elene," "Juliana," und
                "Crist". Diss., Greifswald, 1887. 99 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Extends the Sievers system, demonstrating its applicability to the works of Cy-
                newulf. Cf. Cremer (J63). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J91">
            <bib> Fry, Donald K. "Old English Formulas and Systems." English Studies 48 (1967): 193–
                204.</bib>
            <notes> Milman Parry's classic definition of the oral formula has come under consider-
                able fire for vagueness, and Fry, after a careful review of the scholarship, pro-
                poses that the crucial concept be shifted from formula to system (of formulae),
                which he defines as "a group of half-lines, usually related metrically and se-
                mantically, which are related in form by the identical relative placement of two
                elements, one a variable word or element of a compound usually supply- ing the
                alliteration, and the other a constant word or element of a compound, with
                approximately the same distribution of non-stressed elements." The re- vised
                definition, one sees, isolates the imprecision of the original more pre- cisely.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J92">
            <bib> -----. "Some Aesthetic Implications of a New Definition of the Formula."
                Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 69 (1968): 516–22.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J93">
            <bib> Frye, Prosser H. "The Translation of Beowulf." MLN 12 (1897): cols. 157–63.</bib>
            <notes> Champions blank verse as the proper verseform for translation into modern
                English. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J94">
            <bib> Funke, Otto. "Some Remarks on Wulfstan's Prose Rhythm." English Studies 43 (1962):
                311–18.</bib>
            <notes> Cf. McIntosh (J184). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J95">
            <bib> -----. "Studien zur alliterenden und rhythmisierenden Prosa in der älteren
                altenglischen Homiletik." Anglia 80 (1962): 9–36.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J96">
            <bib> -----. "Zur Rhythmik des altenglischen Alliterationsverses: Eine kurze
                Betrachtung." Anglia 76 (1958): 60–63.</bib>
            <notes> A concise and convenient comparison of the three principal modern theories of OE
                meter, Sievers, Heusler, and Pope. Funke notes that though Heusler ac- cepted
                Sievers' view that the poetry was recited not sung, there are differences between
                them, especially concerning "contractions." The differences between Heusler's system
                and Pope's modification of it is that Heusler considers the anacrusis extrametrical,
                while Pope includes it in the meter. This slight shift has enormous consequences
                rhythmically. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J97">
            <bib> Furkert, Friedrich G. M. Der syntaktische Gebrauch des Verbums in dem
                angelsächsischen Gedichte vom Heiligen Guthlac; ein Beitrag zur angelsächsischen
                Grammatik. Diss., Leipzig, 1889. 59 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J98">
            <bib> Garnett, James M. "The Translation of Anglo-Saxon Poetry." PMLA 6 (1891): 95–
                105.</bib>
            <notes> The proper verseform for translating Old English is a four-stress line, with
                free variation in unstressed syllables and the alliteration preserved wherever
                possible without wrenching of the sense. Garnett supports the zweihebungstheorie.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J99">
            <bib> Gattiker, Godfrey L. "The Syntactic Basis of the Poetic Formula in Beowulf." DAI
                23 (1962): 2114A (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> Regardless of whether or not the verses of Beowulf show formulaic (lexical)
                structure, they conform to a simpler underlying paradigm of syntactic identity
                containing 29 syntactic verse-formulae. The scop's formulaic lexicon, it seems, is
                derived from a formulaic syntax/verse-structure. Five of these 29 syntactic
                patterns, all of which are based on the syntactic relation of the two words in the
                verse bearing primary stress, occur over 400 times each (in 3500 verses) in Beowulf.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J100">
            <bib> Gerould, Gordon H. "Abbot Ælfric's Rhythmic Prose." MP 22 (1925): 353–66.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J101">
            <bib> -----. "Studies in the Christ." Englische Studien 41 (1909): 1–19.</bib>
            <notes> Trautmann's view (see J317) is censured in "Metre," pp. 11–15. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J102">
            <bib> Goebel, Julius. "Zur Vorgeschichte der Sieversschen Typentheorie." Anglia 19
                (1897): 499–508.</bib>
            <notes> Attempts to show that Sievers' Five Types were recognized--though not very
                clearly--by Lachmann a half-century earlier. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J103">
            <bib> Gomme, G. Laurence. "Rhythmical Laws." The Antiquary 8 (1883): 12–15. Reply by Fry
                on pp. 164–66.</bib>
            <notes> On early English laws, wills, and charters commonly set in verse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J104">
            <bib> Gradon, Pamela. "Cynewulf's 'Elene' and Old English Prosody." English and Germanic
                Studies 2 (1948–49): 10–19.</bib>
            <notes> A better system than Sievers' Five Types of verses (half-lines) would be a
                treatment which takes the whole line as the unit, the "feet" of which "form
                rhythmical patterns essentially the same as those which form the basis of Mod- ern
                English verse." Nine such patterns are isolated, mainly trochaic-dactylic, which is
                also the rhythm of Elene. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J105">
            <bib> Graz, Friedrich. Die Metrik der sog. Caedmonischen Dichtungen mit Berücksichtigung
                der Verfasserfrage. I: Die Metrik des "Exodus." Diss., Königsberg, 1894. Weimar: E.
                Felber, 1894. 109 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Anzeiger für deutsches Alterum 23 (1897): 40–54; in Anglia Beiblatt 6
                (1895–96): 1–4; in Englische Studien 22 (1896): 74–75. Simply applies the metrical
                system of his director Kaluza, listing examples of the 90 metrical subtypes, then
                discussing the alliteration and the question of authorship. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J106">
            <bib> Green, Donald C. "Formulas and Syntax in Old English Poetry: A Computer Study."
                Computers and the Humanities 6 (1971): 85–93.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation at Wisconsin in 1967, "The Syntax of Poetic Formula in
                a Cross-Section of Old English Poetry." DA 28 (1967): 629A. Describes in detail a
                computerized study of about half the extant corpus of Old English poetry in search
                of a workably small number of syntactic (not seman- tic) formulas used to compose
                half-lines of verse. Earlier studies (Magoun, Creed, C. Diamond) had shown no strong
                case for oral composition by se- mantic formulas, but the small size of Sievers'
                metrical formulas (five) suggested to other researchers (O'Neil, Gattiker) that a
                similar set of syntactic formulas might exist. Green finds that only six syntactic
                types will account for about 60% of the verses, a conclusion which significantly
                confirms the hypothesis. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J107">
            <bib> Greenfield, Stanley B. "The Canons of Old English Criticism." ELH 34 (1967):
                141–55.</bib>
            <notes> Criticism of the oral-formulaic approach. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J108">
            <bib> -----. "Grendel's Approach to Heorot: Syntax and Poetry." Old English Poetry:
                Fifteen Essays. Ed. Robert P. Creed. Providence, R.I.: Brown University Press, 1967.
                pp. 275–84.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J109">
            <bib> -----. The Interpretation of Old English Poems. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan
                Paul, 1972.</bib>
            <notes> A discursive "handbook" of expressive effects attainable in OE verse; chapter 5
                treat the relation of syntax to meaning (verseform is mentioned only briefly),
                chapter 2 formulae and diction, chapter 3 variation, and chapter 4 ambiguity and the
                various relations of phonology to semantics. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J110">
            <bib> -----. "Some Remarks on the Nature and Quality of Old English Poetry." A Critical
                History of Old English Literature. New York: New York University Press, 1965; rpt
                1968. pp. 69–79.</bib>
            <notes> An elementary account of meter, lexical collocations, and oral formulae.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J111">
            <bib> -----. "Syntactic Analysis and Old English Poetry." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen
                64 (1963): 373–78.</bib>
            <notes> Analyzes one sentence in The Wanderer. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J112">
            <bib> Greg, W. W. "The 'Five Types' in Anglo-Saxon Verse." MLR 20 (1925): 12–17.</bib>
            <notes> Not a rejection but a reformulation of Sievers' Five Types so as to show all the
                "abstractly possible mutations of a two-stressed group," a complete typology being
                the first step toward explaining why the types that appear appear and those that
                don't don't. Greg wants to show that these particular types, and these particular
                five types, are not simply arbitrary, or even the descendant spe- cies of an earlier
                Germanic genus of verseform, but simply the natural varieties which would be
                expected to occur, given the linguistic conditions. See the supplementary
                observations by E. V. Gordon in The Year's Work in English Studies, vol. 6 (1925),
                pp. 75–77. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J113">
            <bib> Grissemann, Anna. Metrisch-stilistische Untersuchungen zum "Beowulf". Diss.,
                Innsbruck, 1922.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J114">
            <bib> Gummere, Francis B. "The Translation of Beowulf, and the Relations of Ancient and
                Modern English Verse." American Journal of Philology 7 (1886): 46–78. See also C. G.
                Child's letter in MLN 20 (1905): 157–58.</bib>
            <notes> In the midst of an argument that the only adequate form for translating Anglo-
                Saxon verse is a direct imitation of the features of the alliterative meter (blank
                verse is too modern, intellectual, and literary, and ballad-meter and simple
                stress-meter are alien), appears an altogether extraordinary digression (pp. 53–
                70), in which Gummere broaches the whole question of the early evolution of English
                verse. Following the map laid down by Schipper, he undertakes to show that English
                verse-structure "is simply the result of forcing the iambic pentameter movement
                (influence of foreign models played its part here) upon some late form of our old
                four-stress verse." The older four beats, in short, can still be heard under the
                more recent five. Recent research has suggested that this view is wrong, possibly
                entirely wrong, and if so, one is led to confront head-on the huge question of what
                the history (nature) of our verse really was (is). Gummere also gives close
                attention to Spenser's Shepheardes Calendar. ---- Halle, Morris, and Samuel J.
                Keyser. "Old English Alliterative Verse." See E777, pp. 147–64. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J115">
            <bib> Hamrick, William R. "The Prosody of Old English Hypermetrics: An Analysis." DA 28
                (1967): 1418A (Brown).</bib>
            <notes> An elaboration of Creed's theory of hypermetric verses (J61), which is a re-
                finement of Pope's (J242), with application to the expanded verses in The Dream of
                the Rood. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J116">
            <bib> Harmatiuk, Sandra J. "A Statistical Approach to Some Aspects of Style in the
                Signed Poems of Cynewulf: A Computer-Assisted Study." DAI 36 (1975): 1492A (Notre
                Dame).</bib>
            <notes> Analyzes the distribution of word-classes and types of clauses within the sen-
                tence. The results show a distinct stylistic difference between Juliana and the
                other Cynewulfian poems. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J117">
            <bib> Hart, Thomas E. "Beowulf: A Study of the Tectonic Structures and Patterns." DA 28
                (1967): 631A (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> Argues for a justification of the 44 fits of manuscript division, based on fit-
                groups in regular multiples of 330 and 290 lines. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J118">
            <bib> Heath, H. Frank. "The Old English Alliterative Line." Transactions of the
                Philological Society, 1893, pp. 375–95.</bib>
            <notes> An exposition of the theory of (his former teacher) Ten Brink. Therein, the
                verse consists of four beats, each of two "morès" of the form x / . The "Fun-
                damental Type" for the full verse then is (x) // x / (x) // x /. with four
                Variations: (x) / x // x // x / (x) / x // x / x // (x) // x / x / x // (x) // x //
                x / x / and adjustments for catalexis and anacrusis. His view of the latter is
                curious: he seems to think that the extrametrical member is appended to the end of
                the a- verse but to the beginning of the b-verse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J119">
            <bib> Hertel, Bruno. Der syntaktische Gebrauch des Verbums in dem angelsächsischen
                Gedichte "Christ". Diss., Leipzig, 1891. 52 pp.</bib>
            <notes> ---- Heusler, Andreas. Deutsche Versgeschichte. See L387. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J120">
            <bib> -----. "Sievers und die Sprachmelodie." Deutsche Literaturzeitung 33 (1912): cols.
                1477–86.</bib>
            <notes> Doubts the objectivity of the melodic patterns Sievers finds in verse (L604).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J121">
            <bib> Hickes, George. Institutiones Grammaticae Anglo-Saxonicae et Moeso-Gothicae.
                Oxford: Sheldonian Theater, 1689.</bib>
            <notes> The eighteen chapters in the first edition of Hickes' Anglo-Saxon grammar are
                expanded to twenty-four in Part One of the second, i.e.: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J122">
            <bib> -----. Linguarum vett. septentrionalium Thesaurus Grammatico-Criticus et
                Archaelogicus. . . . Oxford: Sheldonian Theater, 1705.</bib>
            <notes> Two (sometimes three) very large folio volumes. See chapters 23 and 24, "De
                Poetica Anglo-Saxonum" and "De Poetica Semi-Saxonica," pp. 177–235. A redaction of
                Hickes's work was subsequently written by William Wotton: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J123">
            <bib> Linguarum vett. septentrionalium Thesauri grammatico-critici et archaeologici,
                auctore G. Hickesio, conspectus Brevis. . . . London, 1708,</bib>
            <notes> which was thereafter translated from the Latin into English by Maurice Shelton
                as: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J124">
            <bib> Wotton's Short View of George Hickes's Grammatico-Critical and Archeological
                Treasure of the Ancient Northern-Languages. London, 1735; 2nd ed. 1737. (Here see
                pp. 17– 18).</bib>
            <notes> Hickes's opus is the first full grammar of Old English published in English. His
                view of OE meter, unfortunately, was that it was determined by quantities as in the
                classical languages. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J125">
            <bib> Hieatt, Constance B. "Alliterative Patterns in the Hypermetric Lines of Old
                English Verse." MP 71 (1974): 237–42.</bib>
            <notes> A recalculation of the incidence of transverse, double, and triple alliteration
                in the hypermetric lines of the six OE poems where they appear most promi- nently
                reveals that "more than ten times as many verses as those Pope lists show crossed or
                transverse alliteration." Single alliteration is rare. But to treat these lines as
                Pope and Bliss do--i.e., as having regular measures supplemented by a longer
                "opening" or "close"--will wreck the alliteration when these outer members are
                removed. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J126">
            <bib> -----. "A New Theory of Triple Rhythm in the Hypermetric Lines of Old English
                Verse." MP 67 (1969): 1–8.</bib>
            <notes> Creed and Pope's treatment of hypermetric verses as "double time" measures leads
                to several kinds of unsatisfactory results, such as overweighting. But if we treat
                them as having three stresses (and measures) instead of two in each half- line,
                these difficulties will be removed and certain other regular features will become
                evident: (1) there are no more than four syllables in any measure; (2) double
                alliteration is frequent in the on-verse; (3) the first stress in the off-verse is
                regularly non-alliterative; and (4) the effect on tempo is to quicken the opening of
                the verse but weight its end. In any event there does seem to be a distinct
                rhythmical shift in the hypermetrical passages. That such lines are in fact
                clustered is some additional support for distinguishing them. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J127">
            <bib> -----. "Prosodic Analysis of Old English Poetry: A Suggested Working Approach with
                Sample Applications." Revue de l'Université d'Ottawa 42 (1972): 72–82.</bib>
            <notes> Praxis: it is easier to teach OE meter to students by moving from Creed through
                Pope to Sievers than vice versa. She also suggests that the hypermetri- cal lines be
                read as in triple rhythm rather than duple, three measures to the verse; such
                measures could then be scanned normally. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J128">
            <bib> Hirt, Herman. Untersuchungen zur westgermanischen Verskunst. I: Kritik der neueren
                Theorien Metrik des Angelsächsischen. Diss., Leipzig, 1889. 83 pp.</bib>
            <notes> The theory criticized is that by Sievers. Though Hirt stands mainly within the
                vierhebungstheorie school, he believes that each verse has three stresses rather
                than four, three being obligatory in the b-verse but sometimes alternating with four
                in the a-verse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J129">
            <bib> Hoffmann, Otto. Reimformeln im Westgermanischen. Diss., Freiburg. Darmstadt, 1885.
                88 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Anzeiger für deutsches Altertam 13 (1897): 135–36. That is, compounds
                and idiomatic phrases formed by rhyme-reduplication in Old English speech and verse,
                with a lesser catalogue of forms appearing in Old Saxon, Old Frisian, and OHG.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J130">
            <bib> Hollowell, Ida M. "Linguistic Factors Underlying Style Levels in Four Homilies of
                Wulfstan." Neophilologus 61 (1977): 287–96.</bib>
            <notes> Based on her dissertation, "Wulfstan's Style: A Linguistic Analysis." DAI 34
                (1973): 299A (North Carolina). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J131">
            <bib> Hoover, David L. "Old English Meter Again." JEGP 76 (1977): 491–505.</bib>
            <notes> A full critique of Cable (J42), which, while admitting that the notion of me-
                lodic contours, or pitch patterns, is an attractive one, nevertheless concludes that
                they are (like some other systems) altogether too "loose and inclusive," failing to
                screen out unmetrical patterns as Cable claims. In general, Cable's re- finements on
                Sievers are judged much less radical or effective than Cable would have us believe.
                Hoover accepts the argument that the verse contains four members, but rejects the
                three arguments for the "clashing-stress princi- ple" (i.e. duration, compounds, and
                alliteration), and rejects the conflation of types D2 and E. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J132">
            <bib> Hüttenbrenner, Felix. "Probe eines metrischen Wörterbuchs für das Altenglische
                (Phoenix)." Englische Studien 56 (1922): 240–56.</bib>
            <notes> Indexes all the words in the poem under 41 basic metrical types (of words).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J133">
            <bib> Huguenin, Julian. Secondary Stress in Anglo-Saxon (Determined by Metrical
                Criteria). Baltimore: John Murphy Co., 1901. 37 pp.</bib>
            <notes> His dissertation posthumously accepted at Johns Hopkins University, 1901. Like
                Miller (E596), Melton (E1018), and Brown (E1112) in that he is a stu- dent of
                Bright's (E500), Huguenin extends Bright's theory of secondary stresses to Old
                English, analyzing the stressing of compound words in order to show that whenever a
                secondary accent falls between two arses (i.e. syllables outside of the ictic
                positions), or between an arsis and a pause at the verse-end, the secondary accent
                on that syllable is metrically demoted or suppressed. (The corollary, promotion of
                such syllables when they are in ictic positions, he does not demonstrate
                explicitly.) Bright's theory of "pitch-accent" is acquiesced to. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J134">
            <bib> Hulme, William H. "Quantity Marks in Old English MSS." MLN 11 (1896): cols.
                17–24.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J135">
            <bib> Isaacs, Neil D. "Afterword on the Scansion of Old English Poetry." Structural
                Principles in Old English Poetry. Knoxville: University of Tennessee Press, 1968.
                pp. 167–90.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Anglia 92 (1974): 227–29. Offers ten "amendments" to the current views
                on scanning Old English verse, followed by six pages giving a careful but approving
                review of Creed (J61) and nearly a dozen quarreling with Pope (J242). The ten: (1)
                syllabic (quantitative) length "may be discounted in rhythmic analysis"; (2) the
                metrical unit is the line not the verse; (3) the line forms around the alliterating
                pair of syllables; (4) formulaic evidence is sometimes admissible to settle
                ambiguities; (5) syllables are resolved when they can be, if they must be; (6)
                allowance for anacrusis indi- cates the failure of a metrical system; (7) A3 verses
                may contain initial rests; (8) an E3 verse may be postulated as an analogue to the
                A3; (9) syncopation is es- sential to the rhythm; and (10) initial exclamatory Hwaet
                is totally extraneous to the meter. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J136">
            <bib> Jambeck, Thomas J. "The Syntax of Petition in Beowulf and Sir Gawain and the Green
                Knight." Style 7 (1973): 21–29.</bib>
            <notes> The convolution of Beowulf's supplication to Hrothgar is purposeful and should
                not be removed in translation, as is confirmed by Gawain's parallel re- quest to
                Arthur. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J137">
            <bib> Jones, Frederick G. "The Hypermetric Lines of the Rune Poem." Neuphilologische
                Mitteilungen 74 (1973): 224–31.</bib>
            <notes> Finds the motivation for the four hypermetrical lines in the poem to be the-
                matic and symbolic; their central position gives a cruciform shape to the poem and
                also emphasizes the potently symbolic PASTE IN (nied) rune. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J138">
            <bib> Joynes, Mary L. "Structural Analysis of Old English Metrics." DA 19 (1958): 1076A
                (Texas).</bib>
            <notes> A simpler and more coherent account of OE meter than the two current theories is
                one based on a description/explanation of OE suprasegmentals: metrical ictus
                correlates with primary stresses, alliteration correlates with pitch- peak, and
                syntactic boundaries correlate with juncture. Evidence for the nature of OE
                suprasegmentals may be found in the MS marks. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J139">
            <bib> Kaluza, Max. Der altenglische Vers: Eine metrische Untersuchung. Studien zur
                germanischen alliterationsvers, no. 1. Berlin: Emil Felber, 1894.</bib>
            <notes> Part I: "Kritik der Bisherigen Theorien." 96 pp. Part 2: "Die Metrik des
                Beowulfliedes." 102 pp. Rev: in Anglia Beiblatt 5 (1894): 131–36, 198; in Englische
                Studien 20 (1895): 293–96; in ZDP 27 (1895): 539–43; in Anzeiger für deutsches
                Altertum 21 (1895): 313–17. Both Pope and Cable have acknowledged that Kaluza's work
                is considerably more important than it may at first seem. Publishing his work soon
                after Siev- ers', Kaluza intends to reconcile the Five Types description of
                stress-patterns, which he considered irrefragable, with the older vierhebungstheorie
                by adjusting the emphasis of the latter somewhat to call for four members in the
                verse rather than four beats. But in order to do so he is forced to construct a
                typology of 90 subtypes, which later scholars have understandably found too unwieldy
                to use. The full theory is revised and expanded in A3 and can be most conveniently
                consulted in A4, the English translation. The success of Kaluza's synthesis,
                however, is open to question even aside from the ponderous bulk of his own system.
                The dispute between the vierhebungstheorie and zweihebungstheorie schools had arisen
                precisely over the issue of whether the Old Germanic line consisted of four stresses
                (two major and two minor) or only two (major). In this the dispute may seem nearly
                tau- tological and synthesis easy. But Kaluza, with a gesture toward the old Indo-
                Germanic ur-meter x / | x / | x / | x / | as the fullest form, being reduced and
                corrupted over time, trivializes the whole issue and only effects his syn- thesis by
                what looks very much like a lexical feint, in claiming that the term member (German
                glied--the word originally referred to the members of the human body) should be
                substituted for the term beat (hebung). That substitution enables Kaluza to speak of
                the OE verse as a four-member verse, regardless of stresses, a formulation that has
                been much approved of later. But it is one thing to speak of members, in the sense
                of abstract metrical positions, and quite an- other to speak of linguistic stresses,
                particularly in metrics. Calling oranges ap- ples will not change their taste.
                Kaluza is right to deplore quibbling about terms but wrong to duck the questions of
                whether the bar (measure, foot) consists of one syllable or two and whether the
                stresses of the alternate bars al- ternate dipolically. Takt does not equal glied.
                And after all, Kaluza's own para- digm for the verse consists of four members
                divided into two feet (Fusse), each foot beginning with a stress. Does, then, takt =
                fuss? A difference, it has been said, ought to make a difference. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J140">
            <bib> -----. "Die Schwellverse in der altenglischen Dichtung." Englische Studien 21
                (1895): 337–83.</bib>
            <notes> Reply by Luick in 22 (1896): 332; rejoinder by Kaluza, pp. 333–34. Kaluza's
                account of the hypermetrical lines in OE verse can be more conven- iently studied in
                A4. His position is that Sievers was originally correct to inter- pret the form as a
                normal verse preceded by an irregular number of syllables but incorrect in trying to
                regularize this initial section: we must simply call it an "extended anacrusis." The
                present essay catalogues the known instances. The difficulty with this view is that
                Kaluza allows the first alliteration and pri- mary stress of the line to fall in the
                "extended anacrusis," which seems an un- reasonable extension of the sense of
                "anacrusis." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J141">
            <bib> -----. Zur Betonunges- und Verslehre des Altenglischen. Königsberg, 1896. 33
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rpt in Festschrift zum siebzigsten Geburtstag Oskar Schade. Königsberg: Hartung,
                1896. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J142">
            <bib> Kauffmann, Friedrich. "Die sogenannten Schwellverse der alt- und angelsächsischen
                Dichtung." PBB 15 (1891): 360–76.</bib>
            <notes> Critical of the earlier work of Sievers and Luick on the hypermetric lines,
                Kauffmann counters that they are in fact merely extended D-Types (he is con- cerned
                with the verse-endings not with their beginnings). And what seem to be exceptions to
                the rule in the on-verse are the rule in the off-verse; Kauff- mann thinks these
                latter varieties actually A- and B-Types. Luick demolishes this theory in J181. ----
                Keyser, Samuel J. "Old English Prosody." See E777 and E789. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J143">
            <bib> Kim, Joo-Hyon. "Metrical Observations of OE Verse." English Language and
                Literature 31 (1969): 69–80.</bib>
            <notes> Brief explication of the Five Types system, followed by comparison with Creed's
                (J61) revision of Sievers' types B and C, which Kim approves for re- moving any
                "iambic" quality. Heusler and Pope are noticed in passing at the end. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J144">
            <bib> Kintgen, Eugene R., Jr. "Echoic Repetition in Old English Poetry, Especially The
                Dream of the Rood." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 75 (1974): 202–23.</bib>
            <notes> Parallel with and of equal importance to phonological repetition (alliteration)
                and phrasal repetition (formula) in OE poetry is the morphological (echoic)
                repetition of specific words, their root syllables, or at least syllables related
                etymologically as well as phonetically similar. Kintgen takes the maximum range for
                recognition of such lexical correlates to be about twenty lines, but the
                preponderance of them echo at from five lines to ten, and the phenome- non is
                consistently evident in both early and late OE poetry. By far, it is the identical
                word that is repeated, though the lesser echoes of etymologues and analogues all
                contribute to larger complexes or "echoic sets." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J145">
            <bib> -----. "'Lif,' 'Lof,' 'Leof,' 'Lufu,' and "Geleafa' in Old English Poetry."
                Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 78 (1977): 309–16.</bib>
            <notes> Quirk (J243) might also have realized that lexical collocations fixed and "fore-
                grounded" by alliteration in OE verse may come to constitute a larger integral set
                of elements available for purposes of cohesion, codification of traditional
                elements, and phonological intensification. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J146">
            <bib> -----. "Word-Echo in Old English Poetry." DAI 31 (1970): 2883A (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J147">
            <bib> Klaeber, Frederick. "Beowulf" and "The Fight at Finnsburg": Edited, With
                Introduction, Bibliography, Notes, Glossary, and Appendices. Lexington, Mass.: D. C.
                Heath and Company, 1922; 2nd ed. 1928; 3rd ed. 1936.</bib>
            <notes> See "Tone, Style, and Meter," pp. lviii–lxxi, and Appendix IIIB for remarks on
                expressive metrical variations, abstracts of Sievers' and Heusler's systems of
                scansion, and notes on metrical features bearing on textual criticism. There is also
                an excellent bibliography of versification studies on pp. clxxii–clxxvi. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J148">
            <bib> -----. "King Oswald's Death in Old English Alliterative Verse." PQ 16 (1937):
                214.</bib>
            <notes> Notes the ease with which a memorable phrase may be given alliterative form. In
                such a way seemingly unversified texts may be deceptive. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J149">
            <bib> Kock, Ernest A. Jubilee Jaunts and Jottings: 250 Contributions to the
                Interpretation and Prosody of Old West Teutonic Alliterative Poetry. Lunds
                Universitets Arsskrift, n.s. 1, vol. 14, no. 26. Lund: C. W. K. Gleerup, 1918. 82
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Klaeber in JEGP 19 (1920): 409–13; in Anglia Beiblatt 30 (1919): 1–5.
                Mainly short notes on textual interpretation, arranged alphabetically. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J150">
            <bib> Koziol, Herbert. "Zur Alliteration in Altenglischen." Anglia 70 (1951):
                43–45.</bib>
            <notes> Approbation for, addenda to, and commentary on Flasdieck (L342). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J151">
            <bib> Krämer, Ernst. "Die altenglischen Metra des Boetius." Bonner Beiträge zur
                Anglistik 8 (1902): 1–150.</bib>
            <notes> An edition with textual apparatus and commentary. Metrics discussed on pp. 4–10;
                Krämer follows Trautmann (see J317). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J152">
            <bib> Krauel, Hans. Der Haken- und Langzeilenstil im "Beowulf". Diss., Göttingen, 1908.
                Halle, 1908. 43 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J153">
            <bib> Kuhn, Sherman M. "Cursus in Old English: Rhetorical Ornament or Linguistic
                Phenomenon?" Speculum 47 (1972): 188–206.</bib>
            <notes> Agrees with Fijn van Draat (J82) that the cursus in OE prose is "nothing more
                than a part of the natural rhythm of the language." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J154">
            <bib> Kyte, E. Clemons. [nee Clemons, q.v.] "On the Composition of Hypermetric Verses in
                Old English." MP 71 (1973): 160–65.</bib>
            <notes> A combination of Bliss's (J20) conceptions of double-hypermetric (normal) verses
                and single-hypermetric light verses (resolution of the first stress) will ac- count
                for all the expanded verses which Pope listed as problematic and will further
                confirm that anacrusis, far from being erratic, was a carefully controlled
                phenomenon, limited to only one or two syllables of the a-verse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J155">
            <bib> Lawrence, Barbara J. "A Computerized Metrical Analysis of Cynewulfian Poetry." DAI
                34 (1974): 5184A (St. Louis).</bib>
            <notes> (The data was analyzed according to Bliss's metrical system). Known poems by
                Cynewulf--Elene, Juliana, Christ II, and Fates of the Apostles--show marked dif-
                ferentiation from a control group of poems--The Wanderer, The Seafarer, and The
                Battle of Maldon--and marked similarities to the three poems formerly at- tributed
                to Cynewulf--Christ I, Christ III, and Andreas, but the only conclusion warranted by
                this analysis is that though there is no clear proof of Cynewulf's authorship of
                these last three poems there was almost certainly a "Cynewulfian school" of poets,
                at the very least. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J156">
            <bib> Lawrence, John. Chapters on Alliterative Verse. London: Henry Frowde, 1893. 113
                pp. His dissertation at the University of London, 1892.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Anglia Beiblatt 4 (1893): 193–201. From an examination of the metrical
                pointing in the manuscript Codex Junius XI, Lawrence takes the position (following
                Möller [L505] explicitly) that the alliterative line is divided twice (into
                quarters), rather than once (into half- lines), each section being comprised of four
                Moren (a More = the duration of one short syllable) and a primary and a secondary
                stress: / x \ x | / x \ x | / x \ x | / x \ x | If syllables are absent, the time is
                filled by rests. Chapter One is a useful introduction to the state of the
                controversy among philologists of the time. Subsequent chapters treat Crossed
                Alliteration and Vowel Alliteration (Middle English poems compared to Beowulf).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J157">
            <bib> Lawrence, R. F. "Formula and Rhythm in The Wars of Alexander." English Studies 51
                (1970): 97–112.</bib>
            <notes> Of all the studies of oral formulae in OE and ME verse, this one focuses the
                most directly on the metrical function of the formula. While preserving the
                connotation and the grammar of the formula essentially unchanged, the poet could
                adapt slight variations in morphology and word-order in order to meet the metrical
                requirements of the context. In WA the preferred metrical pattern for the on-verse
                is / x x /; for the off-verse, either / / x or / x x / x. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J158">
            <bib> -----. "The Formulaic Theory and its Application to English Alliterative Poetry."
                Fowler (A14), pp. 116–83.</bib>
            <notes> A review of the scholarship on the question of oral-formulaic composition in Old
                and Middle English alliterative verse, prefaced by an introductory section on
                Parry's work on Homer. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J159">
            <bib> Lefèvre, P. "Das altenglische Gedicht vom heiligen Guthlac." Anglia 6 (1883): 181–
                240.</bib>
            <notes> See "Metrik," pp. 185–88, and the Appendix "Der Reim bei Cynewulf," pp. 233–40.
                Lefèvre mainly discusses the shortcomings of his predecessors in the attribution of
                authorship (to Cynewulf) on metrical grounds. The Appendix catalogues eight types of
                alliteration and end-rhyme proper within and be- tween successive lines in the two
                most sensitive linear positions, caesural and final, sorting the examples by number
                of syllables. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J160">
            <bib> Lehmann, Ruth. "Broken Cadences in Beowulf." English Studies 56 (1975):
                1–13.</bib>
            <notes> Analysis of the positioning of modifiers (before vs. after the noun) and the
                verse-types used to begin sentences reinforces the accepted view that the Beo-
                wulf-poet consciously strived for variety wherever possible. In this respect--
                deliberate avoidance of establishing a metrical paradigm for the line which would
                then be repeated and so "fixed"--Old English poetry is quite contrary to Old Irish.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J161">
            <bib> -----. "The Metrics and Structure of Wulf and Eadwacer." PQ 48 (1969):
                151–65.</bib>
            <notes> The metrical form of the poem (summarized on p. 152) is unique, but it seems to
                have more affinity with other English verse than with Norse, as has been suggested.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J162">
            <bib> Lehmann, Winfred P. "Metrical Evidence for Old English Suprasegmentals." Texas
                Studies in Literature and Language 1 (1959): 66–72.</bib>
            <notes> The evidence suggests a reduction from secondary stress and long quantity to
                weak stress and short quantity in the final syllable of bisyllabic compounds, es-
                pecially proper names, such as Wiglaf. Such an assumption will eliminate nearly all
                the aberrant "extended" lines in Beowulf. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J163">
            <bib> -----. "Post-Consonantal l m n r and Metrical Practice in the Beowulf." Nordica et
                Anglica: Studies in Honor of Stefan Einarsson. Ed. Allan H. Orrick. The Hague:
                Mouton, 1968. pp. 148–67.</bib>
            <notes> Word-final resonants present a familiar problem in methodology for metrical
                research: almost the only available evidence for early stages of the language lies
                in poetic texts, and we do not know a priori if forms therein represent the stan-
                dard language or artificial convention, or even (given the MSS) if the poet and
                scribe were ever consistent in usage. Therefore, the linguistic evidence must be
                assessed before any metrical evidence is considered. On this basis Lehmann concludes
                that l, m, n, and r possessed full syllabic value for metrical purposes after heavy
                syllables, but not after light ones. This will lead to a reassessment of the
                metrical status of a considerable number of lines in Beowulf. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J164">
            <bib> Lehmann, Winfred P., and Takemitsu Tabusa. The Alliterations of the "Beowulf".
                Austin: University of Texas Department of Germanic Languages, 1958. 134 pp.</bib>
            <notes> An alphabetical index of alliterants, preceded by a thirteen-page Introduction.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J165">
            <bib> Lehmann, Winfred P., and Virginia F. Dailey. The Alliterations of the Christ,
                Guthlac, Elene, Juliana, Fates of the Apostles, and Dream of the Rood. Austin:
                University of Texas Department of Germanic Languages, 1960.</bib>
            <notes> An alphabetical index of the alliterations. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J166">
            <bib> Leonard, William E. "Beowulf and the Niebelungen Couplet." University of Wisconsin
                Studies in Language and Literature, no. 2 (1918), pp. 99–152.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Klaeber in Anglia Beiblatt 32 (1921): 145–48. Begin at section G. For
                his translation of Beowulf the poet-critic Leonard chose the eight-beat,
                hemistichic, couplet-rhymed long-line of the Niebelungenlied; he therefore accepts
                what Kaluza called "the-good-old-much-despised-and-
                often-pronounced-dead-but-on-this-account-only-so-much-the-more-
                tenaciously-clinging-to-life-Lachmannian-four-accent-theory." But unlike Trautmann
                (a teacher of Leonard's), who alone believed that all four of the stresses in the
                half-line were weighted equally, Leonard's view is that they are dipodic: two are
                primary, and two others are lesser stresses, but nevertheless stresses. Thus the
                difference between his view and Sievers' is merely one of how to treat the
                intermediary stresses--whether as weaker than full, but still stronger than weakest,
                or as weaker than full, hence weak. Leonard prefers the gravity, solemnity, and
                slowness which overstressing gives to the poetic line. The little children's rhyme
                given on p. 133 says everything in a nutshell. See Leonard's later articles (K215
                and L461) and Stewart's article (E379) and book (E333). There is a criticism of his
                position in the second edition of Pope (J242), pp. 15–20. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J167">
            <bib> Le Page, R. B. "Alliterative Patterns as a Test of Style in Old English Poetry."
                JEGP 58 (1959): 434–41.</bib>
            <notes> Statistical analysis of double and crossed alliteration and "stress-links" (con-
                secutive lines repeating the alliteration) in order to assess the degree of inten-
                tionality behind these phenomena by screening out the chances for their ran- dom
                occurrence. It turns out that both Cynewulf and the Beowulf-poet con- sciously
                avoided these devices, the latter more than the former, revealing thereby his
                superior artistry. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J168">
            <bib> -----. "A Rhythmical Framework for the Five Types." English and Germanic Studies 6
                (1957): 92–103.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation at the University of Birmingham in 1952, "Studies in
                Old English Prosody." A critique of Pope (J241) and his theory of isochronous bars
                in meter always beginning with a stress, fixed in number, invariable in
                time-signature, and marked with the vexing musical notation. The Sievers system is,
                on fur- ther reflection, approved, with the qualifications that "unusual patterns of
                allit- eration are in fact more common than Sievers allowed" and that the "foot-
                divisions of the five-type theory are rhythmically meaningless," since the unit of
                rhythm is the line not the half-line. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J169">
            <bib> Lewis, Charlton M. The Foreign Sources of Modern English Versification With
                Especial Reference to the So-Called Iambic Lines of 8 and 10 Syllables. Yale Studies
                in English, no. 1. New York: Henry Holt and Co., 1898</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1969. 104 pp. His dissertation
                at Yale, 1897. Around the turn of the century, interest ran high in philological
                circles on the question of the primitive origins of poetry (F. B. Gummere published
                an important book). Lewis is interested not in the earliest (Hebrew) syllabic
                versification nor in the (later) classical quantitative system (Greek, then taken
                over into Latin), but in the origin of the modern accentual versification. Several
                theories had been proposed for this major shift in verse-technique in the early
                Middle Ages, for it was not immediately obvi- ous how an accentual system could
                evolve from a quantitative one, if at all; some believed the two systems had no
                connection at all, the accentual system deriving from another foreign source or from
                vernacular Latin poetry (which was accentual). Lewis examines the crude Commodian
                verse of the mid third century, the Latin hymns of Ambrose and the later
                high-medieval Church music, and Old French syllabic verse in order to demonstrate
                the genealogy of the native, Old English verseform (that is, before the French
                modification of the native form after the Norman Conquest). The disintegration of
                classical Latin quantitative verse into a looser, accentually rhythmical form often
                remains obscure at points, and we can see that medieval music is still not entirely
                un- derstood, but Lewis manages to establish his line of descent from the high Latin
                forms through to the sophisticated and complex artistic form of the Old English
                line. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J170">
            <bib> -----. "Notes on Transverse Alliteration." MLN 16 (1901): cols. 85–88. Reply by
                Emerson, cols. 181–83</bib>
            <notes>; rejoinder by Lewis, col. 256. O. F. Emerson's (J78) rejection of Frucht's
                conclusions (J90) on the intention- ality of transverse alliteration does not accord
                with simple laws of probability. In fact, quite the contrary: Frucht understated his
                case considerably by using unreasonably low percentages. Lewis concludes that Old
                English poets avoided transverse alliteration consciously yet occasionally allowed
                it as an ornament. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J171">
            <bib> Lewis, C[live] S[taples]. "The Alliterative Metre." Lysistrata 2 (1935)</bib>
            <notes>. Rpt in his Rehabilitations and Other Essays. Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                1939 ; rpt Folcroft Press, 1970. pp. 117–32. A suggestion that modern poets revive
                the old native meter by writing hemis- tichs of Sievers' Types with alliteration,
                strong caesura and manifest attention to both quantity (he gives rules) and accent.
                Any accentual-analogue meter which disregards quantity will only produce
                "rubbish"--verse that is "thin." Specimen verses adjoined. It is more than meiosis
                to say that "a good deal of re-education is here necessary." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J172">
            <bib> Lewis, Richard A. "Alliteration and Old English Metre." Medium Ævum 42 (1973):
                119–30.</bib>
            <notes> Randolph Quirk's suggestion (J243) that lexical collocations tend to appear as
                alliterants in OE meter can be restated as a general rule--"linguistic connection
                complements metrical connection"--that will permit a superior account of certain
                lines than that given by the nine types of "light verses" distinguished by Bliss
                (J20). The fact is, traditional metrical analyses such as his tend to assign stress
                to syllables on the basis of relatively rigid phonetic and syntactic laws, such as
                Kuhn's Law for particles. But, arguably, the context--the specific lin- guistic and
                metrical environment--is also very influential. The grammatical rules are not
                inviolable; they interact with prosodic conventions such as allit- eration, lexical
                collocations, and formulae. Bliss's light verses can be accounted for by such
                factors as these latter, since itself "alliteration is a signal of corre- spondence
                between items considered metrically and linguistically." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J173">
            <bib> -----. "Literary Correspondence of Alliterating Items in Old English Poetry." DAI
                32 (1971): 3258A (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> In the earliest, oral stages of OE poetry, alliteration served primarily
                metrical ends, whereas later, in the literate stage, it served to conjoin
                grammatically and thematically important items. These latter functions were served
                even further by extending the (originally linear) alliteration into "plurilinear"
                units, thereby sustaining the theme or mood over a greater expanse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J174">
            <bib> -----. "Old English Poetry: Alliteration and Structural Interlace." Language and
                Style 6 (1973): 196–205.</bib>
            <notes> Thin: amounts to the unremarkable assertion that alliteration "foregrounds" and
                links important semantic elements, alliteration being the manifestation, in verbal
                art, of the general OE aesthetic principle of "interlace." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J175">
            <bib> -----. "Plurilinear Alliteration in Old English Poetry." Texas Studies in
                Literature and Language 16 (1975): 589–602.</bib>
            <notes> Following Malone (J198) [without citing him], Lewis proceeds to identify four
                varieties of alliteration within a two-line span--enjambed, reverse-enjambed or
                "envelope," a free-position type, and something very close to end-rhyme. But he
                dismisses out of hand the probabilities for occurrence of these phenomena based on
                random chance, a matter which C. M. Lewis (J170) and Emerson (J78) have shown to be
                highly relevant. Stronger proof is required that this is not mere fortuitous,
                residual, or morphologically-determined ornamentation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J176">
            <bib> Liebermann, F. "Zur rhythmischen Prosa Englands im 10–11. Jahrhundert." Archiv 110
                (1903): 98.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J177">
            <bib> Lipp, Francis R. "Ælfric's Old English Prose Style." SP 66 (1969): 689–718.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J178">
            <bib> Luecke, Jane-Marie. Measuring Old English Rhythm: An Application of the Principles
                of Gregorian Chant Rhythm to the Meter of "Beowulf". Literary Monographs, vol. 9.
                Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1978. 158 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Based on her dissertation, "Meter and the Free Rhythm of Beowulf," DA 25 (1964):
                2495A (Notre Dame), which is abstracted in Linguistics 15 (1965): 116–18. Taking the
                position that the meter of Old English poetry is "a pattern of four members having
                two phrase stresses and making up a short, phrasal line- unit called a verse,"
                Luecke proceeds through a detailed (though misleading) history of Old English
                metrical studies to her thesis, the argument that the Heusler-Pope school of
                "musical" metrists applies its theory--or analogy--of isochronous barring to Old
                English verse erroneously, since, historically speaking, music was not notated in
                equal measures until the twelfth century, whereas even in the Anglo-Saxon age there
                existed a tradition of unequal- measure notation for the Gregorian Chant. Luecke's
                purpose is to demonstrate the similarity of the Chant rhythms (mixed binary and
                ternary measures) to the rhythm (not meter, she insists) of Beowulf. In her system
                the verse (half-line) consists of four members, each of which is constituted
                minimally by a syllable but which may be constituted maximally by a syllable flanked
                by two "word- boundary pulses," producing a fully-expanded abstract pattern of
                twelve pulses (a pattern not found in Beowulf). "Member" = "measure." The two
                phrasal stresses may fall on any of the four members to produce six possible
                patterns of stressing. Cf. Silver-Beck (J289). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J179">
            <bib> -----. "Measuring the Rhythmic Variations of Old English Meter." Language and
                Style 8 (1975): 95–110.</bib>
            <notes> A short version of the principles and conclusions more fully elaborated in her
                book. In this metric the OE verse consists of two pitch-accents augmented by one to
                two word-stresses. Summary of her research on Gregorian chant. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J180">
            <bib> Luick, Karl. "über den Versbau des angelsächsischen Gedichtes Judith." PBB 11
                (1886): 470–92.</bib>
            <notes> Extends the Sievers system to Judith. Luick and Sievers maintained a strong re-
                lationship both privately and in print for a number of years even despite cer- tain
                disagreements over matters of theory. There is a photograph of Luick in the
                Festschrift honoring him in Englische Studien 70 (1935). A minor note: his term
                "crossed alliteration" (p. 478) for the pattern abab has not been adopted; Emerson
                termed it "transverse." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J181">
            <bib> -----. "Zur altenglischen und altsachsischen Metrik: (Schwellvers und Normalvers,
                Alliteration und Versrhythmus)." PBB 15 (1891): 441–54.</bib>
            <notes> In reply to Kauffmann (J142), Luick shows that the endings of hypermetric verses
                are not all identical, nor are they the endings of D-Types. He then dis- cusses the
                notions he had broached earlier, the idea of a symmetrical principle in Germanic
                verse (stress in the on-verse inclines toward the beginning, while that in the
                off-verse toward the end) and an idea of "counterbalancing" or overweighting (only a
                limited number of syllables may follow the main stress in foot or else their
                combined "weight" overbalances it). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J182">
            <bib> -----. "Zur Theorie der Entstehung der Schwellverse." PBB 13 (1887): 388–92.</bib>
            <notes> Luick had been inclined originally to accept Sievers' first published view,
                which was that the hypermetric verses were formed by affixing anacrusis to the head
                of an otherwise-normal verse, but the fact that one of the primary stresses in the
                anacrusis participated in the alliteration made the anacrusis-theory very unlikely,
                so Luick proposes here an alternate view (accepted by Sievers in 1893) that these
                verse are formed by a medial fusion of two verses, an imper- fect first one to a
                regular second. Out of all the possible permutations of the Types only eleven will
                actually work, five being Sievers' Five and the other six variations. There seems to
                be some difficulty with the B-forms, and Luick thinks perhaps they should be
                eliminated. His account is generally very close and ingenious, and it is entirely
                organic and autonomous: he wishes to account for the origin of these verses entirely
                on the basis of phonetic law; authorial purpose never enters the discussion at all.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J183">
            <bib> McFayden, Neill Lindsey. "Architecture and Alliteration in the Old English
                Advent." Language Quarterly 15 (1977): 56, 60.</bib>
            <notes> Structural alliteration in one crucial sentence reinforces its semantic content,
                the key image of the poem, that of Christ as cornerstone. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J184">
            <bib> McIntosh, Angus. "Wulfstan's Prose." Proceedings of the British Academy 35 (1949):
                109–42.</bib>
            <notes> Exceedingly extensive notes. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J185">
            <bib> Mackie, W. S. "The Old English Rhymed Poem." JEGP 21 (1922): 507–19.</bib>
            <notes> Text, translation, and discussion of "the first resolute metrical experiment in
                English literature . . . a metrical tour de force." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J186">
            <bib> McRae, Michael H. "The Syntactic Base of Anglo-Saxon Poetry." DAI 35 (1975): 5381A
                (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> A broadly synthesizing effort aimed at promoting the neglected study of syntax
                to an equal rank with those of meter and formula in order to construe a uni- fied
                account of all three simultaneously within the theory of transformational grammar.
                Alliteration, metrical types, and formular frames can all be accounted for more
                adequately than is presently believed by introducing a separate stylis- tic level
                (component, filter) into the normal hierarchy of grammatical rules. Separate
                chapters examine each of the three stylistic aspects in Beowulf. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J187">
            <bib> Madden, John F. "A Frequency Word-Count of Anglo-Saxon Poetry." Mediaeval Studies
                15 (1953): 221–25.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation at Harvard in 1953. The author describes the one he
                produced for Magoun as his thesis, but it was never formally published, nor is it
                reproduced in whole or in part here. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J188">
            <bib> Magoun, F. P., Jr. "Bede's Story of Caedmon: The Case History of an Anglo-Saxon
                Oral Singer." Speculum 30 (1955): 49–63.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J189">
            <bib> -----. "Oral-Formulaic Character of Anglo-Saxon Narrative Poetry." Speculum 28
                (1953): 446–67.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J190">
            <bib> -----. "Strophische überreste in den altenglischen Zaubersprüchen." Englische
                Studien 72 (1937): 1–6.</bib>
            <notes> Lindquist in his study of Old Norse incantations was able to show that there
                existed a common Germanic tripartite stanza-like form (termed the galder-form)
                having three distinctive rhyme criteria for identification, and he was further able
                to show that the remnants of this grundform appear in several OE charms. Magoun
                adduces five further examples, with discussion. Cf. Schneider (J267). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J191">
            <bib> -----. "The Theme of the Beasts of Battle in Anglo-Saxon Poetry." Neuphilologische
                Mitteilungen 56 (1955): 81–90.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J192">
            <bib> Maling, Joan M. "Sentence Stress in Old English." Linguistic Inquiry 2 (1971):
                379– 99.</bib>
            <notes> Application of the transformational apparatus to the problem of assigning stress
                to the alliterants in the half-lines of Old English verse produces the conclusion
                that "most of the alliterative patterns of Beowulf are correctly predicted if we
                allow the COMPOUND [NOUN] RULE to cycle on the nodes NP, VP, and S after all
                transformations affecting word order internal to the NP and S, with the exceptions
                of verb-movement transformation(s)." I.e., in broader terms, OE meter cannot be
                accounted for by any theory which assigns stress to alliterants on the basis of
                grammatical category (word stress); grammatical con- nection, or syntax (sentential
                stress), is the proper approach. Maling rewrites Rieger's (J253) alliteration rule
                in the newer terminology: "in any half-line, a word bearing 1 stress must
                alliterate; in initial half-lines, a word bearing 2 stress may also alliterate, and
                will do so approximately 70% of the time. Words bearing less than 2 stress never
                alliterate. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J193">
            <bib> Malone, Kemp. "Alliteration in Widsith." ELH 2 (1935): 291–93.</bib>
            <notes> The poem shows four patterns of alliteration (abac, aaab, abbc, abab), extension
                of one alliteration over several lines in succession, and the foreshadowing and
                echoing of the alliteration of a line in the two lines flanking it. See J195.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J194">
            <bib> -----. "Lift Patterns in Old English Verse." ELH 8 (1941): 74–80.</bib>
            <notes> In Malone's simplified scansion system the "lifts" (hebungen) or prominent
                (stressed) syllables are classed as primary (marked by alliteration), secondary
                (prominent but not bearing alliteration), and tertiary (less prominent but still
                prominent), these being denoted (respectively) by the numerals 1, 2, and 3. The
                essay gives examples of the various patterns which appear in the OE long line; the
                most common are the four-life patterns 11–12, 12–12, and 21–12, with 11–11, 11–21,
                12–11. and 21–11 less common, but three-, five-, six-, and seven-life patterns also
                occur occasionally with either single or double al- literation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J195">
            <bib> -----. "A Metrical Note on Widsith." Anglia Beiblatt 48 (1937): 351–52.</bib>
            <notes> Certain lines in Widsith force a slight revision in the common rule that in Type
                C verses "the syllable under the second of the two primary stresses does not
                alliterate alone." There are actually two sorts of C verses: those where the second
                stress is subordinate to the first, and those where both are equal. In this latter
                variety of Type C, in the on-verse, the poet felt free to use the first, the second,
                or both arsis syllables alliteratively. see J173 above. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J196">
            <bib> -----. "A Note on Beowulf 1. 1379." MLR 25 (1930): 191.</bib>
            <notes> Only two alliterating staves in this line will suffice, as in 11. 445 and 2220.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J197">
            <bib> -----. "The Old Tradition: Poetic Form." A Literary History of England. Ed. A. C.
                Baugh. New York: Appleton-Century-Crofts, 1948. pp. 20–31.</bib>
            <notes> Professor Malone's simplified account of the technical features of the Anglo-
                Saxon verseform gives equal space to Sievers and Heusler/Pope, perhaps in- clining
                somewhat to the former; he also reminds us of the frailty of written re- cords,
                since the originals were only spoken, and MS texts undoubtedly reflect the interests
                of the clergy. Variation and kennings also discussed. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J198">
            <bib> ----. "Plurilinear Units in Old English Poetry." Review of English Studies 19
                (1943): 201–4.</bib>
            <notes> Two types of syntacti-metrical style appear in Old English poetry: the earliest,
                "pre-classical" verse is exclusively end-stopped and inclined toward the epi-
                grammatic, giving it a highly linear character; the classical poetic monuments
                however are plurilinear, their lines being enjambed either with or without a
                syntactic pause. The plurilinear style exhibits three stages, depending on degree of
                consistency in bondings. Cf. Lewis (J175). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J199">
            <bib> -----. "The Rhythm of Deor." Old English Studies in Honour of John C. Pope. Ed.
                Robert B. Burlin and Edward B. Irving, Jr. Toronto: University of Toronto Press,
                1974. pp. 165–69.</bib>
            <notes> Simply a listing of the 42 lines of the poem with each on-verse and off-verse
                classified by Pope's system (J242) and notes on particular problems. This is
                probably the last essay Professor Malone wrote before his death. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J200">
            <bib> March, Francis A. "Prosody." A Comparative Grammar of the Anglo-Saxon Language; in
                which Its Forms are Illustrated by Those of the Sanskrit, Greek, Latin, Gothic, Old
                Saxon, Old Friesic, Old Norse, and Old High-German. New York, 1869, 1873, 1888, etc.
                pp. 222–28.</bib>
            <notes> This American treatment of Old English grammar is curious: the account given of
                the prosody is actually whittled to fit modern verse then rounded on a few edges so
                as to fit another shape of hole: March defines the long line as consisting of two
                sections, each section containing four feet. An arsis "falls on every prose accent
                and the last syllable of every section." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J201">
            <bib> Mather, Frank J. "The Cynewulf Question from a Metrical Point of View." MLN 7
                (1892): cols. 193–213.</bib>
            <notes> Reviews the course of the nineteenth-century German philological work on the
                question of the authorship of the extant Old English poems, then gives a close
                critique of the methods and conclusions of Cremer (J63). Mather himself accepts as
                legitimate only the evidence of (1) distribution of verse-types in both half-lines,
                (2) double alliteration, and (3) hypermetrical verses; he con- cludes that only
                Juliana, Elene, Christ (in its entirety), and the Vercelli fragment are definitely
                by Cynewulf. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J202">
            <bib> Mayr, Maria. Metrische Untersuchung der Episoden des Epos "Beowulf". Diss.,
                Innsbruck, 1917.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J203">
            <bib> Menthel, E. "Zur Geschichte des Otfridischen Verses im Englischen." Anglia
                Anzeiger 8 (1885): 49–86; 10 (1888): 105–26, 186.</bib>
            <notes> See J317. Menthel was a student of Trautmann's, and hence believed that the Old
                and Middle English alliterative line was written in four-beat half-line cou-
                plets--this form from Otfrid in Germany. This essay is the fullest application of
                that erroneous theory by any of Trautmann's school. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J204">
            <bib> Metes, George S. "Word-Order Variation as a Stylistic Feature in the Old English
                Andreas." DAI 33 (1973): 3621A (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> The effects of subject-verb inversion. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J205">
            <bib> Mitchell, Bruce. "Adjective Clauses in Old English Poetry." Anglia 81 (1963): 298–
                322.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J206">
            <bib> -----. "Five Notes on Old English Syntax." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 70
                (1969): 70–84.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J207">
            <bib> -----. "More Musings on Old English Syntax." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 69
                (1968): 53–63.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J208">
            <bib> -----. "Pronouns in Old English Poetry: Some Syntactical Notes." Review of English
                Studies n.s. 15 (1964): 129–41.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J209">
            <bib> -----. "Some Syntactical Problems in The Wanderer." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen
                69 (1968): 172–98.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J210">
            <bib> -----. "Two Syntactical Notes on Beowulf." Neophilologus 52 (1968): 292–99.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J211">
            <bib> Möller, Hans. Das altenglischen Volksepos in der ursprünglichen strophischen Form.
                Kiel, 1883.</bib>
            <notes> Cited by both Schipper and Leonard, but unlocated; not in NUC or BMC. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J212">
            <bib> Monnin, Pierre. "The Making of the Meters of Boethius: Studies in Traditional Art
                and Aesthetics." DAI 36 (1976): 6117A (Massachusetts).</bib>
            <notes> Lexical irregularities in the versified version of the Consolation of
                Philosophy, as compared with the prose source, may be attributed to (1) prosodic
                necessity and (2) the poet's imperfect memory of his source, either as he had read
                it or had heard it read to him. An Appendix gives a full scansion of the Meters
                using the Creed-Foley approach, with analysis of metrical variation. Cf. Myrvaagnes
                (J217). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J213">
            <bib> Morgan, Bayard Q. Zur Lehre von der Alliteration in der westgermanischen Dichtung.
                Diss., Leipzig, 1907</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt in PBB 33 (1908): 95–181. Sievers regarded crossed alliteration as a
                result of higher pitch on stressed sylla- bles: "stresses with a high pitch can
                alliterate; others cannot"; sentence-accent alone would not suffice. Morgan,
                Sievers' pupil, takes up this theory, distin- guishing three grades of pitch-height:
                (1) the alliterating syllables bear "leading tones," which need not be the highest
                pitches in the line; these are "isotonic"; (2) then there are "near tones," as well
                as (3) "remote (far) tones," which ap- pear in two subtypes, overtones and
                undertones. The remote tones a listener will perceive as contrastive to the lead
                tones. There are also "deflected tones" which are separated from the lead tone by
                some lesser but recognizable dis- tance. (All these positions are relative not
                absolute.) Therefore: (1) stresses with lead tones must alliterate; (2) those with
                near tones may alliterate; and (3) those with far tones never alliterate with
                syllables of a different pitch. Alliteration, then, binds both by connection and by
                contrast. Why for example do Types B and C have so much less double alliteration?
                The second stress has a deflected tone. Symbols for pitches are given on p. 101.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J214">
            <bib> Morris, John. "Sidney Lanier and Anglo-Saxon Verse-technic." American Journal of
                Philology 20 (1899): 435–38.</bib>
            <notes> The author prefers the intuition of Lanier to the empiricism of Sievers, de-
                fending the older mora, takt conception of Germanic verse against the Five- Type
                theory with a stridency verging on fanaticism. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J215">
            <bib> Müller, [?]. Der syntaktische Gebrauch des Verbums in dem angelsächsischen
                Gedichte vom "Judith". Diss., Leipzig, 1892.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J216">
            <bib> Müller, Hugo. über die angelsächsischen Versus Gnomici. Diss., Jena, 1893. 55 pp.
                See chapter 4 on "Metrum, Alliteration, Reim," pp. 39–49.</bib>
            <notes> Müller applies the Sievers system. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J217">
            <bib> Myrvaagnes, Naomi S. "A Stylistic Study of the Old English Meters of Boethius."
                DAI 31 (1971): 4131A (N.Y.U.).</bib>
            <notes> A detailed comparison of meter (Types) and syntax in the Meters as compared to
                Beowulf. The prevalence of Types A and B in Meters produces an overt metrical
                monotony, aligned with heavy subordination in the syntax. Cf. Mon- nin (J212).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J218">
            <bib> Nager, Hans. Die Halbversfüllung im "Beowulf." Mit einem Anhang, der eine
                Untersuchung der Halbversfüllung in Cynewulf's "Juliana," in Byrthnods "Tod" und in
                "Beowulf's Rückkehr" im Vergleich mit der im gesamten Beowulfliede enthält. Diss.,
                Graz, 1911.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J219">
            <bib> "The Native Meter." Schipper (All), Book I, Part 1. pp. 15–125.</bib>
            <notes> Includes four chapters: "General Introduction to the Science of Metre and the
                Structure of Verse" (see E539); "The Alliterative Verse in Old English"; "The
                Further Development of the Freer Form of the Alliterative Line in Late Old English
                and Early Middle English"; and "The Alliterative Line in its Conserva- tive Form
                during the Fourteenth and Fifteenth Centuries." Schipper's Book I, Part 1 mainly
                treats alliterative verse in Old English and its survival to Bale and Skelton, with
                scattered examples up to the present. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J220">
            <bib> Nelson, Marie. "Sound as Meaning in Old English Charms, Riddles, and Maxims." The
                Twenty-Seventh Annual Mountain Interstate Foreign Language Conference. Ed. Eduardo
                Zayas-Bazan et al. Johnson City, Tenn., 1978. pp. 122–28.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J221">
            <bib> Neuner, Erich. über ein- und dreihebie Halbverse in der altenglischen
                alliterierenden Poesie. Diss., Berlin, 1920. Berlin: Mayer-Muller, 1920. 87
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Bright in MLN 36 (1921): 59–63; in Englische Studien 59 (1925): 275– 80.
                An attempt to show that the Sievers A3 verse-type has sometimes one, some- times
                three stresses, instead of the uniform two postulated. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J222">
            <bib> Nicholson, Lewis E. "Oral Techniques in the Composition of Expanded Anglo- Saxon
                Verses." PMLA 78 (1963): 287–92.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation at Harvard in 1957. Adopting the treatment of hy-
                permetrical lines given by Pope (J241), Nicholson is able to show that in for-
                mulaic terms, such verses may be constructed by adding additional material to the
                base formula at the beginning (first measure), end (final measure), or mid- dle of
                the verse, or even by splitting the formula between an off-verse and the following
                on-verse by enjambment (a novel suggestion). The purpose or func- tion of
                hypermetric verses? The sheer aesthetic pleasure the Anglo-Saxons so evidently took
                in complex pattern qua pattern. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J223">
            <bib> Nist, John A. "Alliterative Patterns in Beowulf: A Key to Authorship." Papers of
                the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts, and Letters 44 (1959): 347–53</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt in revised form as chapter 6 of his The Structure and Texture of "Beowulf"
                (J224). Statistics on the frequency and distribution of consonant- and vowel-
                alliteration strongly support the theory of single authorship. Nist distinguishes
                between single and shared alliteration and tallies the frequencies for all the con-
                sonants in either case: for single, the most frequent occurrences are h, s, and w
                (in descending order), for shared, s is the most-commonly used sound. The
                most-avoided consonant in both cases is p. Nist also notices that transverse vo-
                calic alliteration seems to correlate highly with nasalization. Conclusion: gravity
                rather than acuity is the distinctive feature most essential to Old English allit-
                eration. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J224">
            <bib> -----. "The Metrics of Beowulf." In his The Structure and Texture of “Beowulf”.
                Universidade de São Paulo Faculdade de Filosofia, Cièncias e Letras Boletim no. 229,
                Lingua e Literatura, no. 1. Sao Paulo, Brazil, 1959. pp. 89–110;</bib>
            <notes> revised as </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J225">
            <bib> "Metrical Uses of the Harp in Beowulf in Old English Poetry: Fifteen Essays. Ed.
                Robert P. Creed. Providence: Brown University Press, 1967. pp. 27–43.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation at Indiana in 1953. Nist's position on OE meter rep-
                resents an enthusiastic approval of that of W. E. Leonard (J166), combined with the
                scansion of Stewart (E333)--i.e., he accepts the four-beat, rhythmical theory, yet
                he is disinclined to follow Pope, preferring instead to work out the idea that OE
                verse is dipodic. The half-line contains two isochronous measures, which, if
                unequal, may be restored to balance by "compensation." Sixteen ba- sic measure-types
                or "cadences" are possible. Metrical rests or pauses are speci- fied as "Harpbeats";
                these may fill pauses, replace missing secondary stresses, or separate contiguous
                primary stresses. The effect of these Harpbeats is to heighten the emotional level
                of a passage; the wider effect of the verseform as a whole is "overstressing," or
                promotion of every degree of natural speech stress one degree higher. Hypermetric
                lines Nist redefines as normal lines by grading down primary stresses to
                secondaries, thus effectually defining the problem out of existence, at least
                verbally. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J226">
            <bib> O'Neil, Wayne A. "Another Look at Oral Poetry in The Seafarer." Speculum 35
                (1960): 596–600.</bib>
            <notes> Reply to Campbell (J46). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J227">
            <bib> -----. "Oral Formulaic Structure in Old English Elegaic Poetry." DA 21 (1960):
                625A (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> The nine principal elegies are "heavily" formulaic (50% of their verses are for-
                mulas). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J228">
            <bib> -----. "Some Remarks on Old and Middle English Stress." A Festschrift for Morris
                Halle. Ed. Stephen R. Anderson and Paul Kiparsky. New York: Holt, Rinehart and
                Winston, 1973. pp. 158–65.</bib>
            <notes> Economizing of rule-systems in English Stress (E777): adding the Latin Stress
                Rule for OE and deleting the Germanic Stress Rule for ME. Also notes the weakness of
                relying solely on metrical evidence (in the absence of solid ortho- epic evidence)
                in OE and ME. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J229">
            <bib> Orrick, Allan H. "Reðes and Hattres, Beowulf 2523." MLN 71 (1956): 551–56.</bib>
            <notes> Denies any metrical grounds for emendation of this line. Responses by Pope
                (J238) and Stevick (J301). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J230">
            <bib> Overholser, Lee C. "A Comparative Study of the Compound Use in Andreas and
                Beowulf. DAI 32 (1971): 1498A (Michigan).</bib>
            <notes> According to Charles Fillmore's case grammar system. Compounds appear in two
                types: normal-order and reverse-order. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J231">
            <bib> Past, Raymond E. "A Note on The Rhythm of 'Beowulf.'" MLN 64 (1949): 310–11.</bib>
            <notes> A critique of Pope's musical-scansion-sigla: "while Professor Pope's notation is
                easier to read and, doubtless, more convenient to write, it no more determines the
                tempo of the reading than does Heusler's." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J232">
            <bib> Pender, Robert L. "A Structural Study of the Old English Metrical Charms." DAI 30
                (1970): 4952A (Indiana).</bib>
            <notes> A high incidence of verbal repetition at all levels--lexical, syntactic,
                metrical, and alliterative--suggests that repetition for repetition's sake was
                believed to enhance the efficacy of the incantation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J233">
            <bib> Petheram, John. An Historical Sketch of the Progress and Present State of
                Anglo-Saxon Literature in England. London: Edward Lumley, 1840. 180 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Besides being a delight to read, Petheram's history of the rise of Old English
                scholarship offers very interesting details on the lives and work of early gram-
                marians such as Hickes, Rask, and Conybeare--even Guest. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J234">
            <bib> Pflueger, Solveig M. "Syntax and Verse in Beowulf and Selected Passages of
                Germanic Poetry." DAI 31 (1971): 6037A (Texas).</bib>
            <notes> Analysis of the syntactic patterns of the verses in Beowulf shows that syntactic
                constraints were of equal rank with metrical, and that it is the syntactic frame
                which underlies the (lexical frame or) oral formula. Comparison with selected
                smaller texts. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J235">
            <bib> Pilch, Herbert. "Syntactic Prerequisites for the Study of Old English Poetry."
                Language and Style 3 (1970): 51–61.</bib>
            <notes> Illustrations of the necessity of a thorough grounding in Old English syntax for
                the proper interpretation of its verse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J236">
            <bib> Planer, Johannes G. E. Untersuchung über den syntaktischen Gebrauch des Verbums in
                dem angelsächsischen Gedichte vom "Phoenix". Diss., Leipzig, 1891. 50 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J237">
            <bib> Pope, John C. "Aelfric's Rhythmical Prose." Homilies of Aelfric: A Supplementary
                Collection. . . . Early English Texts Society, Original Series, nos. 259, 260. New
                York: Oxford University Press, 1967–68. Vol. 1, pp. 105–36.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J238">
            <bib> -----. "The Emendation 'Oreðes and Attres,' Beowulf 2523." MLN 72 (1957): 321–
                28.</bib>
            <notes> A response to Orrick (J229); see also Stevick (J301). Pope defends the tradi-
                tional emendation of this line primarily on the basis of the standard rules for
                alliteration laid down by Rieger and Sievers, as well as on the basis of superior
                sense. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J239">
            <bib> -----. "Old English Versification." Seven Old English Poems. Indianapolis: Bobbs-
                Merrill, 1966. pp. 97–138.</bib>
            <notes> A convenient abstract of Pope's system, long enough to be full for the begin-
                ning student, yet not unduly detailed. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J240">
            <bib> -----. Old English Versification with Particular Reference to the Normal Verses of
                "Beowulf". New Haven, 1957.</bib>
            <notes> Mimeographed. Superseded by J241. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J241">
            <bib> -----. The Rhythm of Beowulf: An Interpretation of the Normal and Hypermetric
                Verse- Forms in Old English Poetry. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1942.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Review of English Studies 19 (1943): 73–77; by Oakden in MLR 38 (1943):
                136–37; in JEGP 42 (1943): 115–16; by Klaeber in Archiv 185 (1948): 121–24. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J242">
            <bib> -----. The Rhythm of Beowulf: An Interpretation of the Normal and Hypermetric
                Verse- Forms in Old English Poetry. New Haven: Yale University Press, Rev. ed.,
                1966.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Roger Fowler in Anglia 87 (1969): 444–49. The most substantial treatise
                on Old English versification published in this century, and the chief rival to
                Sievers. Pope accepts the typology of stress- patterns demonstrated by Sievers, the
                Five Types, as legitimate, but takes an opposing position, maintaining that these
                abstract patterns tell us nothing valu- able about the actual recitation or delivery
                of the line; that is, Rhythm is more crucial than Meter. (But as counter to the
                antagonism shown in the text, note Pope's free admission of his indebtedness to and
                admiration for Sievers in the preface to the 2nd ed.) In emphasizing Rhythm, Pope is
                following Heusler (L387)--who viewed the verse (half-line) as comprised of two
                compound measures, each having four members or positions--as opposed to Kaluza
                (J139)--who viewed the verse as set in four duple measures. But Pope elabo- rates
                his system much further than Heusler did, using musical notation to de- note the
                rhythm rather than Heusler's symbols, disagreeing about the tempo of delivery (he
                prefers a 4/8 signature to Heusler's 4/4), and adding the crucial feature of initial
                rests in the measures, a feature not found in Heusler. (Pope found it in Kaluza,
                although there it was not established as fundamental to the metrical scheme, as it
                is in his own system.) It is these initial rests that Pope employs to account for
                Sievers' troublesome Types B and C verses, thus so- lidifying the whole structure of
                musical scansion. Then, late in the book, after the feature has been supported at
                length on purely theoretical grounds, Pope introduces as external evidence the use
                of the harp as accompaniment to reci- tation, on the grounds that an initial pause
                at the beginning of the line pre- ceding the first stress cannot be heard by an
                audience unless a harp-note is sounded to denote it. The whole argument is shrewdly
                deployed. The rhythmical pattern in Pope, then, is a verse of two compound quadruple
                measures, preceded by an indeterminate anacrusis, with stresses al- ternating within
                the measures, and each member representing the time re- quired for one grammatically
                short syllable, or one eighth-note in 4/8 time. Schematically: . . . | / x \ x | | /
                x \ x |. The difficulty with Pope's system, however, is its extension. In order to
                account for every variety of rhythmic actualization, and as a result of his evi-
                dent obsession for total inclusiveness and formality in the theory, Pope is forced
                away from a few simple, conceptually elegant patterns to a very de- tailed,
                complicated, and cumbrous descriptive typology of over 286 rhythmic subtypes for the
                a-verse alone (the number of varieties for each of Sievers' Five Types is: A, 107;
                B, 58; C, 39; D, 58; E, 17; with 7 more undetermined or corrupt). As Bliss put it,
                "a classification which is too detailed ceases to be a classification and becomes a
                description." And though Pope dismisses all these subtypes as not crucially
                important, he devotes one-half of his very large book to an exhaustive catalogue and
                statistical analysis of them. Worse still is the criticism levelled by other
                scholars that Pope's fundamental assumption of iso- chronous measures for OE verse
                is both historically and theoretically a total misapplication of the musical analogy
                to metrics (Pope does confess his ap- proval of Lanier), since isochronous barring
                only appeared in the West as a convention for notating music in the thirteenth
                century and was totally un- known to the Anglo-Saxons. There are critiques by Past
                (J231), Cable (J42), Fowler (J86), Silver-Beck (J288 and J289), and Luecke (J178).
                Creed (J61) has produced a valuable simplification of Pope's system. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J243">
            <bib> Quirk, Randolph. "Poetic Language and Old English Metre." Early English and Norse
                Studies. Ed. Arthur Brown and Peter Foote. London: Methuen, 1963. pp. 150–71.</bib>
            <notes> Studies of the metrical requirements of the OE alliterative system and of com-
                position by traditional formulae should avoid being unduly narrow or else they blind
                us to the crucial fact that "the whole metrical tradition [had] established a
                tradition of lexical connexion" beyond the merely formulaic. That is, the allit-
                eration, through contiguity, "marked" or "endorsed" an expectation of lexical and
                syntactic complementarity--i.e. collocation--as well. The range of conno- tative
                subtlety and power established by alliterative collocations was enormous, and the
                study of their functions and effects must be entirely synthetic, keeping metrical,
                lexical, and rhetorical strategies simultaneously in view. Identification of
                verse-types, figures, or formulae is a mere preliminary. An influential study; see
                Lewis (J172). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J244">
            <bib> Raffel, Burton. "Judith: Hypermetricity and Rhetoric." Anglo-Saxon Poetry: Essays
                in Appreciation for John C. McGalliard. Ed. Lewis E. Nicholson and D. W. Frese.
                Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame Press, 1975. pp. 124–34.</bib>
            <notes> Suggests that "in the hypermetrical passages of Judith, the scop uses two basic
                techniques, in one of which the rhetoric inflates and the rhythm delays, in the
                other of which the rhetoric goes taut and the rhythm drives ahead," the latter
                technique being altogether the more effective. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J245">
            <bib> Rankin, James W. "Rhythm and Rime Before the Norman Conquest." PMLA 36 (1921):
                401–28.</bib>
            <notes> The belief that rhyme came into English poetry in the ME period is erroneous
                because it ignores an entire gamut of popular songs, chants, spells, and rhymes in
                the OE period not in the classical Five-Types meter. These verses were not preserved
                because they were not the sort of thing monks thought worthy of preservation, but
                they unquestionably existed, as did an entire tradition of classical and medieval
                Latin accentual rhymed verse behind them. Indeed rhythmus had come to denote rime as
                early as the eighth century. See response by Routh (J258). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J246">
            <bib> Rarick, Louise. "Ten-Syllable Lines in English Poetry." Neuphilologische
                Mitteilungen 75 (1974): 66–73.</bib>
            <notes> They predominate even in Old English verse (9-, 10-, and 11-syllable lines
                comprise 81% of Beowulf, for example) as compared to Old Norse (heavier
                consonantally, shorter in line) and Old Germanic (weaker in consonants, longer in
                line). Conjectural reason for this particular number: the number of human fingers.
                [Saxon sign-language??] </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J247">
            <bib> Rask, Erasmus [Rasmus Christian]. "Of Versification." A Grammar of the Anglo-
                Saxon Tongue, With a Praxis. Translated from the Danish by B. Thorpe. Copenhagen,
                1830. pp. 135–72.</bib>
            <notes> The Swedish original, Angelsaksisk Sproglaere, appeared in Copenhagen in 1817.
                Though Professor Rask's conception of the alliterative structure of OE meter is
                substantially the correct one, his perspective seems odd to us now since he can view
                Old English only within the framework of the older Northern ver- seforms, especially
                Icelandic (Skaldic). Thus he categorizes the OE poetic genres in forms of the
                Icelandic ones, namely Narrative Verse, Heroic Verse, and Popular Verse, the latter
                two being comparatively absent in OE. In the Narrative (i.e. Alliterative) Verse
                Rask recognizes the structural function of the alliteration as well as the
                ornamentation of occasional internal- and end- rhymes, and he censures Hickes for
                not recognizing accent as the basis of the meter. "The characteristics of this
                species of verse are a) the alliteration . . . and b) the number of emphatic
                syllables. The length of each line of Narrative Verse is not so accurately
                determined as in Latin, by feet. All that here has in- fluence upon the measure
                seems, as in Icelandic, to be the long or accented syllables, which have an emphasis
                in the context, of which there are two in a line, each of which is usually followed
                by one, two, or even more, syllables . . . but these long and short syllables do not
                seem to be arranged according to other rules than those prescribed by the ear, and
                the cadence of the verse. . . ." Notice too Rask's insistence on setting the
                half-lines of OE verse separately rather than as long-lines. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J248">
            <bib> Raw, Barbara C. "Rhythm and Style." The Art and Background of Old English Poetry.
                London: Edward Arnold, 1978. pp. 97–122.</bib>
            <notes> Undertakes to establish correlations between specific metrical forms (Sievers'
                five types) and certain stylistic and semantic features (such as register or recur-
                rent thematic devices) in an effort to demonstrate "a system of rhetoric which was
                based on rhythm rather than on figures" and which "involved different levels of
                style. . . . Shifts from one style to another were indicated by shifts in rhythm."
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J249">
            <bib> Ray, Tommy J. "A Statistical Examination of Theme as a Style Determiner in
                Anglo-Saxon Poetry." DAI 31 (1971): 3517A (Oregon).</bib>
            <notes> The general theme of "battle" is analyzed for syntactic distribution in 28 poems
                by a computer program; a significant variation in distributions for "battle" vs.
                "non-battle" passages is very tentatively affirmed. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J250">
            <bib> Rehrmann, Heinrich. Essay concerning Anglo-Saxon Poetry. Lübben, 1877. 20
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> The first few sections give the canonical literary history; sections 5, 6, and 7
                treat (respectively) alliteration, rhyme, and rhythm; sections 13, 14, 15, and 16
                treat syntax, parallelism, and diction. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J251">
            <bib> Remly, Lynn L. "Ars Praedicandi: Poetic Devices in the Prose Homily Vercelli X."
                Mid-Hudson Language Studies 1 (1978): 1–16.</bib>
            <notes> Not only in manifest borrowings but also in original composition the homilist
                sought to reproduce the doublings and alliteration characteristic of OE verse in
                order to create a "dichterisch gehobene Sprache." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J252">
            <bib> Richter, Carl. Chronologische Studien zur angelsächsischen Literatur auf Grund
                sprachlich- metrischer Kriterien. Studien zur englischen Philologie, vol. 33. Halle:
                Max Niemeyer, 1910. 101 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Archiv 130 (1913): 430–32; in Anglia Beiblatt 22 (1911): 78–80. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J253">
            <bib> Rieger, Max. Die alt- und angelsächsische Verskunst. Halle, 1876. 64 pp. Rpt from
                ZDP 7 (1876): 1–64.</bib>
            <notes> Historically, Rieger's work is second in importance only to Sievers', a fact
                which Sievers readily admitted, for his Five Types typology would never have been
                possible had Rieger not made the analysis identifying the rules for per- missible
                alliteration in Old English verse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J254">
            <bib> Roberts, Jane. "A Metrical Examination of the Poems Guthlac A and Guthlac B."
                Proceedings of the Royal Irish Academy, vol. 71, section C (1971), pp. 91–137.</bib>
            <notes> Employs the system of Bliss (J20) to examine differences in meter, alliteration,
                and rhyme in the two poems. Conclusions, pp. 116–20. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J255">
            <bib> Rogers, H. L. "Rhymes in the Epilogue to Elene: A Reconsideration." Leeds Studies
                in English 5 (1971): 47–52.</bib>
            <notes> An aggressive but detailed and orderly piece of forensics rebutting the tradi-
                tional view (stated by Sievers) that Cynewulf was an Anglian, based on the evidence
                of his rhymes. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J256">
            <bib> Rosier, James L. "The Two Closings of Beowulf." English Studies 54 (1973):
                1–6.</bib>
            <notes> Close attention to texture. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J257">
            <bib> Ross, Alan S. C. "Philological Probability Problems." Journal of the Royal
                Statistical Society, series B, vol. 12 (1950), pp. 19–41</bib>
            <notes>. Discussion follows, pp. 41–59. Complaining that "the numerical data used in
                philology have received no mathematical treatment . . . consequently, the
                conclusions drawn have almost always been invalid," Ross outlines
                statistically-valid approaches to various kinds of problems in philology, including
                "the detection of abnormal fre- quency of occurrence of 'extra-alliterative'
                features in Anglo-Saxon verse." See the second part of section 4, pp. 31–36.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J258">
            <bib> Routh, James. "Anglo-Saxon Metre." MP 21 (1924): 429–34</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt in his Theory of Verse (B187). A response to Rankin (J245): Sievers' Five
                Types are neither arbitrary nor eru- dite metrical forms; they are "a simple,
                rudimentary, instinctive, and even primitive form of musical, or at least
                rhythmical, expression." Old English verse preserves the syntax of prose and "a
                singing type of meter." That is, the verse was sung to music. The standard metrical
                form of the verse (half-line) was x / x / x, and if the x's are replaced by one and
                two syllables, the permu- tations will be discovered to be nothing other than the
                Five Types. And the rule that each verse must have at least two unstressed syllables
                will prevent va- rieties other than the Five Types from appearing. This is the
                direction taken by Pope (J241). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J259">
            <bib> Russom, Geoffrey R. "Sequential Repetition of Similar Narrative Units as Proof of
                the Scop's Originality." DAI 34 (1973): 2577A (S.U.N.Y. at Stony Brook).</bib>
            <notes> Instead of formulaic composition being a convenience, it probably compli- cated
                verse-making by adding a requirement prohibiting repetition of the same alliterants
                in the same order; i.e., one of its principles was Variety. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J260">
            <bib> Rynell, Alarik. Parataxis and Hypotaxis as a Criterion of Syntax and Style,
                Especially in Old English Poetry. Lunds Universitets Arsskrift, vol. 48, no. 3.
                Lund: C. W. K. Gleerup, 1952. 60 pp.</bib>
            <notes> See especially pp. 31–38: poetry inclines toward a paratactic style for several
                reasons, one of which is metrical. End-stopping encourages parataxis, whereas
                enjambment encourages hypotaxis. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J261">
            <bib> Saintsbury, George. "The Prosody of Old and Middle English." The Cambridge History
                of English Literature. Ed. A. W. Ward and A. R. Waller. 14 vols. New York: G. P.
                Putnam's Sons, 1907–16. Vol. 1, chapter 18, pp. 416–23.</bib>
            <notes> Since this material did not appear in the History of English Prosody (A8), it is
                naturally of some interest. As expected, Saintsbury scarcely deigns to be spe-
                cific; he has read Sievers and others but to characterize Old English meter will
                only go so far as to suggest that the rhythm of the standard line, normal and
                hypermetric indiscriminately, is tum-ti-ti + ti-tum-ti > tum-ti | tum-ti tum-ti;
                such verse he calls "curiously non-metrical, or hardly more than half-metrical." All
                the verse after 1200, including the revived (?) alliterative form, Saintsbury sees
                as falling under the hegemony of syllable-counting, the Romance con- straint which
                altered English verse irrevocably. But to believe this within his larger views he is
                forced to claim that the one constraint the native tradition never relinquished was
                trisyllabic substitution. Better Theory Than Facts, the Scotchman thinks. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J262">
            <bib> Schabram, Hans. "The Season for Fasting 206 ff. Mit einem Beiträge zur
                altenglischen Metrik." Britannica: Festschrift für Hermann M. Flasdieck. Ed.
                Wolfgang Iser and Hans Schabram. Heidelberg: Carl Winter, 1960. pp. 221–40.</bib>
            <notes> Metrical criticism begins on p. 228. Of interest in this passage of verse is the
                "unusual and doubtful" Type A line in the Sievers system, which Schabram ar- gues
                should not be emended, against the opinions of Holthausen, Trautmann, Graz, and
                Heusler. ---- Schipper, Jakob. Altenglische Metrik. Bonn, 1881. This is vol. 1 of
                his 3-volume Englische Metrik (A9), q.v. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J263">
            <bib> -----. "Metrische Randglossen." Englische Studien 9 (1886): 184–94.</bib>
            <notes> A critique of Trautmann's theory; see J317. Replies by </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J264">
            <bib> Trautmann, "Metrische Antglossen," Anglia Anzeiger 8 (1885): 246–52</bib>
            <notes>; and by Eugen Einenkel, J265 "Zur Schipper's 'Metrischen Randglossen,'"
                Englische Studien 9 (1886): 368–73. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J266">
            <bib> Schmitz, Theodor. "Die Sechstakter in der altenglischen Dichtung." Anglia 33
                (1910): 1–76, 172–218.</bib>
            <notes> A misguided and unsuccessful attempt to account for hypermetric lines in OE
                poetry on the basis of Trautmann's four-beat theory (see J317); Schmitz con- siders
                them "six-bar" lines of the form / u | ú u || ú u | ú u | ú u | ú u |. What is of
                value here, though, is the series of detailed synopses and commen- taries on all the
                other German theories of the schwellvers which Schmitz pro- vides on pp. 172–98.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J267">
            <bib> Schneider, Karl. "Zur den altenglischen Zaubersprüchen wið wennum und wið
                wÆterÆlfadle." Anglia 87 (1969): 282–302.</bib>
            <notes> Includes metrical analysis of these two charms, using Heusler's system. Note the
                author's earlier study cited in the first footnote. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J268">
            <bib> Schröder, Edward. "Steigerung und Häufung der Alliteration in der westgerman-
                ischen Dichtung." ZDA 43 (1899): 361–85.</bib>
            <notes> Subtitled Part I, but apparently no more were published. Here Schröder treats,
                in some very loose language, the accumulation of alliteration in the formation of
                compounds within colloquial speech, as a preliminary to the poetic em- ployment of
                that device, and the appearance of such compounds in virtually all the extant OE
                poetry. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J269">
            <bib> Schubert, Herman F. P. De Anglosaxonum Arte Metrica. Diss., Berlin, 1870. 54
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Schubert scans verses by the Beowulf-poet, Caedmon, and Cynewulf on the basis of
                the vierhebungstheorie, that is, with four beats to the half-line, though he argues
                that some have only three. Reply by Vetter (L627). Gayley and Scott (L46) thought
                this work excellent. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J270">
            <bib> Schulze, Fritz W. "Reimstrukturen im Offa-Preislied Aethilwalds und die
                Entwicklung des altenglischen Alliterationsverses." ZDA 92 (1963): 8–31</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt in Ernst and Neuser (L337), pp. 213–45. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J271">
            <bib> Schwarz, Franz. Cynewulfs Anteil am Christ: Eine metrische Untersuchung. Diss.,
                Königsberg. Königsberg: Hartung, 1905. 105 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Metrical inventory of verse-types and their positions, alliteration, and rhyme
                in order to try to determine the authorship of the tripartite Christ. Schwarz con-
                cludes that Cynewulf was not the author of all three parts. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J272">
            <bib> Schwetman, John W. "The Formulaic Nature of Old English Poetry: A Transformational
                Analysis of the Cynewulf Poems." DAI 35 (1975): 6110A (Kansas).</bib>
            <notes> Suggests that the whole mechanism of conceiving of OE verse-composition in
                formulaic terms is superfluous, since the same data can be accounted for more
                conveniently and more intelligibly by the mere addition of a metrical compo- nent to
                a standard transformational apparatus. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J273">
            <bib> Scripture, E. W. "Experimentelle Untersuchungen über die Metrik in Beowulf."
                Archiv für die gesamte Psychologie 66 (1928): 203–15</bib>
            <notes>. See E430. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J274">
            <bib> -----. "Die Grundgesetze des altenglischen Stabreimverses." Anglia 52 (1928): 69–
                75. See E430.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J275">
            <bib> Sedgefield, Walter J. "Appendix on Anglo-Saxon Versification." An Anglo-Saxon Book
                of Verse and Prose. Manchester University Press, 1928. pp. 125–30.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J276">
            <bib> -----. "Old English Notes." MLR 18 (1923): 471–72.</bib>
            <notes> The first note: twelve rhyme pairs in a passage of verse in the Anglo-Saxon
                Chronicle for 1086 show what is apparently a much earlier instance of the
                lengthening of short vowels in an open syllable than has hitherto been known.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J277">
            <bib> Setzler, Edwin B. On Anglo-Saxon Versification From the Standpoint of
                Modern-English Versification. Baltimore: J. H. Furst, 1904. 87 pp.</bib>
            <notes> His dissertation at Virginia in 1902. A wholehearted endorsement of the Siev-
                ers system. Following Frucht and Cremer, Setzler extends the Sievers analysis to The
                Wanderer, The Seafarer, Exodus, and The Battle of Maldon. The curious subtitle
                simply denotes Setzler's desire to point up the continuities in the Eng- lish
                language, historically, and hence those that ought to inhere in its verse- forms.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J278">
            <bib> Seyfarth, Hermann. Der syntaktische Gebrauch des Verbums in dem Caedmon
                beigelegten angelsächsischen Gedichte von den "Genesis". Diss., Leipzig, 1891. 50
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J279">
            <bib> Sheets, Louis A. "Wulfstan's Prose: A Reconsideration." DA 25 (1965): 6611A (Ohio
                State).</bib>
            <notes> McIntosh's view of Wulfstan's prose rhythm (J184) is "an oversimplification of
                an exceedingly complex matter" because it ignores the punctuation in the MSS, which
                was expressly intended, Sheet argues, to denote the contours of "rhythmic rise and
                fall." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J280">
            <bib> Sievers, Eduard. "Zur Rhythmik des germanischen Alliterationsverses, I.
                Vorbemerkungen: Die Metrik des Beowulf." PBB 10 (1885): 209–314.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J281">
            <bib> -----. "Zur Rhythmik des germanischen Alliterationsverses, II: sprachliche
                Ergebnisse." PBB 10 (1885): 451–545.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J282">
            <bib> -----. "Zur Rhythmik des germanischen Alliterationsverses, III: Der
                angelsächsische Schwellvers." PBB 12 (1887): 454–84.</bib>
            <notes> Offprints of the first two articles were published at Halle in 1885 and in
                Tübingen in 1887, and by G. E. Stechert in New York in 1909 (240 pp.). Sievers then
                revised and expanded these articles into his </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J283">
            <bib> -----. Altgermanische Metrik. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1893. Rev: in Anzeiger für
                deutsches Altertum 20 (1894): 337–43; in LGRP, no. 9 (1893), cols. 455–57.</bib>
            <notes> This should be considered the standard text. In the same year Sievers J284
                contributed a summary of his theory to the first (1893) edition of Paul's J285
                Grundriss der germanischen Philologie (L531). The same article was later prepared
                for the second (1905) edition of Paul by Kaufmann and Gering, though no substantive
                changes were made at all. The 1905 edition of Altgermanische Metrik is simply an
                offprint of the article in J286 the second edition of Paul. Two sections of the
                standard text have been trans- lated by G. D. Luster as: "Old Germanic Metrics and
                Old English Metrics." In Essential Articles for the Study of Old English Poetry. Ed.
                Jess B. Bessinger and Stanley J. Karhl. Hamden, Conn.: Archon Books, 1968. pp.
                267–88. There is a biographical essay with photograph of Sievers by Karl Breul in
                Modern Quarterly of Language and Literature (later MLQ), vol. 1, no. 3 (1898):
                173–75; another photograph appears as the frontispiece to PBB 57 (1933); and yet
                another will be found in PBB 79 (1957): 321. The work of Eduard Sievers rises out of
                the great mass of nineteenth- century German philology as a model of scholarship, in
                industry, in method, in conceptual elegance, in results. Setting out to find some
                simple, discernible, metrical pattern amid the welter of verses in the Beowulf, his
                catalogue of stress-patterns yielded up not one base meter but rather a small
                typology of five simple types of verses (half-lines). These are: A / X | / X B X / |
                X / C X / | \ X D1 / | / \ X D2 / | / X \ E / \ X | / . Each Type covers a range of
                subtypes which are extended in various ways though still recognizably of the type.
                Sievers' work came to be called the Five Types theory, then, but it is important to
                recognize that what he pro- duced is not a theory at all--it is not an explanation,
                but simply a description of what occurs (and does not occur), a typology, an
                empirical catalogue. Only re- cently have scholars begun to tackle the more
                formidable problem of explain- ing what Sievers showed beyond question was there.
                After Sievers' results were published in 1885, his Types were quickly verified, and
                it is a measure of the incisiveness of Sievers' analysis that every subsequent
                theorist of OE meter has been compelled to frame his thesis at least partly in terms
                of the Five Types. No matter what aspect of OE verse may be the subject of
                inquiry--timing, pitch patterns, syntax, performance--the account of stressing
                accepted is likely to be Sievers' (there are voices from the wilderness; see J2,
                J64, and J67). Siev- ers himself scanned OE verse with two stresses to the
                half-line, and the op- posing view, the vierhebungstheorie, was dealt crippling
                blows both by the suc- cess of Sievers' account and by the intransigent
                improbability of Trautmann's theory; consequently, subsequent four-stress theorists
                such as Kaluza (J139) were forced to attempt compromises of various sorts. On the
                hypermetric verses, Sievers' views shifted. In 1887 he considered that such verses
                were formed generally by the prefixing of an "anacrusis" of / x (x) or sometimes x /
                (x) to an otherwise-normal verse. But in 1893, based on arguments made by Luick in
                the interim, he changed his mind, adopting the view that they were formed by the
                overlap and merger of two verses with a common interval portion; schematically,
                ----------------------|-------| + |-------|----------------------- =
                ----------------------|-------| ----------------------- For a critique of this
                theory see Pope (J242, pp. 105–15). On vowel al- literation Sievers accepted the
                "glottal catch" theory. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J287">
            <bib> -----. "Zu Cynewulf." Neusprachliche Studien: Festgabe Karl Luick. In Die Neueren
                Sprachen, Supplement no. 6. Marburg, 1925. pp. 60–81.</bib>
            <notes> Late work: Sievers recants his earlier adherence to the "dogma" that stress is
                welded to alliteration and promotes his new theory of "Schallanalyse" (there is no
                adequate translation; "pitch-idiolect analysis" seems awkward), whereby personal
                intonation curves can be recovered from texts. This was much criti- cized (see Ipsen
                and Karg [L403] and Nowack [L523]), but Scripture approved of it and Berry's work
                (C35) is a clear echo. Sievers insists on "continuous beat" as essential to verse,
                procured by "hovering stress," on normalization of texts into their original
                dialects, and on three-stress OE lines in 2/4-time. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J288">
            <bib> Silver, Barbara E. L. "A Critical Review of Anglo-Saxon Metrical Theory." DAI 31
                (1971): 6569A (Cornell).</bib>
            <notes> The essential preliminaries: a distinction between Meter and Rhythm; a rec-
                ognition that what is currently considered Theory is mere Description; a sur- vey of
                the two principal approaches so far, the Isochronous and the Non- Isochronous; and a
                realization that while the latter of these is the only legiti- mate approach it
                merely provides, in its schemata of Stress-Types, a description of "inevitable"
                patterns. The correct theory of Old English Meter: "two basic, simple rules":
                alliteration and two stresses per half-line. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J289">
            <bib> Silver-Beck, Barbara L. "The Case Against The Rhythm of Beowulf." Neuphilologische
                Mitteilungen 77 (1976): 510–25.</bib>
            <notes> The case rests on the simple but very powerful fact that the concept of iso-
                chrony is an anachronism, a modern concept that does not apply to primitive music
                (in several geographical regions) or to medieval Gregorian chant. Cf. Luecke (J178).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J290">
            <bib> Skeat, W. W. "An Essay on Alliterative Poetry." Bishop Percy's Folio Manuscript:
                Ballads and Romances. Ed. J. W. Hales and F. J. Furnivall. 3 vols. London: N.
                Trübner, 1867–68. Vol. 3. pp. xi–xxxix.</bib>
            <notes> Convinced that accent is the principle of English verse, Skeat complains of the
                terminology of prosody, proposing loud and soft for long and short, and Tonic,
                Return, and Dominant for Trochaic, Iambic, and Dactylic. For OE alliterative verse
                he adduces a set of rules, but unfortunately he mistakes the OE stress- meter for a
                syllable-counting meter, leading him to scan it by feet; this explains the statement
                that the Tonic foot is the basis of OE verse while the Dominant is the basis of the
                ME (alliterative) poems. Skeat lists all the ME alliterative MSS known to him and
                concludes with remarks on OE prose rhythms. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J291">
            <bib> Skeat, W. W., ed. Aelfric's Lives of Saints. Vol. 2. Early English Text Society,
                Original Series, no. 114. London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co., 1900.
                "Ælfric's Alliteration," pp. 1–1iii.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J292">
            <bib> Sklar, Elizabeth S. "The Battle of Maldon and the Popular Tradition: Some Rhymed
                Formulas." PQ 54 (1975): 409–18.</bib>
            <notes> Increases in unstressed syllables, triple alliteration, three-stress half-lines,
                ab- sence of caesura, and (chiefly) rhyme as evidence for the influence of the
                popular tradition on Old English verse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J293">
            <bib> Slay, D. "Some Aspects of the Technique of Composition of Old English Verse."
                Transactions of the Philological Society, 1952, pp. 1–14.</bib>
            <notes> Catalogues words into three categories--nominals, verbs and adverbs, and
                connectives--in order to show how the stress-patterns of the words are fitted
                systematically into the metrical patterns of the line. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J294">
            <bib> Smirnickaja, O. A. [The Linguistic Factors in the Growth and Loss of English
                Alliterative Verse.] Voprosy anglijskoj filologii. Tula, 1970. pp. 71–90</bib>
            <notes>. Not seen. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J295">
            <bib> Smith, Garland G. "Recurring First Elements of Anglo-Saxon Nominal Compounds: A
                Study in Poetic Style." Diss., Harvard University, 1931.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J296">
            <bib> Sokoll, Eduard. "Zur Technik des altgermanischen Alliterationsverses." Beiträge
                zur neueren Philologie. Ed. Jakob Schipper. Vienna and Leipzig: Wilhelm Braumüller,
                1902. pp. 351–65.</bib>
            <notes> The seemingly free changes of rhythm in the alliterative long line which Siev-
                ers noticed have not been explained. Cremer's explanation has so far been the best,
                but he could only hold that the poet preferred joining half-lines of differ- ent
                Types simply for the sake of variety. But in fact many lines appear with both
                verse-types identical. Kauffman's notion of a "balancing" system is not much better.
                It is true that any type verse can be matched with any other, and true also that the
                type chosen for the off-verse does not seem to control that for the on-verse. But we
                can perceive certain evident preferential groupings of types, as B with C in
                Beowulf. Sokoll offers five categories: (1) both verses be- gin withprepositions;
                (2) both are mainly verb phrases; (3) both begin with co- ordinating conjunctions;
                (4) or with attributive pronouns; or (5) both are sen- tences or main or subordinate
                clauses. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J297">
            <bib> Solo, Harry J. "The Twice-Told Tale: A Reconsideration of the Syntax and Style of
                the Old English Daniel, 245–429." Papers on Language and Literature 9 (1973):
                347–64.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J298">
            <bib> Spaeth, John D. E. Die Syntax des Verbums in den angelsächsischen Gedichte
                "Daniel": ein Beitrag zur angelsächsischen Grammatik. Diss., Leipzig, 1893. 50
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J299">
            <bib> Stanley, E. G. "Some Observations on the A3 Lines in Beowulf." Old English Studies
                in Honour of John C. Pope. Ed. Robert B. Berlin and Edward B. Irving, Jr. Toronto:
                University of Toronto Press, 1974. pp. 139–64.</bib>
            <notes> Mainly a compilation of all the lines, with their syntactic position identified
                by symbols; not much can be gleaned for certain beyond the previously-known
                generalization that the A3 lines (which almost invariably occur in the first half-
                line) seem to announce or introduce a particularly important line soon to fol- low.
                Editorial punctuation offers little help. Stanley also tries to show that
                "transverse alliteration" is accidental rather than intentional. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J300">
            <bib> -----. "Verbal Stress in Old English Verse." Anglia 93 (1975): 307–34.</bib>
            <notes> Micrometrical analysis of two specific problems: the alliterating finite verb in
                the second half-line (the paradigm case is Beowulf 2717b), and the metrically
                unstressed infinitive in the initial dip of the verse (either verse). Cf. Fakundiny
                (J80). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J301">
            <bib> Stevick, Robert D. "Emendation of Old English Poetic Texts: Beowulf 2523." MLQ 20
                (1959): 339–43.</bib>
            <notes> An attempt to assess the validity and weight of the arguments and their as-
                sumptions presented by Orrick (J229) and Pope (J238) in their dispute over
                emendation in this line and the principles behind such an action. Stevick sup- ports
                Pope on the evidence of MS status, alliteration, rhetoric, and meter. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J302">
            <bib> -----. "The Meter of The Dream of the Rood." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 68
                (1967): 149–68.</bib>
            <notes> A summary exposition of the principles and methods of his monograph. Stevick
                treats each of the hypermetric lines of this poem and Genesis B as if it were two
                normal lines. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J303">
            <bib> -----. "The Oral-Formulaic Analyses of Old English Verse." Speculum 37 (1962):
                382–89.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J304">
            <bib> -----. Suprasegmentals, Meter, and the Manuscript of "Beowulf". Janua Linguarum,
                Series Practica, no. 71. The Hague: Mouton, 1968. 88 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Linguistics 62 (1971): 110–17; in English Studies 52 (1971): 157–59.
                Stevick presents here his formal argument that the spacing between morpho- logical
                units in the MS of Beowulf was very precisely regulated by the scribes so as to
                indicate timing features, specifically the internal open and terminal junc- tures,
                which Stevick terms the "phonological phrasing." The scribes gave scant attention to
                word-boundaries, and the occasional accent marks in the MSS seem to have only a very
                limited function, so the speech-rhythm could only be dented by spacing. Stevick
                believes that the intervals between stresses in Beowulf were isochronic, so that
                identification of junctures and hence recovery of the suprasegmental phonemes of the
                text may be used, as Joynes has shown (J138), to determine the metrical stressing.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J305">
            <bib> Stock, Rudolph. Die Verstärkung der Alliteration im Beowulfliede. Diss.,
                Königsberg, 1921. 159 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J306">
            <bib> Stoddard, Francis H. "Accent Collation of Caedmon's Genesis B." MLN 2 (1887):
                cols. 165–74.</bib>
            <notes> Restoration of MS marks. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J307">
            <bib> Strobl, Joseph. "Zur Spruchdichtung bei den Angelsächsen." ZDA 31 (1887): 54–
                64.</bib>
            <notes> Statistics on vocalic alliteration near the end. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J308">
            <bib> Sweet, Henry. An Anglo-Saxon Reader. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1876</bib>
            <notes>; many subsequent editions. Sections 356–92 concern meter, but these are
                discontinued in all editions past the tenth. Sweet gives a simplified traditional
                account of the line, verse, stave, lift, dip, extended verses, and the Five Types.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J309">
            <bib> Taglicht, Josef. "Beowulf and Old English Verse Rhythm." Review of English Studies
                n.s. 12 (1961): 341–51.</bib>
            <notes> A general survey and summary of the two competing theories of Old English meter,
                the "musical" and the "nonmusical," with specific observations and criticisms on the
                work of each principal theorist--Sievers and Bliss, on the one side, and Kaluza,
                Heusler, and Pope on the other. Taglicht concludes that the "chronometric" element
                in the verse cannot be dispensed with in a metrical analysis, yet long and short
                syllables cannot be considered temporally equal (i.e. isochronism does not obtain);
                hence, the verse should be scanned in unequal measures having relative proportions
                of 1, 1.5, 2, and 2.5 in duration. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J310">
            <bib> Thornley, G. C. "Studies in the Versification of the Old English MS Junius II: An
                Investigation into the Use and Function of the Accents, and a Consideration of the
                Poetical Rhythms and Their Relation to Sense and Style." Diss., University of
                London, 1952.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J311">
            <bib> Timmer, B. J. "Expanded Lines in Old English Poetry." Neophilologus 35 (1951):
                226–30.</bib>
            <notes> An inventory of the hypermetric lines in OE poetry, ordered chronologically,
                shows (inter alia) that their use did not increase over time. The highest fre-
                quencies appear in Judith and the Dream of the Rood. Their functions included
                introducing and concluding both speeches and whole poems, and also retard- ing the
                tempo of a passage for expressive effect, usually solemnity. Timmer gives a closer
                look to the lines in Beowulf. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J312">
            <bib> Tolkien, J. R. R. "Prefatory Remarks on Prose Translations of Beowulf." "Beowulf"
                and "The Fight at Finnsburg": A Translation into Modern English Prose, with an
                Introduction and Notes. Ed. John R. Clark Hall. London, 1901; 2nd ed. 1911;</bib>
            <notes> rev. ed. 1940; new rev. ed. 1950. pp. ix–xliii. Esp. Part 2 of the Preface, "On
                Metre," pp. xxviii–xliii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J313">
            <bib> Tolman, Albert H. "The Style of Anglo-Saxon Poetry." PMLA 3 (1887): 17–47. Rpt in
                his The Views About Hamlet and Other Essays. Boston: Houghton, Mifflin and Company,
                1904. pp. 339–82.</bib>
            <notes> Mainly on style, repetition, and metaphor, but Tolman declares himself a sup-
                porter of the zweihebungstheorie and claims that the Anglo-Saxon meter is not a
                cause of but merely connected to the style of Anglo-Saxon verse; the two are in-
                terdependent. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J314">
            <bib> Touster, Eva K. "Formal Aspects of the Meter of Beowulf." DA 12 (1952): 623A
                (Vanderbilt).</bib>
            <notes> The author formulates a more simplified account of OE meter than the tradi-
                tional ones. Conclusions: hypermetrical lines are more important in the first part
                of Beowulf than in the second; the dragon-episode is an interpolation. The J314a
                dissertation is summarized in her article "Metrical Variation as a Poetic Device in
                Beowulf," Anglia 73 (1955): 115–26. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J315">
            <bib> -----. "Phonological Aspects of the Meter of Beowulf." Essays in Honor of Walter
                Clyde Curry. Nashville: Vanderbilt University Press, 1954. pp. 27–38.</bib>
            <notes> An argument that traditional metrical analysis has been remiss in its treatment
                of diphthongs as monosyllabic; there is some (ambiguous) phonetic and MS evidence
                that they were disyllabic, or at least that some were so and thus should be
                distinguished from the monosyllabic variety. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J316">
            <bib> Tow, Richard. "Old English Prosody and Descriptive Linguistics." The Second LACUS
                [Linguistic Association of Canada and the United States] Forum, 1975. Ed. Peter A.
                Reich. Columbia, South Carolina: Hornbeam Press, 1976. pp. 605–12.</bib>
            <notes> An exposition of Henry Lee Smith's structural-linguistic approach to OE met-
                rics, which Tow claims is much more adequate than Keyser's theory (E789), especially
                in accounting for unusually heavy verses. In Smith's system, (1) there must be at
                least two primary stresses in every verse (half-line), (2) at least one syllable in
                the verse must bear pitch level 3 or higher and alliterate, and (3) the verse may
                contain no more than eight syllables. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J317">
            <bib> Trautmann, Mortiz. "Zur alt- und mittelenglischen Verslehre." Anglia Anzeiger 5
                (1882): 111–30.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J318">
            <bib> -----. "Oftrid in England." Anglia Anzeiger 7 (1884): 211–15; 8 (1885): 144.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J319">
            <bib> -----. "Zur Kenntnis des altgermanischen Verses, Vornehmlich des Altenglischen."
                Anglia Beiblatt 5 (1895): 87–96.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J320">
            <bib> -----. "Cynewulf's Werke: Der Versbau." Bonner Beiträge zur Anglistik 1 (1898):
                23– 30</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt in his Kynewulf der Bischof und Dichter. Bonn: Hanstein, 1898. pp. 23– 30.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J321">
            <bib> -----. "Der Heliand: Eine übersetzung aus dem Altenglischen." Bonner Beiträge zur
                Anglistik 17 (1905): 123–41.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J322">
            <bib> -----. "Auch zum Beowulf: Ein Gruss an Herren Eduard Sievers." Bonner Beiträge zur
                Anglistik 17 (1905): 143–74.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J323">
            <bib> -----. "Die neuste Beowulfausgabe und die altenglischen Verslehre." Bonner
                Beiträge zur Anglistik 17 (1905): 175–91.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J234">
            <bib> -----. "über angelsächsischen (altenglischen) Versbau." Verhandlungen der
                fünfzigsten Versammlung deutscher Philologien und Schülmanner (Graz 1909). Leipzig:
                B. G. Teubner, 1910. pp. 15–19.</bib>
            <notes> Abstract of his lecture at the congress. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J325">
            <bib> -----. "Zum altenglischen Versbau." Englische Studien 44 (1912): 303–42.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J326">
            <bib> -----. "Sprache und Versbau der altenglischen Rätseln." Anglia 38 (1914):
                355–64.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J327">
            <bib> -----. "Weiteres zu den altenglischen Rätseln und Metrisches." Anglia 43 (1919):
                245–60.</bib>
            <notes> Trautmann's work on Old English versification (cited here in chronological
                order) was both preceded and followed by a number of articles on Middle English
                versification, especially on Layamon (see K404), not to speak of the many other
                articles he produced on philology and phonetics. His students (in Old English:
                Kuhnke, Einenkel, Menthel, and Schmitz) also published several long articles
                applying Trautmann's theories to the whole corpus of Old Ger- manic, Old English and
                Middle English verse. But all of their work is deriva- tive so I treat the entire
                body of it together here as being almost literally a sin- gle-minded effort.
                Trautmann's work is significant not in terms of its accuracy or its legitimacy but
                in terms of its sheer bulk. His own publications and the publications of his
                students are quite extensive, and though his theory has not been followed by later
                scholars--indeed it is hardly ever cited at all anymore-- still Trautmann was the
                last and probably the most vigorous proponent of the old vierhebungstheorie in
                Germany (the theory which Kaluza described as "the-
                good-old-much-despised-and-often-pronounced-dead-but-on-this-account-
                only-so-much-the-more-tenaciously-clinging-to-life-Lachmannian-four-
                accent-theory"), and for that reason merits notice. But even in Germany the theory
                was not widely accepted, and in fact after it had been rejected by both Sievers and
                Schipper in the '80s, Trautmann was responsible for palpitating the corpse of the
                system for several decades thereafter so as to make it give feeble signs of life. In
                Trautmann's view, Old and Middle English verse consisted not of one long line
                divided into two hemistichs but of a couplet of two short lines (verses), an
                extension of the (rhyming) short-couplet form first introduced into Germany by
                Otfrid in the ninth century. And, in contrast to Sievers, he con- sidered the
                Germanic line to be sung verse not recited verse (sprechvers). More specifically, he
                scanned each short line or verse as having four bars (takte) and strict measurement
                of time (Zeitmass), each takt being composed of two parts, a lift and a dip, each of
                which was equivalent to one short syllable, two short equaling one long, the whole
                system producing sixteen types of verses (as op- posed to Kaluza's ninety), eight of
                them in disyllabic and eight in monosyllabic bars. Within these sixteen there were
                twelve "seemingly three-bar" types (Trautmann thought they had been two-bar types in
                an older stage of the lan- guage) of four disyllabic and eight monosyllabic bars.
                This Viertakte or four-bar theory Trautmann applied rigorously to Old English verse,
                but when it came to Middle English verse he recognized that the second half-line or
                off-verse was weaker and adjusted his theory from an eight-bar to a seven-bar. The
                dif- ficulty with the whole theory is that it requires a considerable distortion of
                the linguistic material to find four beats or four bars in one half-line of Old
                English verse when frequently there are only four syllables in that verse. Further,
                Trautmann insisted, against all the other four-stress theorists, that all four
                stresses were equal. The traditional four-stress view had argued for only two
                primary stresses, accompanied by two secondary stresses, and even some of
                Trautmann's own students quailed before the extremity of his position on this
                matter. Following the publication of Einenkel's and Menthel's papers in 1884 and
                1885, Schipper made an effort to combat Trautmann's views in print in 1886 (see
                J263). Schipper's position in support of two stresses per half-line has been the one
                borne out by history. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J328">
            <bib> Tschischwitz, Benno. Die Metrik der angelsächsischen Psalmenübersetzung. Diss.,
                Greifswald, 1908. Breslau: Fleischmann, 1908. 116 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Follows Sievers, giving an inventory of the metrical Types, the varieties of al-
                literation, and the number and quantity of syllables. Results begin on p. 93.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J329">
            <bib> Turner, Sharon. "On the Anglo-Saxon Versification." The History of the Anglo-
                Saxons, From the Earliest Period to the Norman Conquest. 3 vols. London: Longman,
                Brown, Green, and Longmans, 1829. Vol. 3, Book 9, chapter 4, pp. 308–11.</bib>
            <notes> Only of historical interest; Turner believed that OE verse "had really no other
                rule than the poet's ear." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J330">
            <bib> Waterhouse, Ruth. "Affective Language, Especially Alliterating Qualifiers, in
                Ælfric's Life of St. Alban." Anglo-Saxon England 7 (1978): 131–48.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J331">
            <bib> Watts, Ann Chalmers. The Lyre and the Harp: A Comparative Reconsideration of Oral
                Tradition in Homer and Old English Epic Poetry. Yale Studies in English, no. 169.
                New Haven: Yale University Press, 1969.</bib>
            <notes> The work of F. P. Magoun inconsistently and inadequately applies the Parry- Lord
                theory of oral-formulaic composition to Old English. The evidence is ambiguous, we
                do not know enough, and Magoun is not thorough-going in his explanation. The best
                introduction to the whole field of oral-formulaic theory: Watts reviews the
                literature for both Homeric Greek and Old English. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J332">
            <bib> Webster, A. Blyth. "Translation from Old English: A Note and an Experiment."
                Essays and Studies 5 (1914): 153–71.</bib>
            <notes> William Morris's mistake in translating Beowulf into alliterative stress-verse
                was to take the rhythmical form too literally: "instead of writing a modern form of
                the measure based on the same principles as the old, he ignored the changes in the
                structure and character of the language and tried to write again the actual form of
                the original verse itself." Sample. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J333">
            <bib> Westlake, J. S. "The Old English Sung, or Ballad, Metre." The Cambridge History of
                English Literature. Ed. A. W. Ward and A. R. Waller. 14 vols. New York and London:
                G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1907–16. Vol. 1, pp. 461–68. (Appendix to Chapter VII.)</bib>
            <notes> The popular verse, Westlake argues, was in a dipodic meter having four stresses
                to the verse instead of the two of the epic meter. Of these four two were full and
                two half stresses, with a slack or resolved pair of slacks interca- lated optionally
                between each stress, i.e.: (X) / (X) \ (X) / (X) \ Such a view mediates between the
                two-beat and four-beat theories. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J334">
            <bib> Whitman, F. H. "A Major Compositional Technique in Old English Verse." ELN 11
                (1973): 81–86.</bib>
            <notes> A claim that much Old English verse was composed by the "primitive" tech- nique
                of merely adding semantically weak or redundant words to straightfor- ward prose so
                as to fill out the alliterative requirements of the line. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J335">
            <bib> -----. "The Meaning of 'Formulaic' in Old English Verse Composition." Neuphilo-
                logische Mitteilungen 76 (1975): 529–37.</bib>
            <notes> The meaning of "formulaic" as applied to the composition of verse may be
                sharpened considerably if we recognize it as a twofold process, entailing first the
                translation of crucial Latin phrases rather literally and second the addition of
                semantically empty or redundant words to meet the alliterative requirements of the
                meter. That is, [this is striking] what is "formulaic" about a phrase is not the
                fixity of its essential idea or head noun but the actual variation of its exte- rior
                members. These appendages do not detract from the sense of the kernel, but they do
                not add to it either, and it is they who perform the critical work of fitting the
                kernel idea into the metrical context. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J336">
            <bib> -----. "Rules Governing the Meter of ÞA-, ÞÆR-, and SIÐÐAN-Verses in Beowulf."
                English Studies 59 (1978): 385–89.</bib>
            <notes> A micrometrical rule to be added to the standard descriptive system: in those
                specific environments where one of the above three adverbs (sometimes con-
                junctions) begins the verse, "the Beowulf poet followed a consistent rule gov-
                erning how many unstressed syllables might precede the first stress ( þa / þær / or
                stem + 1 for 'standard' verses; þa / þær / or stem + 2 for 'light' verses) and only
                departed from this rule in a limited number of specific contexts." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J337">
            <bib> Whittier, Phyllis G. "Syntax and Poetry in Four Old English Elegies." DA 29
                (1969): 2232A (Oregon).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J338">
            <bib> Willard, Rudolph, and Elinor D. Clemons. "Bliss's Light Verses in the Beowulf."
                JEGP 66 (1967): 230–44.</bib>
            <notes> They anatomize Bliss's light verses syntactically and metrically but only
                quarrel with certain lesser matters of sigla and treatment. Generally approbatory.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J339">
            <bib> Williams, Donald M. "Syntactic Units, Verse Types, and the Long Line in Beowulf."
                DAI 37 (1976): 346A (Texas).</bib>
            <notes> Part of the explanation for the distribution of verse-types within the lines of
                Beowulf lies in the fact that certain types either do or do not conveniently be- gin
                or conclude syntactic phrases. But Type A verses, more flexible, appear in pairs
                less frequently than they might, which suggests that Bliss was partly right to claim
                that the Beowulf-poet preferred to have one a-verse in every line but not two.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J340">
            <bib> Wolf, Jerome L. "Bearwas: An Experiment in Old English Prosody." DAI 35 (1975):
                4465A (Southern Illinois).</bib>
            <notes> Two experiments to show that "the language itself is the chief formative ele-
                ment of Old English prosody irrespective of theories of rhythm." In the first, the
                author composes 1833 lines of OE verse to see if he can duplicate its rhythm. In the
                second, he attempts to reproduce in Old English verses the metrical systems of Latin
                quantitative verse, the medieval Latin cursus, and the Old Norse skaldic verse;
                success in each case is in direct proportion to the closeness of the language to Old
                English. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J341">
            <bib> Woolf, Henry B. "The Naming of Women in Old English Times." MP 36 (1938):
                113–20.</bib>
            <notes> Alliteration and variation were used in the naming of women as well as men.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J342">
            <bib> -----. "Subject-Verb Agreement in Beowulf." MLQ 4 (1943): 49–55.</bib>
            <notes> Adds instances of failure of subject-verb agreement to those noted by Klaeber.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J343">
            <bib> Wrenn, C. L. "Form and Style in Anglo-Saxon Literature." In his A Study of Old
                English Literature. London: George G. Harrap, 1967</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt 1975. pp. 35–56. This third chapter provides an admirably succinct account
                of Old English me- ter (the Five Types system), formulaic diction, kennings, and
                rhyth- mic/alliterative prose. But the third chapter also treats the continuity of
                meter and language from Old English forward, and there are other references to me-
                ter throughout this useful book; see the Index s.v. "Meter." The Anglo-Latin works,
                Bede's De Arte Metrica and Aldhelm's Epistola ad Acircium are discussed early in
                chapter 4. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J344">
            <bib> -----. "Sutton Hoo and Beowulf." Mélanges de linguistique et de philologie,
                Fernand Mossé In Memoriam. Paris: Didier, 1959. pp. 495–507.</bib>
            <notes> See the section on "The Musical Instrument." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J345">
            <bib> -----. "Two Anglo-Saxon Harps." Comparative Literature 14 (1962): 118–28.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="J346">
            <bib> Youngberg, Karin L. "A Comparative Study of Stylistic Patterns in Old English
                Heroic Poetry and in the Old Norse Poetic Edda." DA 28 (1968): 3162A (Iowa).</bib>
            <notes> Examines patterns of parallelism and repetition, compounding, and endstop-
                ping/enjambment. Not an exhaustive catalogue. </notes>
        </item>
    </chapter>
</bibliography>
