<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="MIDDLE ENGLISH">

        <item id="K1">
            <bib>Adam, E., ed. "[Sir] Torrent of Portyngale." Early English Text Society, Extra
                Series, no. 51. London: Trübner, 1887.</bib>
            <notes> "Metre and Versification," pp. vi–x. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K2">
            <bib>Adams, Percy G. "Chaucer's Assonance." JEGP 71 (1972): 527–39.</bib>
            <notes> Scholarly interest in the structural and ornamental properties of
                alliteration--so obvious a feature--has obscured the role--even the degree--of
                assonance and its effects in Middle English verse, but as Adams shows, Chaucer's use
                of the latter device is if anything even more pervasive than the less subtle
                alliteration. He may have learned it from either the French or the Italian
                traditions, where it is common due to inflection, but it also appears more
                frequently than we think in the native OE and ME tradition, often as a result of
                rhetorical figuration. See the author's larger study (C127), but see also the
                criticism by Finnie (K116). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K3">
            <bib>Agard, Frederick B. "The Anglo-Norman Versification of the Roman de Toute
                Chevalerie." Romanic Review 33 (1942): 216–35.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K4">
            <bib>Amours, F. J., ed. Scottish Alliterative Poems in Riming Stanzas. Scottish Text
                Society Publications, no. 27. Edinburgh: William Blackwood, 1897.</bib>
            <notes> "Remarks on the Versification," pp. lxxxii–lxxxix, discusses the use of the
                bob-and-wheel stanza in five poems. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K5">
            <bib>Anttila, Raimo. "Sound Preference in Alliteration." Statistical Methods in
                Linguistics 5 (1969): 44–48.</bib>
            <notes> The Gawain poet, tested by tabulation and chi-square, definitely prefers k, b,
                g, and l sounds for alliteration, while avoiding fricatives and vowels. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K6">
            <bib>Auden, W. H. "John Skelton." In The Great Tudors. Ed. Katherine Garvin. New York:
                E. P. Dutton, 1935. pp. 55–67.</bib>
            <notes> Approbation for Skelton's metrical virtuosity in Magnyfycence. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K7">
            <bib>Babcock, Charlotte F. "A Study of the Metrical Use of the Inflectional E in Middle
                English, with Particular Reference to Chaucer and Lydgate." PMLA 29 (1914):
                59–92.</bib>
            <notes> A study of intralinear apocopation in Chaucer (and Lydgate) which is consid-
                erably hampered by the absence of a firmly-established chronology for the canon.
                Allowing for trisyllabic and inverted feet, epic caesurae and the "bro- ken-backed"
                line, and headless lines, the frequency of apocopation (based on a sample) seems to
                be about 30% in Chaucer, decreasing over time. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K8">
            <bib>Basilius, Harold A. "A Phonology of the Alsfeld Passion Play as Determined Rimes."
                Diss., Ohio State University, 1935.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K9">
            <bib>-----. "Rhymes in Eger and Grime." MP 35 (1937): 129–33.</bib>
            <notes> Dialectal evidence in the rhymes furnishes indications of location and date of
                composition for this Middle English versified romance. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K10">
            <bib>Baum, P. F. "Chaucer's Metrical Prose." JEGP 45 (1946): 38–42.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K11">
            <bib>-----. Chaucer's Verse. Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press, 1961. 144 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: by Standop in Anglia 80 (1962): 448–53; in Review of English Studies n.s.
                14 (1963): 397–98; in JEGP 63 (1964): 141–47; in Speculum 39 (1964): 112– 14; in MP
                62 (1964): 60–62; in Arizona Quarterly 19 (1964): 271–74. Baum's handbook of
                Chaucerian versification is designed both to entertain and to instruct, by
                illustrating various aspects of Chaucer's verse-technique. Conse- quently it is not
                a treatise or a theory of Chaucerian meter; it is a reassertion of the traditional
                views. Baum draws his conclusions from limited samples and generally prefers to
                treat all questions as matters of taste, not wishing to inquire into any one
                question so far as to take a decided position. He sees Chaucer's line as both
                syllabic and accentual, ultimately "a series of five iambs." Chapter 1 treats the
                technicalities of versification: metrical variation (weak stresses, spondees,
                substitution, use of final -e, and elision), the iambic tetrameter (oc- tosyllabic)
                couplets (they show greater irregularity because they are founded on both native and
                foreign models, the native accentual influence being strong), rhyme (Chaucer
                decidedly prefers feminines, and certain specific rhyme-pairs as well) and stanza
                (his favorite was the royal, of course, which may have been the source for the
                couplet if it did not come from lengthening the short cou- plets). Chapter 2 treats
                sound texture and further metrical variation (irregular lines, enjambement, pauses,
                and variant weighting of consecutive lines); chap- ter 3 illustrates the
                "embellishments," the "purple inlays" in the verse. An Ap- pendix criticizes
                Southworth's theory (K367). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K12">
            <bib>Bazire, Joyce. "ME *e and *e in the Rhymes of Sir Gawain and the Green Knight."
                JEGP 51 (1952): 234–35.</bib>
            <notes> Two instances of tensing of the slack form. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K13">
            <bib>Behre, Frank. "A Middle English Rhyme-Pair: Further Studies in Scandinavian
                Origins." English Studies 40 (1959): 353–58.</bib>
            <notes> Semantic congruity in the rhymes ouse:trouse in the fourteenth-century work
                Thomas Castleford's Chronicle. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K14">
            <bib>Benson, Larry D. King Arthur's Death: The Middle English "Stanzaic Morte Arthur"
                and "Alliterative Morte Arthure." Indianapolis: Bobbs-Merrill, 1974.</bib>
            <notes> "Versification and Style," pp. xxix–xxxii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K15">
            <bib>-----. "The Style." Art and Tradition in "Sir Gawain and the Green Knight."
                Brunswick, N.J.: Rutgers University Press, 1965. pp. 110–66.</bib>
            <notes> Especially pp. 112–17, a simplified description of the ME alliterative line.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K16">
            <bib>Berdan, John M. "The Poetry of Skelton: A Renaissance Survival of Medieval Latin
                Influence." Romanic Review 6 (1915): 364–77.</bib>
            <notes> The Skeltonic verseform also appears contemporaneously in French and Ital- ian,
                suggesting that the model for all three cases is the rhymed accentual Latin verse of
                the Middle Ages. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K17">
            <bib>Bergen, Henry, ed. Lydgate's "Fall of Princes." Part I. Early English Text
                Society, Extra Series, no. 121. London: Oxford University Press, 1924 (for
                1918).</bib>
            <notes> "The Metre," pp. xxviii–xlvi. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K18">
            <bib>-----. Lydgate's Troy Book. Part I. Early English Text Society, Extra Series, no.
                97. London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co., 1906.</bib>
            <notes> Pages xi–xvii of the "Introductory Note" provide an inventory of metrical
                verse-types based on Schick's categories. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K19">
            <bib>Beschorner, Franz. Verbale Reime bei Chaucer. Studien zur Englischen Philologie,
                vol. 60. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1920. 32 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Promotes the thesis that the use of verbs as rhyme-words was an "uncom- monly
                strong" predilection of Chaucer's. Disputed by Mustanoja (K267). Cf. Masui (K248).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K20">
            <bib>Biggins, Dennis. "Chaucer's Metrical Lines: Some Internal Evidence." Parergon 17
                (1977): 17–24.</bib>
            <notes> Interesting comparative scansions of the Prologue's first 18 lines by South-
                worth, Baum, Robinson, and Conner are cited. Biggins buttresses his homely thesis
                that Chaucer's lines were meant to be iambic pentameters by showing 80 of the first
                100 lines to be acceptable pentameters, in five varieties, even if final -e is
                ignored. Beyond such a statistic, however, everything--both general prin- ciples and
                specific scansions--is uncertain. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K21">
            <bib>Bihl, Josef. Die Wirkungen des Rhythmus in der Sprache von Chaucer und Gower.
                Anglistische Forschungen, vol. 50. Heidelberg: Carl Winter, 1916. 271 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in Englische Studien 52 (1918): 94–97; in Die Neuren Sprachen 24 (1916):
                561–62; in Archiv 135 (1916): 467; 138 (1919): 243–44. Metrical treatment of
                syllables, stressing, word-formation, and syntax. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K22">
            <bib>Bischoff, O. über zweisilbige Senkung und epische Caesur bei Chaucer. Diss.,
                Königsberg. Darmstadt, 1897. Rpt. in Englische Studien 24 (1898): 353–92; 25 (1899):
                339– 98.</bib>
            <notes> On the question of double-unaccented syllables at line-beginning and at cae-
                sura; as to the latter, Bischoff concludes in the negative, thinking elision always
                occurs there. Lists of syllabic variations in Chaucer's lines. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K23">
            <bib>Björkman, Erik. "Zum alliterierende Morte Arthure." Anglia 39 (1916):
                253–67.</bib>
            <notes> Argument about the legitimacy of textual emendations on metrical grounds.
                Björkman considers that unstressed prefixes may occasionally bear alliteration, and
                that the alliteration does not invariably mark the primary stresses. A great deal,
                he concludes, remains unclear. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K24">
            <bib>Björkman, Erik, ed. "Morte Arthure": Mit Einleitung, Ammerkungen, und Glossar.
                Heidelberg: Carl Winter, 1915.</bib>
            <notes> "Metrik," pp. xxiv–xxvi. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K25">
            <bib>Blake, N. F. "Chaucer and the Alliterative Romances." Chaucer Review 3 (1969):
                163–69.</bib>
            <notes> Judging from a close explication of the "rum, ram, ruf" passage in the Prologue
                to the Parson's Tale and analysis of vocabulary and alliteration in the alliterative
                passages in the Knight's Tale and the Legend of Good Women, Chaucer was not
                explicitly intending to imitate the style of the alliterative romances, nor is there
                much reason on any other grounds to believe he knew them at all. The "rum, ram, ruf"
                passage refers to alliteration in general. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K26">
            <bib>-----. "Rhythmical Alliteration." MP 67 (1969): 118–24.</bib>
            <notes> The older view that ME Alliterative Revival verse must have sprung from a
                (hypothesized) continuous tradition of OE popular poetry (now entirely lost) is
                really not very tenable; a much more probable explanation (heretofore ig- nored)
                results from our recollection of the very close "interanimation" of prose and verse
                in ME. There "the boundary between verse and prose was so blurred that a clear
                division is impossible," and this intermediary, mixed form may be termed rhythmical
                alliteration; it was a verbal mode which could be al- ternately lined or unlined
                without concern. Moreover, it was the OE prose texts, preserved by the clergy and
                less vulnerable to change in the language than more strictly ordered verbal
                structures, which were recopied throughout the twelfth century, not the high OE
                poetry. The Brut shows a later develop- ment of this hybrid mode. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K27">
            <bib>Bock, Franz. Metrische Studien zu Thomas Hoccleves Werken. Diss., Munich,
                1900.</bib>
            <notes> Finds Hoccleve's verse to be syllabically irregular and metrically full of
                hover- ing accents (schwebende Betonung). Reply by Kern (K188). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K28">
            <bib>Boerner, Oskar. "Reimuntersuchung über die Qualität der betonten langen E- Vokale
                bei Robert of Brunne." Festschrift für Lorenz Morsbach. Ed. F. Holthausen and H.
                Spies. Studien zur englischen Philologie, vol. 50. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1913. pp.
                298–351.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K29">
            <bib>Börsch, Joseph. über Metrik und Poetik der altenglischen Dichtung "The Owl and the
                Nightingale." Münster, 1883. 78 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Part 1 (pp. 13–27) summarizes the metrical, alliterative, and rhyme features.
                The poem is in four-beat iambic tetrameter couplets. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K30">
            <bib>Bond, George D. "The Factors Governing the Pronunciation of Chaucer's Final - E."
                Diss., University of Michigan, 1947.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K31">
            <bib>Borroff, Marie. "Pearl": A New Verse Translation. New York: W. W. Norton, 1977.
                "The Metrical Form" and "Specimen Scansions," pp. 32–39.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K32">
            <bib>-----. "Sir Gawain and the Green Knight": A Stylistic and Metrical Study. New
                Haven: Yale University Press, 1962</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. Hamden, Conn.: Archon/Shoe String, 1973. Rev.: in MLQ 24 (1963): 307–8;
                in JEGP 62 (1963): 364–65; in MLR 58 (1963): 234–35; in Anglia 81 (1963): 477–81; in
                Speculum 39 (1964): 494–96; in Archiv 201 (1964): 64–66; in Review of English
                Studies n.s. 15 (1964): 194– 96; in Medium Ævum 33 (1964): 145–47. See Part 2 on
                Meter, though Part 1 on Style is also of interest. After an examination of the
                stressing of OF loan-words in ME and the question of the sounding of inflectional
                -e, Borroff makes a preliminary metrical analysis (for purposes of comparison) of
                the meter of Cursor Mundi, finding it accentual- syllabic (in fact, a plain iambic
                tetrameter with inversions, etc.), the syllable- counting deriving from French and
                the accent-alternation from Medieval Latin. About a dozen unambiguous examples show
                that the final -e in rhyme was not pronounced. She then reviews (valuably, in
                detail) the dispute be- tween the four-beat and the seven-beat theories of the ME
                long-line meter; following Leonard (K215) and Stewart (K379), Borroff tries to
                negotiate a middle course between them by scanning the stresses as dipodic (her term
                is "compound"), but in the end she settles on the four-beat view, allowing five in
                "extended" lines, which are treated in the final chapter. The analysis as a whole is
                based on Thomson [one had hoped he had been forgotten, but no], Elder Olson (B158),
                and Kokeritz; it is, both in its conception and its method- ology, an exceedingly
                conservative approach. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K33">
            <bib>Bowen, Edwin W. "Confusion between *o and o in Chaucer's Rimes." Englische Studien
                20 (1895): 341–44.</bib>
            <notes> On the basis of quite a few instances, we can conclude that Chaucer occasion-
                ally allowed the rhyming of closed and open o "in order to meet the exigencies of
                his verse." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K34">
            <bib>Brandstädter, Kurt. Stabreim und Endreim in Layamons "Brut." Diss., Königsberg.
                Kirchhain, 1912. 42 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Analyzes the number, types, and positions of alliteration, the influence of end-
                rhyme on the alliteration, and the varieties of end-rhyme in the poem, in- cluding a
                summary table (p. 25) of statistics on alliteration patterns in the solely
                alliterative vs. alliterating-and-rhymed lines, by thousand-line sections. The al-
                literation is looser in Layamon than in its classical form, and "rhyme" is much more
                difficult to define adequately here than later. The usual form is internal rhyme (in
                the long-line), giving short couplets, but long couplets do appear, and, more
                rarely, even longer schemes. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K35">
            <bib>Breier, W. "Bemerkungen zur Metrik von Eule und Nachtigall." Englische Studien 42
                (1910): 306–7.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K36">
            <bib>Brie, Friedrich. "Skelton-Studien." Englische Studien 37 (1906): 1–86. "Das
                Skelton'sche Metrik," pp. 78–83.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K37">
            <bib>Bright, James W. "The Rhetoric of Verse in Chaucer." PMLA 16 (1901): xl–xlii
                (Proceedings).</bib>
            <notes> On the relation of stressing and inflection to meaning: "by the rhetoric of
                verse . . . is meant the emphasis elicited by verse-stress when it is at variance
                with the usual (prose) emphasis." Bright shows how Chaucer bases metrical stressing
                on prepositions and other words not normally stressed in speech. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K38">
            <bib>Brink, August. Stab und Wort in Gawain: Eine stilistische Untersuchung. Studien
                zur englischen Philologie, vol. 59. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1920. 56 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: by Luick in Englische Studien 56 (1922): 411–14. A study of the frequency
                of single words in alliteration and the relationship between the alliteration
                system, morphology, and semantics ("poetic value"). The staves generally demand
                syntactically strong words but weak ones do ap- pear; it also prefers those words
                bearing primary stress which are also strong semantically. Gawain is compared to
                four of its ME fellows. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K39">
            <bib>Brink, Bernard Ten. Chaucers Sprache und Verskunst. Strasburg and Leipzig,
                1884.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in Anglia 7 (1884): 141–43 and in Englische Studien 10 (1887): 114–17.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K40">
            <bib>Second edition revised by Kluge Friedrich. Leipzig: C. H. Tauchnizt, 1899,
                1901</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. New York: Haskell House, 1968. Rev.: in Anglia Beiblatt 12 (1901):
                237–40. Translated by </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K41">
            <bib>Smith, M. B. The Language and Meter of Chaucer. London: Macmillan, 1901.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K42">
            <bib>Revised third edition ed. by E. Eckhardt. Leipzig: C. H. Tauchwitz, 1920;</bib>
            <notes> rpt. Westport, Conn.: Greenwood Press, 1969. Rev.: in Englische Studien 36
                (1906): 131–33; by Bright in MLN 36 (1921): 123–27; in Archiv 142 (1921): 281–82; by
                Kaluza in Anglia Beiblatt 32 (1921): 265–67; in Neophilologue 6 (1921): 4; in
                Englische Studien 54 (1920): 400–3. See </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K43">
            <bib>Smith, M. B. "Some Remarks on Chapter III of Ten Brink's Sprache und
                Verskunst"</bib>
            <notes> (K361) and also </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K43a">
            <bib>Jiriczek. "Skeat's Debt to Ten Brink"</bib>
            <notes> in Anglia Beiblatt 33 (1922): 120. A monument of Chaucer scholarship, surpassed
                up to its time perhaps only by Tyrwhitt in the eighteenth century: Ten Brink's
                formulations and synthesis of the German work before him became the foundation for
                all the work on Chaucer's prosody after the turn of the twentieth century. To be
                sure, some of his principles are now (a century later) outdated, but the edifice
                remains ad- mirable in form even if it is seldom used. The edifice contains three
                chambers: Phonology, Accidence, and Verse and Stanza Structure, each carefully
                delim- ited, divided, organized, and ordered. In Chaucer's metric, Ten Brink distin-
                guishes the natural stresses from the metrical rhythm, and further, three possi- ble
                results when these two systems conflict: "either the accent must yield to the
                exigencies of the verse--accent shift; or the rhythm must conform to the normal
                accentuation--inversion of the metrical measure; or finally, in delivery a
                compromise must be attempted of such a character that the hearer remains conscious
                both of the natural accentuation and of the claims of the rhythm-- level
                stress--veiled rhythm" [italics added]. The "level stress" is a compromise scansion.
                How modern all this sounds! The cracks in the edifice arise from a ground-fault: Ten
                Brink takes the Chaucerian line as an iambic decasyllable more than pentameter, and
                so whenever a line fails to be ten-syllabled, he immediately emends. We know better
                than that now. But his text is the irreproachable Chaucer Society Six- Text Edition,
                his terms are very clear, and his command of detail is sure. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K44">
            <bib>Brock, Edmund, ed. "Morte Arthure," or "The Death of Arthur." Early English Text
                Society, Original Series, no. 8. 2nd ed. London: Oxford University Press, 1871</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. 1967. Brock's revised edition reprints Perry's "On the Metre of the Poem"
                un- changed on pp. ix–xiii (see K292). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K45">
            <bib>Brown, Arthur C. L. "On the Origin of Stanza Linking in English Alliterative
                Verse." Romanic Review 7 (1916): 271–83.</bib>
            <notes> A companion-piece to Medary (K252). The devices of stanza-linking and be-
                ginning and ending a poem with the same word cannot have originated under the
                influence of Romance or Medieval Latin, as has been suggested, since no body of
                sources can be found. The devices are very common in Irish and Welsh, however, which
                must surely be the sources. Brown notes that the in- fluence of Irish and Welsh
                prosodic conventions on the Alliterative Revival in the North of Britain has been
                entirely unexplored. But cf. Travis (L264, L266). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K46">
            <bib>Brown, Jack A. "Melodic and Rhythmic Patterns in the First Extant Songs in the
                English Language." DA 29 (1968): 864A (Florida).</bib>
            <notes> An examination of the dozen or so extant thirteenth-century songs having both
                music and text in order to determine the influence of medieval music on the metering
                of lyrics. Certain relations can be shown: one stressed syllable is set equivalent
                to two unstressed ones, and in general the music is a respecter of neither line-end
                nor rhyme. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K47">
            <bib>Bruce, J. Douglas. "The Middle English Metrical Romance 'Le Morte Arthur'
                (Harleian MS 2252): Its Sources and Its Relation to Sir Thomas Malory's 'Morte
                D'Arthur.'" Anglia 23 (1901): 67–100.</bib>
            <notes> Nothing on metrics, but valuable background information. Both Malory and the
                romance have a common French source. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K48">
            <bib>Bruce, J. Douglas, ed. "Le Morte Arthur": A Romance in Stanzas of Eight Lines.
                Early English Text Society, Extra Series, no. 88. London: Kegan Paul, Trench,
                Trübner &amp; Co., 1903.</bib>
            <notes> "The Metre," pp. xxv–xxvii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K49">
            <bib>Brunner, Karl. "Die Reimsprache der sog. kentischen Fassung der 'Sieben weisen
                Meister.'" Archiv 140 (1920): 199–206.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K50">
            <bib>Brusendorff, Aage. The Chaucer Tradition. Copenhagen: V.P.P. Branner, and London:
                Oxford University Press, 1925. 510 pp.</bib>
            <notes> See especially pp. 45–48 and Index B on rhyme-tests, etc. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K51">
            <bib>Buck, Howard. "Chaucer's Use of Feminine Rhyme." MP 26 (1928): 13–14.</bib>
            <notes> It is "at the very least upon an equal footing" with the masculine, and it even-
                tually came to be used nearly systematically in rhyme royal. Such lines also tend to
                appear in clusters. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K52">
            <bib>Bülbring, K. D. "Untersuchungen zur mittelenglischen Metrik." In Festschrift für
                Lorenz Morsbach. Ed. F. Holthausen and H. Spies. Studien zur englischen Philologie,
                vol. 50. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1913. pp. 510–624.</bib>
            <notes> Still a valuable study and worth consultation, since in the first part of his
                ex- amination of the meter of the tail-rhyme romances, chiefly The Avowyng of
                Arthur, Bülbring gives a very judicious and full review of the various other
                theories put forward on the structure of the tail-rhyme meter which still re- mains
                the best available account. Disagreeing with Luick, he argues that the tail-lines
                contain three stresses and the "triplet-verses" four, the former being derived from
                the second half-line of the MEAV, the latter from the first. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K53">
            <bib>Bunzen, Asmus. Ein Beitrag zur kritik der Wakefielder Mysterien. Diss., Kiel,
                1903. 58 pp.</bib>
            <notes> An adherent of the vierhebungstheorie, the author scans the ME long-line as 4 +
                3 stresses, but he emphasizes sharply the difference between primaries and sec-
                ondaries, a point which separates him visibly from the Trautmann school. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K54">
            <bib>Butler, Norbert P. "An Analysis of the Metrics of Sir Gawain and the Green
                Knight." Diss., University of Wisconsin, 1930.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K55">
            <bib>Cargill, Oscar. "The Authorship of the Secunda Pastorum." PMLA 41 (1926):
                810–31.</bib>
            <notes> See pp. 814–19 on the meter of this best of the Towneley Plays. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K56">
            <bib>Casling, Dennis, and V. J. Scattergood. "One Aspect of Stanza-Linking."
                Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 75 (1974): 79–91.</bib>
            <notes> Medary (K252) found stanza-linking in ME verse so pervasive that she as- sumed
                that instances of its absence were due to either incompetence or textual corruption,
                but at least some of these lacunae or breaks seem to be intentional variations.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K57">
            <bib>Casson, L. F., ed. "The Romance of Sir Degrevant." Early English Text Society,
                Original Series, no. 221. London: Oxford University Press, 1949 (for 1944).</bib>
            <notes> "Metre," pp. xxxi–xli, discusses the theories of Trautmann, Luick, and Finster-
                busch on scanning the tail-rhyme and triplet-lines, followed by "Alliteration" on
                xlii–xlv. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K58">
            <bib>Child, C. G. "Verse as Prose in the Ayenbite." MLN 10 (1895): col. 127.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K59">
            <bib>Child, Francis J. "Observations on the Language of Chaucer." Memories of the
                American Academy of Arts and Sciences n.s. 8 (1863): 445–502</bib>
            <notes>. Abridged and reordered by A. J. Ellis in his Early English Pronunciation (C9),
                pp. 342–97. Child gives the first formulation of the strict syllabist theory of
                Chaucer's me- ter, a view accepted later by Ten Brink, and a view which Child
                derived from Tyrwhitt, who saw the origin of the Chaucerian line in the Italian
                endecasyl- labo. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K60">
            <bib>Christophersen, Paul. "The Scansion of Two Lines in Chaucer." English Studies
                Presented to R. W. Zandvoort. Amsterdam, 1964. pp. 146–50.</bib>
            <notes> As a buttress of the iambic-pentameter theory against the assailing foe, South-
                worth (K368), the author argues meticulously a regular scansion for the trou-
                blesome lines A49 and A173 of the General Prologue (Manly-Rickert ed.). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K61">
            <bib>Clark, Cecily. "Sir Gawain and the Green Knight: Characterization by Syntax."
                Essays in Criticism 16 (1966): 361–74.</bib>
            <notes> Syntactic idiosyncrasies--especially imperatives, overfamiliarity, and avoidance
                of hypotaxis--are very closely paralleled in the speech of both the Green Knight and
                the Lord of the Castle, as well as in that of Arthur and--curiouser and
                curiouser--the Guide. In contrast, the Lady's idiom is (appropriately) much like Sir
                Gawain's own: it is highly conditional, digressive, suspenseful, and complex.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K62">
            <bib>Clark, John W. "'The Gawain-Poet' and the Substantial Adjective." JEGP 49 (1950):
                60–66.</bib>
            <notes> Clark rejects Oakden's (K274) attribution of common authorship to Sir Ga- wain,
                Pearl, Purity, Patience, and St. Erkenwald on the basis of this feature, as he does
                for another feature, vocabulary distribution, in: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K63">
            <bib>-----. "On Certain 'Alliterative' and 'Poetic' Words in the Poems Attributed to
                'The Gawain-Poet.'" MLQ 12 (1951): 387–98.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K64">
            <bib>Clasby, Eugene S. "The Rhythm of the Fourteenth-Century English Religious Lyric."
                DA 28 (1967): 621A (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> These lyrics are written in stress-verse, not in syllable-counting verse, the
                stresses being used (Clasby thinks) to mark off isochronous time-periods, the whole
                metrical system being "surprisingly similar" to that of the rhythmical modes in
                medieval music, even though no precise correlation of verse-time to musical-time can
                be shown. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K65">
            <bib>Clemen, Wolfgang. Chaucer's Early Poetry. Tr. C. A. M. Sym. London: Methuen &amp;
                Co., 1963</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. 1968. Passim; s.v. "Metre" in the Index. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K66">
            <bib>Coblentz, H. E. "A Rime-Index to the 'Parent Cycle' of the York Mystery Plays and
                of a Portion of the Woodkirk Conspiracio et Capito. PMLA 10 (1895): 487– 557.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K67">
            <bib>-----. "Some Suggested Rime Emendations to the York Mystery Plays." MLN 10 (1895):
                cols. 77–81.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K68">
            <bib>Conner, Jack. English Prosody From Chaucer to Wyatt. The Hague: Mouton, 1974. 98
                pp. + Bibliography and Index.</bib>
            <notes> Both Saintsbury and Wimsatt would have admired this book: with grace, lu-
                cidity, candor, and rigor, Conner sets forth his argument that "a single tradi- tion
                of prosodic theory extends all the way from Chaucer to the Elizabethans . . . all
                used the same metrical pattern . . . that of iambic feet in four-foot or five-foot
                lines." In short, Chaucer invented, and wrote, the iambic pentameter (not
                necessarily the iambic decasyllable). As support, Conner offers a hypothesis in
                medieval phonology: every consonant which ended a word had an obligatory release
                (schwa), a feature which disappeared from the language between 1500 and 1550. Thus,
                Conner directs metrical attention away from inconsistent scribal texts (and the
                vexations of the final -e) and toward the pronunciation of the words in the lines.
                His scansions thereby become considerably more com- plex, but the lines can still be
                shown to be iambic. The advantage of the the- ory is that the entire medieval
                metrical tradition from Chaucer to Shakespeare may be seen as coherent and
                continuous. In metrical studies, work of this sort- -a graceful presentation where
                the author is completely candid about his ar- gument, its assumptions, the evidence,
                and the consequences--is very, very rare. (But for a contrary appraisal see K136).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K69">
            <bib>Coote, Henry C. "Chaucer's Ten-syllable Verse." The Antiquary 8 (1883): 5–8.</bib>
            <notes> A claim that Chaucer arrived at the figure of ten syllables for a workable
                verse- line by the observation that eight was too few and twelve too many. Such an
                observation would be elementary; such a claim is something less. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K70">
            <bib>Cowling, G. H. "A Note on Chaucer's Stanza [ababbcc]." Review of English Studies 2
                (1926): 311–17.</bib>
            <notes> Chaucer's seven-line stanza rhyming ababbcc is less often tripartite (two pedes
                and a cauda), as Ten Brink thought, than bipartite; the form is bipartite--abab,
                bcc--about 40% of the time it is used, and Cowling terms this type the 4:3 type.
                Other less frequent versions are the 3:4 (aba, bbcc--over 20%), the 5:2 (ababb,
                cc--less than 20%), and a rare 2:5 (ab, abbcc). The shift from usage of the 4:3 type
                to the 3:4 type also provides a very rough metrical test for dating some of the
                poetry. All of the types show an internal syntactic or semantic pause, the volta.
                Cf. Lineberger (K220). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K71">
            <bib>Craigie, William. "The Scottish Alliterative Poems." Proceedings of the British
                Academy 28 (1942): 217–36.</bib>
            <notes> On the continuance of the old southern alliterative tradition in Scotland from
                the mid-fifteenth through the sixteenth century. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K72">
            <bib>Cromie, Henry. Rhyme-Index to the Ellesmere Manuscript of Chaucer's "Canterbury
                Tales." Chaucer Society Publications, First Series, vols. 45, 46. London: Trübner,
                1875.</bib>
            <notes> Corrections and addenda appear in vols. 47, 49. Continued by Marshall-Porter
                (K247) and Skeat (K355). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K73">
            <bib>Crosby, Ruth. "Chaucer and the Custom of Oral Delivery." Speculum 13 (1938):
                413–32.</bib>
            <notes> Background information. See also her </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K74">
            <bib>-----. "Oral Delivery in the Middle Ages." Speculum 11 (1936): 88–110.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K75">
            <bib>Cross, James E. "A Point of Chaucer's Syntax." Notes &amp; Queries 197 (1952):
                468.</bib>
            <notes> The use of the preposition "of" with a noun as an adjective. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K76">
            <bib>Crow, Charles L. Zur Geschichte des Kurzen Reimpaars im Mittelenglischen
                ("Harrowing of Hell," "Cursor Mundi," Chaucer's "House of Fame"). Diss., Göttingen,
                1892. 63 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Analyzes metrical features of the verse in each of the three poems. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K77">
            <bib>Curtis, Francis John. An Introduction of the Rimes and Phonology of the
                Middle-Scotch Romance "Clariodus": A Contribution to the History of the English
                Language in Scotland. Diss., Heidelberg, 1892. 53 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rpt. in Anglia 16 (1894): 387–450; 17 (1895): 1–68, 125–60. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K78">
            <bib>Cutler, John L. "A Manual of Middle English Stanzaic Patterns." Diss., Ohio State
                University, 1949.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K79">
            <bib>-----. "The Versification of the 'Gawain Epigone' in Humfrey Newton's Poems." JEGP
                51 (1952): 562–70.</bib>
            <notes> A detailed argument that the poem, though probably not by Newton (1466– 1536)
                himself, is masterly in metrical technique, being formed in the bob-and- wheel
                stanza, and based on Sir Gawain and the fifteenth-century De Tribus Re- gibus
                Mortuis. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K80">
            <bib>Daniel, Neil. "A Metrical and Stylistic Study of The Tale of Gamelyn." Studies in
                Medieval, Renaissance, and American Literature: A Festschrift. Fort Worth: Texas
                Christian University Press, 1971. pp. 19–32.</bib>
            <notes> The poem exhibits both rhyme and also a more-than-ornamental alliteration, and
                its meter may be read convincingly as either a four-stress or a seven-stress line;
                these facts suggest that the poem stands precisely in the gap between the two major
                traditions in English verse, the Germanic and the Romance. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K81">
            <bib>Dannenberg, Bernhard. Metrik und Sprache der mittelenglischen Romanze "The Sege
                off Melayne." Diss., Göttingen, 1890. 51 pp.</bib>
            <notes> "Metrik," pp. 4–14: a summary of metrical and rhyme characteristics of this
                tail-rhyme romance. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K82">
            <bib>D'Ardenne, S. "Two Important Metrical Facts Generally Overlooked in The Owl and
                the Nightingale." Album Willem Pée de jubilaris aangeboden bij zijn zenventigste
                verjaardag. Tongeren: George Michiels, 1973. pp. 79–84.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K83">
            <bib>Day, Mabel. "Alliteration of the Versions of Piers Plowman in its Bearing on their
                Authorship." MLR 17 (1922): 403–9.</bib>
            <notes> Marked differences in the distribution of alliterations of prepositions, and of
                the prefixes of compounds lends support to Manly's theory of multiple authorship.
                The variations are especially wide between the first and second ten Passus of the
                B-Text. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K84">
            <bib>-----. "Strophic Division in Middle English Alliterative Verse." Englische Studien
                66 (1931): 245–48.</bib>
            <notes> Kaluza (K182) was right in believing that several of the non-alliterative Middle
                English poems were divided into quatrains; there is considerable MS evidence. But no
                such evidence exists for larger strophes. The very regular marginal quatrain markers
                in the MSS reflect a strong presupposition on the part of the scribes, though there
                are cases in which the poet clearly added anomalous lines to a Passus in order to
                make the line-total equal a multiple of four. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K85">
            <bib>Deakin, Mary. "The Alliteration of Piers Plowman." MLR 4 (1909): 478–83.</bib>
            <notes> Comparative analysis of the three texts does not support Manly's thesis, but
                rather the theory of sole authorship. Deakin censures Rosenthal's work in An- glia 1
                (K320). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K86">
            <bib>Dean, Christopher. "Chaucer's Use of Function Words with Substantives." Canadian
                Journal of Linguistics 9 (1964): 67–74.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K87">
            <bib>Degginger, Stuart H. L. "The Earliest Middle English Lyrics, 1150–1325: An
                Investigation of the Influence of Latin, Provençal, and French." DA 14 (1954): 107A
                (Columbia).</bib>
            <notes> "Contemporaneously with the Norman Conquest, English lyric poetry aban- doned
                its traditional prosody, the essence of which was a fusion of natural Germanic
                accent and metre with alliteration in continuous, loose, unrhymed long-lines, and
                adopted quite a different rhythm in which stress alternated regularly with unstress
                and the lines were shorter, rimed, and commonly or- ganized into stanzas." The
                source of the new form of ME lyrics was almost ex- clusively the Latin hymn meters,
                not the Provençal or Romance verse tradi- tions. But was the source of the form the
                source of the change? The author ar- gues that it was the religious lyric in England
                which preserved the native tra- dition, combined it with the Latin one, and
                transmitted this fusion to the secular lyric later in the ME period. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K88">
            <bib>Deligiorgis, S. "Structuralism and the Study of Poetry: A Parametric Analysis of
                Chaucer's Shipman's Tale and Parlement of Fowles." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 70
                (1969): 297–306.</bib>
            <notes> A philosophy of form . . . an attempt to go "beyond quantification and de-
                scription to the discovery of universals," by drawing out constants from the study
                of relationships. The sententious middle of ShT is packed solidly with closed
                couplets, formal, disciplined, rational, whereas the more heartfelt opening and
                conclusion allow interspersed open couplets. The linking of stan- zas in PF has a
                wider significance--or symbolism--nearly equal to that of the rhyme-and-semantic
                scheme of the rhyme royal stanza itself, for indeed the whole poem is one rhyme
                royal in structure, writ both large and small. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K89">
            <bib>Dickerson, A. Inskip. "The Book of the Duchess, Line 480." Papers of the
                Bibliographical Society of America 66 (1972): 51–54.</bib>
            <notes> Argument, mainly on the basis of the rhyme, that there is no good reason for
                deleting this line from all the modern editions as spurious. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K90">
            <bib>Donaldson, E. Talbot. "Chaucer's Final -E." PMLA 63 (1948): 1101–24.</bib>
            <notes> A reply to Southworth (K366), who replies to Donaldson in "Chaucer's Final - E
                (Continued)," PMLA 64 (1949): 601–9, followed by a summary statement from both
                parties on pp. 609–10. Donaldson turns aside from the question of the rhymes for the
                bulk of his essay in order to defend the account traditionally given of the final -e
                (it had dropped out of pronunciation by Chaucer's time or was well along in the
                process of doing so, a state of affairs leaving Chaucer in the virtually unique
                position among English poets of having an unusually supple language (dou- blets) to
                work with, and allowing him to use the -e selectively for metrical exi- gency), to
                demonstrate that Southworth's statistics are grossly distorted by a failure to
                consider elision (in fact if elision is taken into account the figures are nearly
                reversed), and to argue that Southworth's logic by a curious twist actu- ally
                confirms the traditional account. On sounding of the -e in the rhymes Donaldson
                argues in effect for consistency (if within the line then surely at the end as well)
                and for the unlikely possibility of eye-rhymes, given the aural bent of the age.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K91">
            <bib>Douglas-Lithgow, R. A. "Early-English Alliterative Poetry: (A.D. 1150 to A.D.
                1550)." Transactions of the Royal Society of Literature, series 2, vol. 16 (1894),
                pp. 99–134.</bib>
            <notes> Follows J73; succeeded by C136. Literary history, with many examples ad- duced.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K92">
            <bib>Dürmüller, Urs. Narrative Possibilities of the Tail-Rime Romances. Swiss Studies
                in English, vol. 83. Bern: Francke, 1975. 245 pp.</bib>
            <notes> At last critics begin to move beyond catalogues of forms and summaries of
                plotting to consider the intrinsic potentials and limitations for narrative devel-
                opment offered by a given form--in this case, the tail-rhyme stanza of twelve lines,
                in eight ME romances, primarily the neglected The Erl of Tollous (ca. 1400). See
                chapters 2, 3, 6.1, and 14 especially. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K93">
            <bib>Duggan, Hoyt M. "Strophic Patterns in Middle English Alliterative Poetry." MP 74
                (1977): 223–47.</bib>
            <notes> A fresh examination of the MS at The Wars of Alexander not only vindicates Max
                Kaluza's theory of strophic divisions in the poem (K182) (which most other critics
                deny) by noting additional marginal marks hitherto missed but also adds further
                weight to the theory by providing a cogent motivation for the larger strophic units:
                they are intended to correlate with units in the text of the Latin source. Further,
                the concept of a stanzaic grouping of lines which nonetheless lacks any rhyme to
                bind it together is a technique which came into MEAV from Old Norse poetry, not Old
                English. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K94">
            <bib>Easton, Morton W. "Some Features of Chaucer's Verse, especially Stress and
                Hiatus." PMLA 11 (1896): xxxiii–xxxiv (Proceedings).</bib>
            <notes> Abstract. We are informed the paper is "to be published," but if so, I have been
                unable to locate it. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K95">
            <bib>Eby, James A. "The Alliterative Meter of Piers Plowman A." DAI 32 (1972): 3948A
                (Michigan).</bib>
            <notes> Analysis of a thousand lines of the A-text fails to confirm the traditional view
                that the poem is metrically careless, loose, and erratic. All five of the conven-
                tional OE verse-types described by Sievers can be identified in Piers Plowman with
                only a minimum of divagation, and the alliterations correlate closely with the
                primary lexical stresses. Hence, we must conclude that the poet both un- derstood
                and intended to perpetuate the older alliterative verse-form, which shows that the
                tradition was continuous, not revived. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K96">
            <bib>Eckhardt, Eduard. "Die metrische Unterscheidung von ernst und komik in den
                englischen Moralitäten." Englische Studien 62 (1927–28): 152–69.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K97">
            <bib>Einenkel, Eugen. "über den Verfasser der neuangelsächsischen Legende von
                Katharina." Anglia 5 (1882): 91–123.</bib>
            <notes> "Der Vers," pp. 105–9. This scansion--the "Otfridian" four-beat theory--is in-
                correct. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K98">
            <bib>Einenkel, Eugen, ed. "The Life of St. Katherine." Early English Text Society,
                Original Series, no. 81. London: N. Trübner, 1884.</bib>
            <notes> "The Metrical Form of the Legend," pp. xxi–xxxix, treats meter and rhyme;
                Einenkel's account of the former is unreliable, as it was in his earlier study of
                this text (supra). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K99">
            <bib>Eitle, Hermann. Die Satzverknüpfung bei Chaucer. Anglistische Forschungen, vol.
                44. Heidelberg: Carl Winter, 1914. 214 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Syntax studies. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K100">
            <bib>Eliason, Norman E. "The Sound of the Verse." The Language of Chaucer's Poetry: An
                Appraisal of the Verse, Style, and Structure. Anglistica, vol. 17. Copenhagen:
                Rosenkilde and Bagger, 1972. pp. 16–59.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in Anglia 92 (1974): 451–54; in MP 72 (1974): 60–70; in Speculum 49
                (1974): 727–30; in Notes &amp; Queries 1 (1974): 230–32; in Studia Neophilologica 46
                (1974): 547–51; in English Studies 56 (1975): 153–54; in Review of English Studies
                n.s. 25 (1974): 74–76. An excellent purview of Chaucer's art of versification,
                written in an elegant, leisurely style, but accurately and widely informed on
                matters of meter, rhyme-practice, usage, and Middle English phonology
                (pronunciation). Should be ideal for advanced undergraduates. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K101">
            <bib>Ellinger, Johann. über die sprachlichen und metrischen Eigenthumlichkeiten in "The
                Romance of Sir Perceval of Galles." Troppau, 1889 (36 pp.), 1893 (39 pp.). See pp.
                26–36.</bib>
            <notes> The poem is in sixteen-line stanzas, each stanza having four parts, each part
                having three four-stress lines and a three-stress coda; the rhyme-scheme is aaab
                cccb dddb eeeb and alliteration appears. The meter is iambic-trochaic, varied by
                missing and doubled slacks, double anacrusis, and hovering stress. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K102">
            <bib>Elster, Gertrude. Zur Syntax von Barbours "Bruce." Diss., Vienna, 1936.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K103">
            <bib>Emerson, Oliver F. "Imperfect Lines in Pearl and the Rimed Parts of Sir Gawain and
                the Green Knight." MP 19 (1921): 131–41.</bib>
            <notes> An argument for emendation of 23 metrically irregular lines in Pearl and a dozen
                or so in Sir Gawain by the addition of a regularized final -e, on the grounds of
                scribal carelessness. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K104">
            <bib>-----. "The Old French Diphthong EI (EY) and Middle English Metrics." Romanic
                Review 8 (1917): 68–76.</bib>
            <notes> Skeat's hypothesis that the diphthong -ey- should be considered disyllabic for
                metrical purposes is entirely unreasonable; a whole series of ME adjectives of the
                sort seint-seinte can be accounted for as regular doublets. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K105">
            <bib>Erdmann, Axel, and Eilert Ekwall, eds. Lydgate's "Siege of Thebes." Early English
                Text Society, Extra Series, no. 125. London: Oxford University Press, 1930 (for
                1920).</bib>
            <notes> See "Lydgate's Metre and Rhymes," pp. 32–35, and the Rime-Index on pp. 137–60.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K106">
            <bib>Evans, Robert O. "Whan that Aprill(e)?" Notes &amp; Queries 202 (1957):
                234–37.</bib>
            <notes> The first line of the General Prologue may be the most disputed scansion in
                Chaucer: is it an acephalous iambic pentameter (with Aprill disyllabic) or a regular
                decasyllable with initial trochaic substitution (Aprille trisyllabic)? At least
                seven scansions are possible, but close scrutiny of the MSS evidence sug- gests that
                the traditional (Ten Brink's) view favoring the latter scansion is more likely than
                Manly's preference for the former. Indeed it is possible that Chau- cer never
                intended any of the headless lines catalogued by Freudenberger (K125) and Seeberger
                (K344). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K107">
            <bib>Evans, William W., Jr. "The Second-Person Pronoun in Sir Gawain and the Green
                Knight." DAI 24 (1964): 4184A (Florida).</bib>
            <notes> The poet's functional use of thou and you. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K108">
            <bib>Everett, Dorothy. "Chaucer's Good Ear." Review of English Studies 23 (1947): 201–
                8</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. in her Essays on Middle English Literature (see K109). pp. 139–48.
                Evidence of Chaucer's keen ear for language--his ability to distinguish and imitate
                nuances in the several varieties of speech and literature available to him in
                fourteenth-century London--may be found, inter alia, in his skillful repro- ductions
                of the alliterative and metrical structure of the long-line of the metri- cal
                romances, especially in the battle scenes of the Knight's Tale and the Legend of
                Cleopatra. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K109">
            <bib>-----. "Layamon and the Earliest Middle English Alliterative Verse" and "The
                Alliterative Revival." In her Essays on Middle English Literature. Ed. Patricia
                Kean. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1955, 1965. pp. 23–45, 46–96.</bib>
            <notes> Both of these posthumously-published essays (originally written for her vol- ume
                in the OHEL) are marvelously supple; on meters and stanzas see espe- cially pp.
                23–28, 74–75, and 87–88. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K110">
            <bib>Farish, John. "Some Spellings and Rhymes in the Scots Sege of Troy." English
                Studies 38 (1957): 200–6.</bib>
            <notes> The scribe seems to have substituted o *[o] for a in writing the manuscript,
                based on analogy. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K111">
            <bib>Ferris, Sumner. "A Hissing Stanza in Chaucer's Prioress's Tale." Neuphilologische
                Mitteilungen 80 (1979): 164–68.</bib>
            <notes> Inspection of "a tour de force of sustained onomatopoetic alliteration" in the
                PT (VII, 558–64 *[B2 1748–54]) in comparison with the only other passages of
                extended alliteration in Chaucer, KT 2601–16 and LGW 635–49. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K112">
            <bib>Fifield, Merle J. "Alliteration in the Middle English Lyrics." DAI 21 (1960):
                1553A (Illinois).</bib>
            <notes> Continuity of the old native verseform must be established not on the absence of
                metered verse in ME (as Schipper tried to do), since metered-and-rhymed verse does
                exist in ME, but on the basis of alliteration, which (upon analysis of the extant
                lyrics of the thirteenth through fifteenth centuries) can be shown to exist as a
                structural principle in ME verse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K113">
            <bib>-----. Theoretical Techniques for the Analysis of Variety in Chaucer's Metrical
                Stress. Ball State Monographs, no. 23. Muncie, Ind.: Ball State University Press,
                1973. 41 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A condensed prospectus and survey which presumes considerable linguistic and
                prosodic sophistication. Fifield reviews the works of Ten Brink, Baum, Southworth,
                and Halle-Keyser on Chaucerian metrics and finds them all in- adequate; he then
                approves and applies both the Trager-Smith and the Chomsky-Halle phonologies
                (considering the latter as an advance over the former) to the problem of Chaucerian
                stress. The four levels of stress possible in Trager-Smith will allow six possible
                forms of iambic feet, and, with addi- tional constraints, 4,004 legitimate forms of
                iambic lines (by computer analy- sis). See the Appendix for a most succinct
                statement of those constraints. The generative phonology, however, "reveals aspects
                of prosody never before ob- jectively recognized: tessitura of stress, range of
                stress, distribution and position of stress levels, the function of word order, and
                the actual operation of metrical tension on running speech-stress." A provocative
                argument that Chaucerian meter has "still unmeasured variety within its order."
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K114">
            <bib>-----. "Thirteenth-Century Lyrics and the Alliterative Tradition." JEGP 62 (1963):
                111–18.</bib>
            <notes> A summary of the results of a catalogue of alliterative formulae given in his
                dissertation (supra). Oakden did not discuss these lyrics. Continuity in MEAV is
                supported by the evidence here that over half of these formulae appear in either OE
                poetry or in fifteenth-century verse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K115">
            <bib>Finlayson, John, ed. "Morte Arthure." London: Edward Arnold, and Evanston:
                Northwestern University Press, 1967.</bib>
            <notes> "Verse," pp. 24–30, mainly discusses formulaic composition. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K116">
            <bib>Finnie, W. Bruce. "On Chaucer's Stressed Vowel Phonemes." Chaucer Review 9 (1975):
                337–41.</bib>
            <notes> Sharp criticism of Percy Adams (K2) for failing to distinguish significant
                quali- tative (open-closed) and quantitative (long-short) differentiation in Middle
                English vowels, as well as consonantal r. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K117">
            <bib>Finsterbusch, Franz. Der Versbau der mittelenglischen Dichtungen "Sir Perceval of
                Gales" und "Sir Degrevant." Wiener Beiträge zur englischen Philologie, vol. 49.
                Vienna: Wilhelm Braumüller, 1918. 181 pp.</bib>
            <notes> His dissertation at Vienna in 1916. Following Luick's analysis of The Avowyng of
                Arthur (K266), in which he showed the tail-line to be derived from the second and
                the triplet-line from the first half-line of the regular alliterative long-line,
                both verses having two beats, Finsterbusch, a student of Luick's, analyzes both
                these verseforms in two additional romances, inventorying the metrical variations
                exhaustively. Cf. Casson (K57). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K118">
            <bib>Fischer, Joseph. "Die Stabende Langzeile in den Werken des Gawaindichters." Bonner
                Beiträge zur Anglistik 11 (1901): 1–64.</bib>
            <notes> Fischer, a student of Trautmann's (see K404), applies his "seven-bar" theory
                (four in the on-verse, three in the off-verse) to Sir Gawain, Pearl, Purity, Pa-
                tience, and St. Erkenwald. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K119">
            <bib>Fischer, Joseph, and Franz Menniken. "Zur mittelenglischen Stabzeile." Bonner
                Beiträge zur Anglistik 11 (1901): 139–54.</bib>
            <notes> Students of Trautmann (see K404) and his "seven-bar" theory. Here they pursue
                their quarrel with their mortal foe Luick. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K120">
            <bib>Fisiak, Jacek. Morphemic Structure of Chaucer's English. Alabama Linguistic and
                Philological Series, no. 10. University, Ala.: University of Alabama Press, 1965.
                125 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K121">
            <bib>"The Foreign Meters in General." Schipper (A11), Book I, Part 2, Division 1. pp.
                126–82.</bib>
            <notes> This section, along with Chapter 1 on the "General Introduction to the Sci- ence
                of Metre and the Structure of Verse" (see E539), presents Schipper's con- ception of
                modern English meter as it was codified in the ME period. Includes "Verse-Rhythm,"
                "The Metrical Treatment of Syllables," and "Word-Accent." In "Verse-Rhythm" Schipper
                recognizes only the four commonest meters, though many variations of the plain
                metrical pattern are noted: suppression of the anacrusis, hovering stress, missing
                weak syllables in the middle of a line, extra syllables, inverted feet, polysyllabic
                thesis in the foot, enjambement, rhyme-breaks (on the odd lines of couplets), and
                alliteration. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K122">
            <bib>Fort, Margaret D. "The Metres of the Brome and Chester Abraham and Isaac Plays."
                PMLA 41 (1926): 832–39.</bib>
            <notes> Disputing Hohlfeld's conclusions from metrical evidence (K161) that the Chester
                miracle play on the sacrifice-of-Isaac theme was based on the earlier Brome play of
                the same subject, Fort concludes on the basis of the rhymes that Chester was the
                original and Brome the revised version. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K123">
            <bib>Frankis, P. J. "The Syllabic Value of Final -es in English Versification about
                1500." Notes &amp; Queries 212 (1967): 11–12.</bib>
            <notes> Strict syllable counting in a variant-tail-rhyme, semi-pattern poem by Stephen
                Hawes [1509] shows that final -es had full syllabic value metrically though probably
                not in pronunciation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K124">
            <bib>French, Robert D. "Chaucer's Language and Versification." A Chaucer Handbook. New
                York: F. S. Crofts, 1927; 2nd ed. 1947. pp. 339–67.</bib>
            <notes> Very slight: versification merits only the last six pages. A full treatment that
                is more recent is Eliason (K100). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K125">
            <bib>Freudenberger, Markus. über das Fehlen des Auftakts in Chaucers heroischem Verse.
                Diss., Leipzig, 1889. Erlanger Beiträge zur englischen Philologie, vol. 4. Erlangen:
                A. Deichert, 1889.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in Anglia Beiblatt 1 (1890): 88–90. The famous crux of the first line of
                the General Prologue raises the whole question of whether "headless" lines, lines
                showing a "suppression of anacrusis" or missing first slack syllable, should be
                emended, on the assumption that Chaucer's meter is strict in its syllabism, or
                retained, as metrical variations. Freudenberger examines closely each such line in
                the Skeat text of the Chau- cer canon for precedents and analogues. Appendix by
                Varnhagen on Chaucer's spellings and stressings of the name of the fourth month. See
                K106 and K344. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K126">
            <bib>Friederici, Hans. Der Lautstand Londons um 1400. Forschungen zur englischen
                Philologie, vol. 6. Jena, 1937. 95 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K127">
            <bib>Friedlander, Carolynn V. "Early Middle English Accentual Verse." MP 76 (1978– 79):
                219–30.</bib>
            <notes> The surviving fragments show that Early ME accentual verse is defined by neither
                alliteration nor rhyme but by two other specific characteristics: a verse
                (half-line) of two stresses, and heavy syntactic stopping at the end of both the
                verse and the line. These two constraints were sufficiently weak that they en-
                couraged considerable metrical variety while discouraging metrical complexity,
                whereas the stronger constraints of the Five Types did not survive changes in the
                stress-rules of the language. In this respect meter was but one element among many
                in EME verse, which as a rule chose simplification, stereotyping, and formula
                instead of their opposites. The source of EME verseform was probably not French
                (this was the nineteenth century view), OE popular po- etry (Oakden's), or
                rhythmical prose (Blake's, and the least improbable one), but rather the classical
                OE line in a degenerate form (Layamon tells us his sources are books) and Latin,
                which would have suggested rhyme to the ME poet, even though the real impetus behind
                rhyming was ultimately change in the language itself. An outstanding study. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K128">
            <bib>Friedman, Albert B., and Norman T. Harrington, eds. "Ywain and Gawain." Early
                English Text Society, Original Series, no. 254. London: Oxford University Press,
                1964 (for 1963).</bib>
            <notes> Rhyme, meter, and alliteration are discussed in the Introduction, pp.
                xlviii–liii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K129">
            <bib>Frieshammer, Johann. Die sprachliche Form der Chaucerschen Proza, ihr Verhältnis
                zur Reimtechnik des Dichters sowie zur Sprache der älteren Londoner Urkunden.
                Studien zur englischen Philologie, vol. 42. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1910.</bib>
            <notes> Part 1 presents the phonology; it is Part 2, especially p. 126 ff., that is of
                inter- est. Examples of Chaucer's use of doublets on pp. 132–34. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K130">
            <bib>Fritzsche, A. "Ist die altenglische Story of Genesis and Exodus das Werke eines
                Verfassers?" Anglia 5 (1882): 43–90.</bib>
            <notes> Meter, rhyme, and alliteration are examined on pp. 50–62. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K131">
            <bib>Fuchs, Johann. Otuelstudie: Eine grammatische und metrische Untersuchung der im
                Auchinleck-Manuskript überlieferten Fassung. Diss., Vienna, 1888.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K132">
            <bib>Fuhrmann, Johannes. Die alliterierenden Sprachformeln in Morris' "Early English
                Alliterative Poems" und in "Sir Gawaine and the Green Knight." Diss., Kiel. Hamburg,
                1886. 82 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Lists of alliterative phrases with etymologies. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K133">
            <bib>Gage, Phyllis C. "Syntax and Poetry in Chaucer's Prioress's Tale." Neophilologus
                50 (1966): 252–61.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K134">
            <bib>Gardner, John. "Versification and Form." The Complete Works of the "Gawain"-Poet.
                Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1965. pp. 85–90.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K135">
            <bib>Gaylord, Alan T. "Chaucer's Dainty 'Dogerel': The 'Elvyssh' Prosody of Sir
                Thopas." Studies in the Age of Chaucer 1 (1979): 83–104.</bib>
            <notes> After Sir Thopas is over, the matter may lurch somewhat but the meter is sure;
                we have been returned to the sure order and control of the couplets; the poet's in
                his narrative place and all's right with the world. Within, however, it is the meter
                that lurches, as Chaucer turns his hand to witty and ironic parody of the profession
                of the poet and thereby himself. (It is so with the doggerel poems that
                Shakespeare's characters proffer as good poetry in the plays.) Chaucer's joke is on
                himself, but underneath the wit there is art: when he comes to tell of poetry he
                tells it straight, so it is the way of the telling, the meter, which must serve his
                ends and belie his words, making him seem a driveler and a hack. This is the good
                art that can make bad art for play--and for purpose. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K136">
            <bib>-----. "Scanning the Prosodists: An Essay in Metacriticism." Chaucer Review 11
                (1976): 22–82.</bib>
            <notes> Not only an immensely useful article, as a full review of the major studies of
                Chaucer's versification in this century--Ten Brink, Baum, Southworth, Robinson,
                Knight, Fifield, Conner, and Halle-Keyser--but also a remarkably lucid critique of
                prosody theory itself: from fifteen exemplary passages in the "General Prologue,"
                Gaylord extracts some questions that one would want to answer about them,
                prosodically, and also a set of broader a priori questions-- assumptions--about
                Text, Pronunciation, Metrical Patterns, Versification, and Poetic Effect--that will
                have to be answered in any satisfactory theory, and that any prosodist does answer,
                implicitly if not explicitly, whenever he writes about Chaucer's versification. The
                ensuing review of the prosodic work leaves the reader glum, though, despite the
                reviewer's grace, wit, and lambent good sense, because pretty clearly the
                scholarship has made no advance in this cen- tury: no new breakthroughs have
                occurred, several bizarre theories have been proposed, the older "standard"
                philological works have not been corrected, and a general opinion has developed in
                scholarly circles that work on Chau- cer's verse-craft is just not interesting or
                important. Hopefully the present essay will effect some change in that attitude. Had
                it kept the same title and applied the same methodology, except to all of Eng- lish
                verse, I would have judged it one of the five most important works on versification
                written since Schipper. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K137">
            <bib>Gilbert, Dorothy. "The Rude Sweetness: A Study of Chaucer's Prosody and of Its
                Examiners." DAI 37 (1976): 288A (California).</bib>
            <notes> A comprehensive review of the "voluminous" scholarship on Chaucer's versifi-
                cation and analyses of his three most characteristic metrical forms: octosyllabic
                couplets, decasyllabic couplets, and rhyme royal. Gilbert views Chaucer's met- ric
                as "balancing" the foreign, literate, accentual-syllable tradition and the na- tive,
                oral, strong-stress meter, so that his lines fit the syllabic norms yet also tend to
                fall into recognizable hemistichs, resulting in a "highly complex" met- rical system
                that allows "immense variety, subtlety, and power" in its verses. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K138">
            <bib>Glauning, Otto, ed. Lydgate's Minor Poems: The Two Nightingale Poems (A.D. 1446).
                Early English Text Society, Extra Series, no. 80. London: Kegan Paul, Trench,
                Trübner &amp; Co., 1900.</bib>
            <notes> "The Metre," pp. xx–xxvi. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K139">
            <bib>Gnerlich, Robert. Bemerkungen über den Versbau der Anglonormannen. Diss.,
                Strassburg. Breslau, 1889. 57 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K140">
            <bib>Goller, Karl H. "Stab und Formel im alliterierenden Morte Arthure." Neophilologus
                49 (1965): 57–67.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K141">
            <bib>Grant, Judith, C. Peterson, and A. S. C. Ross. "Notes on the Rhymes of Pearl."
                Studia Neophilologica 50 (1978): 175–78.</bib>
            <notes> Specific etymological notes on problematic rhymes as addenda to the notes in
                Appendix 3 of E. V. Gordon's edition of Pearl. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K142">
            <bib>Green, A. Wigfall. "Chaucer's 'Sir Thopas': Meter, Rhyme, and Contrast."
                University of Mississippi Studies in English 1 (1960): 1–11.</bib>
            <notes> A schematic diagram of the rhymes, meters, and stanza-structures in the poem,
                with discussion. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K143">
            <bib>-----. "Meter and Rhyme in Chaucer's Anelida and Arcite." University of
                Mississippi Studies in English 2 (1961): 55–63.</bib>
            <notes> Analysis of the meters and rhyme schemes of the poem by stanza or group of
                stanzas, with discussion of irregularities and special effects. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K144">
            <bib>Greg, W. W. "The Continuity of the Alliterative Tradition." MLR 27 (1932):
                453–54.</bib>
            <notes> Criticizes the three arguments put forth by Oakden (K274) in support of a
                continuous alliterative tradition from Old English into Middle English. Reply by
                Oakden (K276). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K145">
            <bib>Haas, Lydia. über die Metrik des mittelenglischen Gedichtes "Die Kriege
                Alexanders" in den Handschriften Ashmole und Dublin. Diss., Vienna, 1922.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K146">
            <bib>Haggard, Elias W. "Syllable Stress in French Words as Used by Chaucer and
                Spenser." Diss., George Peabody College, 1944.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K147">
            <bib>Hall, Joseph, ed. "Metre." "King Horn": A Middle-English Romance. Oxford:
                Clarendon Press, 1901. pp. xlv–l.</bib>
            <notes> ---- Halle, Morris, and Samuel J. Keyser. "Chaucer and the Study of Prosody."
                See E777. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K148">
            <bib>Hammond, Eleanor P. English Verse Between Chaucer and Surrey. Being Examples of
                Conventional Secular Poetry, Exclusive of Romance, Ballad, Lyric, the Drama, in the
                Period from Henry the Fourth to Henry the Eighth. Durham, N.C.: Duke University
                Press, 1927.</bib>
            <notes> This well-known anthology of fifteenth-century verse offers an excellent Gen-
                eral Introduction (see pp. 18–26 on versification), very useful--sometimes
                lengthy--chapter introductions (especially for Lydgate), and short bibliogra- phies
                for each chapter. Should be consulted particularly for work on the versi- fication
                of Lydgate, Hoccleve, and Skelton. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K149">
            <bib>-----. "Linguistics and Versification." Chaucer: A Bibliographical Manual. New
                York: Macmillan, 1908</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. New York: Peter Smith, 1933. pp. 464–509. The chapter is composed of a
                collection of historical observations on the sub- ject, a short bibliography of
                studies, and several short essays by the author on Chaucer's language,
                versification, line forms and variations, stanzas, and rhymes. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K150">
            <bib>-----. "The Nine-Syllabled Pentameter Line in Some Post-Chaucerian Manu- scripts."
                MP 23 (1925): 129–52.</bib>
            <notes> Systematic, keen-eyed scrutiny of the scribal practices (and errors) behind the
                recension of each MS will allow us to "filter out" the scribal influence and more
                adequately assess authorial intent. Hammond provides a model of such scrutiny,
                examining headless and broken-backed lines in Chaucer, Hoccleve, and Lydgate.
                Chaucer apparently intended few such if any. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K151">
            <bib>Hampel, Ernest. Die Silbenmessung in Chaucers Fünftaktigem Verse. Diss., Halle,
                1898. 45 pp.</bib>
            <notes> On the metrical treatment of syllables--syncope, apocope, and aphaeresis of
                vowels and consonants--in Chaucer, using the Skeat edition as text. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K152">
            <bib>Hanna, Ralph, III. "The Awntyrs off Arthure at the Terne Wathelyn." Manchester:
                Manchester University Press, and New York: Barnes &amp; Noble, 1974. "Stanza Form
                and Authorship," pp. 11–24.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K153">
            <bib>Hausknecht, Emil, ed. "The Romaunce of The Sowdone of Babylone and of Ferumbras
                his Sone who conquerede Rome." Early English Text Society, Extra Series, no. 38.
                London: Trübner, 1881. </bib>
            <notes> "Metre and Versification," pp. xl–xlv. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K154">
            <bib>Heesch, Gustav. über Sprache und Versbau des halbsachsischen Gedichts "Debate of
                the Body and the Soul." Diss., Kiel, 1884. Bergedorf: Wagner, 1884. 80 pp.</bib>
            <notes> "Metrik," pp. 70–80. The poem is in eight-line stanzas (rhyming abababab) of
                four-stress verse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K155">
            <bib>Hempl, George. Chaucer's Pronunciation and the Spelling of the Ellesmere MS.
                Boston: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., 1893. 37 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A short primer for students: chapters on spelling, pronunciation, imperfect
                rhymes, quantity of vowels, loss of vowels, etc. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K156">
            <bib>Heuer, Hermann. Studien zur syntaktischen und stilistischen Funktion des Adverbs
                bei Chaucer und im Rosenroman. Anglistische Forschungen, vol. 75. Heidelberg, 1932.
                168 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in JEGP 34 (1935): 105–7; in Anglia Beiblatt 45 (1934): 141–47; in Eng-
                lische Studien 67 (1933): 391–95. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K157">
            <bib>Hieatt, Constance B. "The Rhythm of the Alliterative Long Line." Chaucer and
                Middle English Studies in Honour of Russell Hope Robbins. Ed. Beryl Rowland. London:
                Allen &amp; Unwin, 1974. pp. 119–30.</bib>
            <notes> An effort to apply a simplified version of Pope's rhythmical scansion (J242) to
                MEAV, chiefly Sir Gawain. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K158">
            <bib>Hilker, Wilfred. Der Vers in Layamons "Brut": Untersuchungen zu seiner Struktur
                und Herkunft. Diss., Münster. Gadderbaum, 1965.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K159">
            <bib>Hilligoss, Susan J. "Conventional Style in Middle English Tail-Rhyme Romance." DAI
                38 (1978): 4844A (Pennsylvania).</bib>
            <notes> The received opinion of this stanza-form has been that it is "uniquely unsuited
                for narrative use," despite its very wide usage. Analysis of meter, syntax,
                stanza-linking, and stylistic modification of source-material in fourteen ro-
                mances, however, shows that the stanza is organized metrically into three- and
                four-line phrases dominated by hypotactic constructions, that the tail-line is used
                for rhetorical not narrative purposes, and that narrative continuity is es-
                tablished by means other than direct stanza-linking. The stanza thus seems best
                adapted to amplification of theme, even though it does not actually inhibit de-
                velopment of the narrative. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K160">
            <bib>Höfer, Paul. Alliteration bei Gower. Diss., Leipzig, 1890. 82 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Mainly a typology of alliteration in various metrical configurations within the
                line and patterns of linkage between lines. Short introduction, conclusion, and
                discussion throughout, however. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K161">
            <bib>Hohlfeld, Alexander R. "Two Old English Mystery Plays on the Subject of Abraham's
                Sacrifice." MLN 5 (1890): cols. 222–37.</bib>
            <notes> Based on metrical and rhyme evidence, an original version of the extant Brome
                text must have been the source for the extant Chester play. Cf. Fort (K122).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K161a">
            <bib>Honour, Margaret C. "The Metrical Derivations of the Medieval English Lyric
                (Volumes I and II)." DAI 31 (1970): 2346A (Yale, 1949). 578 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Originally intended only as a prolegomenon to a study of the early English
                lyric, this full-scale metrical analysis of the Medieval Latin lyric was prompted by
                the discovery that no such systematic study had been made. The results of that work,
                in conjunction with a returning examination of the Provençal and Romance verse
                traditions, suggest that the Latin tradition was the foremost in- fluence on the
                English, especially in terms of the adoption of the Goliard stanza and the
                polyphonic musical form. Provençal forms seem to have been relatively alien to the
                English. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K162">
            <bib>Hooker, Edward V. "Johnson's Understanding of Chaucer's Metrics." MLN 48 (1933):
                150–51.</bib>
            <notes> Dr. Johnson relied for his very imperfect (indeed uninformed) understanding of
                Chaucerian versification on the very corrupt edition by Urry in 1721 (Tyrwhitt
                called it "the worst that was ever published"), and he seems not to have realized
                the syllabic value of the final -e. In short he never troubled him- self to
                substantiate his low estimation. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K163">
            <bib>Horne, R. H. "Introduction." The Poems of Geoffrey Chaucer Modernized. London:
                Whittaker &amp; Co., 1841. pp. v–cv.</bib>
            <notes> After some discussion of translation problems, the Introduction turns, on p.
                xxxvii, to Chaucer's versification, where Horne defends Chaucer's virtuosity with
                great vigor, by siding with Tyrwhitt against all those who hold that any line not
                exactly decasyllabic is lame or inept and on these grounds prove Chaucer to be an
                awkward versifier, since he has many longer and shorter lines. Horne's informal
                survey of the history of English versification shows ex- actly the same case to hold
                for all the greatest poets, and a further argument compressing lines with extra
                syllables into the same time-periods as the normal verses completes his defense.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K164">
            <bib>Hulbert, James R. "A Hypothesis Concerning the Alliterative Revival." MP 28
                (1931): 405–22.</bib>
            <notes> Especially p. 412 ff. Argument that the Revival was fostered by the baronial
                opposition to the crown, on the grounds that only such a presumption of pa- tronage
                by certain nobility away from London can account for the audience, courtly tone,
                archaic diction, and native meter of the verse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K165">
            <bib>-----. "Quatrains in Middle English Alliterative Poems." MP 48 (1950):
                73–81.</bib>
            <notes> A careful review of the early-twentieth-century scholarship and opinions, fol-
                lowed by a review of the problems posed by the MSS. Hulbert concludes most
                significantly that Piers Plowman (among others) has "no systematic use" of
                quatrains, and he prints 109 lines in stanzas so the reader may see the effects of
                grouping for himself. Cf. Kaluza (K182). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K166">
            <bib>Hupe, Heinrich. "Cursor" Studies. Early English Text Society, Original Series, no.
                101. London: Karl Trübner, Trench, &amp; Co., 1893.</bib>
            <notes> "Notes on the Versification," pp. 253–61. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K167">
            <bib>Hussey, S. S. "Langland's Reading of Alliterative Poetry." MLR 60 (1965):
                163–70.</bib>
            <notes> Section 1 of the article provides a useful review of the scholarship on
                allitera- tion. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K168">
            <bib>Ilyish, B. A. "Notes on Chaucer's Syntax." Transactions of the First Leningrad
                Pedagogical Institute of Foreign Languages 1 (1940): 186–205.</bib>
            <notes> Not seen. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K169">
            <bib>Ito, M. "Gower and Rime Royal." Bulletin of the College of General Education,
                Tohoku University (Sendai, Japan) 12, 2 (1971): 46–65. English summary, pp.
                ii–iii.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K170">
            <bib>-----. "Gower's Use of rime riche in Confessio Amantis As Compared with his
                Practice in Mirrour de l'Omme and with the Case of Chaucer." Studies in English
                Literature (Tokyo) 46 (1969): 29–44. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K171">
            <bib>Iwasaki, Haruo. "A Peculiar Feature in the Word-Order of Gower's Confessio
                Amantis." Studies in English Literature (Tokyo) 45 (1969): 205–20.</bib>
            <notes> The feature: phrases, especially adverbial, preceding a connective and its fol-
                lowing principal clause (e.g. "Unkindly for thou hast wrought"), apparently for
                purposes of rhyme. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K172">
            <bib>-----. "A Peculiar Feature in the Word-Order of Layamon's Brut." Geibun-Kenkyu
                (Tokyo) 25 (1968): 64–77.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K173">
            <bib>Jacobs, Nicolas. "Alliterative Storms: A Topos in Middle English." Speculum 47
                (1972): 695–719.</bib>
            <notes> Second only to battles, storm set-pieces appear nearly everywhere in MEAV, but
                hardly anywhere, surprisingly, in non-alliterative verse. They seem not to have been
                derived from OE sources, but rather from Latin texts and from Guido's Historia. Why
                the alliterative long line was such a congenial mode for this motif is not clear,
                though that it was so is evident enough. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K174">
            <bib>Jambeck, Thomas J. "Characterization and Syntax in the Miller's Tale." Journal of
                Narrative Technique 5 (1975): 73–85.</bib>
            <notes> The style of this tale is unusually high in its proportion of parataxis--78%, in
                fact, as compared with 42% for the Knight's Tale and 27% for the Squire's Tale-
                -especially the conjunctive and used for anaphora. The miller, one may ob- serve,
                has a hard time elaborating a sentence. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K175">
            <bib>Joerden, Otto. Das Verhaltnis von Wort-, Satz-, und Vers-Akzent in Chaucers
                "Canterbury Tales." Diss., Göttingen, 1914. Studien zur englischen Philologie, vol.
                55. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1915. 56 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in Englische Studien 51 (1917): 84–94; in Archiv 134 (1916): 466; 137
                (1918): 127–28. Under the rubrics of correspondence and noncorrespondence of the
                linguistic stress with the metrical ictus of the pentameter pattern Joerden gives a
                rela- tively traditional account of (respectively) the "so-called inversion" and
                modu- lation (taktverschleierung: literally, camouflaging the measures) in the
                Chaucerian five-foot line. Indebted to Schipper and Ten Brink. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K176">
            <bib>Johnson, James D. "Formulaic Diction and Thematic Composition in The Alliterative
                Morte Arthure." DAI 30 (1970): 3462A (Illinois).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K177">
            <bib>Johnston, R[onald] C. The Versification of Jordan Fantosme. Oxford: Basil
                Blackwell, 1974. 34 pp.</bib>
            <notes> The long-assumed metrical irregularity of this twelfth-century Anglo-Norman
                writer can be disproven if one considers the metrical unit as the hemistich rather
                than the line: the second hemistich is almost invariably hexasyllabic, while the
                lengths of the first hemistichs show discernible patterns of variation. Cf. Rose
                (K319). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K178">
            <bib>Jong, R. R., de. "On ME Rhymes in end(e) and ent(e)." Englische Studien 21 (1895):
                321–25.</bib>
            <notes> In six minor poems. Scanty evidence. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K179">
            <bib>Joseph, Ruth E. F. "Alliterative Style in The Awntyrs off Arthure, The Avowing of
                King Arthur, The Turke and Gowin, and Golagros and Gawane. Diss., University of
                Pittsburgh, 1977.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K180">
            <bib>Kaluza, Max. "Chaucers Versbau." In his Chaucer-Handbuch für Studierende:
                Ausgewahlte Texte mit Einleit, einem Abriss von Chaucers Versbau, und einem
                Wörterverzeichnis. Leipzig: Bernhard Tauchnitz, 1919; 2nd ed., 1927. pp. 209–
                15.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in Die Neueren Sprachen 30 (1922): 86–88. A simplified account of the
                metrical structure of the tetrameter and pentameter couplets, rhyme, and
                stanza-forms. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K181">
            <bib>-----. "Der Reim love:behove, Rom. of the Rose v. 1091 f." Englische Studien 23
                (1897): 336–38.</bib>
            <notes> A quarrel with Luick, who replies at 24 (1898): 342–43. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K182">
            <bib>-----. "Strophische Gliederung in der mittelenglischen rein alliterierenden
                Dichtung." Englische Studien 16 (1892): 169–80.</bib>
            <notes> This is Kaluza's original argument that ME alliterative poems are, based on
                regular marginal marks in the MSS, divided into quatrains and then grouped into
                larger strophic units of multiples of quatrains, i.e. (title of poem followed by
                number of lines to the strophe): The Wars of Alexander, 24; Crouned King, 16; St.
                Erkenwald, 32; Chevelere Assigne, 8; The Siege of Jerusalem, 36; Sir Gawain and
                Patience, 12; Pearl and Purity, 60 (quintuple groupings of these triple- quatrain
                units); and the Morte Arthure, among others, 8 or 12. Kaluza's theory has not been
                generally accepted--see Day (K84) and Vantuono (K416)--but recently it has been
                defended vigorously by Duggan (K93). Cf. Hans Möller on OE poetry (J211) and Hulbert
                (K165). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K183">
            <bib>Karpf, Fritz. Studien zur Syntax in den Werken Geoffrey Chaucers, Teil 1. Wiener
                Beiträge zur englischen Philologie, vol. 55. Vienna: W. Braumüller, 1930. 148
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in MLR 27 (1932): 98–99; in Die Neuren Sprachen 40 (1932): 240; in English
                Studies 15 (1933): 38–43; in Englische Studien 67 (1933): 391–95; in Re- view of
                English Studies 12 (1936): 246. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K184">
            <bib>Kendle, Burton S. "The Ancestry and Character of the Skeltonic." DAI 21 (1961):
                3090A (Wisconsin).</bib>
            <notes> Views the Skeltonic line as stress-verse, consisting of two (sometimes three)
                stresses and a variable number of slacks, on the presumption that this form evolved
                from the fourteenth-century alliterative line, also stress-verse, and for Kendle a
                model of the accentual character of all of English verse. The Latin sequences and
                leonine hexameter seem too regular to have been sources. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K185">
            <bib>Kenyon, John S. "The Syntax of the Infinitive in Chaucer." Diss., Harvard
                University, 1908.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K186">
            <bib>Ker, W. P. "Metrical Romances, 1200–1500, I." The Cambridge History of English
                Literature. Ed. A. W. Ward and A. R. Waller. 14 vols. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons,
                1907–16. Vol. 1, chapter 13, pp. 308–34.</bib>
            <notes> Of the thirteen essays in the volume on ME verse Ker's gives the most exten-
                sive attention to versification. But cf. Saintsbury (J261). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K187">
            <bib>Kerkhof, J. Studies in the Language of Geoffrey Chaucer. Leiden: Universitaire
                Pers Leiden, 1966. 251 pp.</bib>
            <notes> The most recent full-scale study of Chaucerian syntax; organized by parts of
                speech. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K188">
            <bib>Kern, J. H. "Hoccleve's Verszeile." Anglia 40 (1916): 367–69.</bib>
            <notes> A response to Bock (K27) in which Kern reiterates (from his review of Bock in
                Anglia 39 (1915): 389 ff.) his view that Hoccleve's line regulates its syllables
                closely, having invariably either ten or eleven. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K189">
            <bib>Kinsman, Robert S. "Skelton's 'Uppon a Deedman's Hed': New Light on the Origin of
                the Skeltonic." SP 50 (1953): 101–9.</bib>
            <notes> Skelton learned his versification from the popular medieval "Signs of Death"
                poetry. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K190">
            <bib>Kipling, Gordon. "John Skelton and Burgundian Letters." Ten Studies in Anglo-
                Dutch Relations. Ed. Jan Van Dorsten. London and Leiden: The Sir Thomas Browne
                Institute, 1974. pp. 1–29.</bib>
            <notes> Argues in part that Skelton's distinctive rhyme- and stanza-forms were derived
                from the Burgundian tradition of "vers septaine," "vers brisiez," "rhetorique
                batelée," and "rime rurale." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K191">
            <bib>Kirkpatrick, Hugh. "The Bob-Wheel and Allied Stanza Forms in Middle English and
                Middle Scots Poetry." DAI 37 (1976): 3608A (North Texas State).</bib>
            <notes> Formulates a definition of this stanzaic mode in ME poetry based on inventory of
                47 ME and MS texts. As for its origin, closer analogues are found in medie- val
                Latin poetry than in Old French, and its development in England pro- ceeded in the
                South before it did in the North, contrary to received opinion. Showing frequent but
                inconsistent alliteration, the bob-and-wheel seems to be a transitional form between
                the old alliterative line and the later ME rhymed syllabic verse. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K192">
            <bib>Kirwin, William J., Jr. "Inflectional and Principal Syntactic Classes in Chaucer's
                Canterbury Tales." Diss., University of Chicago, 1964.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K193">
            <bib>Kittredge, George L. Observations on the Language of Chaucer's "Troilus." Chaucer
                Society Publications, Second Series, no. 28. London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner
                &amp; Co., 1891.</bib>
            <notes> Part I treats Syntax, Part II (pp. 346–421) Meter, i.e., the metrical treatment
                of syllables, chiefly the final -e, in order to preserve Chaucer's line as
                decasyllable, which is what Kittredge assumes it is to be, following Ten Brink very
                closely in this view. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K194">
            <bib>Kivimaa, Kirsti. Clauses in Chaucer Introduced by Conjunction with Appended
                "That." Helsinki, 1969.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K195">
            <bib>-----. The Pleonastic "That" in Relative and Interrogative Constructions in
                Chaucer's Verse. Helsinki: Societas Scientiarum Fennica, 1967.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K196">
            <bib>Kjellman, Hilding, ed. La Vie Seint Edmund le Rei, poème anglo-normand du XIIe
                siècle par Denis Piramus. Gothenburg, 1935.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K197">
            <bib>Kjellmer, Gordon. Did the "'Pearl' Poet" Write "Pearl"? Gothenburg Studies in
                English, vol. 30. Gothenburg (Sweden), 1975.</bib>
            <notes> Based on a computerized analysis of lexical, syntactic, and alliterative
                distribu- tion, the author concludes that the poet who wrote Gawain did not write
                Pearl. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K198">
            <bib>Klee, Frederich. Das Enjambement Bei Chaucer. Diss., Halle, 1913. 70 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Enjambement is analyzed, first, by types of syntactic structures which break
                across the line-end, and second, vis à vis its chronological development in Chaucer,
                especially in respect to the "hardness" or roughness of the syntactic break. Three
                pages of tables at the end. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K199">
            <bib>Kliman, Bernice W. "Alliteration in Barbour's Bruce: A Study Using SNAP
                Programming." The Computer and Literary Studies. Ed. A. J. Aitken et al. Edinburgh:
                Edinburgh University Press, 1973. pp. 263–71.</bib>
            <notes> A description of problems in programming, not results, especially the problem of
                what constitutes a legitimate structural alliteration in the looser ME verse.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K200">
            <bib>Knight, Stephen. Rymyng Craftily: Meaning in Chaucer's Poetry. Sydney: Angus &amp;
                Robertson, 1973; New York: Humanities, 1974.</bib>
            <notes> An essay in stylistics, treating three poems and four tales in Chaucer, with at-
                tention to the semantic functions of stanza and rhyme, passim. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K201">
            <bib>Kökeritz, Helge. A Guide to Chaucer's Pronunciation. New Haven: Whitlock, 1954;
                Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksells, 1961.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K202">
            <bib>Kölbing, Eugen. "Die Alliteration in Sir Beues of Hamtoun (Auchinleck MS.)."
                Englische Studien 19 (1894): 441–53.</bib>
            <notes> Merely lists of examples of types. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K203">
            <bib>-----. "Zu Chaucer's Sir Thopas." Englische Studien 11 (1888): 495–511.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K204">
            <bib>Kölbing, Eugen, ed. "The Romance of Sir Beues of Hamtoun." Early English Text
                Society, Extra Series, no. 65. London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co.,
                1894.</bib>
            <notes> "Metre and Versification," pp. x–xiii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K205">
            <bib>Köster, Hans. Huchown's "Pistel of Swete Susan": kritische Ausgabe. Quellen und
                Forschungen, no. 76. Strassburg: Karl Trübner, 1895.</bib>
            <notes> "Metrik," pp. 15–36. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K206">
            <bib>Koppel, Emil. "Gowers französische Balladen und Chaucer." Englische Studien 20
                (1895): 154–56.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K207">
            <bib>Koziol, Herbert. Brundzüge der Syntax der mittelenglischen Stabreimdichtungen.
                Wiener Beiträge zur englischen Philologie, vol. 58. Vienna: W. Braumüller, 1932. 172
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in Review of English Studies 12 (1936): 246; in Englische Studien 68
                (1933): 249–50; in Language 10 (1934): 212–17; in Archiv 165 (1934): 254–55; in JEGP
                34 (1935): 440–41; in Anglia Beiblatt 46 (1935): 363–64. The fullest study of syntax
                in MEAV; organized by parts of speech. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K208">
            <bib>-----. "Zur Frage der Verfasserschaft einiger mittelenglischer
                Stabreimdichtungen." Englische Studien 67 (1932–33): 165–73.</bib>
            <notes> In response to Oakden (K274) and Luick (K224). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K209">
            <bib>Krishna, Valerie, ed. The Alliterative "Morte Arthure": A Critical Edition. New
                York: Burt Franklin, 1976.</bib>
            <notes> "Alliteration and Meter," pp. 22–27. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K210">
            <bib>Kuhnke, Bruno. Die alliterierende Langzeile in der mittelenglischen Romanze "Sir
                Gawayn and the Green Knight I." Diss., Königsberg. Weimer: Emil Felber, 1899. 46
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Published thereafter under the same title as vol. 4 in the series Studien zum
                germanischen Alliterationsvers. Berlin: E. Felber, 1900. 88 pp. Rev.: in Anglia
                Beiblatt 12 (1901): 65–76. In his Introduction Kaluza reviews the scholarship on the
                two-beat/four-beat theories of OE and ME verse, then criticizes all the theorists
                for attempting too much. He himself accepts the four-beat theory of Kaluza and
                Trautmann, and, being perhaps a more myopic soul, he prefers close-detail work. The
                work he furnishes here is simply a series of long lists of examples of verse-types
                in Sir Gawain. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K211">
            <bib>Laeseke, Bernhard. Ein Beitrag zur Stellung des Verbums im Orrmulum. Diss., Kiel,
                1917. Berlin: Emil Ebering, 1917. 114 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A mere list of examples of the various positions of the verb. Unusually full
                bibliography. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K212">
            <bib>Langhans, Victor. "Der Reimvokal e bei Chaucer." Anglia 45 (1921): 221–82, 297–
                392.</bib>
            <notes> Ten Brink's view that Chaucer allowed only etymologically pure rhymes is
                rejected as being an unsupported assumption, like the correlate view that he never
                rhymed closed vowels with open. Long tables of examples are appended. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K213">
            <bib>Lawlor, John. "Rhythm, Speech, and Argument." In his "Piers Plowman": An Essay in
                Criticism. London: Edward Arnold, 1962. pp. 189–239.</bib>
            <notes> Especially pp. 189–200, 230, and 234–36. This very widely informed discus- sion
                of meter actually ranges over the whole gamut of English poetry and has little
                directly to do with Langland, except insofar as his meter--in which the unit of
                metrical organization is the phrase, exactly coterminous with the half- line, two
                phrases being formally balanced to make the line--is paralleled strik- ingly in
                modern free verse: no metrical modulation or tension is possible in this meter;
                there is no norm to play against, as in syllable-counting meter. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K214">
            <bib>Lawton, David A. "Gaytryge's Sermon, Dictamen, and Middle English Alliterative
                Verse." MP 76 (1978–79): 329–43.</bib>
            <notes> An obscure by-way leads to a major reassessment of perspective. An instruc- tion
                to his diocese written by the Archbishop of York in 1357, as found in an authorized
                translation of this sermon by John Gaytryge, provoked a quarrel between Skeat and
                others in the late nineteenth century as to whether the piece was in prose or verse.
                Skeat thought that unrhymed MEAV influenced the form of the sermon, but in fact it
                was ME rhythmical prose, and behind that the medieval cursus of the ars rithmica.
                The sermon itself was very influen- tial and may actually have influenced MEAV. Its
                form is--not verse, but not prose--lineated near-verse, rhythmical, spasmodically
                rhymed and alliterated, in four-stress lines, but extremely irregular in all of
                these. When we reflect that over half of the extant corpus of unrhymed MEAV
                represents translations of Latin texts, we begin to see the origin of the MEAV
                long-line as a conscious effort to parallel, in the vernacular, the Latin ars
                dictaminis. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K215">
            <bib>Leonard, William E. "The Scansion of Middle English Alliterative Verse."
                University of Wisconsin Studies in Language and Literature, no. 11 (1920), pp. 57–
                103.</bib>
            <notes> An extension of his earlier argument in favor of the vierhebung scansion of the
                OE verse (J166) to ME, though like the others of that persuasion Leonard considers
                that the eight-beat long-line in OE was reduced to seven in the ME, the second verse
                being looser. But he prefers to make his case (in the Tale of Gamelyn) without
                reference to OE, as if it had not existed. Cunningly, he shows that the seven-beat
                line of Gamelyn is in fact indistinguishable from the "four-beat" line of Piers
                Plowman by mixing extracts from both and asking the reader if he can tell which is
                which. Leonard has a feisty temperament and also--rarity of rarities in this
                field--a wonderfully lively style, full of vigor, wit, directness of speech, and
                homely examples. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K216">
            <bib>Lewis, C. S. "The Fifteenth-Century Heroic Line." Essays and Studies 24 (1938):
                28–41</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. in his Selected Literary Essays. Ed. Walter Hooper. Cambridge: Cambridge
                University Press, 1969. pp. 45–57. We think the fifteenth-century line bad only
                because we try to read it as a decasyllable, an iambic pentameter, which Lewis
                believes it is not. In fact, he argues, it is plainly the familiar, old, popular
                ballad meter: "a long line divided by a sharp medial break into two half-lines, each
                containing not less than two nor more than three stresses, and most hovering between
                two and three stresses." This meter can be found in Chaucer even though many of his
                lines are certainly pentameters. Whence came the pentameter form? Not from the
                French--their line counts syllables but knows nothing of the principle of stress-
                alternation. We must conclude then that Chaucer "attempted a compromise"; he
                intended to write five-stress decasyllables, but the older tune "was running in his
                head and he allowed it to intrude; he even welcomed it." Such a combi- nation or
                conflation was possible precisely because [this is the crux] "the one metre slips
                easily into the other." And still slips, today, not only in nursery rhymes and
                popular songs but in serious verse. What Chaucer received as a native verse
                tradition (from early ME), and what the post-Chaucerians re- verted to so quickly,
                was a hemistich of simply "two, or two-and-a-half, or three" stresses. That is the
                most one can say of the meter. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K217">
            <bib>Licklider, Albert H. Chapters on the Metric of the Chaucerian Tradition.
                Baltimore: J. H. Furst Company, 1910. 241 pp.</bib>
            <notes> His dissertation at Johns Hopkins University, 1907. Not a work on Chaucer's
                metric, but rather a study of the Chaucerian Tradi- tion between Chaucer and Wyatt,
                inclusive on both ends. The prevailing the- sis is that "the versification of the
                Tradition is not a misapprehension but an exaggeration of Chaucer's system."
                Licklider was a student of Bright's and fol- lows faithfully his doctrines of
                resolution of stress (i.e., multisyllabic arsis or thesis with "hovering" stress),
                "arsis-thesis variation," and "pitch accent" (i.e., ictus in English marked by
                quantity and sometimes also by pitch). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K218">
            <bib>Lindner, Felix. "Chaucers Alliteration." Jahrbuch für romanische und englische
                Sprache und Literatur 14 (1875): 311–35.</bib>
            <notes>Translated as </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K219">
            <bib>Lindner, Felix. "The Alliteration in Chaucer's Canterbury Tales." In Essays on
                Chaucer, His World and Works. Chaucer Society Publications, Second Series, part 3,
                no. 8. London: N. Trübner &amp; Co., 1876. pp. 197–226.</bib>
            <notes> Following Regel's demonstration (K311) of extensive alliteration in Layamon,
                Lindner shows that it extends even up to Chaucer. He gives three reasons for Chaucer
                preserving the Germanic form well after English verse had taken up the Romance
                practice of rhyme, and the remainder of the essay (the greater part) is given over
                to examples of alliterating words related (1) etymologically, (2) semantically, and
                (3) grammatically. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K220">
            <bib>Lineberger, Julia E. "An Examination of Professor Cowling's New Metrical Test."
                MLN 42 (1927): 229–31.</bib>
            <notes> Finds evidence discrediting Cowling's (K70) stanza-division test as an instru-
                ment for dating Chaucer's work. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K221">
            <bib>Locock, Katharine B. "Lydgate's Metre." The Pilgrimage of the Life of Man. Ed. F.
                J. Furnivall. Early English Text Society, Extra Series, no. 92. London: Kegan Paul,
                Trench, Trübner &amp; Co., 1904. pp. xxxi–xli.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K222">
            <bib>Lounsbury, Thomas R. Studies in Chaucer, His Life and Writings. 3 vols. New York:
                Harper &amp; Brothers, 1892.</bib>
            <notes> Matters of meter, rhyme, and stanza are discussed principally at: i, 285–300,
                328–35, 371–76, 388–98; ii, 57–65, 75–77; and iii, 295–316. But see also s.v.
                "Versification of Chaucer" and "Verse" in the Index. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K223">
            <bib>Luick, Karl. "Englische Metrik: Geschichte der heimischen Versarten." In Paul's
                Grundriss (L531), pp. 141–80.</bib>
            <notes> An omnibus survey of ME verse, both (1) rhymed-alliterative (as in Layamon and
                King Horn) and (2) fully (Revival) alliterative, based on the work Luick had earlier
                published in Anglia. On the verse of the Alliterative Revival Luick is generally
                sound, but his position on the nature of the unusual fully-rhymed-
                but-occasionally-alliterative verseform in the Brut and King Horn, however, is
                unsound: Luick adopted the theory that the verse of Layamon and the Horn was not
                derived from the OE alliterative long-line ("stress-verse") but was a separate form
                which appeared only in ME, as an analogue to Otfrid's rhymed verse in Germany, and
                contained four beats (takte, "beat-verse") to the verse (half-line)--i.e., according
                to the old vierhebungstheorie (cf. Trautmann). Thus, Luick believed that ME verse
                showed three distinct and wholly detached tradi- tions--the revival of the older
                native alliterative long-line, the Otfridian four- beat rhymed short line, and the
                Romance syllable-counting "foot-verse." Op- posed to this view stand Schipper (A9),
                who sees the Layamon-Horn verse as simply a loosened form directly descended from
                the OE verse tradition, and West (K430). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K224">
            <bib>-----. "Die englische Stabreimzeile im 14, 15, und 16 Jahrhundert." Anglia 11
                (1889): 392–443, 553–618.</bib>
            <notes> Still a valuable study for reference purposes, even though Luick's belief that
                the inflectional -e continued to be sounded is now discredited and his principles
                for determining stressing outside of alliteration are also unsound. The essay ap-
                plies the zweihebungstheorie to MEAV, Luick being intent to show that the Five Types
                are evident even in the later verse, even though metrical mutation has taken place
                in the interim via regular linguistic processes. Luick also argues that stressing
                should be determined without reference to the alliteration. Discussed in Borroff
                (K32), chapter 7 and Notes, especially pp. 183–86. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K225">
            <bib>-----. "Zur Metrik der mittelenglischen reimend-alliterierenden Dichtung." Anglia
                12 (1889): 437–53.</bib>
            <notes> Three short studies: The first examines the meter of the last four "wheel" lines
                in the bob-and-wheel stanza, Luick arguing that the first three of these are de-
                rived from the first verse of the alliterative long-line while the last is from the
                second, which explains why it is generally shorter than they. The second sec- tion
                treats stressing which is not supported by the alliteration; the third treats the
                final -e. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K226">
            <bib>-----. "Zur mittelenglischen Verslehre." Anglia 38 (1914): 269–348; 39 (1915):
                274.</bib>
            <notes> A response to Bülbring (K52) on the meter of the tail-rhyme romances, Luick
                agreeing that the "triplet-verses" and tail-line verses have four and three mem-
                bers (respectively) but denying that they bear four and three stresses: in his view
                both bear only two stresses. Lists of types. Summary, pp. 339–48. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K227">
            <bib>Lumby, J. Rawson, ed. "King Horn," "Floris and Blauncheflur," "The Assumption of
                Our Lady." Early English Text Society, Original Series, no. 14. London, 1866.</bib>
            <notes> Re-edited by George H. McKnight in 1901. "Versification," pp. xxi–xxiv, xlii,
                and lviii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K228">
            <bib>Lupack, Alan C. "Structure and Tradition in the Poems of the Alliterative
                Revival." DAI 36 (1975): 323A (Pennsylvania).</bib>
            <notes> A defense of MEAV against the charge of structural weakness by demonstrat- ing
                (1) the functional ends of structures such as quatrains, stanzas, and passus, and
                (2) use of a traditional, bipartite principle of narration and description. Analyzes
                eight major works. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K229">
            <bib>Lyle, E. B. "A Comment on the Rhyme-Scheme of Two Stanzas in Thomas of
                Erceldoune." Notes &amp; Queries 214 (1969): 48.</bib>
            <notes> Some slight support for the view that the unusual stanza-form abcb derives from
                an earlier ballad, "Thomas the Rhymer." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K230">
            <bib>Macaulay, G. C., ed. The English Works of John Gower. Early English Text Society,
                Extra Series, no. 81. London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co., 1900. pp.
                cxx–cxxvii.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K231">
            <bib>McClumpha, Charles F. The Alliteration of Chaucer. Diss., Leipzig. Leipzig: Grimme
                &amp; Tromel, 1888</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. Folcroft, Pa.: The Folcroft Press, 1974. 56 pp. Six areas are examined:
                "Examples and Rules for Alliteration"; "Relation of Alliteration to Accent" (e.g. to
                preserve rhyme or meter); "Different Forms and Disposition of Alliteration"
                (Position and Quality); "Application [in] dif- ferent Forms of Verse" ("heroic
                verse" and "short verse"); "Proportional Rela- tion between Alliteration and
                different Works"; "Character of Alliteration in the various Works with comparison of
                the same"; and "Relation of Alliteration to the Subject-Matter." Throughout,
                McClumpha denies emphatically that Chaucer used any regular rule for alliteration as
                did his predecessors; rather, Chaucer echoed sounds solely for "poetical effect . .
                . to color and vivify." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K232">
            <bib>MacCracken, Henry N. "King James' Claim to Rhyme Royal." MLN 24 (1909):
                31–32.</bib>
            <notes> He has none. See Maynard (K250). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K233">
            <bib>MacCracken, Henry H., ed. The Minor Poems of John Lydgate. Part I. Early English
                Text Society, Extra Series, no. 107. London: Oxford University Press, 1911 (for
                1910).</bib>
            <notes> Rhyme and metrical evidence for authorship are discussed on pp. vi–ix of the
                introduction on the Canon. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K234">
            <bib>McFayden, Neill L. "The Stylistic Influence of the Alliterative Tradition on the
                Poetry of William Dunbar." DAI 37 (1977): 4372A (Florida).</bib>
            <notes> Separating Dunbar's poetry into aureate, comic, and plain styles, McFayden shows
                the variety of alliteration's uses: formal decoration, characterization, comic or
                ironic counterpoint, and contrast. The final chapter applies the Halle-Keyser
                generative-metrics analysis (E775) and Kiparsky's morphopho- nemic approach (E827)
                in order to show that Dunbar created metrical effects like those in the alliterative
                long-line by adapting the resources of metrical variation and complexity (H-K) and
                metrical range, or linguistic complexity (Kiparsky). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K235">
            <bib>McGalliard, John C. "Links, Language, and Style in The Pearl." Studies in
                Language, Literature, and Culture of the Middle Ages and Later. Ed. E. Bagby Atwood
                and A. A. Hill. Austin: University of Texas, 1969. pp. 279–99.</bib>
            <notes> A detailed explication of the ends and effects of about half of the twenty link-
                words or refrains connecting the twenty five-stanza sections of the poem dem-
                onstrates that "the verse carrying the end-refrain is an integral, functional ele-
                ment of the poem's assertion, not a dangling, jingling excrescence appended to
                satisfy the metrical form." Part 2 of the article assays the amount of alliteration,
                and Part 3 the phonetic symbolism, in the poem. See also: </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K236">
            <bib>Milroy, James. "Pearl: The Verbal Texture and the Linguistic Theme." Neophilologus
                55 (1971): 195–208.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K237">
            <bib>Macrae-Gibson, O. D. "Pearl: The Link-Words and the Thematic Structure."
                Neophilologus 52 (1968): 54–64.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K238">
            <bib>McJimsey, Ruth B. Chaucer's Irregular -E: A Demonstration among Monosyllabic Nouns
                of the Exceptions to Grammatical and Metrical Harmony. New York: King's Crown Press,
                1942.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in MLR 38 (1943): 138–39; in MLQ 4 (1943): 113–14; in Review of English
                Studies 20 (1944): 234–36; in MLN 59 (1944): 188–90; in Language 20 (1944): 257–60.
                The author is able to demonstrate a clear pattern of regularity in the seemingly
                irregular distribution of final -e's on monosyllabic nouns in Chaucer's English,
                yielding the conclusion that his speech was neither archaic nor overly "poeti- cal"
                but a judicious middle course within contemporaneous East Midlands us- age. The -e
                had been regularly affixed to OE feminine nouns by analogy be- fore Chaucer's time,
                and it was still being used after final double consonants (and long vowels) to
                distinguish them from single. Employing a metrical "arsis- test," McJimsey shows
                that monosyllables ending in -e never stand in the first position of an iamb.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K239">
            <bib>McNary, Sarah J. Studies in Layamon's Verse. Diss., New York University, 1902.
                Baltimore: J. H. Furst, 1904. 36 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Layamon's verse presents to us the remarkable spectacle of an attempt to com-
                bine two major--and inconsistent--verse-traditions. The Brut shows both allit-
                eration and rhyme. But the use of rhyme increases over the course of the poem while
                that of alliteration decreases, and in general the usage of allitera- tion here is
                not sufficient to justify classifying the poem as alliterative rather than rhymed
                (84.4% of the lines have rhyme, 67.6% alliteration). The influ- ence of Wace is
                heavy both in the principle of rhyme, the new device which steadily supplanted
                Layamon's familiarity with the old alliteration, and also in meters. Layamon had
                neither the desire nor the capacity to imitate the syllabic regularity of Wace's
                lines, yet they affected him sufficiently to lengthen his ha- bitual (shorter) OE
                lineform whenever he followed his source-material most closely; the result is that
                Layamon would write a series of longer lines, then re- vert to shorter lines out of
                neglect or instinct, thereby confounding the stabil- ity and homogeneity of his
                verse. It was the capacity for allowing more stresses (and possibly iambicity) in
                the French line which attracted Layamon (even un- consciously) to it. But Layamon
                never could forget or outgrow the OE model that he had learned early, and so his
                focus on line-length and/or rhyme, even though it increased as the poem progressed,
                produced not a new form but a curious, mixed, hybrid type of the old form. Trautmann
                and his followers were wrong in their account of Layamon's meter--Schipper was
                correct to up- hold the zweihebungstheorie--but even Schipper's classification of
                the meters in the Brut is "redundant" in its types and "incomplete" in its
                categories. McNary's revised classification appears on pp. 24–25. This is a very
                solid study, with important results and an excellent conclusion. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K240">
            <bib>McNeill, G. P. "Note on the Versification and Metre of Dunbar." The Poems of
                William Dunbar. Ed. John Small. Scottish Text Society Publications, no. 2.
                Edinburgh: William Blackwood, 1893. pp. clxxii–cxcii.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K241">
            <bib>Malone, Kemp. "Chaucer's Book of the Duchess: A Metrical Study." In Chaucer und
                seine Zeit: Symposium für Walter F. Schirmer. Ed. Arno Esch. Tübingen: Max Niemeyer,
                1968. pp.71–96.</bib>
            <notes> Following up a suggestion made formerly by Karl Luick that OE and ME verseforms
                are more similar than we think, it being unreasonable to be- lieve that the OE meter
                simply disappeared altogether, Malone proceeds to ar- gue that "BD can be scanned in
                terms of the Germanic metrical tradition and that this approach yields better
                results than does a scansion in terms of the French octosyllabic line of verse."
                I.e., he provides a complete metrical cata- logue of BD, scanning each line as an OE
                line according to Sievers' Five Types. Extensive notes appended. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K242">
            <bib>-----. "Chaucer's Double Consonants and the Final E." Mediaeval Studies 18 (1956):
                204–7.</bib>
            <notes> We have tolerably good knowledge of whether or not final -e's are to be pro-
                nounced in words within the line, but what about at line-end? Rhymes pro- vide some
                information, especially the fact that Chaucer never rhymes a word with double
                consonants (e.g. sonne) with a correlate single-consonant form (sone) though he
                often rhymes members of each of these types with each other. Therefore we may
                conclude that in the former type "Chaucer habitually pro- nounced the final
                unstressed e at the end of a line." Cf. Borroff (K32). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K243">
            <bib>Manabe, Kazumi. "Finite and Non-Finite Clauses in Early Middle English Verse."
                Studies in English Language and Literature 26 (1976): 141–54.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K244">
            <bib>-----. "Notes on Gramstylistic Analysis: With Reference to Articles in Chaucer."
                Studies in English Language and Literature 27 (1977): 95–107 (Summary in English,
                pp. 141–42).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K245">
            <bib>Manly, John M. "The Stanza-Forms of Sir Thopas." MP 8 (1910): 141–44.</bib>
            <notes> The eight varieties of tail-rhyme stanza ought not be seen as laxities,
                imperfec- tions, deviances, imitations or satires of the metrical romances, or
                displays of virtuosity; they are ebulliences, flourishes--rich, playful, gleeful
                gestures of bra- vura. Cf. Kölbing (K203), to which this essay is a response, and
                Gaylord (K135). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K246">
            <bib>Manzalaoui, Mahmoud. "Lydgate and English Prosody." Cairo Studies in English. Ed.
                Magdi Wahba. Cairo, 1960. pp. 87–104.</bib>
            <notes> Though published in a somewhat obscure vehicle, this essay is in fact a very
                important contribution to metrical theory; admitting Lydgate's shortcomings as
                metrist, Manzalaoui searches for an adequate theoretical description, which leads
                directly to a reconsideration of the whole theory of meter. Taking three descriptive
                terms from the fine arts, Manzalaoui sketches out the varieties of metrical form:
                Function Descriptive Decorative Expressive Regularity Natural speech-rhythms Strict
                meter Perfect identity between natural rhythm and abstract meter Irregularity Simple
                incompetence at metrics Variety for variety's sake Semantically expressive metrical
                variation Then he defines the levels of requiredness (necessity, constraint) of
                metrical elements in a theoretical system: • Exigency: obligatory aspects such as
                stress (in English verse); • Contingency: secondary or non-ordered but unavoidable
                elements such as quantity or pitch patterning; • Speech-Rhythm: in its interplay
                with meter; • Secondary Exigency: elements ordered merely by convention rather than
                linguistic necessity, such as rhyme; • Special Cases of the Exigency: certain
                specific conventions become quite rigid; • Constraint Within a "Special Case":
                sub-constraint within specific convention; • Delivery: recitative, chant, and oral
                interpretation. Finally, Manzalaoui suggests that in the long, complex transition
                from stress-verse to syllable-counting verse and alliteration to rhyme, regressions
                and atavisms occurred: the iambic pentameter, losing the special constraint of its
                iambicness, relaxed into alliterative stress-verse (an exigency) without the special
                exigency of the alliteration itself. Within the system both major rules and minor
                constraints may have shifted or relaxed at separate times. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K247">
            <bib>Marshall, Isabel, and Lela Porter. Ryme-Index to the Manuscript Texts of Chaucer's
                Minor Poems. Chaucer Society Publications, First Series, vols. 78, 80. London: Kegan
                Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co., 1887, 1889.</bib>
            <notes> Continuation of Cromie (K72); followed by Skeat (K355). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K248">
            <bib>Masui, Michio. The Structure of Chaucer's Rime Words: An Exploration into the
                Poetic Language of Chaucer. Tokyo: Kenkyusha, 1964. 371 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in Études Anglaises 18 (1965): 301–2; in Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 66
                (1965): 262–63; in Notes &amp; Queries 210 (1965): 389–90. The very long Part 1 of
                this book inventories the syntactic positions, relations, and functions of rhyme
                words to other rhyme words and also to other ele- ments within the line; a short
                following Part 2 discusses semantic structures. The dissertation behind the book
                originally contained a Part 3 providing a complete rhyme index, here abbreviated in
                two Appendices. A useful refer- ence. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K249">
            <bib>Matthews, William. The Tragedy of Arthur: A Study of the Alliterative "Morte
                Arthure." Berkeley: University of California Press, 1960.</bib>
            <notes> Virtually nothing on versification. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K250">
            <bib>Maynard, Theodore. The Connection Between the Ballade, Chaucer's Modification of
                It, Rime Royal, and the Spenserian Stanza. Washington, D.C.: Catholic University of
                America Press, 1934. 140 pp. His dissertation.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in TLS, 6 December 1934, p. 878; in Anglia Beiblatt 48 (1937): 13–14.
                Though there is a recent study of the rhyme royal by Stevens (K378), Maynard is
                still the authoritative study. He demonstrates amply the hegemony of this form from
                about 1350 to 1500--a domination more complete than that of the couplet over the
                eighteenth century--and provides an even more vari- able survey of its antecedents
                in medieval Latin, Old French, and Old English verse. Conclusions: the seven-line
                rhyme royal is not a modification of ottava rima, it is a simplification of the
                ballade and as such is by far Chaucer's most im- portant borrowing from the French
                (he persistently avoided all Italian verse- forms). Similarly, the Spenserian stanza
                is not based on ottava or terza rima but on the rhyme royal in Chaucer. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K251">
            <bib>Mead, D. S. "Verse Tags." Essays in Honor of A. Howry Espenshade. New York: Thomas
                Nelson and Sons, 1937. pp. 119–45.</bib>
            <notes> Proposing that modern verse differs from medieval in its insistence on novelty
                of phrase, Mead examines Chaucer, Gower, and other contemporaries for "stock
                phrases" (formulae, poetic diction) and "verse tags" (stock phrases and other
                occasional words used merely to fill out the meter). Finds that the force of
                convention in poetic phrasing was very strong, and a force which Chaucer readily
                accepted. Examples. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K252">
            <bib>Medary, M. P., and A. C. L. Brown. "Stanza-linking in Middle English Verse."
                Romanic Review 7 (1916): 243–70.</bib>
            <notes> An examination of the six Middle English poems which show the devices of
                stanza-linking and beginning and ending the stanza with the same word; Medary
                identifies seven principal types of linkages, three of which had not been noticed by
                the nineteenth-century German editors, which shows that the linkage convention was
                much more consistently employed than was formerly believed. Summary table, p. 258.
                The six romances are compared to the York Mystery Plays, the popular ballads, and
                Pearl. Stanza-linking appears only in the northern poetry and always in conjunction
                with alliteration; see the fol- lowing essay by Brown (K45) for an explanation.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K253">
            <bib>Meier, Hermann. Die Strophenformen in den englischen Misterienspielen. Diss.,
                Freiburg, 1921. 70 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Three foldout tables after p. 48 provide all the data on meters and rhyme
                schemes in a convenient form. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K254">
            <bib>Menner, Robert J., ed. "Purity": A Middle English Poem. Yale Studies in English,
                vol. 61. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1920.</bib>
            <notes> "Metre and Alliteration," pp. liii–lviii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K255">
            <bib>Mennicken, Franz. "Versbau und Sprache in Huchowns Morte Arthure." Bonner Beiträge
                zur Anglistik 5 (1900): 33–144.</bib>
            <notes> Mennicken extends Trautmann's "seven-bar" theory (see K404)--four bars to the
                on-verse, three to the off-verse--to the alliterative Morte Arthure. The Ver-
                sification section covers pp. 34–118. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K256">
            <bib>Mersand, Joseph. "Chaucer's Romance Rimes." Chaucer's Romance Vocabulary. New
                York: The Comet Press, 1937. pp. 85–89.</bib>
            <notes> Summarizes the work of Vockrodt (K422) and Beschorner (K19) ordering the
                chronology of the canon based on rhyme practice, lists percentages of rhyming
                Romance-origin words in each of the works, and dismisses Skeat's suggestion about
                the frequency of sentences ending at the end of the first line of a cou- plet.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K257">
            <bib>Miller, Francis H. "Stanzaic Division in York Play XXXIX." MLN 35 (1920):
                379–80.</bib>
            <notes> Proposes a rearrangement of stanzas 5–7 based on rhyme-schemes. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K258">
            <bib>Mitchell, Bruce. "The Couplet System in Havelock the Dane." Notes &amp; Queries
                208 (1963): 405–6.</bib>
            <notes> An argument for a triplet or even larger brace of rhymed lines at 1.546, citing
                evidence of similar disruptions in the run of couplets in other ME texts. Cf.
                Wittenbrinck (K435). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K259">
            <bib>Mitchell, Jerome. "Meter." Thomas Hoccleve, a Study in Early Fifteenth Century
                English Poetic. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1968. pp. 96–109.</bib>
            <notes> Trying to salvage, if not elevate, Hoccleve's reputation as a metrist, Mitchell
                rejects the scansions and judgments of Schipper, Bock, Saintsbury, and Lick- lider
                (K217). The lines will turn out much better, we are told, if we scan them according
                to the systems of either (1): Brooks and Warren (E501) allowing metrical
                substitutions; or (2) Schick (K328), adapting the five line-type system from
                Lydgate; or (3) Southworth (K368), reading the lines rhythmically not metrically.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K260">
            <bib>Mitsui, Toru. "Notes on the Stanzaic Division and the Metre of Judas." Studies in
                English Literature (Tokyo) 44 (1968): 209–20.</bib>
            <notes> Discarding the Child version in favor of a transcription of the MS by Skeat, the
                author discusses the sign "ii," suggesting that it meant "repeat the melody of this
                line once again" (rather than "repeat this line again") and argues that the ballad
                is in triple meter (rather than Common Measure). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K261">
            <bib>Miura, T. "Arrangement of Two or More Attributive Adjectives in Chaucer, I."
                Anglica (Osaka) 6 (1966): 1–23.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K262">
            <bib>Moorman, Charles. "The Origins of the Alliterative Revival." Southern Quarterly 7
                (1969): 345–71.</bib>
            <notes> This essay should be a summary of what is now the Received Opinion on the
                subject. Following Oakden (K242) fairly closely, Moorman characterizes the OE
                verseform (heroic, pagan, tribal) and social milieu, then argues that there was a
                continuous preservation of the meter, language, and themes of classical OE poetry
                into the ME period (there is no example anywhere in art of the complete extinction
                and subsequent recovery of a major technique in a pe- riod). In the late OE period
                alongside the professional scops and clerics there appeared a class of popular
                minstrels, less proficient but more experimental metrically, who preserved the
                alliterative technique in an oral tradition (the sentiments of which were not
                acceptable to the copyists in the monasteries) until it reflowered in the fourteenth
                century. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K263">
            <bib>Morrill, Georgiana L., ed. Speculum Gy de Warewyke. Early English Text Society,
                Extra Series, no. 75. London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co., 1898. "On the
                Metrical Structure," pp. cxxv–cxliii; "On the Riming Structure," pp.
                cxliii–cxlviii.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K264">
            <bib>Morris, Richard, ed. "The Story of Genesis and Exodus": An Early English Song,
                about A.D. 1250. Early English Text Society, Extra Series, no. 7. London: Trübner,
                1865. "The Metre of the Poem," pp. xxxvii–xl.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K265">
            <bib>Morton, Edward P. "Chaucer's Identical Rimes." MLN 18 (1903): 73–74.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K266">
            <bib>Mustanoja, Tauno F. "Chaucer's Prosody." In Companion to Chaucer Studies. Ed.
                Beryl Rowland. New York: Oxford University Press, 1968. pp. 58–84.</bib>
            <notes> An excellent introductory essay on Chaucer's verse-craft, followed by an equally
                thorough bibliography. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K267">
            <bib>-----. "Verbal Rhyming in Chaucer." Chaucer and Middle English Studies in Honour
                of Russell Hope Robbins. Ed. Beryl Rowland. London: Allen &amp; Unwin, 1974. pp.
                104–10.</bib>
            <notes> Beschorner's (K19) claim that the use of verbs--especially infinitives--for
                rhymes is a feature peculiar to Chaucer is not borne out by a wider inspection of ME
                verse; the feature seems to be fairly common, to judge from selected OE, MHG, ME,
                and ModE texts. Cf. Masui (K248). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K268">
            <bib>Nelson, Marie. "Submorphemic Values: Their Contribution to Patterns and Meaning in
                the Morte Arthure." Language and Style 6 (1973): 289–96.</bib>
            <notes> The poet used (1) the alliterating sounds to suggest, mimetically, certain
                lexical and semantic points, as with the use of gr- and bilabial stops to body
                forth, kinesthetically, the fight scenes, and (2) the grouping and repetition of
                alliter- ants (elsewhere termed "plurilinear alliteration") as a mnemonic device to
                "help the listener to perceive the grouping of details." This last is significant,
                has not been suggested before, I think, and deserves considerable attention.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K269">
            <bib>Neufeldt, Victoria E. "The Metric of English Alliterative Verse: Piers the Plowman
                and Beowulf." Diss., University of Toronto, 1976.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K270">
            <bib>Nolan, Edward P. "Medieval Versification: Style and Meaning in Hartmann von Aue's
                Iwein and the Middle English Ywain and Gawain." DA 28 (1967): 2217A (Indiana).</bib>
            <notes> Both poems have a common Old French source--Chrétien de Troye's Ywain-- and
                (perhaps surprisingly) their meters are nearly identical, though the ME poem is
                metrically very much inferior to von Aue's version. Nolan devises a system for
                comparative scansion. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K271">
            <bib>Northrup, Clark S. "A Study of the Metrical Structure of the Middle English Poem
                The Pearl." PMLA 12 (1897): 326–40.</bib>
            <notes> Notes on the metrical and pronunciational treatment of -e in fourteen types of
                syllabic environments, with two additional notes on irregular lines and allitera-
                tion. Each note catalogues all occurrences of its type. Concludes that final un-
                stressed -e's within the line were probably not pronounced. Conclusions about those
                at line-end must await analysis of the rhymes. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K272">
            <bib>Norton-Smith, John. "The Origins of 'Skeltonics.'" Essays in Criticism 23 (1973):
                57–62.</bib>
            <notes> Notices two Skeltonics written by Gabriel Harvey and discovers some others in
                the Paston Letters; Skelton may have been related to the Pastons and learned the
                form directly from them. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K273">
            <bib>Noyes, G. R. "A Peculiar Rime in Chaucer." MLN 19 (1904): 256.</bib>
            <notes> Noyes noticed an apparently unique instance of rhyming close with open e. J. S.
                P. Tatlock's reply (K393) adds other instances, however. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K274">
            <bib>Oakden, James P. Alliterative Poetry in Middle English. 2 vols. Vol. 1: The
                Dialectal and Metrical Survey. Vol. 2: A Survey of the Traditions. Publications of
                the University of Manchester, nos. 205, 236, English series, nos. 18, 22.
                Manchester: Manchester University Press, 1930, 1935</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. 2 vols. in 1, Hamden, Conn.: Archon/Shoe String, 1968. Rev.: in English
                Studies 13 (1931): 142–45; in Archiv 159 (1931): 293–96; in Anglia Beiblatt 42
                (1931): 334–41; in MP 28 (1931): 485–86; in Englische Studien 66 (1932): 406–11; in
                MLR 27 (1932): 72–75; in SP 29 (1932): 123– 29; in Review of English Studies 9
                (1933): 89–94. Second vol. rev.: in TLS, 25 January 1936, p. 67; in Anglia Beiblatt
                47 (1936): 231–34; by Hulbert in MP 34 (1936): 198–200; in Archiv 170 (1936):
                113–16; in JEGP 36 (1937): 120–23; in MLN 52 (1937): 430–33; in Review of English
                Studies 13 (1937): 217–25. Vol. 1: I. The Dialectal Survey II. The Metrical Survey
                Vol. 2: I. The Poems as Literature II. The Vocabulary [formulae: nominal compounds
                in OE, Early ME, and the Alliterative Revival] III. The Alliterative Phrases
                [alliterative formulae] IV. Style ["tags," fillers; style in general]. Though later
                work has modified this perspective in details, Oakden is still the standard
                authority on Middle English Alliterative Verse (MEAV). Note however from his title
                the extent of his domain: he does not treat at all the other two primary streams of
                ME verse, the tail-rhyme romances and the truly syllabic and stanzaic,
                Romance-influenced meters (most prominently Chau- cer's). But since Oakden's account
                of MEAV is a major one--on a level with Schipper's--and since it is not especially
                easy to follow, a summary (with schema) will be in order. The true OE alliterative
                line (meter) was preserved intact in the monas- teries even as late as 1150 (the
                Anglo-Saxon Chronicle verses, 1065; the Descrip- tion of Durham, ca. 1100, for
                example). Meanwhile the popular verseform (showing irregular rhyme and assonance
                with alliteration), preserved through- out the OE period and probably closely
                related to rhythmical prose as Blake suggests, combines with the classical (Five
                Types) meter; "the long line breaks up and a couplet is formed," having rhyme
                (internal rhyme in the long-line becomes final rhyme in the half-line couplets;
                Oakden neglects to say this though he clearly assumes it) together with alliteration
                (e.g., the Worchester fragment and the Departing Soul's Address to the Body, both
                ca. 1170; the Proverbs of Alfred, 1180; Layamon, 1189–1207; and the Bestiary, ca.
                1200–50). This na- tive couplet "inevitably becomes more and more syllabic, until it
                is written side by side with the French couplet and becomes indistinguishable from
                it," as witnesses the Brut, a poem in which alliteration is still dominant over
                rhyme, Layamon generally preferring not to mix the two, though the syllabic influ-
                ence of the French is everywhere evident. In the West the more-strictly- classical
                line without rhyme must have been preserved (though we have no extant major works)
                until it flowered again in the Alliterative Revival, ca. 1340–1450. (To this
                movement Oakden naturally devotes considerable atten- tion; see below.) In the
                Southwest, however, the popular verse tradition seems to have survived in another
                line of development; here the long-line adopted end-rhyme (instead of medial-rhyme
                followed by breaking into hemistichic couplets), apparently under the influence of
                the Latin septenary, and formed long couplets with some syllabic regularity. The
                line is not very strong but it is there, as witnesses On God Orison of Our Lady (ca.
                1200), up until about 1300; thereafter, this form appears in the Northeast and
                Scotland, where it soon after gave way to the bob-and-wheel stanza, a form of
                extraordinary versatility and vigor, dominant from ca. 1350 to 1550. The hybrid
                short-couplet form seen in Layamon and apparently also the long end-rhymed couplets
                are eventually subsumed into a strictly syllabic couplet, under the pressure of
                French, which is the form we see in Chaucer. This way Wyatt lies. As for the
                disputed Alliterative Revival in the West, Oakden cites the evidence of (1) patterns
                of identical alliteration in consecutive lines, (2) in- stances of full-line
                alliteration "foreshadowed" or prefigured in earlier lines, and (3) the survival of
                Sievers' Type C as proving the direct descent of the fourteenth-century alliterative
                line from the OE. Even further proof can be gleaned by observing six other metrical
                features already evident in Early ME which continued to develop: heavy end-stopping;
                alliteration only on identical vowels as well as identical consonants; lengthening
                of the line; recognizable OE alliteration patterns; extended half-lines; and a
                general collapse of the OE verse-types into one amorphous, general, flexible type in
                ME. New character- istics of the MEAV of the Revival period include stanzas, eye
                alliteration, and excessive alliteration. In an Appendix Oakden argues for the sole
                authorship of Sir Gawain, Purity, Patience, and St. Erkenwald by the "Gawain-poet,"
                and separate author- ship for each of three other poems, the Destruction of Troy,
                the Wars of Alexan- der, and the Morte Arthure. Compare Oakden's theory with the
                later, contrastive view of Turville- Petre (K412). Part I of volume 2 of Oakden's
                study is reprinted in a student's edition as </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K275">
            <bib>Oakden, James P. The Poetry of the Alliterative Revival. Manchester: Manchester
                University Press, 1937. 40 pp.</bib>
            <notes> [GRAPHIC] OAKDEN'S VIEW OF THE DEVELOPMENT OF MIDDLE ENGLISH ALLITERATIVE VERSE
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K276">
            <bib>-----. "The Continuity of the Alliterative Tradition." MLR 28 (1933):
                233–34.</bib>
            <notes> In response to Greg (K144), Oakden argues that the cumulative weight of metrical
                evidence for a continuous alliterative tradition in ME is convincing, especially the
                evidence of alliterative enjambement, consecutive alliteration, and the C-Type.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K277">
            <bib>O'Loughlin, J. L. N. "The Middle English Alliterative Morte Arthure." Medium Ævum
                4 (1935): 153–68.</bib>
            <notes> On problems of emendation and cavalier treatment of the text by editors, with
                some attention to alliteration. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K278">
            <bib>Olson, Clair C. "Chaucer and the Music of the Fifteenth Century." Speculum 16
                (1941): 64–91.</bib>
            <notes> There are some few remarks in section III (especially p. 84) on the setting of
                lyrics to music. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K279">
            <bib>Olszewska, E. S. "The Alliterative Phrases in the Ormulum." Leeds Studies in
                English and Kindred Languages, no. 6 (1936), pp. 50–67.</bib>
            <notes> Corrections to Oakden (K274). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K280">
            <bib>-----. "Alliterative Phrases in the Ormulum: Some Norse Parallels." English and
                Medieval Studies Presented to J. R. R. Tolkien. Ed. Norman Davis and C. L. Wrenn.
                London: Allen &amp; Unwin, 1962. pp. 112–27.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K281">
            <bib>-----. "Illustrations of Norse Formulas in English." Leeds Studies in English and
                Kindred Languages, no. 2 (1933), pp. 76–84.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K282">
            <bib>-----. "Norse Alliterative Tradition in Middle English I." Ibid., no. 6 (1937),
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> 50–64. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K283">
            <bib>-----. "Middle English trowe 7 traist." Notes &amp; Queries 219 (1974): 325.</bib>
            <notes> Suggests a Norse origin for this alliteration. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K284">
            <bib>Osberg, Richard H. "The Alliterative Lyric and Thirteenth-Century Devotional
                Prose." JEGP 76 (1977): 40–54.</bib>
            <notes> Based on his dissertation work, "The Alliterative Tradition in the Middle Eng-
                lish Lyric," DAI 35 (1974): 1666A (Claremont College). Argues that "struc- tural
                alliteration in the Middle English lyric does not derive either from the decadent
                long-line and arcane vocabulary of the alliterative revival poems, or from the
                octosyllabic pattern and hackneyed alliterative tags of minstrel verse, but evolved
                rather from the rhythmical alliteration of certain veins of devo- tional prose."
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K285">
            <bib>Ostermann, Ludwig. "Untersuchung zu 'Ratis Raving' und dem Gedicht 'The Thewis of
                Gud Women.'" Bonner Beiträge zur Anglistik 12 (1902): 41–102. Metrics, pp.
                74–94.</bib>
            <notes> In the author's view both poems are in short four-bar couplets. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K286">
            <bib>Owen, Charles A., Jr. "'Thy Drasty Ryming. . . . '" SP 63 (1966): 533–64.</bib>
            <notes> A patient and searching yet broad assessment of Chaucer's developing skill at
                rhymecraft--at the deployment and pacing of thematic material in his stanzas, at
                metrical expressiveness, and at creating satire through form--especially in the
                tail-rhyme stanza, in rhyme royal, and in couplets. In contrast to the French, who
                cultivated the difficulty of complex rhymes, Chaucer explored its adapt- ability.
                For him it was a means not an end. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K287">
            <bib>Palmatier, Robert A. A Descriptive Syntax of the "Ormulum.' The Hague: Mouton,
                1969. 137 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: by Albert H. Marckwardt in Journal of English Linguistics 5 (1971): 145–
                49; in Linguistics 135 (1974): 125–28. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K288">
            <bib>-----. "Metrical -e in the Ormulum." Journal of English Linguistics 6 (1972):
                35–45.</bib>
            <notes> Orm had the final -e available to him as an optional suffix for a great many
                words in his dialect, and he adapted it selectively for purposes of regularizing his
                meter. He did not employ the -e solely as an orthographic feature having no reality
                in contemporary speech. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K289">
            <bib>Payne, Joseph. "The Use of Final -e in Early English, with especial reference to
                the final -e at the end of the verse in Chaucer's Canterbury Tales." Essays in
                Chaucer, His Life and Works. Chaucer Society Publications, series 2, part 2, no. 4.
                London, 1874</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. 1896. pp. 83–154. K290 An earlier version appeared in Transactions of the
                Philological Society, 1868–69, pp. 86–153. Payne concludes that by Chaucer's time
                the inflectional -e had ceased to be pronounced in colloquial speech but was
                preserved in verse, though only when necessary (which would not include the rhyme at
                the end of the line), so that Chaucer could employ it at his discretion as a "help
                to the meter." In denying feminine rhymes Payne is disagreeing with Child (K59); he
                also demurs in deriving the Chaucerian line from the French decasyllable, preferring
                instead the Italian endecasyllabo. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K291">
            <bib>Percy, Thomas, Bishop of Dromore. "On the Metre of Pierce Plowman's Visions." In
                his Reliques of Ancient English Poetry. 3 vols. London: J. Dodsley, 1765. Vol. 2,
                Book 3, pp. 260–70.</bib>
            <notes> Notes that the alliterative line in Langland--a distich comprised of two short
                verses--was, by the sixteenth century, "at length swallowed up and lost in our
                common burlesque alexandrine," the measure having lost all its force in the face
                (here, mouth) of rhyme. The French alexandrine is the "same legitimate offspring" of
                the old alliterative line, a meter not akin to blank verse but hav- ing "a sort of
                harmony of its own, proceeding not so much from its allitera- tion, as from the
                artful disposal of its cadence, and the contrivance of its pause." See also </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K291a">
            <bib>Dennis, Leah. "Percy's Essay 'On the Ancient Metrical Romances'" in PMLA 49
                (1934): 81–97.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K292">
            <bib>Perry, George G., ed. "Morte Arthure." Early English Text Society, Original
                Series, no. 8. London: Trübner &amp; Co., 1865. Second edition edited by Edmund
                Brock (K44).</bib>
            <notes> "On the Metre of the Poem," pp. xv–xix, seems indebted to Guest (E543); Perry
                identifies two stresses to the verse (occasionally three) and the system of
                alliterating staves as essential and thinks "the general effect of the metre is
                dactylic" (italics original). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K293">
            <bib>Pesta, Theodor. Die alliterierende Langzeile in "Sir Gawayn and the grene Knyght"
                und ihr Verhältnis zur Altenglischen. Diss., Innsbruck, 1903.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K294">
            <bib>Petzold, Ernst. über Alliteration in den Werken Chaucers mit Ausschluss der
                "Canterbury Tales." Diss., Marburg, 1889. 98 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K295">
            <bib>Pilch, Herbert. Layamons "Brut": Eine literarische Studie. Heidelberg: Carl
                Winter, 1960.</bib>
            <notes> "Versbau und Rhythmus," pp. 135–56, is the most extended discussion avail- able.
                Pilch gives a quasimusical scansion in 4/4 time. Criticized by Standop (K372).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K296">
            <bib>Pilch, Leo. Umwandlung des altenglischen Alliterationsverses in den
                mittelenglischen Reimvers. Diss., Konigsberg, 1904. 72 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A student of Trautmann's (see K404), Pilch turns his attention to both the al-
                literative and rhymed verse of Middle English, hoping to show a steady and unified
                development throughout all of ME verse in the twelfth through four- teenth
                centuries. The Introduction reviews the history of the vierhebungstheorie and its
                opponent on the question of ME verseform succinctly and accurately; Pilch then turns
                to separate metrical analyses of eighteen ME poems, chiefly the Brut and King Horn.
                His view of the rhymed verse in ME (MERV) is that these short couplets were derived
                from a fusion of the Latin hymn verse with the French octosyllabic, producing an
                English meld which originally had counted only stresses (not syllables) but
                gradually came to regulate the number of slacks as well, resulting in a regular
                alternation of both. The alliterative verse, however, was a reversion of the Latin
                septenary to the unrhymed allit- erative form of OE verse; the MEAV is thus in
                effect an unrhymed septenary. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K297">
            <bib>Plessow, Gustave, ed. [Metrical Transcript of the Manciple's Tale.] Des
                Haushalters Erzählung. Berlin: Walter de Gruyter, 1929. pp. 52–69.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K298">
            <bib>Pollard, Alfred W., ed. The Towneley Plays. Early English Text Society, Extra
                Series, no. 71. London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co., 1897.</bib>
            <notes> See pp. xx–xxiii, especially the chart of meters on this last page. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K299">
            <bib>Pucks, Karl. Die Abhängigkeit der Inversion vom in eingeleiteten Aussagesätzen mit
                einem Pronomial-Subjekt in Chaucers "Canterbury Tales." Diss., Graz, 1911.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K300">
            <bib>Purcell, J. M. "The 'Troilus Verse.'" PQ 12 (1933): 90–91.</bib>
            <notes> The term was used by King James in 1585 for "rime royal." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K301">
            <bib>Pyle, Fitzroy. "The Barbarous Metre of Barclay." MLR 32 (1937): 353–73.</bib>
            <notes> Argues that "the Eclogue meter is one of mechanical regularity" and that "the
                line-structure of The Ships of Fools is also essentially metrical." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K302">
            <bib>-----. "Chaucer's Prosody." Medium Ævum 42 (1973): 47–56.</bib>
            <notes> An exceptionally close and careful critique of the position taken by Robinson
                (K318), most especially his conception of the "balanced pentameter," the me- ter
                that he believes Chaucer was able to create by fusing the characteristics of both
                the old native alliterative meter and the imported Romance syllabic me- ter,
                retaining the characteristics of both forms together. Pyle reinforces the tra-
                ditional view, that Chaucer's hybrid meter gave up certain characteristics of both
                its parent forms in order to become a distinctively new--albeit unstable-- form.
                Also discussed: trochaic substitution, spondees, pronunciation, MS evi- dence.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K303">
            <bib>-----. "A Metrical Point in Chaucer." Notes &amp; Queries 170 (1936): 128.</bib>
            <notes> At two points in his narrative where a character recites an old proverb, Chau-
                cer makes an effort to preserve its colloquial flavor (i.e., order of phrasing), so
                that the meter for a moment slips from the pentameter mode into the older
                four-stresses mode. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K304">
            <bib>-----. "The Origins of the Skeltonic." Notes &amp; Queries 171 (1936):
                362–64.</bib>
            <notes> Skelton's verseform seems to have been an extension of forms popular before the
                Conquest, and its two identifying characteristics--shortness of line-length and
                irregular rhyme-grouping--were probably derivatives of (respectively) the OE
                half-line, with its descendant the short rhyming couplet showing a lesser influence
                from Medieval Latin and French verse, and the (much-neglected) Anglo-Norman
                tradition. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K305">
            <bib>-----. "The Pedigree of Lydgate's Heroic Line, With a Note on his Use of the
                Line-types." Hermathena, no. 50 (1937), pp. 26–59.</bib>
            <notes> One can discern actual orderliness in Lydgate's metrical ineptitude by recog-
                nizing that he employs a fixed medial caesura even though the flanking hemis- tichs
                vary greatly; in this practice he was following the pre-Chaucerian tradi- tion of
                the Alexandrine and fourteener. The analysis seems exhaustive. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K306">
            <bib>-----. "The Place of Anglo-Norman in the History of English Versification."
                Hermathena, no. 49 (1935), pp. 22–42.</bib>
            <notes> Must not be ignored: the decline of the speaking of French at the English court
                in Chaucer's time is paradoxically responsible for two seemingly-divergent
                processes--the revival of the older native alliterative verseform, and also the
                preservation of the strict French forms in verse articulated in English. Anglo-
                Norman is pivotal. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K307">
            <bib>Ramsay, Robert L., ed. "Magnyfycence": A Moral Play by John Skelton. Early English
                Text Society, Extra Series, no. 98. London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co.,
                1908 (for 1906).</bib>
            <notes> "Versification," pp. li–lxxi, cxxxiv–cxlvii (the first installment treats the
                verse- structure of the play itself, the second its position in the metrical
                experimenta- tion evident throughout the Morality Plays). The staple meter of the
                play is "the rimed native long line of four stresses" and strong caesura, but
                Skelton thought of it as two short lines in a rough triple rhythm. With this
                four-stress line alternates a more regular four-foot iambic tetrameter line (Ramsay
                terms these "heavy" and "light"); both of these together give four general types of
                line--short and long/heavy and light. Skelton keeps them pretty well distinct by
                rhyme schemes, chiefly rhyme royal, couplets, and the repeated "leash" rhyme. On the
                whole Magnyfycence [ca. 1516] shows a surprising variety of forms and a rich
                profusion of new forms which are nevertheless skillfully posi- tioned and controlled
                for purposes of characterization. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K308">
            <bib>Rankin, J. W. "The Hymns of St. Godric." PMLA 38 (1923): 699–711.</bib>
            <notes> Structure of these verses is treated on pp. 701–7; they are in a four-stress
                line, the rhyme-scheme generally aabb. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K309">
            <bib>Raymond, James C. "Lydgate's Verse and the Nature of English Prosody." DAI 34
                (1974): 5925A (Texas).</bib>
            <notes> The modern disparagement of Lydgate's versecraft, a sharp contrast to the high
                praise of the Renaissance, can only be explained as a modern misunderstand- ing:
                Lydgate was not trying to imitate Chaucer's meter. We must distinguish between his
                four-stress verse and his octosyllables (which regulate syllable count strictly).
                His pentameters, however, combine features of the octosyllable with the variable
                caesura of the fourteener. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K310">
            <bib>Reese, Jesse B. "Alliterative Verse in the York Cycle." SP 48 (1951):
                639–68.</bib>
            <notes> Shows that nearly all the major studies dating the plays (Chambers, Greg,
                Hohlfeld, etc.) were not based on any thorough analysis of versification. Reese's
                own analysis shows the meter to be alliterative not syllabic. A study valuable in
                both length and detail. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K311">
            <bib>Regel, Karl. "Die Alliteration in Lajamon." In Germanistische Studien: Supplement
                zur "Germania." Ed. Karl Bartsch. Vienna, 1872. Vol. 1, pp. 171–246.</bib>
            <notes> This study established a classification system for the relation of alliterating
                words which was widely followed in German dissertations thereafter: 1. Etymological
                2. Associative A. Concrete B. Abstractions, or abstract + concrete C. Emphasis D.
                Contrast 3. Grammatical A. Substantive, with modifiers if any B. Verb or Adjective,
                with modifiers C. Substantive + Verb (Subject + Predicate) D. Verb + Substantive
                (Predicate + Object). Cf. Lindner (K218). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K312">
            <bib>Reger, Hans. Die epische Cäsur in der Chaucerschule. Diss., Munich. Bayreuth:
                Lorenz Ellwanger, 1910. 88 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Mainly lists of occurrences in Lydgate, with some slight attention to the older
                Chaucerians near the end. The "epic caesura," it will be recalled, is preceded by an
                extra (hypermetrical) syllable, resulting in an eleven-syllable line. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K313">
            <bib>Reicke, Curt. Untersuchungen über den Stil der mittelenglischen alliterierenden
                Gedichte "Morte Arthure," "The Destruction of Troy," "The Wars of Alexander," "The
                Siege of Jerusalem," "Sir Gawayn and the Green Knight": Ein Beiträge der Lösung der
                Huchown-Frage. Diss., Konigsberg, 1906.</bib>
            <notes> "Verse-filling" as a test for authorship. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K314">
            <bib>Renoir, Alain. "An Echo to the Sense: The Patterns of Sound in Sir Gawain and the
                Green Knight." English Miscellany 13 (1962): 9–23.</bib>
            <notes> On sound (imagery) in the poem not of the poem. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K315">
            <bib>Robbins, Russell H. "The Burden in Carols." MLN 57 (1942): 16–22.</bib>
            <notes> Problems of stanzaic and melodic form in some Middle English carols in Brit- ish
                Museum MS Additional 5665. A "burden" is a line or short group of lines before the
                first stanza and each additional stanza. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K316">
            <bib>Robertson, Stuart. "Old English Verse in Chaucer." MLN 43 (1928): 234–36.</bib>
            <notes> Finds alliterative four-stress verses in The Knight's Tale. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K317">
            <bib>Robinson, Fred N. "On the Modal Syntax of Finite Verbs in The Canterbury Tales."
                Diss., Harvard University, 1894.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K318">
            <bib>Robinson, Ian. Chaucer's Prosody: A Study of the Middle English Verse Tradition.
                London: Cambridge University Press, 1971</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. 1973. Rev.: by G. A. Fraser in Language and Style 5 (1972): 313–15: a
                very interesting and useful review giving examples of second- and fifth-foot
                reversals. Also re- viewed by M. Gretsch in Anglia 92 (1974): 454–60; in ELN 11
                (1973): 123– 26; in English Studies 54 (1973): 272–74; in Cambridge Quarterly 5
                (1971): 589– 93; in Speculum 49 (1974): 148–51. Robinson's book stands somewhere
                between the introductory level and the scholarly; his principles are iconoclastic,
                and seem, from a certain distance, al- most silly at times. For example, he is very
                much distressed that the student will try to read Chaucer in Middle English, and so
                disparages the sound-charts of all the standard editions, claiming that we know
                nothing concrete about fourteenth-century phonology. His chapter on "Rhythm and
                Metre" gives rhythm the precedence: "in much of the best English verse the metre
                does not fully replace speech-rhythms." He agrees with Northrop Frye that Chaucer's
                line is not an iambic pentameter but a four-beat line (p. 52) and considers that the
                best way to understand "the notion of an ideal metre is to think of it in terms of
                expectation and call it 'a willingness to create the metre.'" He disdains a
                metrically-weighted recitation of Chaucer. Following a chapter on Chaucer's own
                prosodic terms and idea, Robinson takes up the final -e in a long chapter (perhaps
                the best) which con- cludes equivocally: "if the metre seems to demand an -e sound
                it, but if the resulting reading damages the poetry, suspect the metre that led to
                it." But, staggeringly, he rejects "variable stress" on Middle English words; this
                course leads to fifth-foot trochees in some of Chaucer's pentameters, a consequence
                which Robinson prefers. He thinks the verse best punctuated in phrasal-units, as the
                medieval MSS do, because he believes the Chaucerian line to be a "bal- anced
                pentameter"--i.e., a line of five feet, usually iambic, but also divided into
                half-lines, following the alliterative tradition. Two final chapters treat the
                Chaucerians from Hoccleve and Lydgate to Wyatt; an Appendix repudiates any efforts
                to trace the sources of Chaucer's metric in foreign versifications. Bibliography.
                The whole thrust and tone of this work is negative, reactionary, and eccentric: it
                cannot represent any ad- vance in either scholarship or method. See the critiques by
                Pyle (K302) and by Gaylord (K136), and see also E763. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K319">
            <bib>Rose, Hermann. "über die Metrik der Chronik Fantosmes." Romanische Studien 5
                (1880): 301–82.</bib>
            <notes> Cf. Johnston (K177). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K320">
            <bib>Rosenthal, F. "Die alliterierende englische Langzeile im 14 Jahrhundert." Anglia 1
                (1878): 414–59.</bib>
            <notes> The earliest attempt to scan the Middle English alliterative line as being in
                the four-beat (to the half-line) meter described by the vierhebungstheorie. Word-
                stress, meter, and alliteration patterns are examined in eight poems, chiefly Piers
                Plowman, and tables cataloguing the alliterative filling for each of the three texts
                of that poem are provided at the end. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K321">
            <bib>Ross, Alan S. C. "Some Alliterative Phrases in the Bodley Homilies," Notes &amp;
                Queries 215 (1970): 46–48.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K322">
            <bib>Saintsbury, George. "Prosody from Chaucer to Spenser." The Cambridge History of
                English Literature. Ed. A. W. Ward and A. R. Waller. 14 vols. New York: G. P.
                Putnam's Sons, 1907–16. Vol. 3, chapter 13, pp. 273–88.</bib>
            <notes> A very short survey of the material given fuller treatment in Books 1–3 (vol. 1)
                of Saintsbury's History of English Prosody (A8). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K323">
            <bib>Salter, Elizabeth. "Alliterative Modes and Affiliations in the Fourteenth
                Century." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 79 (1978): 25–35.</bib>
            <notes> The "Alliterative Revival" may well have been not so much antiquarianism as a
                transformation process, since alliterative patterns had been preserved con-
                tinuously since the Anglo-Saxon age in a strong but ingrained prose tradition.
                Fourteenth-century poets may have made less of a distinction between prose and verse
                than we do and hence drawn more readily on the materials pre- served in the
                monasteries, the prose works. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K324">
            <bib>-----. "The Alliterative Revival: I, II." MP 64 (1966–67): 146–50, 233–37.</bib>
            <notes> Observations on authorship and provenience, generally critical of Hulbert
                (K164). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K325">
            <bib>Samuels, M. L. "Chaucerian Final -E." Notes &amp; Queries 217 (1972):
                445–48.</bib>
            <notes> A sturdy defense of the traditional view of Chaucer's line as decasyllabic
                against the more recent caviling of Southworth and Robinson. Samuels shows that the
                argument for the metrical retention of syllabic -e is non-circular in logic and
                based on systematic grammatical features in ME irrefragably established by
                philology. And the more difficult questions about Lydgate's and Wyatt's meters ought
                not be conflated with the question about Chaucer's. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K326">
            <bib>Sauerbrey, Gertrud. Die innere Sprachform bei Chaucer. Diss., Halle, 1917. 117
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Syntax of the verbs. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K327">
            <bib>Savage, Henry L., ed. "St. Erkenwald": A Middle English Poem. Yale Studies in
                English, vol. 72. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1926.</bib>
            <notes> "Metre and Alliteration," pp. xliii–xlviii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K328">
            <bib>Schick, J., ed. "Lydgate's Meter." Lydgate's "Temple of Glas." Early English Text
                Society, Extra Series, no. 60. London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co., 1891.
                pp. liv–lxiii.</bib>
            <notes> Schick identifies five types of line in Lydgate: (1) normal iambic pentameters,
                (2) lines adding one weak syllable before the caesura, (3) lines missing a weak
                syllable after the caesura (the "broken-backed" line), (4) acephalous lines, and (5)
                lines with a trisyllabic first foot. This typology has been generally accepted. Cf.
                Hascall (E779). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K329">
            <bib>Schiller, Andrew. "The Gawain Rhythm." Language and Style 1 (1968): 268–94.</bib>
            <notes> An application of Lanier's theory of isochronous musical-bar scansion (E364) to
                Sir Gawain. Schiller identifies the standard long-line as three bars in 2/4 time
                with a quarter-bar anacrusis and a three-quarter-bar hypercatalexis, mak- ing four
                bars altogether as the lines run continuously. In the bob lines the three middle
                bars drop out, as it were, leaving only one. N.B.: Schiller misun- derstands and
                misjudges Trautmann; he recognizes the final -e as mute but then proceeds
                (explicitly) as if it were not, and he naively believes that primary stresses in Sir
                Gawain are "determined by mandatory alliteration." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K330">
            <bib>Schipper, Jakob. "Englische Metrik: Fremde Metra." In Paul's Grundriss (L531). pp.
                181–240.</bib>
            <notes> This study of those aspects of verseform in English influenced by foreign
                (Latin, Romance) models, with almost exclusive attention to Middle English, also
                presents Schipper's views on the metrical treatment of syllables and on verse-
                rhythm. But it also shows us that Schipper had revised and reduced the German text
                of his great Englische Metrik before he translated it, since what we have here is
                virtually identical in substance to Book I Part I and Book II Parts I and II of the
                English version (A11). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K331">
            <bib>Schipper, Jakob, ed. Englische Alexiuslegenden aus dem XIV. und XV. Jahrhundert.
                Quellen und Forschungen, no. 20. Strassburg: Karl Trübner, 1877. "Strophe, Vers, und
                Rhyme," pp. 59–65.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K332">
            <bib>Schirmer, Walter F. John Lydgate: Ein Kulturbild aus dem 15 Jahrhundert. Tübingen:
                Max Niemeyer, 1952. Translated by Ann E. Keep as John Lydgate: A Study in the
                Culture of the XVth Century. London: Methuen, 1961.</bib>
            <notes> In this latter see "Lydgate's Metre and Style," pp. 70–77. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K333">
            <bib>Schlauch, Margaret. "The Art of Chaucer's Prose." Chaucer and Chaucerians:
                Critical Studies in Middle English Literature. Ed. D. S. Brewer. University, Ala.:
                University of Alabama Press, 1966. pp. 140–63.</bib>
            <notes> Section 5, pp. 156–62. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K334">
            <bib>Schlauch, Margaret. "Chaucer's Prose Rhythms." PMLA 65 (1950): 568–89.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K335">
            <bib>Schlüter, A. "über die Sprache und Metrik des mittelenglischen weltlichen und
                geistlichen lyrischen Lieder des Ms. Harley 2253." Archiv 71 (1884): 153–84,
                357–88.</bib>
            <notes> "Metrik," pp. 357–80, catalogues the varieties of stanza, rhyme, alliteration,
                and meter, generally following Schipper. Cf. Schoeck (K337). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K336">
            <bib>Schneider, Adolf. Die mittelenglischen Stabzeile im 15. und 16. Jahrhundert.
                Diss., Bonn, 1902. Rpt. in Bonner Beiträge zur Anglistik 12 (1902): 103–72.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: (in English) in Englische Studien 34 (1904): 99–101. The author construes
                eight late-ME poems, all showing alliteration, four also having end-rhyme and four
                without, as being written in the "seven-bar" line according to the doctrines of
                Trautmann (see K404). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K337">
            <bib>Schoeck, R. J. "Alliterative Assonance in Harley MS. 2253." English Studies 32
                (1951): 68–70.</bib>
            <notes> Notices that a rhyme technique occasionally employed in English poetry (there
                seems to be no established tradition; Wilfred Owen is its chief modern developer,
                though it appears commonly also in Eupheuistic prose) is found in two
                thirteenth-century poems. Schoeck's term is a misnomer: the technique is actually
                "alliterative consonance"; the first and last segments of the rhyming CVC syllable
                are identical, while the vowel changes: e.g., killed, cold. Cf. Schlüter (K335).
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K338">
            <bib>Schöpf, Manfred. "Zur Strophenform einiger Carols." Anglia 87 (1969):
                394–97.</bib>
            <notes> Carols are generally either of the rondel (AB/aA/ab/AB) or virelai (simple:
                AA/bb/ba/AA; complex: ABBA/cdcd/abba/ABBA) form, generally the latter. The secular
                carols actually preceded the religious ones. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K339">
            <bib>Scholle, Wilhelm, ed. Laurence Minots Lieder. Quellen und Forschungen, no. 52.
                Strassburg: Karl Trübner, 1884.</bib>
            <notes> "Metrik," pp. xxix–xlvii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K340">
            <bib>Schrader, Magdalene. Der Spaltreim in der mittelenglischen Literatur. Diss.,
                Heidelberg, 1926. 161 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K341">
            <bib>Schröer, Arnold. "Exkurs über die Metrik." Anglia 5 (1882): 238–64.</bib>
            <notes> The long excursus on the history of English versification (especially in late ME
                and the early Renaissance) which Schröer appends to his study of John Bale's
                (1495–1563) interlude A Comedy Concernynge Thre Laws (dialogue in couplets,
                monologues in ababbcc stanzas) is now entirely forgotten, but undeservedly so. True,
                Schröer does consider the ME alliterative meter to be an eight-beat long line, an
                erroneous conception which forces the reader of this essay to do a good deal of
                mental translation of terms as he goes, but nevertheless the range of Schröer's
                excursus makes it required reading for anyone who would attempt to write the
                long-overdue History of Middle English Meters. He discusses the confusion and
                experimentation resulting from the contact of the old native line with the Latin
                septenary and Romance Alexandrine which produced fourteeners, imperfect tetrameters,
                and other forms, depending on whether a given poet counted syllables or not. Bale
                himself is the perfect exemplar of metrical license and ineptitude, for one can find
                in this interlude virtually any meter one wishes; syllable-counting and
                simple-stress lines are mixed with abandon. And after a long digression on "low
                tone" and "level stress," Schröer discusses the meters of Skelton, Gascoigne, Wyatt,
                Lindsay, and Bale again. See also E1292–93. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K342">
            <bib>Schumacher, Karl. Studien über den Stabreim in der mittelenglischen
                Alliterationsdichtung. Bonner Studien zur englischen Philologie, vol. 11. Bonn,
                1914. 213 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Parts 1 and 2 here (the first 170 pages) analyze (1) the distribution of the
                allit- eration within the line and (2) the quality (perfect or imperfect) of the
                alliter- ating members in 29 ME poems. Part 3 concerns textual criticism. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K343">
            <bib>Scripture, E. W. "Der Versrhythmus in King Horn." Anglia 53 (1929): 382–84.</bib>
            <notes> See E430. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K344">
            <bib>Seeberger, Alfred. Fehlende Auftakt und fehlende Senkung nach der Cäsur in der
                Chaucerschule. Diss., Munich, 1911. Bayreuth: Ellwanger, 1911.</bib>
            <notes> On lines in Chaucer missing the first weak syllable beginning the line or after
                the caesura; cf. Freudenberger (K125) and Evans (K106). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K345">
            <bib>Seronsy, Cecil C. "A Skeltonic Passage in Ben Jonson." Notes &amp; Queries 198
                (1953): 24.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K346">
            <bib>Severs, J. Burke. "Two Irregular Chaucerian Stanzas." MLN 64 (1949): 306–9.</bib>
            <notes> The stanza at 11. 33–40 of An ABC has been regularized by modern editors without
                good justification from the transmission of the MSS and without the recognition that
                the sixth stanza of The Former Age is identical, and intention- ally irregular
                beyond question, in having the rhyme scheme ababbcac, the sev- enth line being an a
                instead of a b. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K347">
            <bib>Shannon, Edgar F. "Chaucer's Use of the Octosyllabic Verse in The Book of the
                Duchess and The House of Fame." JEGP 12 (1913): 277–94.</bib>
            <notes> Chaucer's metrical skill is much firmer in HF than in BD. Trochaic substitu-
                tions in any of the first three feet appear in both poems, but altogether the fre-
                quency is higher in BD; seven-syllable lines, though, appear more often in HF,
                suggesting that Chaucer did not consider the acephalous line a deformity. Hiatus,
                "slurring" (elision), and extra-metrical syllables before the caesura are also less
                frequent in HF, but enjambement there is both heavier and smoother. By contrast,
                Gower's octosyllabics are much more regular metrically and therefore less
                interesting and less expressive. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K348">
            <bib>Shepherd, Geoffrey. "The Nature of Alliterative Poetry in Late Medieval England."
                Proceedings of the British Academy 58 (1970): 57–76</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. as a pamphlet by Oxford University Press, 1971. The one interpretation
                which can embrace and account for all the diverse al- literative poems in the Middle
                English period is that they are all elaborations of a "poetics of memory."
                Alliteration itself was a mnemonic device, a vestige of the oral culture. "These
                poets were making melos out of memory." Especially Richard Rolle. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K349">
            <bib>Short, Douglas D., and Porter Williams, Jr. "'Western Wynde': A Problem in Syntax
                and Interpretation." Papers on Language and Literature 13 (1977): 187– 92.</bib>
            <notes> Recent editors have incorrectly separated lines one and two, judging from the
                musical score of the poem and etymological evidence on "small." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K350">
            <bib>Sieper, Ernst, ed. Lydgate's "Reson and Sensuallyte." Vol. 2. Early English Text
                Society, Extra Series, no. 89. London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co.,
                1903.</bib>
            <notes> "Structure of the Verse," pp. 9–20. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K351">
            <bib>Singh, Catherine. "The Alliterative Ancestry of Dunbar's 'The Tretis of the Tua
                Mariit Wemen and the Wedo.'" Leeds Studies in English n.s. 7 (1973–74): 22–
                54.</bib>
            <notes> Discounting Chaucer's influence on the "Scottish Chaucerians," especially
                Dunbar, Singh argues for a direct link between the older alliterative tradition and
                Dunbar's poem (ca. 1500). See pp. 30–32. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K352">
            <bib>Skeat, Walter W. The Chaucer Canon: with a discussion of the works associated with
                the name of Geoffrey Chaucer. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1900</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. New York: Haskell House, 1965; Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions,
                1974. Dr. Skeat used the invariably regular meter of the Ormulum (to establish the
                syllabic values of final -en, -es, and -e) and various rhyme tests also, in order to
                separate authentic from spurious texts and so establish the Chaucerian canon.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K353">
            <bib>-----. "Chaucer's Virelays." The Athenaeum 8 (1893): 281.</bib>
            <notes> Though Chaucer tells us that he wrote many such, only two are extant (An- elida
                and Arcite, ll. 256–71 and 371–72); a considerable number can be found in Hoccleve,
                however, who clearly learned the form from Chaucer. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K354">
            <bib>-----. "An Essay on the Language and Versification of Chaucer." Preface to The
                Poetical Works of Geoffrey Chaucer. Ed. Richard Morris. 6 vols. London: Bell and
                Daldy, 1866; 2nd rev. ed., 1872. Vol. 1, pp. 121–96</bib>
            <notes> (especially pp. 152– 96 on meter). Sections 1–6, on the pre-Chaucerian verse in
                ME, are written by Tyrwhitt (K414), whose work Skeat endorses and follows in his
                analysis of the meter of the Knight's Tale in sections 7–15. He examines (1) meter
                (pentameter lines, five-stress lines in stanzas, and four-stress couplets), (2)
                variation in syllable-count, (3) elision, and (4) rules for pronunciation. On the
                final -e, see pp. 183, 186–91. Skeat thinks it to be sounded when needed, and at the
                end he approves of the work of Child. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K355">
            <bib>-----. A Rime-Index to Chaucer's "Troilus and Criseyde." Chaucer Society
                Publications, First Series, no. 84. London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co.,
                1892.</bib>
            <notes> Includes Corrections to the Marshall-Porter rhyme-index for the Minor Po- ems
                (K247). See also Cromie (K72). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K356">
            <bib>Skeat, W. W., ed. The Complete Works of Geoffrey Chaucer. 6 vols. Oxford: Oxford
                University Press, 1894.</bib>
            <notes> See vol. 6, Introduction, Glossary, and Indexes, s.v.: "Versification," sections
                98– 117; "Rime," sections 42–51; "Alliteration," section 118; "Metres and Forms of
                Verse," sections 52–62. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K357">
            <bib>-----. The Lay of Havelok the Dane. Early English Text Society, Extra Series, no.
                4. London: Trübner, 1868.</bib>
            <notes> "On the Metre," pp. xliv–liii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K358">
            <bib>-----. "The Vision of William concerning Piers Plowman, together with Vita de
                Dowel, Dobet et Dobest," and "Richard the Redeles" . . . in four Parts--Part IV.
                General Preface, Notes, and Indexes. Early English Text Society, Original Series,
                no. 81. London: N. Trübner, 1885.</bib>
            <notes> Section 30 of the Introduction treats "The Metre of the Poem" in three pages;
                section 31 reprints the comparative table of aberrant alliterations in the A, B, and
                C Texts compiled by Rosenthal (K320)--pp. xlviii–lxiii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K359">
            <bib>Smedick, Lois K. "A Talkyng of þe Loue of God and the Rhythm of Meditation." DA 29
                (1969): 2228A (Bryn Mawr, 1967).</bib>
            <notes> This fourteenth-century devotional work shows the influence of the ecclesias-
                tical cursus on vernacular prose. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K360">
            <bib>Smith, G. Gregory, ed. The Poems of Robert Henryson. Vol. 1. Scottish Text Society
                Publications, no. 64. Edinburgh: William Blackwood, 1914.</bib>
            <notes> See "Prosody," pp. lxxxiii–lxxxviii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K361">
            <bib>Smith, M. Bentinck. "Some Remarks on Chapter III of Ten Brink's Chaucers Sprache
                und Verskunst." MLQ 5 (1902): 13–19.</bib>
            <notes> A general explanation of Ten Brink's position (his absolute insistence on a
                strict decasyllabilism in Chaucer's lines was not well received at first) and a
                gentle apologia for some of his more errant statements, by his English transla- tor.
                Note the remarks on the concresence of the native and foreign verseforms in ME on p.
                15. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K362">
            <bib>Smith, Roland M. "Three Notes on the Knight's Tale." MLN 51 (1936): 318–21.</bib>
            <notes> The third note. The alliterative description of the tournament at 11. 2601–16
                has very close parallels, metrically and verbally, to those in Ipomadon A and
                Partonope of Blois, a fact not hitherto noticed. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K363">
            <bib>Smoot, Maxine B. "The Art of Chaucer's Verse." DAI 35 (1975): 6735A
                (Berkeley).</bib>
            <notes> Sounds rather similar to Baum (K11): Smoot examines metrical tension, end-
                stopping and enjambement, sound-patterning, and onomatopoeia in Chaucer, taking his
                verse to be accentual-syllabic in meter, and she gives a full-scale specimen
                analysis of 11. 1–42 of the General Prologue. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K364">
            <bib>Smyser, H. M. "Chaucer's Use of Gin and Do." Speculum 42 (1967): 68–83.</bib>
            <notes> Both these auxiliaries served primarily metrical functions in Chaucer, propel-
                ling the infinitive into the rhyme-position. Their usage generally increases up
                through Troilus and Criseyde, after which point Chaucer seems to have decided them
                to be too great a convenience, or excresence, for his highest art. Gower scarcely
                uses them at all. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K365">
            <bib>Snouffer, Eugene J. "Verbal Syntax of Cursor Mundi (Cotton MS Vespasian A III)."
                DAI 32 (1972): 6960A (North Carolina).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K366">
            <bib>Southworth, James G. "Chaucer's Final -e in Rhyme." PMLA 62 (1947): 910–35.</bib>
            <notes> See reply by Donaldson (K90) and ensuing exchange. Historical phonology has
                always sounded the final -e suffixed to the rhyme- word at the end of Chaucer's
                lines even though it was of two minds concern- ing whether or not to sound the final
                -e on words within the line, Southworth observes, yet since the -e was entirely
                inorganic (not pronounced) in Chaucer's day and since it is admitted only for
                purposes of metrical exigency, it must be denied in the rhymes since there is no
                question of filling the meter there. N.B.: Southworth here assumes that the
                Chaucerian line was a decasyllable, a position abandoned entirely in his subsequent
                study Verses of Cadence (below; see chapter 4). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K367">
            <bib>-----. Verses of Cadence: An Introduction to the Prosody of Chaucer and His
                Followers. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1954</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Press, 1973. 94 pp. Rev.: in Review of English
                Studies n.s. 6 (1955): 303–4; by Malone in Anglia 78 (1960): 238–40. And see the
                critique in Appendix 1 in Baum (K11). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K368">
            <bib>-----. The Prosody of Chaucer and His Followers: Supplementary Chapters to "Verses
                of Cadence." Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1962</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. Westport, Conn.: Greenwood Press, 1978. 96 pp. Rev.: in Medium Ævum 35
                (1966): 78–82. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K369">
            <bib>-----. "Chaucer's Prosody: A Plea for a Reliable Text." College English 26 (1964):
                173–79</bib>
            <notes>; rev. and rpt. in </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K370">
            <bib>-----. Chaucer's Mind and Art. Ed. A. C. Cowley. New York: Barnes &amp; Noble,
                1970. pp. 86–96.</bib>
            <notes> This last summarizes the position taken in the two monographs; all may be
                conveniently treated together. All of Southworth's theorizing about Chaucer's verse
                rests on the premise of a "fact," recently recovered, that final -e was dis-
                appearing from the speech of Londoners perhaps as early as 1350. From this "fact"
                Southworth argues that therefore we may not pronounce, consider syl- labic, nor
                allow into the meter these suffixes. And since some of the Chaucer MSS have
                significantly fewer final -e's than others, these MSS must of course be the most
                authoritative ones, even though on other grounds they may seem less reliable. Hence,
                Southworth comes to make a direct assault on the well- fortified position of all
                those who believe that Chaucer wrote in meter, specifi- cally an iambic pentameter
                meter. Southworth's counter to this "unsupported and improbable theory": Chaucer
                wrote "not in regular metre, but in rhythms or phrasal units"--meter did not appear
                in English poetry until Wyatt. In short, Southworth wishes to abolish meter, and
                only consider Chaucer's lines as "rhythmical," or else he intends to conflate the
                two under the latter, believing that pronunciation = meter. He views the standard
                Chaucerian line as having four stresses, a natural family characteristic in the
                alliterative genealogy. To de- note the rhythm of the verse he adopts Thomson's
                (E404) musical scansion- notation, since all the rest of the scholars--Tyrwhitt,
                Child, Ellis, Furnivall, Skeat, Schipper, Ten Brink--were wrong, utterly wrong,
                wrong about every- thing--Chaucer's pronunciation, texts, verse-structure,
                intention. All the theo- ries about the sources of his metric being either the
                Italian endecasyllable or the French decasyllable are mere "Myths." Only the
                struggling eighteenth-century editor Urrey, the editor most cavalier with his MSS,
                was right. Urrey, that is, and Southworth. In his second monograph Southworth draws
                upon the researches of Clemoes on MS punctuation and Schlaunch on the cursus in
                order to argue that the virgule was intended by the scribes to divide each line into
                hemistichs, each of which was then scannable as one of the standard types of cursus.
                He seems unaware of the work of Fijn Van Draat (J82) on the cursus in OE; that
                scholar concluded that the cursus as a conscious device in verse and prose was a
                chimera, representing nothing other than the normal phrasal stress-patterns of the
                language. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K371">
            <bib>Spina, Elaine. "Skeltonic Meter in Elynour Rummyng." SP 64 (1967): 665–84.</bib>
            <notes> Based on chapter 3 of her M.A. Thesis, "Skelton's Achievement in The Tunnyng of
                Elynour Rummyng," at Columbia in 1965. Contravening the view that Skeltonic meter is
                more or less homogeneous in its amorphous, loosely structured fluidity, Spina finds
                that a two-stress line is the norm, and metrical expansions of that base are
                thematically expressive. Broader yet closer study of metrical irregularity in
                Skelton is needed. Ten Brink (see vol. 2 pt. 2 of his History) thought Skelton's
                line a three-stress meas- ure. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K372">
            <bib>Standop, Ewald. "Der Rhythmus des Layamon-Verses." Anglia 79 (1962): 267–86.</bib>
            <notes> Standop reconstructs scansions of Layamonic verse according to the systems of
                Heusler, Pope, and Pilch (K295) and gives a critique of each, especially the last.
                His own view is that the Layamonic verse cannot be measured as a classi- cal
                alliterative line: it consists of half-lines of from four to thirteen syllables, in
                four double measures, in 2/4 time. It is a "monopodic verse which realizes the
                traditional dipodic alliterative rhythm only rarely." Prose stress and metrical
                ictus generally coincide, and the anacrusis, like the syllable-count, the distribu-
                tion of stresses, and the filling of bars, is free. Layamon's verse is closer to the
                short rhymed couplet in its freer forms than it is to the alliterative long-line.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K373">
            <bib>Stanley, E. G. "Stanza and Ictus: Chaucer's Emphasis in Troilus and Criseyde."
                Chaucer und seine Zeit. Symposium für Walter F. Schirmer. Ed. Arno Esch. Tübingen:
                Max Niemeyer, 1968. pp. 123–48.</bib>
            <notes> A study of the distribution of narrative movement within the stanza--i.e., (1)
                the various means by which Chaucer establishes continuity both through and between
                his discrete, discontinuous stanzaic metier, focusing on types of stanza- linking
                and last lines, and (2) the characteristic metrical deployments within the
                pentameter line (the second ictus regularly receives an inordinate amount of
                emphasis)--concluding that "in Troilus and Criseyde the last line of the stanza and
                within that line the metrically stressed syllable preceding the caesura are
                positions of special and pivotal emphasis." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K374">
            <bib>-----. "The Use of Bob-Lines in Sir Thopas." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 73
                (1972): 417–26.</bib>
            <notes> Their chief characteristics are "bathos and vapidity," and no other Middle
                English poet shows such technical sophistication and sprezzatura at manufac- turing
                incompetent verses. A valuable four-page table of all the occurrences of bob-lines
                in ME verse, including analysis of rhyme-schemes, is provided. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K375">
            <bib>Starr, David. "Metrical Changes: From Old to Middle English." MP 68 (1970):
                1–9.</bib>
            <notes> A direct comparison of the OE alliterative and ME syllabic (iambic) metrical
                systems. Starr rehearses the commonplaces, noting in this transitional period of the
                language the loss of inflections, the assimilation of foreign vocabulary, and the
                induction of a positional principle (word order) into the syntax, and the effect of
                these three major shifts on meter. But he cannot very well explain his judgment that
                "the change from the Old English verse to the iambic norm [was] quite slight" merely
                by arguing that both systems allow for variation against a norm or that the OE
                long-line seems distinctly iambic at times. All these observations are too familiar
                and too easy; none of them gives us the click of the suddenly-sprung-open lock.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K376">
            <bib>Steffens, Heinrich. "Versbau und Sprache des mittelenglischen Stabreimenden
                Gedichtes 'The Wars of Alexander.'" Bonner Beiträge zur Anglistik 9 (1901): 1–
                104.</bib>
            <notes> Applies Trautmann's "seven-bar" theory (see K404) to the three Alexander-
                fragments. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K377">
            <bib>Sternberg, R. "über eine versificirte mittelenglische Chronik." Englische Studien
                18 (1893): 1–23.</bib>
            <notes> On the "Short English Metrical Chronicle," the meter of which is treated on pp.
                17–23. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K378">
            <bib>Stevens, Martin. "The Royal Stanza in Early English Literature." PMLA 94 (1979):
                62–76.</bib>
            <notes> Challenges the received explanation of the origin and name of the "rhyme royal"
                stanza (from its use by King James I of Scotland for the Kingis Quair) by showing
                from ample evidence of English civic pageantry that the stanza was used at least as
                early as the fourteenth century for poetic contests in the Puy (guild) and was
                firmly associated with addresses to royalty. Chaucer's use of the form in Troilus
                and the Canterbury Tales is examined. But more importantly, Stevens shows that
                Chaucer used the term "prose" to refer not only to unlined sentences (the modern
                sense) but also to the rhyme royal stanza (the medieval sense of prosa), while
                reserving rym for either couplets or the tail-rhyme Sir Thopas stanza. Chaucer
                certainly did not invent the form; he simply established its register--the high
                style--for nearly three centuries, and he was "the first poet in the language to
                endow the long poem with a sophisticated and uni- form stanzaic unit." Stevens seems
                to be completely unaware of the earlier monograph by Maynard (K250), however; had he
                seen that study, part of this essay would have been unnecessary. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K379">
            <bib>Stewart, George R. "The Meter of Piers Plowman." PMLA 42 (1927): 113–28.</bib>
            <notes> The dispute between the four-stress (to the long line) and the seven-stress
                theories of Langland's verse can be reconciled if we see the line as written in four
                dipodic feet. The four-stress theorists (zweihebungstheorie) are right to em-
                phasize primary stresses, and the seven-stressers (vierhebungstheorie) are right to
                note the existence of secondary stresses, but even the latter fail to recognize the
                alternating, dipodic patterning of the stresses. Stewart's view is very close to if
                not derived from Leonard's (K215). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K380">
            <bib>Stobie, M. M. R. "The Influence of Morphology on Middle English Alliterative
                Poetry." JEGP 39 (1940): 319–36.</bib>
            <notes> A crucial essay on the crucial question in the history of English verse, the
                question of what happened, precisely, to the OE verseform in the ME period. Stobie
                takes the intrepid position that the radical changes in English verse which occurred
                in the ME period were not, essentially, the result of the im- ported Romance forms
                but would have occurred in any event due to natural changes in the phonology of the
                language. These changes were three: (1) the gradation of vowels, reduction of
                grammatical cases, and subsequent loss of in- flectional endings increased the
                number of monosyllables and altered such forms as OE Type A, /X/X, to /X/, //, XX//,
                and finally X/X/ --that is, the generally trochaic OE rhythm was changed, as a
                result of the lost inflec- tions, to a prevalently iambic one; (2) the lengthening
                of OE vowels in open stressed syllables blocked resolution of double short
                syllables, adding extra syl- lables everywhere, and causing the collapse of the
                relatively distinct OE Types into one general, amorphous Type; and (3) the
                shortening of the second sylla- ble in compounds had a similar blurring effect,
                adding weak syllables until "the temporal values in alliterative poetry disappeared
                and the native verse became entirely accentual." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K381">
            <bib>Stock, Noel. "Some Notes on Old Scots and Melodic Line in Verse." Shenandoah 6
                (1955): 24–30.</bib>
            <notes> "The superiority of the Scots is most evident in the quality of their rhythms
                and melodic line; the time-value of each word is governed by the length and pitch of
                the syllable before and the syllable after. Each word keeps its own resonance and
                the accents are those of an actual spoken language; there is a tension as accent is
                balanced against quantity." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K382">
            <bib>Stockwell, Brenda S. "Techniques of Aural Poetry in the Middle English Lyric." DAI
                33 (1973): 6886A (Louisiana State University).</bib>
            <notes> Alliteration, rhyme, and (especially) formulaic diction serve structural and
                mnemonic functions for the oral poet, reducing the demands of immediate composition
                and also improving comprehension in his audience. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K383">
            <bib>Stone, Elwood W. "Chaucer's Prosody: Examination Based on a New Method." Diss.,
                University of Denver, 1960.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K384">
            <bib>Storms, G. "A Note on Chaucer's Pronunciation of French u." English Studies 41
                (1960): 305–8.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K385">
            <bib>Strandberg, Otto. The Rime-Vowels of "Cursor Mundi." Diss., Uppsala, 1919.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in Englische Studien 59 (1925): 99. A pronunciation study. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K386">
            <bib>Stüdl, Johann. Das Versmass in Langlands "The Vision of William concerning Piers
                the Plowman." Diss., Vienna, 1936.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K387">
            <bib>Suchier, Hermann. "Zur Versbildung der Anglo-Normannen." Anglia 2 (1879):
                215–24.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K388">
            <bib>Sudo, Jun. "Some Specific Rime-Units in Chaucer." Studies in English Literature
                (Tokyo) 45 (1969): 221–36.</bib>
            <notes> Traces the sources and distribution of some of Chaucer's formulaic rhymes (used
                repeatedly) as well as proper names used for rhymes. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K389">
            <bib>Swallow, Alan. "The Pentameter Line in Skelton and Wyatt." MP 48 (1950):
                1–11.</bib>
            <notes> Analysis of the early verse of the two poets allows Swallow to conclude that
                Skelton was using the pentameter form before Wyatt, that both men under- stood the
                five-foot form very early in their careers, and that their verse is much more
                regular metrically than has been supposed. For support of these conclu- sions,
                Swallow argues that the mute -e is pronounced and muted variously (as in Chaucer),
                that Romance words are to have English pronunciations, that Wyatt aimed at faithful
                matter over meter in his translations, and (finally) that the metrical tradition
                which these poets inherited was a very loose one. Many of their lines more closely
                resemble the fifteenth-century bipartite line de- scribed by C. S. Lewis (K216) than
                the pentameter line. So, their metrical context was weak, and their adherence to the
                pentameter must be seen as an effort at codification. See the critique by Evans
                (E987). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K390">
            <bib>-----. "Principles of Poetic Composition from Skelton to Sidney." Diss., Louisiana
                State University, 1941.</bib>
            <notes> Pp. 82–111 in chapter 2 treats Skelton's versification: Swallow argues that
                Skelton exercised conscious control over his meters, writing good pentameters and
                four-stress lines when he chose, but wrenching accent when that served expressive
                ends, and otherwise preserving Romance pronunciation in rhym- ing. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K391">
            <bib>Swieczkowski, Walerian. Word-Order Patterning in Middle English: A Quantitative
                Study Based on "Piers Plowman" and Middle English Sermons. Janua Linguarum, Series
                Minor, no. 19. The Hague: Mouton, 1962. 114 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K392">
            <bib>Tamson, George J. Word-Stress in English: A Short Treatise on the Accentuation of
                Words in Middle English as Compared with the Stress in Old and Modern English.
                Studien zur englischen Philologie, vol. 3. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1898.</bib>
            <notes> Treats words of Germanic and of Romance origin separately, categorizing by part
                of speech, determining the stressing by the metrical treatment of the word in four
                texts: the Troy-Book, Piers Plowman, Morte Arthure, and Richard the Re- deles.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K393">
            <bib>Tatlock, J. S. P. "Chaucer's dremes-lemes. MLN 20 (1905): 126.</bib>
            <notes> Chaucer and the other Middle English poets did indeed rhyme the closed with the
                open e. See K273. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K394">
            <bib>-----. "Epic Formulas, Especially in Layamon." PMLA 38 (1923): 494–529.</bib>
            <notes> The first half a list, the latter a discussion. Some mention of alliteration and
                rhyme. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K395">
            <bib>-----. "Layamon's Poetic Style and Its Relations." The Manly Anniversary Studies
                in Language and Literature. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1923</bib>
            <notes>. pp. 3–11. Versification is discussed on pp. 8–10. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K396">
            <bib>Teglbjaerg, Leif. "Oral-Formulaic Theories and Their Application to Middle English
                Poetry." Language and Literature 1 (1972): 69–91.</bib>
            <notes> Problems of elaborating a full theory of formula and theme for the Middle
                English alliterative half-line. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K397">
            <bib>Teichmann, Eduard. "Zur Stabreimzeile im William Langlands Buch von Peter dem
                Pflüger." Anglia 13 (1891): 140–74.</bib>
            <notes> An attempt to show that as a rule the lines have feminine endings. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K398">
            <bib>Thomas, Julius. Die alliterierende Langzeile des Gawayn-Dichters. Diss., Coburg,
                1908.</bib>
            <notes> 70 pp. Applying the Luick-Sievers analysis, Thomas finds that the verse of
                Purity, Pa- tience, and Sir Gawain can be matched to the two-beat Five Types
                "without difficulty," though he believes that its meter is generally
                anapestic-dactylic, a view which requires considerable manipulation of the sounded
                inflectional -e to be viable at all. The rhythm of the long lines has influenced
                that of the short lines, but alliteration does not always correlate with primary
                stresses; the short lines are in an alternating meter with end-rhyme, the
                alliteration being merely ornamental. Discussed in Borroff (K32), chapter 7 and
                Notes. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K399">
            <bib>Thormann, Janet. "The Formulaic Element of Language, Structure, and Theme in The
                Parlement of the Thre Ages, an Alliterative Poem of the Fourteenth Century." Diss.,
                University of California at Berkeley, 1972.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K400">
            <bib>Tihany, Leslie C. "The Avowing of King Arthur: A Morphological and Phonological
                Study of the Works in Rime and of Certain Nonriming Works." Diss., Northwestern
                University, 1936.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K401">
            <bib>Tillman, Nathaniel P. "Lydgate's Rimes as Evidence of His Pronunciation." Diss.,
                University of Wisconsin, 1941. </bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K402">
            <bib>Tolkien, J. R. R., and E. V. Gordon, ed. Sir Gawain and the Green Knight. Oxford,
                1925; 2nd ed. edited by Norman Davis. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1967.</bib>
            <notes> "Metre," pp. 147–52. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K403">
            <bib>Tonndorf, M. "Rauf Coilyear": Eine mittelschottisches Gedicht. Litterarische,
                sprachliche und metrische Untersuchungen. Diss., Halle, 1893.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K404">
            <bib>Trautmann, Mortiz. "Der Dichter Huchown und seine Werke, II: sprachliche und
                metrische Untersuchungen." Anglia 1 (1878): 115–34. Supplementary notes on p.
                188.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K405">
            <bib>-----. "über die Vers Layanon's." Anglia 2 (1879): 153–73.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K406">
            <bib>-----. "Zur Kenntnis und Geschichte der mittelenglische Stabzeile." Anglia 18
                (1896): 83–100.</bib>
            <notes> Trautmann published articles on Middle English versification over nearly two
                decades, and after he became editor of the Bonner Beiträge zur Anglistik, the ar-
                ticles that were published in that organ by his students and others all generally
                followed his philosophy, so that his influence extends well over four decades.
                During that time Trautmann never changed his opinion of the nature of Laya- mon's
                meter: he believed the half-line to be comprised of four stresses (as Lachman and
                the other proponents of the vierhebungstheorie had held for Old English verse), with
                a weakening of the off-verse in the ME period, so that the ME long-line had seven
                stresses instead of the eight in OE. Trautmann held this view for ME from the very
                beginning, even when he suffered a temporary lapse and championed the two-stress
                theory for OE briefly. Trautmann's opinions changed in other respects, however, and
                it is important to notice that he changed his position radically after 1895 not on
                the nature but on the source of Layamon's meter. In his first studies (K405)
                Trautmann had held that the verseform of the Brut was derived from Otfrid and
                through him ultimately from Medieval Latin, though later (J317, J318) he thought
                that it was derived originally from Otfrid and not from any earlier Latin source.
                After 1895, how- ever (J319), he abandoned the Otfridian thesis and argued that
                Layamon's ver- seform was derived directly from Old English. Several of Trautmann's
                students (i.e. Fischer, Mennicken, Kramer, Pilch, Schneider, and Steffens, q.v.) ex-
                tended his version of the vierhabungstheorie to most of Middle English verse. But
                that theory has not been borne out by later scholarship and their work has no
                independent authority. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K407">
            <bib>Triggs, Oscar L., ed. The Assembly of Gods: or, The Accord of Reason and
                Sensuality in the Fear of Death. By John Lydgate. Early English Text Society, Extra
                Series, no. 69. London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co., 1896.</bib>
            <notes> "The Metre," pp. xiv–xx, "The Rime," (with Rhyme-Index), pp. xxi–xxx, "The Rime
                and the Final -e," pp. xxxi–xxxiv. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K408">
            <bib>Trounce, A. McI. "The English Tail-Rhyme Romances." Medium Ævum 1 (1932)</bib>
            <notes>: 87–108, 168–82; 2 (1933): 34–57, 189–98; 3 (1934): 30–50. At 92 pages, a
                virtual monograph, and in fact this is still the fullest treatment of this subject.
                Intent to demonstrate how seriously the third major line of Mid- dle English poetry
                has been underrated heretofore, Trounce examines con- ventional elements, formulae,
                the functions of the tail-line, and stanza- construction (vol. 1), meter and
                alliteration (vol. 2, pp. 34–40), and prove- nience (East Anglia), turning
                thereafter (vols. 2 and 3) to a separate examina- tion of each of the 23 poems. See
                also Strong (L140). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K409">
            <bib>Trounce, A. McI., ed. "Athelston": A Middle English Romance. Early English Text
                Society, Original Series, no. 224. London: Oxford University Press, 1951</bib>
            <notes> (for 1946). Meter, stanza, rhyme, and alliteration: pp. 56–60 in the
                Introduction. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K410">
            <bib>Trusler, Margaret. "The Language of the Wakefield Playwright." SP 33 (1936): 15–
                39.</bib>
            <notes> Rime-analysis. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K411">
            <bib>Turville-Petre, Joan. "The Metre of Sir Gawain and the Green Knight." English
                Studies 57 (1976): 310–28.</bib>
            <notes> A much more rigorous, detailed, and exhaustive analysis than those of Schiller
                (K329) and Borroff (K32) and a worthy successor to Luick's study (K224). In the
                verse of Sir Gawain the alliterative structure has become slightly discon- tinuous
                with the accentual one, the staves not always matching the primary stresses, and it
                is useless to search for concealed correct or obvious degenerate OE verse-types. The
                syntactic unit of the verse is the whole line not the hemistich, and its
                characteristic pattern is a longer a-verse in rising rhythm followed by a shorter
                b-verse in falling. The prevalent rhythm is triple time, of three general types,
                variegated by a less frequent, shorter, duple-time rhythm, often in the b-verse,
                also of three types. Both are "syntactically conditioned . . . by major constituents
                in spaced construction." Alliteration is regular in the short rhythms but frequently
                irregular in the standard triple-rhythm verses, with one major stress not alliterant
                being relatively common. Alliteration is still syntacti- cally functional, but not
                metrically. Altogether, though the meter is much less tight than in OE, the syntax,
                alliteration, and accentuation systems are all still operating conjunctively.
            </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K412">
            <bib>Turville-Petre, Thorlac. The Alliterative Revival. Cambridge: D. S. Brewer, and
                Totowa, New Jersey: Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 1977. 152 pp.</bib>
            <notes> To be compared with Oakden (K274): this is not a new theory but a codifica- tion
                and restatement of the older theory. The theory of continuity as set forth by
                Oakden, Turville-Petre finds "hard to accept"; he argues the alternative hy-
                pothesis that "the tradition of 'classical' Old English poetry died out soon after
                the Conquest, and that for over one hundred years it was succeeded by a looser form
                of alliterative verse, which in turn died out, though not before it had sown the
                seeds of the Alliterative Revival." That is, early MEAV such as Layamon's Brut "are
                not milestones in a developing tradition, but examples of individual modifications
                to a fluid and imprecise verseform. . . . At all events the poetry of the
                Alliterative Revival is not a direct descendant of Layamonic verse." Chapter 3
                treats the meter of the Alliterative Revival poems, Turville- Petre distinguishing
                three phases: the earliest, where the meter is over-loose, followed by a second,
                where the meter overreacts to the earlier form by be- coming over-tight, and a final
                stage of synthesis, where the meter has made adjustments in both directions to
                become a supple and vitalic medium. Even though this meter seems best suited for
                narration and description, "the most remarkable quality of the alliterative line is
                its capacity to accommodate a vast range of expression." </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K413">
            <bib>-----. "'Summer Sunday,' 'De Tribus Regibus Mortuis,' and "The Awntyrs off
                Arthure': Three Poems in the Thirteen-Line Stanza." Review of English Studies n.s.
                25 (1974): 1–14.</bib>
            <notes> A consideration of the prospect that there was a coherent Middle English tra-
                dition of alliterative "bob-and-wheel" stanzas. The three poems are compared and a
                list of known poems in this stanza-form is appended. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K414">
            <bib>Tyrwhitt, Thomas. An Essay on the Language and Versification of Chaucer. Vol. 4 of
                The Canterbury Tales of Chaucer. To which are added, An Essay upon his Language and
                Versification; an Introductory Discourse; and Notes. 4 vols. London: Printed by T.
                Payne, 1775</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. 1875, 1877 ; rpt. Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1973. See
                Part 3 of the Essay, pp. 46–111. The first modern assessment of Chaucer's metric.
                Many of Tyrwhitt's judg- ments have been subsequently reversed or amended, yet for
                its time his analysis is relatively thorough and close. He believed that rhyme and
                meter did not exist in English poetry before the Conquest, Anglo-Saxon verse having
                only "pomp of diction," rhyme having come into ME through the offices of the Normans
                from Medieval Latin. He seems to have been the first to detect the syllabic
                regularity of the Ormulum, and indeed syllabism is a very strong point with
                Tyrwhitt. He takes as his ground assumption the belief that a melodic smoothness is
                the unquestionable perfection of metrical style, and hence aim of all the best
                poets, and since Chaucer was a great poet, all deviations and ir- regularities must
                be the work of shoddy scribes and imperfect MSS, and the editor is therefore more
                than justified in removing these blemishes in every instance. This is to say that
                Tyrwhitt was a wholesaler in emendations. The irregularities of meter he lists as:
                supernumerary syllables (few), deficiency of syllables (frequent), and displacement
                of stress. Deficiency he considers espe- cially grievous (no "heroic verse which
                wants a syllable of its complement can be musical, or even tolerable") and to be
                corrected by sounding of final -e's (Tyrwhitt in fact sounded them everywhere, both
                within the line and on the rhyme-words) and by trisyllabic substitutions ("an
                English verse, though chiefly composed of feet of two syllables, is capable of
                receiving feet of three syllables in every part of it, provided only one of the
                three syllables be ac- cented"). These strategies Tyrwhitt employed to regularize
                the count of sylla- bles and the alternation of stresses, thereby assuring the
                "correctness and har- mony" of the verse. He was in fact a strict syllabist even
                though he believed that the Chaucerian line contained eleven syllables rather than
                ten, being de- rived from the Italian endecasyllabo. Chaucer's meters he lists as
                the "long Iam- bic Metre" [fourteener], the Alexandrine, the Octosyllabic, the
                Stanza of Six [tail-rhyme], and the Heroic. The discussion concludes with an
                analysis of ll.1– 18 of the General Prologue. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K415">
            <bib>Ulrich, Karl. über die alliterierenden Reimformeln im Mittelenglischen, besonders
                in Layamons "Brut." Diss., Vienna, 1891.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K416">
            <bib>Vantuono, William. "The Question of Quatrains in Patience." Manuscripta 16 (1972):
                24–29.</bib>
            <notes> Support for the negative side of the question, in opposition to Kaluza (K182).
                The marginal marks which appear every fourth line in the MS are scribal, not
                authorial, and we have no way of knowing their purpose. A quatrain division does not
                match up with the logical and narrative structures of the poem. Cf. Day (K84) and
                Hulbert (K165). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K417">
            <bib>Varnhagen, Hermann. "Ein mittelenglische Gedicht seltener Form." Anglia (Anzeiger)
                7 (1884): 85–86.</bib>
            <notes> A rare form aabbabba appears in the fourth stanza of a seven-stanza poem, no-
                ticed by Schipper, having an otherwise-regular rhyme scheme ababbaba. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K418">
            <bib>Vaughan, M. F. "Consecutive Alliteration, Strophic Patterns, and the Composition
                of the Alliterative Morte Arthure." MP 77 (1979–80): 1–9.</bib>
            <notes> Extending the hypothesis of Kaluza (K182) and Duggan (K93) supporting quatrain
                stanzas and supra-stanzaic strophes in ME poetry, Vaughan finds that the
                alliterative MA is divided into quatrain-like "four-line thought groups" bound in a
                "structural" (not ornamental) pattern of alliteration that is easily demonstrable
                though also extremely diffused: over 4,346 lines, the number of patterns per number
                of lines of extension was 948 twos, 95 threes, 189 fours, 12 fives, 27 sixes, 3
                sevens, 4 eights, 1 nine, 3 tens, and 1 eleven. Given such evident range, he can
                only conclude that the MA is "not a stanzaic poem, at least not by any common
                definition of that term, but neither is it a poem whose sole formal feature is the
                alliterative long line. It exists as a tertium quid." There is also some very rough
                and very ambiguous evidence for strophes. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K419">
            <bib>"Verse-Forms Common to the Middle and Modern English Periods." Schipper (A11),
                Book I, Part 2, Division 2, pp. 183–218.</bib>
            <notes> An inventory of line-types, especially the couplet. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K420">
            <bib>Vising, Johan. "Anglo-Norman Versification." Anglo-Norman Language and Literature.
                London: Oxford University Press, 1923. pp. 79–88.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K421">
            <bib>-----. Sur la Versification Anglo-Normande. Uppsala: Almqvist &amp; Wiksells,
                1884. 91 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev.: in Romania 15 (1886): 144–48. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K422">
            <bib>Vockrodt, Gustav. Reimtechnik bei Chaucer als Mittel zur chronologischen
                Bestimmung seiner im Reimpaar geschriebenen Werke. Diss., Halle, 1914. 75 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Analysis of rhyme-forms in order to establish the chronology of those Tales in
                couplets. The forms: the suffixes -ing, -ly, and -nesse, varieties of simple rhyming
                words, and "split rhyme"--one word rhymed with two, etc. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K423">
            <bib>Vollmer, Erich. "Sprache und Reime des Londoners Hoccleve." Anglia 21 (1899):
                201–21.</bib>
            <notes> Hoccleve's rhymes follow Chaucer's precedent almost entirely. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K424">
            <bib>Von Ende, Frederick A. C. "The Prosody of the Pearl-Poet: A Technical Analysis of
                the Poems in MS Cotton Nero A.x." DAI 33 (1973): 3605A (Texas Christian).</bib>
            <notes> Examines rhythm and meter, rhyme and alliteration, and stanza patterns in Pearl,
                Purity, Patience, and Sir Gawain, concluding that some support of the sin-
                gle-authorship theory is wanted even though Sir Gawain may show stratifica- tion and
                Purity may be a composite. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K425">
            <bib>Wager, W. J. "A Study of Chaucer's Development in his Use of the Decasyllabic
                Line." Diss., New York University, 1919.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K426">
            <bib>Waldron, Ronald A. "Oral-Formulaic Technique and Middle English Alliterative
                Poetry." Speculum 32 (1957): 792–804.</bib>
            <notes> Waldron departs from traditional oral-formulaic theory by suggesting that even
                literate poets working solidly within a written tradition were capable of using
                formulae, that ME alliterative verse shows clearly the presence of such formu- lae,
                and that this fact establishes the continuity of verseform in Old and Middle
                English. Criticized by Finlayson (K115). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K427">
            <bib>Walsh, Edward M. "The Meaning of Rhythmic Changes in Fourteenth-Century English
                Poetry." DAI 35 (1975): 7883A (Southern Illinois).</bib>
            <notes> Within a metrical theory which distinguishes meter from rhythm and, within
                rhythm, simple rhythms (congruence of metrical paradigm with its realizations) from
                complex (disjunction or contrast), Walsh concludes, from analysis of The Parlement
                of the Three Ages, The Siege of Jerusalem, and Sir Gawain, that four- teenth-century
                verse evolved from (simple) dance-rhythms to (complex) speech- rhythms. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K428">
            <bib>Watson, Melvin R. "Wyatt, Chaucer, and Terza Rima." MLN 68 (1953): 124–25.</bib>
            <notes> Chaucer rather than Wyatt first used the form in English (in "The Complaint to
                his Lady"). </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K429">
            <bib>Weese, Walter E. "Word-Order as a Factor of Style in Chaucer's Poetry." DAI 31
                (1971): 4138A (Yale, 1950).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K430">
            <bib>West, Henry S. The Versification of "King Horn." Diss., Johns Hopkins, 1899.
                Baltimore: J. H. Furst Co., 1907. 92 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Wholly in agreement with Schipper, West attacks vigorously Luick's theory that
                the verseform of the Brut and King Horn is written in a four-beat half-line modeled
                on Otfrid in employing rhyme throughout instead of structural allit- eration. That
                is, Luick believed that these rhymed-alliterative poems repre- sented a tradition in
                ME verse wholly unrelated to--underived from--the na- tive tradition of the
                alliterative long-line (two stresses to the half-line) in Old English. Wells agrees
                with Schipper that the Horn verse is within the native "free-rhythm" tradition, even
                though the alliteration has been exchanged for full rhyme; it is precisely this
                interpretation which allows us to trace a "natural and unbroken development" from
                the native OE verse through the assimila- tion of the Romance prosody in ME into
                Modern English. Otherwise we would be forced to believe in the "fundamental fact of
                a double prosody" in English verse. Where Luick found three discrete prosodies, West
                and Schipper find one. But West denies, equally as vigorously, Schipper's scansion
                of the Horn verse (half-line) as having three stresses; West's analysis takes an
                unwav- ering stand on Sievers and finds only two. Indeed, Schipper is chastized
                smartly for "compromising" with the Otfridians. Chapters 1, 2, and 6 and the Conclu-
                sion are required reading that is particularly absorbing, but pp. 18–20 are espe-
                cially good. Any history of English versification must squarely confront and clearly
                explain how the native verseform accommodated itself--if indeed it did--to the
                immigrant principle (rhyme) which quickly took control. The al- ternative
                interpretations are atrophy and assimilation. And even though West's claim that
                alliterative verse could lose alliteration and still survive seems in- credible,
                assimilation is clearly the preferable view. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K451">
            <bib>Wilda, Oskar. über die örtliche Verbreitung der zwölfzeiligen Schweifreimstrophe
                in England. Diss., Breslau, 1887. 66 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Mainly lists of rhymes as evidence for establishing provenience. The tail-rhyme
                poems are treated in three classes, having rhyme schemes aab aab ccb ddb, aab aab
                ccb ccb, and aab ccb ddb eeb. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K432">
            <bib>Wissmann, Theodor. "Zur mittelenglischen Wörtbetonung." Anglia 5 (1882):
                466–500.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K433">
            <bib>Wissman, Theodor, ed. "King Horn": Untersuchungen zur mittelenglischen Sprache-
                und Litteraturgeschichte. Quellen und Forschungen, no. 16. Strassburg: Karl J.
                Trübner, 1876.</bib>
            <notes> "Metrik," pp. 43–63, treats stressing, meter, alliteration, and rhyme. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K434">
            <bib>-----. Das Lied von King Horn. Quellen und Forschungen, no. 45. Strassburg: Karl
                Trübner, 1881.</bib>
            <notes> "Metrik," pp. xiii–xxii. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K435">
            <bib>Wittenbrinck, G. Zur kritik und Rhythmik des altenglischen Lais von Havelok dem
                Dänen. Burgsteinfurt, 1891.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K436">
            <bib>Wolff, Edward J. "Chaucer's Normalized Diction: A Comparison of Recurring Phrases
                in Chaucer and Beowulf to Determine the Validity of the Magoun Thesis." DA 27
                (1967): 3022A (Michigan State).</bib>
            <notes> Tabulation of the lexical repetitions (word echoes) in a sample of Chaucer's
                verse reveals (surprisingly) that its frequency is very nearly the same as that in
                the Beowulf. If, then, the OE epic is said, on precisely these grounds, to have been
                orally composed, we must say that The Canterbury Tales were as well. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K437">
            <bib>Wrenn, C. L. "On the Continuity of English Poetry." Anglia 76 (1958): 41–59</bib>
            <notes> ; rpt. as chapter 2 of his A Study of Old English Literature (J343), pp. 17–34.
                Pp. 50–52 discuss the continuous tradition of the alliterative line. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K438">
            <bib>Zimmermann, Rüdiger. "Verbal Syntax and Style in Sir Gawain and the Green Knight."
                English Studies 54 (1973): 533–43.</bib>
            <notes> On the stylistic functions of shifts in verb tense, voice, and mood. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="K439">
            <bib>Zomberg, Paul G. "The Prosody of English Learned-Verse in the Fifteenth- Century."
                Diss., University of Toronto, 1974.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
    </chapter>
</bibliography>
