<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="APPENDIX 1: GENERAL AND COMPARATIVE STUDIES">

        <item id="L1">
            <bib> Abernathy, Robert. "Mathematical Linguistics and Poetics." Poetics I (A16), pp.
                563-70.</bib>
            <notes>A simplified introduction to information theory as applied to verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L2">
            <bib> -----. "Rhymes, Non-Rhymes, and Antirhyme." To Honor Roman Jakobson: Essays on the
                Occasion of his Seventieth Birthday. 3 vols. The Hague: Mouton, 1967. Vol. 1, pp.
                1–14.</bib>
            <notes> The usual definition of "unrhymed" verse is superficial: in some forms, rhymes
                at certain positions may simply be unconstrained (optional)--"nonrhyme"--and in
                other forms they may actually be prohibited--"antirhyme." Rhyme con- straints thus
                may be either positive or negative and of many degrees of fre- quency and
                complexity, as we see in the fainter echoes of rhyme in Milton and in Browning's
                blank-verse dramatic monologues. Our terminology for rhyme is inexact and
                inconsistent, as can be seen in the case of "identical rhyme," which is neither
                reflexive (a rhyme) nor nonreflexive but actually ir- reflexive; on this account the
                sestina must be considered "a special form of anti-rhymed verse." Examples from
                English and Russian. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L3">
            <bib> Alonso, Dámaso. "Versos plurimembros y poemas correlativos." Revista de la
                Biblioteca, Archivo y Museo del Ayuntamiento de Madrid 13 (1944): 89–191.</bib>
            <notes> Surveys Spanish, French, Italian, German, Latin, Sanskrit, and Arabic. Cf. L45.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L4">
            <bib> "The Antiquity of Rhyme." The Foreign Review and Continental Miscellany 3 (1829):
                57–73.</bib>
            <notes> Maps out a genealogy, from the aboriginal Hebrew to modern times. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L5">
            <bib> Bailey, Richard W. "Statistics and the Sounds of Poetry." Poetics 1 (1971):
                16–-37.</bib>
            <notes> Interested in the application of information theory to poetics, Bailey reviews
                the work of a number of theorists on Czech versification then analyzes two English
                poems, discovering that a statistical inventory of phoneme distribution is not a
                helpful or heuristic procedure for poetry. Testing for the distribution of gaps
                between repetitions of sounds is similarly unhelpful. In fact, relatively stable
                cross-linguistic evidence indicates that "a linguistic universal constrains human
                speech in the deployment of phonemes." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L6">
            <bib> Bailweg, Joachim, and A. Schramm. "Sprachliche Abweichung und ihre Role bei der
                Konstituation poetischer Texte." Sprachsystem und Sprachgebrauch. Ed. Ulrich Engel
                and Paul Grebe. Part I. Dusseldorf: Schwann, 1974. pp. 9–30.</bib>
            <notes> On the problem of syntactic deviation. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L7">
            <bib> Bann, Stephen, ed. "Introduction." Concrete Poetry: An International Anthology.
                London: London Magazine Editions, 1967.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L8">
            <bib> Bartlett, William. The Characteristics of Primitive Poetry. Oxford: Blackwell,
                1884.</bib>
            <notes> Section 3, esp. pp. 16–19, touches on meter, assonance, and sonal mimesis in
                Teutonic, Scandinavian, Greek, and Hebrew poetry. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L9">
            <bib> Beare, William. Latin Verse and European Song: A Study in Accent and Rhyme.
                London: Methuen, 1957; rpt New York: Humanities, 1979. 296 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Traces the origin and development of accentual rhythm and rhyme from the
                earliest quantitative verses in Latin (the Saturnian) down through Provencal,
                Medieval Latin, Old Irish, and Old English, with long side-glancing chapters on the
                older systems of versification in Sanskrit, Greek, Hebrew, and Persian, as well as
                on the theoretical concepts of verse, accent, ictus, etc. A very broad study.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L10">
            <bib> Becher, Johannes. "Philosophie des Sonetts oder kleine Sonettlehre: Ein Versuch."
                Sinn und Form 8 (1956): 329-51.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L11">
            <bib> Beck, Miroslav. "Einige Bemerkungen zur vergleichenden Metrik." In Teorie Verše I
                (L89), pp. 81-85.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L12">
            <bib> Bermann, Sandra L. The Sonnet Over Time. 1990?. Based on her diss., "Perspectives
                on the Sonnet: Poetic Structure in Petrarch, Shakespeare, Baudelaire." DAI 39
                (1978): 2233A (Columbia).</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L13">
            <bib> Blackie, John Stuart. "On the Principle of Onomatopoeia in Language." In his Horae
                Hellenicae. London: Macmillan, 1874. pp. 217-34.</bib>
            <notes>Defends the broad origins and ordering presence of a general principle of
                "phonetic imitation" in the Indo-European languages, arguing that a great part of
                human experience, and hence human language and word-formations, is not "notional" or
                conceptual at all but rather sensory, imitative, and frequently aural. Good
                examples. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L14">
            <bib> Bladon, R. A. W. "Approaching Onomatopoeia." Archivum Linguisticum n.s. 8 (1977):
                158-66.</bib>
            <notes>Along the continuum of expressive sounds produced by humans, from least arbitrary
                to most, Onomatopoeia is second to the least, exceeded only by Mimicry, a category
                from which true onomatopoeia is very sharply distin- guished by Bladon in his
                typology. Analysis of onomatopes in English, Ger- man, French, Turkish, and Japanese
                shows, inter alia, that languages vary con- siderably in the size of their
                repetoires for this phenomenon, that the terms are nearly always monosyllables, and
                that syllabic reduplication is very common. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L15">
            <bib> Boultenhouse, Charles. "Poems in the Shape of Things." Art News Annual 28 (1959):
                64–83, 178.</bib>
            <notes> A short synopsis-essay and many examples, from Rhodes in 300 B.C. to the
                present. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L16">
            <bib> Brackbill, Yvonne, and K. B. Little. "Factors Determining the Guessing of the
                Meanings of Foreign Words." Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology 54 (1957):
                312-18.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L17">
            <bib> Braune, W. "Reim und Vers." Sitzungsberichte der Heidelberger Akademie der
                Wissenschaften, philologisch-historischen Klasse. Heidelberg, 1916.</bib>
            <notes> Examines the origin, history, and senses of the two terms. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L18">
            <bib> Brewster, Paul G. "Some Notes on Verse-capping, Western and Oriental." Revue de
                littérature comparée 35 (1961): 102-6.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L18">
            <bib> a Bühler, K. "La onomatopeya y la función representativa del lenguaje." In
                Psicologia del lenguaje. Buenoe Aires, 1952.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L19">
            <bib> Burling, Robbins. "The Metrics of Children's Verses: A Cross Linguistic Study."
                American Anthropologist 68 (1966): 1418-41.</bib>
            <notes>Finds common characteristics of form (sixteen "beats" in four "lines," with the
                fourth beat in any line replaceable by a "rest"--i.e., Long Measure, Common Measure,
                Half Measure, etc.) in children's verses of English, Chinese, Beng- kulu, and other
                African and Asian languages. A traditional approach, toward a "science of
                comparative metrics," without any apparent recognition of ballad meters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L20">
            <bib> Byars, William V. Homeric Memory Rhymes and the Principles of Melody in Poetry.
                South Orange, N.J., 1895. 18 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A piece of eccentricity: Byars believes that all the classical and "Indo-Aryan"
                poets composed in a verseform having initial rhymes. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L21">
            <bib> Carroll, Carleton W., and W. F. Orr. "On the Generalization of the Sestina." Delta
                (University of Wisconsin Department of Mathematics) 5,1 (1975): 32-44.</bib>
            <notes> Noticing that the rhyme shift from the first stanza of a sestina to the second
                is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 > 6, 1, 5, 2, 4, 3 (by position; the movement actually is 1, 2,
                3, 4, 5, 6 > 2, 4, 6, 5, 3, 1), the authors write a formula for "n-ina"'s, where n
                is any positive integer. Proof of the theorem follows. Bibliography. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L22">
            <bib> Censi Mancia, Carlo. Saggio sulla poesia quantitativa antica e moderna; come si
                possano comporre poesie in lingua moderna secondo il metodo quantitativo degli
                antichi Greci e Romani. Opera postuma redatta e presentata da Amedeo Bricchi.
                Matelica (Macerata): Stampato da A. Bricchi, 1955.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L23">
            <bib> Clark, Robert W. "Some Remarks on Verse Techniques." Poet-Lore 56 (1951): 76–
                88.</bib>
            <notes> Examples of English, Teutonic, French, Chinese, and Japanese verse-structure,
                mainly metrical and sonal. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L24">
            <bib> Coetzee, A. J. "Die ritme van die 'vrye vers' 'n tentatiewe benadering."
                Standpunte 82 (1969): 35-42.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L25">
            <bib> Dagiri, O. [On Phonetic Symbolism.] In Science of Language. 3 vols. Ed. Y. Endo et
                al. Tokyo: Nakajima Shoten, 1958. [In Japanese].</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L26">
            <bib> De Campos, Augusto, H. De Campos, and D. Pignatari. Teoria de poesia concreta:
                Textos críticos e manifestos 1950–1960. Sao Paulo: Ediçoes Invençao, 1965.</bib>
            <notes> The introduction, "Theory of Concrete Poetry," is translated by J. M. Tolman in
                Studies in the Twentieth Century 7 (1971): 39-47. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L27">
            <bib> Draper, John W. "The Origin of Rhyme." Revue de littérature comparée 31 (1957):
                74-85.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L28">
            <bib> -----. "The Origin of Rhyme: A Supplement." Revue de littérature comparée 39
                (1965): 452–53.</bib>
            <notes> (Reverses an important point in the original). "Though rhyme has long been a
                commonplace, it is native to the vernacular literatures of none of the Western
                peoples and . . . appears only during, or some time after, their conversion to
                Christianity." The rhymes of medieval Latin hymns derive from the De Judicio Domini
                of Tertullian, in Africa ca. 200 A.D. But "rhyme could not have been derived from
                Germanic, Classical, He- brew or Celtic sources"; to Rome it travelled with Persian
                mystery cults, and the oldest extant source of rhyme in Persian is in the Avesta
                (ca. 1550 B.C.). It seems to have come from prehistoric Iran, then, and only later
                (ca. 1200 B.C.) spread to China, since Chinese versification has included rhyme
                since about 1000 B.C. This densely informative article is due for a revision in
                detail and support, I should think, though not in general outline. Cf. L153.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L29">
            <bib> Dühr, A. Über Metrik und Rhythmik. Friedland, 1885.</bib>
            <notes> Traces the development of accent and quantity in both the classical and mod- ern
                languages. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L30">
            <bib> Étiemble, [Rene]. "Dialectique du vers libre et du haiku." Revue de littérature
                comparée 51 (1977): 212-22.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L31">
            <bib> Fenollosa, Ernest. The Chinese Written Character as a Medium for Poetry: An Ars
                Poetica. Ed. Ezra Pound. Washington, D. C.: The Square Dollar Press, n.d.</bib>
            <notes> Criticized sharply by </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="L32">
            <bib> Achilles Fang, "Fenollosa and Pound," Harvard Journal of Asiatic Studies 20
                (1957): 213–38</bib>
            <notes>, and by </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="L33">
            <bib> Étiemble, [Rene]. "Dialectique du vers libre et du haiku." Revue de littérature
                comparée 51 (1977): 212-22.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>

        <item id="L34">
            <bib> James J. Y. Liu, in his The Art of Chinese Poetry. Chicago: University of Chicago
                Press, 1962.</bib>
            <notes> See also L. D. Martin's "Pound and Fenollosa: The Problem of Influence,"
                Critical Quarterly 20 (1978):48–60, and see </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="L35">
            <bib>Presley, John. Fenollosa's Theories of Poetic Language and Syntax," Lost Generation
                Journal 4 (1976): 25-26.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L36">
            <bib> Flatter, Richard. "The Veil of Beauty: Some Aspects of Verse and Prose in
                Shakespeare and Goethe." JEGP 50 (1951): 437-50.</bib>
            <notes>Discusses the relation of emotional intensity to rhythm and its transformation of
                prose into verse, in order to conclude that "Shakespeare . . . uses verse to express
                nature; Goethe, to hide it." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L37">
            <bib> Foley, John M. "The Ritual Nature of Traditional Oral Poetry: Metrics, Music, and
                Matter in the Anglo-Saxon, Homeric Greek, and Serbo-Croatian Poetries." DAI 35
                (1974): 3676A (Massachusetts).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L38">
            <bib> Fónagy, Iván. "Communication in Poetry." Word 17 (1961): 194-218.</bib>
            <notes>Poetic language has a much higher entropy than standard language. The pat- terns
                of sound show a distinctive and unusual distribution in verse, compared to normal,
                and the words are much less predictable than are those in everyday prose. Other
                low-predictability devices such as metaphor or collocation also carry superordinate
                amounts of information. Seemingly plain repetitions actu- ally open up new
                possibilities. Sounds, patterns of sound, and rhymes convey information. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L39">
            <bib> -----. "Form and Function of Poetic Language." Diogenes 51 (1965): 72–110.</bib>
            <notes> A wide-ranging survey of metrical, sonal, syntactic, and metaphoric expres-
                siveness in the poetries of half a dozen languages. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L40">
            <bib> -----. "Informationsgehalt von Wort und Laut in der Dichtung." Poetics I (A16),
                pp. 591-606.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L41">
            <bib> -----. "Le Langage Poétique: Form et Function." Problèmes du langage. Paris:
                Gallimard, 1966.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L42">
            <bib> -----. "Die Redepausen in der Dichtung." Phonetica 5 (1960): 169-203.</bib>
            <notes>Argues very explicitly that "metrical pauses" exist in verse as "substitutes for
                speech pauses," and that "the written verse contains information which in other
                circumstances is only imparted orally." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L43">
            <bib> Fowler, Rowena. "Comparative Metrics and Comparative Literature." Comparative
                Literature 29 (1977): 289-99.</bib>
            <notes>A review of selected scholarship to suggest some dead-ends in comparative
                metrical study (diachronic philology, oral poetry, and music and meter) as well as
                some more useful avenues (generative metrics, studies of single languages,
                comparisons of meters in different languages, metrical typology, Formalist po-
                etics, study of a single meter in several languages, and study of different meters
                in a single language). An unreasonably catholic position at the end belies the
                opening caveats. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L44">
            <bib> Fraser, Robert D. "Verbal Parallelism in Ballad and Medieval Lyric." DAI 33
                (1973): 6869A (Oregon).</bib>
            <notes> Compares grammatical parallelism in English ballads with that in Portugese,
                French, and English lyrics; explicates its twin functions of delay and advance-
                ment. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L45">
            <bib> Fucilla, Joseph G. "A Rhetorical Pattern in Renaissance and Baroque Poetry."
                Studies in the Renaissance 3 (1956): 23-48.</bib>
            <notes> Based on the methodology of Alonso (L3). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L46">
            <bib> Gayley, Charles Mills, and Fred Newton Scott. An Introduction to the Methods and
                Materials of Literary Criticism. Boston: Ginn and Company, 1901.</bib>
            <notes> The final chapter, "The Principles of Versification," directs the student to nu-
                merous authorities for inquiry into various questions on English versification then
                appends a bibliography of these sources, with annotations. A "General Note"
                thereafter adds innumerable source-citations for "Classical Metres" (Greek and
                Latin) and "Modern Metres" (English, French, German, Spanish and Portuguese,
                Italian, Russian, Lapp, Finnish, Indian, Hebrew, Egyptian, Chinese, Japanese,
                Arabian, and Turkish versification systems). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L47">
            <bib> Gosse, Edmund. "Assonance." Encyclopaedia Britannica. 11th ed. 29 vols. Cambridge:
                Cambridge University Press, 1910–11. Vol. 2, pp. 786-87.</bib>
            <notes>See also s.v. "Alliteration," vol. 1, p. 697, and "Rhyme," vol. 23, pp.
                274-75.</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L48">
            <bib> -----. "Verse." Encyclopaedia Britannica. 11th ed. 29 vols. Cambridge: Cambridge
                University Press, 1910–11. Vol. 27, pp. 1041-47.</bib>
            <notes>A general survey of versification in the Classical Greek and Latin and Modern
                Romance and Teutonic languages. There is no heading for "Metre," but there is one
                for "Rhythm" (in verse and in music), vol. 23, pp. 277-80.</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L49">
            <bib> Groot, A. Willem, de. Algemene Versleer [General Prosody]. The Hague, 1946. 157
                pp. There is a long review (with summary) in English by C. F. P. Stutterheim in
                Lingua 1 (1947): 104-17.</bib>
            <notes>In De Groot's theory the essential feature of verse is neither meter nor rhyme
                but correspondence; it is this principle which precedes, establishes, legiti- mizes,
                and orders all the other elements and relations in verse. Four types of
                verse-systems are distinguished: syllabic (French), alternating (English, Classical
                Greek), word (Chinese), and word-group (Hebrew). De Groot's acoustic re- searches
                convinced him that "rhythm is a distance between two cores of in- tensity of about
                three-quarters of a second." In the alternating verse, the meter is established both
                by syllabic constraints and regularity and by the principle of alternation; the
                metrical markers may be accentual (stress), quantitative (length), or tonic (pitch).
                A very advanced and important monograph; we could profit from a translation.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L50">
            <bib> -----. "The Description of a Poem." Proceedings of the Ninth International
                Congress of Linguists. Ed. Horace G. Lunt. The Hague: Mouton, 1964. pp.
                294-301.</bib>
            <notes>Highly theoretical. Quoting Omond, De Groot asks whether a generally ac- cepted
                descriptive system (prosody) for poetry will ever be possible, and, by way of
                affirmative answer, identifies five factors in the structure of a poem:
                segmentation, dominance, alternation, correspondence, and harmony. A Gestalt ap-
                proach. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L51">
            <bib> -----. "Le Mètre et le rythme du vers." Journal de psychologie 30 (1933): 326–32;
                rpt in Psychologie du langage. Ed. H. Delacroix et al. Paris: F. Alcan, 1933. pp.
                326-32.</bib>
            <notes>The essential law of verse is correspondence between elements, syllable to sylla-
                ble, verse to verse, strophe to strophe, in series. For rhythm, isochrony is not
                indispensable but the "period" is; in normal speech the interval between stresses is
                about 3/4 second, but when speech is intentionally retarded this in- terval remains
                the same, so that the number of syllables stressed increases, even up to 100%. But
                if the 3/4 second interval is intentionally lengthened, then the auditor's sense of
                rhythmicity is lost. For meter, the correspondence lies in the stress-demarked
                intervals; meter is not an abstraction but a real, psychic movement, a felt motor
                response, that may also be a physiological movement as well. Meter demonstrates to
                us the correspondence of the poem's formation process in the unconscious of the poet
                to the formation of the performer's ar- ticulation of it, in either an
                acoustico-motor or psycho-motor fashion. The best scansion would be a jointly
                intuitive and mechanical determination of the intensity levels of each syllable in
                the line. Examples. Psychological metrics is not much in fashion these days, but one
                re- calls that such eminences as I. A. Richards, Jespersen, and Sievers took it
                seri- ously. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L52">
            <bib> -----. "La Métrique générale et le rythme." Bulletin de la société linguistique de
                Paris 30 (1929): 202-32.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L53">
            <bib> -----. "Phonetics and Its Relation to Aesthetics." Manual of Phonetics. Ed. Louis
                Kaiser. Amsterdam: North-Holland Publishing Co., 1957. pp. 385-400.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L54">
            <bib> -----. "Der Rhythmus." Neophilologus 17 (1932): 81–100, 177–97.</bib>
            <notes> Includes Bibliography. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L55">
            <bib> -----. "Zur Grundlegung der allgemeinen Versbaulehre." Archives néerlandaises de
                phonétique expérimentale 8–9 (1933): 68-81.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L56">
            <bib> Guillen, Claudio. "Some Observations on Parallel Poetic Forms." Proceedings from
                the International Comparative Literature Conference . . . July 1971 . . . Taiwan.
                Ed. Y.-S. Yen. Rpt in Tamkang Review, 2–3 (October 1971–April 1972): 395– 415.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L57">
            <bib> Hardie, W. R. "What is Metre, and How Should It Be Taught?" Proceedings of the
                Classical Association of Scotland 11 (1912-1913): 12–30. Discussion follows, pp.
                30-35.</bib>
            <notes> A sensible essay which examines English, French, and classical metrics, dis-
                cussing vexations of terminology and pedagogy. "I want to limit metre. . . . to
                separate it from music. . . . to make metre a simple, regular scheme or skeleton for
                spoken verse. . . . It follows that what a musician has to say is at best irrele-
                vant; irrelevant also what the science of phonetics may discover or what may be
                revealed by a scientific instrument." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L58">
            <bib> Hatzfeld, Helmut A. "The Language of the Poet." SP 43 (1946): 93–120.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L59">
            <bib> Herdan, Gustav. "The Mathematical Theory of Verse." Zeitschrift für Phonetik,
                Sprachwissenschaft und Kommunikationsforschung 22 (1969): 225-34.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L60">
            <bib> Hills, E. C. "Irregular Epic Metres: A Comparative Study of the Metre of the Poem
                of the Cid and of Certain Anglo-Norman, Franco-Italian, and Venetian Epic Poems." In
                Homenaje ofrecido a Menéndez Pidal. Madrid, 1925. Vol. 1, pp. 759-77.</bib>
            <notes>Examines the metrical form and genealogy of these late medieval poems; con-
                cludes that they show no syllabic regularity. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L61">
            <bib> Höweler, Casper. Rhythme in Vers en Muziek. The Hague: Mouton, 1952. 349 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L62">
            <bib> Holmes, James S. "Forms of Verse Translation and the Translation of Verse Form."
                The Nature of Translation. Ed. James S. Holmes. The Hague: Mouton, 1970. pp. 91–105;
                rpt in Babel 15 (1969): 195-201.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L63">
            <bib> Hrushovski, Benjamin. "On Free Rhythms in Modern Poetry: Preliminary Remarks
                Toward a Critical Theory of Their Structures and Functions." Sebeok (A19), pp.
                173-90.</bib>
            <notes>Despite its self-acknowledged limitations (a full-scale study is promised, which
                we look forward to), this prolegomenon to rhythmology is an excellent succinct
                account of the nature of "free rhythms" in French, German, Russian, and English
                verse. H. asserts directly that "to make a good poem, meter is not enough,"
                reminding us thereby that "free rhythms" in verse are "often highly organized and
                are by no means a border area between prose and poetry. There is a
                misunderstanding--going back to the Greeks--which requires strict num- bers as the
                only differentia of poetry." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L64">
            <bib> Jacquier, H. "Métrique traditionnelle et métrique zéro." Actes du Xe Congres
                International des Linguistes. Ed. A. Grauer et al. Bucarest: Editions de l'Academie
                R.S.R., 1970. Vol. 3, pp. 121-25.</bib>
            <notes>On metered and free ("unmetered") verse. The conclusion applauds the suc- cess of
                the latter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L65">
            <bib> Jakobson, Roman. "Closing Statement: Linguistics and Poetics." Sebeok (A19), pp.
                350–77; rpt in Chatman and Levin (A21), pp. 296-322.</bib>
            <notes>Jakobson's summation speech at the 1958 Conference on Style has become nearly a
                locus classicus. He defines poetics as the study of the aesthetic nature of verbal
                messages, and since he takes linguistics to be "the global science of ver- bal
                structure," poetics therefore lies within the domain of linguistics. In the basic
                schematization of the language situation: Context
                Addresser-----------Message-----------Addressee Contact Code which has as its
                respective functions: Referential Emotive-------------Poetic-------------Conative
                Phatic Metalingual it is evident that the poetic function occupies the position of
                highest importance. That is, "the set (Einstellung) toward the MESSAGE as such,
                focus on the message for its own sake, is the POETIC function of language." (N.B.:
                "This function, by promoting the palpability of signs, deepens the fundamental di-
                chotomy of signs and objects.") And Jakobson's formulation of the nature of poetic
                ordering--"the poetic function projects the principle of equivalence from the axis
                of selection to the axis of combination"--has become a seminal critical dictum. What
                it reveals is that the measuring or metering of sequent syllables which is
                indispensable to verse is based not simply on a principle of repetition but on a
                more fundamental principle generated by the fact of available lexical alterna- tives
                for any syntactic slot in a sentence. This principle of identity or equiva- lence,
                when elevated and directed to controlling the deployment of syllables, creates
                verse. The nature of verse, in short, is "similarity superimposed on contiguity."
                Jakobson then turns to an extensive schematic analysis of metrical systems
                (syllabic, accentual, quantitative, and tonal) and sound-patterning (rhyme,
                sound-symbolism) in various verseforms of the world, pausing only to map out his
                other important taxonomy: verse-design (meter, which "underlies the structure of any
                single line" and is therefore "far from being an abstract theoretical scheme"),
                verse-instances, delivery-instances (recitations), and delivery- design (the set of
                unconscious rules a reciter selects for the choices he must make when performing
                verses). His final appeal for a unification of literary and linguistic procedures in
                approaching poetry is as eloquently compelling as his assent to John Crowe Ransom's
                tenet, "poetry is a kind of language." Cf. L49, and for further discussion, see the
                five following studies among many: </notes>
        </item>


        <item id="L66">
            <bib> Richards, I. A. "Factors and Functions in Linguistics" and "Powers and Limits of
                Signs." In his Poetries: Their Media and Ends. Ed. Trevor Eaton. The Hague: Mouton,
                1974. pp. 1–16, 17-38.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="L67">
            <bib> Bloomfield, Morton W. "Jakobsonian Poetics and Evaluative Criticism." University
                Review 37 (1971): 165-73.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="L68">
            <bib> Culler, Jonathan. "Jakobson and the Linguistic Analysis of Literary Texts."
                Language and Style 5 (1971): 53-66.</bib>
            <notes> A ranging criticism. Analyses of Baudelaire's "Spleen" and Shakespeare's Son-
                net 129. </notes>
        </item>
        <item id="L69">
            <bib> Erlich, Victor. "Roman Jakobson: Grammar of Poetry and Poetry of Grammar." In
                Approaches to Poetics. Ed. Seymour Chatman. New York: Columbia University Press,
                1973. pp. 1–27.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>

        <item id="L70">
            <bib> Werth, Paul. "Roman Jakobson's Verbal Analysis of Poetry." Journal of Linguistics
                12 (1976): 21-73.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L71">
            <bib> -----. [Poetry of Grammar and Grammar of Poetry.] Poetics I (A16), pp. 397–418 (in
                Russian); translated into English in Lingua 21 (1968): 597-609.</bib>
            <notes>An important modern statement on the grammatical aspect of poetry in all world
                languages: "there is one domanin of verbal activities where 'the classifi- catory
                rules of the game' acquire their highest significance . . . in verbal art. . . . It
                is quite evident that grammatical concepts--or . . . 'formal meanings'--find their
                widest application in poetry as the most formalized manifestation of lan- guage."
                Innumerable examples. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L72">
            <bib> Jernigan, John C. "The Sestina in Provence, Italy, France, and England (1180–
                1600)." DAI 31 (1971): 6554A (Indiana).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L73">
            <bib> Jost, François. "Le Contexte européen du sonnet." Zagadnienia rodzajow literackich
                13 (1970): 100-20.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L74">
            <bib> -----. "Modes et modulations d'un genre: Le Sonnet." Proceedings of the 6th
                Congress of the International Comparative Literature Association. Stuttgart: Erich
                Bieber, 1975. pp. 65-78.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L75">
            <bib> Ker, W. P. "Analogies Between English and Spanish Verse." Transactions of the
                Philological Society, 1899, pp. 113–28; rpt in his Form and Style in Poetry (B115),
                pp. 293-310.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L76">
            <bib> Keyes, Charles R. "Further Observations on the Use of Alliteration and Rhyme in
                Colloquial English and German." PMLA 22 (1907): xiv [Proceedings].</bib>
            <notes> Abstract. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L77">
            <bib> Kloepfer, Rolf. "Vers Libre--Freie Dichtung: Eine poetische Tradition jenseits von
                Metrik und linguistischer Poetik?" Zeitschrift für Literaturwissenschaft und
                Linguistik, no. 3 (1971), pp. 81–106.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L78">
            <bib> Kopfermann, Thomas, ed. Theoretische Positionen zur konkreten Poesie. Tübingen:
                Niemeyer, 1974.</bib>
            <notes> A collection of statements and manifestoes. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L79">
            <bib> Kurylowicz, Jerzy. "The Linguistic Foundations of Metre." Biuletin polskiego
                towarzystwa jazykoznawczego 34 (1976): 63-72.</bib>
            <notes> Positing a four-member typology of verse-systems (the four combinations of the
                two binary oppositions accentual vs. quantitative and isosyllabic vs. isoic- tic),
                K. summarizes in this important though not readily accessible article the position
                he holds in all his other major publications, namely the view that "any metrical
                system is based on certain metrical conventions; the conventions themselves are
                rooted in the respective language" though not identical to it. In fact, "metrical
                rhythms . . . are independent of the phonetic means by which they are implemented"
                and show a "deviation from the natural rhythm of col- loquial language." Thus,
                "there is a profound difference between language as a tool of expression of meanings
                and language as a tool of forming metrical structures. It isn't the same language.
                Within the sound-system of language we have the metrical one, formed by abstraction,
                representing rules of metrical equivalences and metrical sandhi formed by
                modification and generalization of certain linguistic rules. Not linguistic rules
                but these metrical rules are the proper material serving to build metrical
                structures" [original italics]. On the paradigmatic ("vertical") plane, meters are
                comprised of "responsions" or met- rical equivalences; examples are the spondee for
                the dactyl in the classical hex- ameter and "neutralization," "weakening," and
                "contrastive meter" [formerly "pyrrhics," "spondees," and "trochees" respectively]
                for the iambic pentameter. On the syntagmatic ("horizontal") plane, meters are built
                up by their sandhi, i.e. the changes entailed by contiguous placement of elements;
                in the stress meters a primary example is stress-reduction in compounds. But all
                meters show "a deep homomorphism . . . in contraposition to surface differences. . .
                . entailed by the common tendency to strengthen the cohesion of the verse-line."
                Indo-European probably had some metrical system for its verse, but whatever that was
                cannot now be derived from the false analogy of Greek to Vedic. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L79">
            <bib> a -----. Metrik und Sprachgeschichte. Wroclaw: Wydaw. polskiej akad. nauk., 1975.
                254 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Thirteen essays in comparative metrics--Greek, Latin, Sanskrit, Persian, Old
                Germanic, Old Irish, Russian, Lithuanian, Semitic, and several modern lan- guages.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L80">
            <bib> La Drière, Craig. "The Comparative Method in the Study of Prosody." Comparative
                Literature: Proceedings of the Second Congress of the International Comparative
                Literature Association. Ed. W. P. Friedrich. Chapel Hill: University of North
                Carolina Press, 1959. Vol. 1, pp. 160-75.</bib>
            <notes>Prosody is taken here as an illustration of the two virtues of comparative liter-
                ary study--one, that a broader view will provide more sensible answers to problems
                within a specific national literature, and two, that comparative stud- ies tend to
                isolate those features which are "most significantly distinctive" of verse forms of
                all types, i.e., Verse Form itself. These are sanguine recommen- dations, and their
                utility is obvious even within prosody itself. Consider the problem of the early
                Greek prosodic terminology taken over by the English, or the foreign verse forms so
                regularly attempted by English poets. More inter- estingly, perhaps, La Drière
                insists that prosody is not a mere category of lin- guistics by observing, at some
                length, that the characteristics of the prosodies of the world do not correlate with
                those of the generally accepted language families. Even within Indo-European the
                genetics are not identical. And, of course, we still have no generally accepted
                description of the prosody of even our own language, English. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L81">
            <bib> Laferrière, Daniel. "Automorphic Structures in the Poem's Grammatical Space."
                Semiotica 10 (1974): 333–50; rpt in his Sign and Subject: Semiotic and Psycho-
                analytic Investigations into Poetry. Studies in Semiotics, vol. 14. Lisse: Peter de
                Ridder, 1978. pp. 16-31.</bib>
            <notes> "The analysis of poetry always presupposes spatialization of the temporal," ei-
                ther grammatically or semantically, and usually via automorphism, "the trans-
                formation which carries a figure into another figure that is indiscernible from the
                first if each of the two figures is considered by itself." Four configurations are
                possible: sequence PROPER CONGRUENCE ABC > ABC REFLEXIVE CONGRUENCE ABC > CBA
                polarity PROPER ANTI-CONGRUENCE ABC > -A-B-C REFLEXIVE ANTI-CONGRUENCE ABC > -C-B-A
                These would in some cases be confusible, but apparently "perception of the sequence
                takes precedence over perception of the polarity," perhaps on the basis of the
                psychological principle of economy. The most important auto- morphism in poetry is
                the metrical pattern, which "pervades the entire poem" and thus "superimposes a
                system of coordinates upon the grammatical space and thereby serves to 'chart' that
                space." An immensely provocative essay. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L82">
            <bib> Lancelot, Claude. Quatre Traitez de Poësies Latine, Françoise, Italienne, et
                Espagnole. Paris, 1663. 125 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Edward Bysshe's source (see E505). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L83">
            <bib> Lawton, W[illiam] C[ranston]. "A National Form of Verse the Natural Unit of
                Thought." Proceedings of the American Philological Association 26 (1895): xxvi–
                xxvii (Proceedings of the Special Session, 1894).</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L84">
            <bib> Levickji, V. V. [Sound Symbolism in Linguistics and Psychology.] Filologiceski
                nauki 17, 4 (1975): 54-61.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L85">
            <bib> Levý, Jirí. "A Contribution to the Typology of Accentual-Syllabic Versifica-tion."
                Poetics I (A16), pp. 177–88; rpt in his Paralipomena. Brünn: J. E. Purkyne
                University, 1971. pp. 9–21.</bib>
            <notes> A comparison of English and Czech to show "the ways in which the versifica- tion
                of a nation is dependent on its language." Follows Pike's distinction be- tween
                "stress-timed" (English) and "syllable-timed" (Czech) languages. Exam- ining
                Accentual, Syllabic, then Accentual-Syllabic verse-types, Levý derives a typology
                for the Indo-European languages: Accent Accentual Accentual-Syllabic Syllabic Old
                English Old Norse Old High German German English Russian Czech Polish Spanish French
                Syllabism </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L86">
            <bib> -----. "Generative Poetics." In Sign, Language, Culture. Ed. A. J. Greimas et al.
                Janua Linguarum, Series Major, no. 1. The Hague: Mouton, 1970. pp. 548-57.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L87">
            <bib> -----. "The Meanings of Form and the Forms of Meaning." Poetics II (A17), pp.
                45–60; rpt in his Paralipomena. Brünn: J. E. Purkyne University Philosophical
                Faculty, 1971. pp. 97–109.</bib>
            <notes> The essential fact to be recognized about verse is the line--i.e., a "sequence
                of consecutive segments," a series. The three basic physical principles (or forms of
                arrangement) of serial ordering are discontinuity, hierarchy, and irregularity,
                along with their opposites. Since "'meaning,' too, is linear in character," i.e.
                sequentially revealed, the three physical principles of linear arrangement cor-
                respond to three semantic ones, namely incoherence, intensity, and unexpect- edness
                (along with their opposites). These in turn interaffect each other in dy- ads
                (incoherence &lt;- -&gt; intensity, incoherence &lt;- -&gt; unexpectedness,
                intensity &lt;- -&gt; unexpectedness), with intensity evidently the dominant
                semantic prin- ciple. Both congruent systems are further congruent to prosodic
                features as follows: Pauses Intonation Rhyme Repetition Rhythm Discontinuity
                Incoherence Hierarchy Intensity Irregularity Unexpectedness All of these jointly
                comprise the "forms of meaning." Whatever "inherent acoustic meanings" or "a priori
                semantic values" may be shown to exist in acoustic features themselves, as a
                "mimesis" or "expressiveness" of pure sound, will occur within the nature
                (direction, rate, change) of articulation itself, and may be measured on such
                polar-opposition scales of semantic space as Os- good's semantic-differential test.
                These comprise the "meanings of form." Thus we come to see that "the relations
                between the acoustic and semantic levels [in verse] consist not in a one-to-one
                relation between segments of both levels, but in a parallel morphology of the two
                systems as wholes," i.e. a systematic homomorphism. Schematically: SEMANTICS OF FORM
                Qualitative Relations Quantitative Relations Acoustic Sub- system FORM Semantic Sub-
                system modes and speeds of movement across phones 1. Continuity – Discontinuity 2.
                Equivalence – Hierarchy 3. Regularity – Irregularity ACOUSTIC QUALITIES FORMS OF
                LINEAR ARRANGEMENT movement in l. Coherence – Incoherence semantic space 2. Lack of
                Intensity – Intensity (polar opposition scales) 3. Predictability – Unexpectedness
                MEANINGS OF FORM FORMS OF MEANING A brilliantly synthetic, seminal essay. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L88">
            <bib> -----. "Die Theorie des Verses--ihre mathematischen Aspekte." Mathematik und
                Dichtung. Ed. Helmut Kreuzer et al. Munich: Nymphenburger Verlagshandlung, 1965. pp.
                211–31.</bib>
            <notes> Translated into English as "Mathematical Aspects of the Theory of Verse." In
                Statistics and Style. Ed. L. Dolezel and R. W. Bailey. New York: American Elsevier
                Publ. Co., 1969. pp. 95–112. A general theoretical examination of "The Sound
                Structure of Verse," "Rhyme," "Rhythm," and "Stanza Structures," citing statistics
                (e.g. on the dif- ficulty and probability of rhymes). There is some concentration on
                Russian Formalism and Prague Structuralism. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L89">
            <bib> Levý, Jirí, ed. Teorie Verše I [Theory of Verse]: Sbornik Brnenské versologické
                Konference, 1st, 1964. Brno, 1966.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L90">
            <bib> -----. Teorie Verše II: Sbornik Brnenské versologické Konference, 2nd, 1966. Brno,
                1968.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L91">
            <bib> Lotman, Jury M. "On Some Principal Difficulties in the Structural Description of a
                Text." Linguistics, no. 121 (1974), pp. 57-63.</bib>
            <notes> On stasis and dynamos. Lotman is inquiring about the ways that "static" de-
                scriptions of the structure of a text can express its "dynamic" aspects as well. The
                dynamics may arise from the relations of several static models, for exam- ple. "No
                static model reflects the structure of a text, but only the structure of one of the
                constructive principles on the crossing of which the poem lives." The "energy" of a
                poem may be accurately described, and accurate structural analysis will preclude
                impressionism. An important study. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L92">
            <bib> Lotz, John. "Elements of Versification." Wimsatt (A20), pp. 1–21. Reprint of the
                work in L94-96.</bib>
            <notes> A cogent summary of the formal linguistic approach to verse-structure. Begin-
                ning with definitions of terms and alternative approaches to verse (music and
                "objective" experimentation), Lotz distinguishes metric performance, metric score,
                metric line-type, and metric system. Lotz also draws a rigid distinction between the
                "linguistic constituents" and the "metric superstructure" of verse. Four possible
                metric systems, which together constitute the complete "metric typol- ogy," are
                examined--these systems order the features of (1) syllabicity (Hun- garian syllable
                verse), (2) pitch or tone (Chinese), (3) syllabic duration (Classi- cal Greek), or
                (4) stress (English). Reprinted (with slightly narrowed focus) as </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L93">
            <bib> -----. "Metrics." Current Trends in Linguistics, XII: Linguistics and Adjacent
                Arts and Sciences. Ed. Thomas A. Sebeok. 4 vols. The Hague: Mouton, 1975.</bib>
            <notes> Part 2, pp. 963-84.</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L94">
            <bib> -----. "Metric Typology." Sebeok (A19), pp. 135–48.</bib>
            <notes> See L92 above. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L95">
            <bib> -----. "Metrics and Linguistics." Report of the Tenth Annual Round Table Meeting
                on Linguistics and Language Studies. Monograph Series on Languages and Linguistics,
                no. 12. Washington, D. C.: Georgetown University Press, 1959. pp. 129–37.</bib>
            <notes> Two questions follow on p. 138. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L96">
            <bib> -----. "Notes on Structural Analysis in Metrics." Helicon 4 (1943): 119-46.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L97">
            <bib> Maddison, Carl. Apollo and the Nine: A History of the Ode. London: Routledge and
                Kegan Paul; Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1960. 427 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A synoptic account of the development of the Ode in Rome, Italy, France, and
                England, paying steady attention throughout to the "intimate relationship between
                meaning and meter." Should be read entire, but for passages, see the Index s.v.
                "Ode, Irregular Prosodically," etc., and "Ronsard's Prosody." Ex- tensive
                Bibliography. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L98">
            <bib> Malkiel, Yakov. "From Phonosymbolism to Morphosymbolism." The Fourth LACUS Forum,
                1977. Ed. Michel Paradis. Columbia, S. C.: Hornbeam, 1978. pp. 469-83.</bib>
            <notes>Phonosymbolism has long been recognized in linguistics, but it may well be that a
                correlate concept of morphosymbolism has been obscured under other labels: what
                Sapir pointed to as reduplication is better seen as a broader process of "iteration"
                or "elaboration of the root morpheme," and a smooth series of gradations can be
                discerned between such "form symbolism" and sound sym- bolism; they very often
                appear together in "certain favorite vowel and conso- nant sequences and certain
                syllabic configurations." Most enlightening. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L99">
            <bib> Marcus, Solomon. Mathematische Poetik. Linguistische Forschungen, no. 13.
                Bucarest: Editura Academiei; Frankfurt am Main: Athenäum, 1973. 437 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L100">
            <bib> -----. "On Types of Meters of a Poem and Their Informational Energy." Semiotica 4
                (1971): 31-36.</bib>
            <notes> The relative informational energy of a system may be denoted by the sums of the
                squares of the probabilities of occurrence of each of its elements. In meters the
                elements are the binary-opposed pairs stressed-unstressed, long-short, etc. Four
                groups of meters are evident: (1) those having an energy index of 1/2, including
                iambs and trochees; (2) those of index 5/9, including dactyls and anapests; (3)
                those of index 5/8, including the paeonics; and (4) those of high- est energy, index
                1/1, including pyrrhics, spondees, and molossi. This highly abstract treatment
                presupposes that abstract metrical patterns may produce cer- tain effects regardless
                of what language or what phonetic features they are ex- pressed in. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L101">
            <bib> Martini, Giuseppe. Tecnica poetica e metrica comparata. Torino, 1972.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L102">
            <bib> Masson, David I. "Poetic Sound-Patterning Reconsidered." Proceedings of the Leeds
                Philosophical and Literary Society, Literary and Historical Section 16 (1976):
                61–124.</bib>
            <notes> Masson's summative monograph aims at an "overall view" of sound-patterning in
                all of Western poetry. It is not, therefore, a magnum opus or a standard ref-
                erence--technicalities are cut to a minimum--but rather a kind of Grand Tour of the
                literatures of eight major cultures conducted by the finest guide imagin- able. Ten
                types of aural effects and nine types of structures are noted and dis- cussed; of
                whole poems as sustained incantations, Masson identifies four of the very first rank
                and perhaps two dozen of the second. Hundreds of the finest aural effects in all of
                Western poetry are gathered together here. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L103">
            <bib> Mayenowa, Maria R. "Quelques differences entre un texte versifié et non-versifié."
                Poetics I (A16), pp. 369–71.</bib>
            <notes> [Abstract] </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L104">
            <bib> Melhem, D. H. "Iván Fónagy and Paul Delbouille: Sonority Structures in Poetic
                Language." Language and Style 6 (1973): 206-15.</bib>
            <notes>As a detailed critique of Delbouille's detailed critique of Fónagy's notions of
                sound symbolism this essay is tedious to read, but the specialist should not
                overlook the general survey of the field in its introduction. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L105">
            <bib> Meyer, Herman. "On the Spirit of Verse." The Disciplines of Criticism. Ed. Peter
                Demetz et al. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1968. pp. 331-47.</bib>
            <notes>Despairing of the insularity of versification but convinced of its importance,
                Meyer asks a fundamental question, "whether specific metric and stanzaic pat- terns
                possess a fixed expressive character." As avenues to an answer, he traces three
                types through numerous examples in German poetry: (1) a poet using a stanzaic
                pattern previously used by another poet differently, or associated with different
                themes; (2) a verse-form being made the theme of its poem; and (3) a verse-form
                wrenched from its original environment into another dissimilar, dislocating one.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L106">
            <bib> Miles, Cecil. "Whatever Happened to Assonance?" Proceedings of the Pacific
                Northwest Council on Foreign Languages 26, 1 (1975): 59-64.</bib>
            <notes> Claims (incorrectly) that very little attention has been paid to a "middle
                ground" between rhyme and non-rhyme in the history of Western poetry and criticism.
                Cites examples from France, Spain, and England, the strongest tradi- tion of
                assonance being Spanish. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L107">
            <bib> Miron, Murray S. "A Cross-Linguistic Investigation of Phonetic Symbolism." DA 21
                (1960): 1263A (Illinois).</bib>
            <notes> Japanese and English "nonsense combinations composed of systematically sam- pled
                speech sounds had expressive symbolic values according to their inherent phonetic
                content and not to any meanings via real-word associates. These af- fective meanings
                were found to bear consistent lawful relations to the phonetic properties of the
                sounds." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L108">
            <bib> -----. "A Cross-Linguistic Investigation of Phonetic Symbolism." Journal of
                Abnormal and Social Psychology 62 (1961): 623-30.</bib>
            <notes>Fifty samples of CVC nonsense syllables were rated on Osgood semantic-
                differential scales by sixteen English and Japanese subjects. Results suggested a
                general response to front vowels and consonants as "pleasant" and "weak" and back
                ones as "unpleasant" and "strong." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L109">
            <bib> Mönch, Walter. Das Sonett: Gestalt und Geschichte. Heidelberg, 1955.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L110">
            <bib> Morgan, Bayard Q. "On Translating Feminine Rhymes." On Romanticism and the Art of
                Translation. Ed. Gottfried F. Merkel. Princeton: Princeton University Press for the
                University of Cambridge, 1956. pp. 163-69.</bib>
            <notes>"To put it succinctly and with not much oversimplification: feminine rhyme is
                almost compulsory in European tongues, almost obsolescent in English. The reason is
                to be found writ large in the dictionaries." But the English poet's meager hoard of
                disyllables can be enlarged by (1) verb + pronoun combina- tions, (2) verb
                conjugation forms, and (3) Latinate nouns ending in -tion. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L111">
            <bib> Müller-Blattau, Joseph. Das Verhältnis von Wort und Ton in der Geschichte der
                Musik. Stuttgart, 1952.</bib>
            <notes> Much on metrics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L112">
            <bib> Nist, John. "The Ontology of Style." Linguistics, no. 42 (1968), pp. 44-57.</bib>
            <notes> See pp. 49–50 for a typology of prosodies in various languages. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L113">
            <bib> Noble, Edmund. "A Philosophy of Rhyme." Poet-Lore 7 (1985): 585-600.</bib>
            <notes>Takes what we should call the Nominalist approach to the principle of rhym-
                ing--"rhymed words seem to convey a sense of some closer connection be- tween the
                things for which those words stand than any which is indicated to the cold reason by
                the mere resemblance of sound" or any which is indicated in plain, referential
                prose. By extension, then, rhymes suggest "the oneness of all things" in the
                universe. The availability of inflected forms is also considered. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L114">
            <bib> Paris, Jean. "Syntaxe du visible." Études littéraires 6 (1973): 411-33.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L115">
            <bib> Park, Ben A. "The Quantitative Experiments of the Renaissance and After as a
                Problem in Comparative Metrics." DA 29 (1968): 905A (Oklahoma).</bib>
            <notes> Reviews the history of efforts to reproduce the classical quantitative meters in
                the vernacular languages of Italy, France, Spain, Germany, and England, argu- ing
                that the Renaissance prosodists did not intend (or attempt) to substitute modern
                accent for the classical syllabic length; and that practice derives from the reforms
                of the German poet Opitz and was "unknown in Europe generally until the nineteenth
                century." Nor did they intend to reproduce a system of longs and shorts in English
                in the belief that the rules for Latin were universal and applicable to any
                language. Though Park never explains what they were doing, he accounts for the
                failure of all their experiments thus: "systems of quantitative versification are
                dependent on [1] the presence in the language of vocalic quantity in a distinctive
                role independent of the place of the accent, and [2] an accent fixed with respect to
                the end of the word by the quantity of the accented and succeeding syllables."
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L116">
            <bib> Paulussen, Hans. Rhythmik und Technik des sechsfüssigen Jambus [Alexandrine] im
                Deutschen und Englischen. Diss., Bonn, 1913. 43 pp. Rpt in Bonner Studien zur
                englischen Philologie, vol. 9. Bonn, 1913. 86 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A companion-work to Zitelmann (L661). Part 1 establishes the theory of "higher
                rhythm," which is to say, dipodic meter. The Alexandrine may consist of (1) two
                "Triplebars," (2) three "Doublebars," or (3) two Doublebars and two "Singlebars."
                Part 2 analyzes the Alexandrines of Robert Manning, Thomas Blener- hasset, Surrey,
                Sidney, Shakespeare, Lodowick Bryskett, Drayton, Word- sworth, and Browning.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L117">
            <bib> Poggioli, Renato. "Poetics and Metrics." Comparative Literature: Proceedings of
                the Second Congress of the International Comparative Literature Association. Ed. W.
                P. Friederich. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1959. Vol. 1, pp.
                192-204.</bib>
            <notes>Although the author tells us at the outset he is interested in the relationship
                of poetics to versification ("poetics" meaning "a set of empirical rules . . . to
                di- rect . . . literature in the making"), in fact he wishes only to reiterate that
                modern poetics is more or less entirely unwritten. But along the way we find useful
                surveys of Classical Greek and Latin and Medieval poetics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L118">
            <bib> Polivanov, E. D. "The General Phonetic Principle of Any Poetic Technique." In his
                Selected Works: Articles on General Linguistics. Compiled by A. A. Leontev. The
                Hague: Mouton, 1974. pp. 350-68.</bib>
            <notes>The feature distinguishing poetry from prose is phonetic organization, of any
                sort, entirely regardless of meaning. Especially close attention is given to sound
                patterning here, and the principle of repetition is formally analogized to the
                principle of symmetry in the visual arts. Systems of metrical and phonetic or-
                ganization are categorized, concluding with rhyme. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L119">
            <bib> Pszczolowska, L. "Le Rôle de la rime dans la structure du vers." Actes du Xe
                Congres International des Linguistes. Ed. A. Graur et al. Bucarest: Ed. Acad.
                R.S.R., 1969–70. Vol. 3, pp. 51-55.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L120">
            <bib> Reichert, Georg. "Literatur und Musik." Reallexikon der deutschen
                Literaturgeschichte. Ed. Paul Merker and Wolfgang Stammler. 2nd ed. Berlin: Walter
                de Gruyter, 1965. Vol. 2, pp. 143-63.</bib>
            <notes>A typology praised highly by Calvin Brown. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L121">
            <bib> Revzin, Issak O. "Generative Grammars, Stylistics, and Poetics." Sign, Language,
                Culture. Ed. A. J. Greimas et al. The Hague: Mouton, 1970. pp. 558-69.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L122">
            <bib> Riesz, János. Die Sestine: Ihre Stellung in der literarischen Kritik und ihre
                Geschichte als lyrisches Genus. Munich: Vilhelm Fink, 1971. 328 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Includes sixteen-page Bibliography. A comprehensive international survey of the
                sestina from the Middle Ages to the present. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L123">
            <bib> Schädlich, Hans-Joachim. "über Phonologie und Poetik." Jahrbuch für internationale
                Germanistik 1 (1969): 44–60; rpt in Literaturwissenschaft und Linguistik: Ergebnisse
                und Perspektiven. Ed. Jens Ihwe. Frankfurt on Main: Athenäum, 1972. Vol. 3, pp.
                42-60.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L124">
            <bib> Scott, Clive. "The Limits of the Sonnet: Towards a Proper Contemporary Approach."
                Revue de littérature comparée 50 (1976): 237-50.</bib>
            <notes>In search of "the rule by which achievement can be measured." The consider- able
                variations in sonnet form should be considered not deviations from an absolute Form
                but natural differentiations for evolution and "attempts to pro- duce a special
                effect." The English reader of sonnets, however, suffers from an extremely
                provincial perspective on form; from the Continental perspective the sonnet stands
                "at the centre of a whole complex of European forms," such as the quatorzain or
                rhymeless sonnet, an important form outside of England. This essay is a very salient
                corrective to our tunnel vision. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L125">
            <bib> Sedgwick, W. B. "The Origin of Rhyme." Revue Benedictine 36 (1924): 330-46.</bib>
            <notes>Dismissing the theories of Meyer, Norden, and others (proposing Syriac, Ara- bic,
                and Christian-liturgical-recitative origins for the device of rhyme), S. ar- gues
                that "the vicissitudes of the history of rhyme can all be explained from
                corresponding vicissitudes in the history of music." Very wide in scope. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L126">
            <bib> Seiberth, Ph. "The Rhythmical Line." JEGP 18 (1919): 242-49.</bib>
            <notes>The structure of the line in the Homeric and Germanic epics may be attrib- uted
                to the very limited skills of the human brain at grouping perceptual phe- nomena;
                the length of the line is constrained by the duration of breath. Rhythm is to be
                explained via psychology and as a result of music and dance, not as a
                "self-generated phenomenon of language." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L127">
            <bib> Šabršula, Jan. "Intonation, pause, et syntaxe dans le langage poétique versifié."
                Acta Universitatis Carolinae. Philologica 1 (1972). Phonetica Pragensia III. Praha:
                University of Karlova, 1972. pp. 239-46.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L128">
            <bib> -----. "Signe linguistique dans la prose et dans la poésie." Acta Universitatis
                Carolinae. Philologica 1 (1971). Romanistica Pragensia VII. Praha: University of
                Karlova, 1971. pp. 119-45.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L129">
            <bib> Shapiro, Michael. Asymmetry: An Inquiry into the Linguistic Structure of Poetry.
                Amsterdam: North Holland Publishing Co., 1976. Rev: in PTL 4 (1979): 345-58.</bib>
            <notes>An attempt to elaborate "a semiotic theory of poetic language" based on the
                principles of Prague School Structuralism (especially markedness) and the theory of
                signs of Charles Sanders Peirce. For the prosodist the most useful part is Chapter 4
                on "Rhyme," which treats primarily Russian verse, though also English. Cf.
                Laferièrre (L81). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L130">
            <bib> -----. "Semiotique de la rime." Poétique 20 (1974): 501-19.</bib>
            <notes>Now superseded by the previous entry. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L131">
            <bib> Singer, Alice. "The Metrical Structure of Macedonian Dance." Ethnomusicology 18
                (1974): 379-404.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L132">
            <bib> Slagter, Erik. "Typografie als Typografie: Konkrete en visuele Poezie." Ons
                Erfdeel (Rekkem) 16 (1973): 104-7.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L133">
            <bib> Smith, Adam. "Of the Affinity Between Certain English and Italian Verses." Essays
                on Philosophical Subjects. London: T. Cadell and W. Davies, 1795. pp. 185-94.</bib>
            <notes>Notes extensive correspondences between the English and the Italian Heroic Verse
                (iambic couplets, ten-syllabled in the former, eleven- in the latter); these "are
                not so properly composed of a certain number of syllables, which vary ac- cording to
                the nature of the rhyme [single or masculine in English, commonly double in
                Italian], as of a certain number of intervals (of five invariably), each of which is
                equal in length, or time, to two ordinary distinct syllables. . . . " </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L134">
            <bib> Solt, Mary Ellen. "Concrete Poetry." Revista de letras 1 (1969): 154–79; rpt in
                her Concrete Poetry: A World View (L136).</bib>
            <notes> A twelve-page history of the movement followed by examples. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L135">
            <bib> -----. "Typography and the Visual Concrete Poem." Visible Language 6 (1972):
                109-22.</bib>
            <notes>One of the elements of concrete poetry hitherto neglected but capable of great
                expressiveness is selection and deployment of typeface (s). Considerable atten- tion
                to Un Coup de dés. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L136">
            <bib> Solt, Mary Ellen, and Willis Barnstone, eds. Concrete Poetry: A World View.
                Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1969.</bib>
            <notes> Solt's Introduction covers work in twenty-one countries. Includes thirteen
                "Manifestoes and Statements on Concrete Poetry," with Notes and Bibliogra- phies,
                163 examples, and word-glosses. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L137">
            <bib> Stankiewicz, Edward. "Poetic and Non-Poetic Language in their Interrelation."
                Poetics I (A16), pp. 11-24.</bib>
            <notes> Argues that "there is no clear demarcation-line between poetic and non-poetic
                language. . . . the distinctive feature of poetic language is . . . the message ori-
                ented towards itself." Verse is the most consistent feature of poetry, and rhyme is
                the feature most emblematic of its synthesizing powers. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L138">
            <bib> -----. "Poetics and Verbal Arts." A Perfusion of Signs: Papers from the First
                North American Semiotics Colloquium. Ed. Thomas A. Sebeok. Bloomington: Indiana
                University Press, 1977. pp. 54-76.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L139">
            <bib> Stephenson, Robert C. "The Chastushka and the Limerick." Southwest Review 47
                (1962): 166-71.</bib>
            <notes>Denies that there are "degrees" of formal compliance: one cannot say that one
                limerick is "more limericky" than another. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L140">
            <bib> Strong, Caroline. "History and Relations of the Tail-Rhyme Strophe in Latin,
                French, and English." PMLA 22 (1907): 371-420.</bib>
            <notes>Cf. Trounce (K408). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L141">
            <bib> Sturtevant, E. H. "On the Frequency of Short Words in Verse." Classical Weekly 15
                (1921): 73-76.</bib>
            <notes> Seven tables displaying the frequency of monosyllabic words in poetry vs. prose
                for English, Greek, and Latin. Total occurrences were tabulated, then unavoidable
                monosyllables such as prepositions and articles were removed, leaving "significant"
                occurrences. The Classical languages have few monosylla- bles which are separate
                morphemes; thus Greek and Latin prose has more "sig- nificant" monosyllables than
                verse, while English has more in poetry than in prose. In all languages, a
                colloquial style (such as in letters and familiar essays) is densely monosyllabic.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L142">
            <bib> Stutterheim, C. F. P. "Modern Stylistics I, II." Lingua 1 (1951): 410–26; 3
                (1952): 52-68.</bib>
            <notes> In the second installment the author develops his theory that objective ele-
                ments of form in verse are entirely distinct from such elements in perception, so
                that for example a rhyme repeated beyond a "certain distance" is no longer heard as
                a rhyme and hence ceases to be a rhyme. Discusses the work of Jacob (E420), the
                hierarchy of formal elements in verse, and theories of rhythm. It will be seen that
                this is a theory of the aesthetic experience not the aesthetic object. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L143">
            <bib> -----. "Poetry and Prose: Their Interrelations and Transitional Forms." Poetics I
                (A16), pp. 225-38.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L144">
            <bib> Swift, Theophilus. "Essay on the Rise and Progress of Rhime." Transactions of the
                Royal Irish Academy 9 (1803): 3–79.</bib>
            <notes> Interestingly, Swift argues that "rhyme hath its origin in no exclusive lan-
                guage"--i.e., that it is a natural phenomenon in every language, "coeval with
                language, and ancient as speech itself," and therefore "cannot be a borrowed quality
                in poetry; neither can it be of European invention, or have been first brought by
                the Barbarians of the north into the more southern provinces." In effect, then, he
                does not believe in the historical transmission of a convention. Still, he does
                insist that Hebrew poetry was rhymed, since he believes Hebrew to have been the
                primal Indo-European "parent-language." Also discussed: Egyptian, Ethiopian,
                Chinese, Arabic, Persian, Turkish, Scythian, Phonecian, Greek, Latin, Italian,
                Provençal, French, Spanish, English, German, and Bel- gian. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L145">
            <bib> Tanz, Christine. "Sound Symbolism in Words Relating to Proximity and Distance."
                Language and Speech 14 (1971): 266-73.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L146">
            <bib> Tarlinskaja, Marina. Metrical Typology of Dol'nik Verse [English and German as
                Compared to Russian]. Lisse: Peter de Ridder Press, 1975.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L147">
            <bib> Terry, Patricia. "A Note on English and French Prosody." Modern French Poetry: A
                Bilingual Anthology. Ed. and tr. Patricia Terry and Serge Gavronsky. New York:
                Columbia University Press, 1975. pp. 26-27.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L148">
            <bib> Thomas, Paruvanani T. "Dramatic Form and the Use of Verse in The Tempest and
                Sakuntalam." DAI 30 (1970): 5005A (New York University).</bib>
            <notes> Comparison of two major plays in world drama, one Western, one Classical
                Sanskrit, each near the apex of a major literary tradition, and both employing verse
                as the appropriate form for the drama. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L149">
            <bib> Thompson, Ewa M. "Sound Correlations in Verse." Language Quarterly 8 (1969):
                39-42.</bib>
            <notes> In-depth analysis of poems by Mandelstam, Verlaine, and Byron reveals some of
                the modes of sound "correlation" (conjunction, patterning): besides overt
                alliterations and more complex patterns, there are sequences of closely-related
                phonemes, often "concealed" in unstressed syllables; besides the repetition of
                single sounds, there are patterns of phonemes elaborated which are perceptu- ally
                whole, as groups; besides replication, there is augmentation, diminution, inversion,
                or variation of constituents; besides outright sound symbolism, there are the force
                and associations that a phoneme acquires merely from residing in a key word; and
                besides the semantic emphasis gained in echoing similar words, there is the more
                emphatic effect gained in correlating words which are semantically very remote. And
                the structure of the language will determine which kinds of patterns are easiest and
                hence most common. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L150">
            <bib> Todorov, Tzvetan. "Le Sens des sons." Poétique, no. 11 (1972), pp. 446-62.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L151">
            <bib> Torbarina, Josip. "On Rendering Shakespeare's Blank Verse into Other Languages."
                Studia Romanica et Anglica Zagrabiensia 8 (1959): 3–12.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L152">
            <bib> Tsura, Shigeto, and H. S. Fries. "A Problem in Meaning." Journal of General
                Psychology 8 (1933): 281-84.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L153">
            <bib> Turner, Sharon. "An Inquiry Respecting the Early Use of Rhyme." Archaeologia 14
                (1808): 168–204.</bib>
            <notes> [Two papers.] Cf. this with Draper's essay over a century later (L27). Turner
                considers the ancient source of rhyme to be China or India, not Arabia, though he
                thinks it to have existed indigenously in the early Indo-European languages as well;
                Otfrid's rhymed Germanic verse (ninth century) is cited as evidence. But he thinks
                that "the word rhime has come to us from the ancient languages of Europe [?] rather
                than from the Latin rythmus, and that the Frankish rimen shows to us the rationale
                of its use." Rhyme is found in Saxon, Spanish, Welsh, and medieval Latin verses. In
                the second essay Turner discusses at length rhyme in Latin and Greek verse, citing
                as significant a poem by St. Austin ca. 400 A.D., but Turner fails to distinguish
                here between rhyme and homoeoteleuton. Cf. Swift (L144). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L154">
            <bib> Valéry, Paul. "Poetry and Abstract Thought." In The Art of Poetry. Vol. 7 of The
                Collected Works of Paul Valéry. Tr. Denise Folliot. Introduction by T. S. Eliot.
                Bollingen Series, 45. New York: Pantheon Books, 1958. pp. 52-82.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L154">
            <bib> a Valesio, Paolo. Strutture dell'alliterazione: Grammatica, retorica e folklore
                verbale. Bologna: Zanichelli, 1968. 436 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Chapter 2 treats alliteration vis à vis metrical structure. Chapters 7, 8, and 9
                analyze alliterative patterns in, respectively, The Rime of the Ancient Mariner,
                Kubla Khan, and Adonais. Valuable bibliography. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L155">
            <bib> Vendryes, J. "La Phonologie et la langue poétique." Proceedings of the Second
                International Congress of Phonetic Sciences. Ed. Daniel Jones and D. B. Fry.
                Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1936. [Abstract] pp. 105-6.</bib>
            <notes>Good remarks on how versification systems remain after their phonetic con- texts
                have disappeared. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L156">
            <bib> Verheul, K. "Poetry and Syntax." Dutch Contributions to the Sixth International
                Congress of Slavicists. Ed. A. G. F. Van Holk. The Hague: Mouton, 1968. pp.
                153-65.</bib>
            <notes>Examines first the relation of syntax to verse-structure across the lines, then
                that of syntax to meter within the line. The general issue is "the way in which the
                linguistic elements in a poem are used and modifed in the aesthetic forms." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L157">
            <bib> Weiss, J. H. "The Role of 'Meaningfulness' versus Meaning Dimensions in Guessing
                the Meaning of Foreign Words." Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology 66 (1963):
                541-46.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L158">
            <bib> Wescott, Roger W. "Linguistic Iconism." Language 47 (1971): 416-28.</bib>
            <notes> Evidence for linguistic "mimesis" in many living species as well as in human
                speech (vowel quality, consonants, suprasegmentals, and syntax), sign-language
                (particularly evident), and writing (iconograms and phonograms). Fascinating.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L159">
            <bib> Whitehall, Harold. "Rhyme: Sources and Diffusion." Ibadan 25 (1968): 21-26.</bib>
            <notes> Recanting the narrow position in his Princeton article (C197), Whitehall
                sketches out a rich and absorbing history of rhyme in Chinese, Arabic, Pro- vençal,
                Old Irish, Old Germanic, and English. Expansive yet detailed specula- tions.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L160">
            <bib> Wiecker, Rolf. "Konkrete Poesie: Die Zukunft des Aesthetischen." Text &amp;
                Kontext 2 (1974): 50-98.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L161">
            <bib> Williams, C. F. Abby. Moved to M.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L162">
            <bib> Williams, Ralph C. "Metrical Form of the Epic, as Discussed by Sixteenth- Century
                Critics." MLN 36 (1921): 449-57.</bib>
            <notes>In Italy and France. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L163">
            <bib> Wissemann, Heinz. Untersuchungen zur Onomatopoiie. Part I: Die
                sprachpsychologischen Versuche. Heidelberg: Carl Winter, 1954. 241 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: by Koziol in Anglia 74 (1956): 239–40; by Roger Brown in Language 31
                (1955): 84-91. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L163">
            <bib> a Wittoch, Z. "Les onomatopées forment-elles une système dans la langue?" Annali
                dell'Istituto Orientale di Napoli, Sezione Linguistica 4 (1962): 107-47.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L164">
            <bib> Wulff, Fredrik. Om Värsbildning. Lund, 1896.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
    </chapter>
    <chapter title="INDO-EUROPEAN">


        <item id="L165">
            <bib> No. 1 Prolegomena to the History of Italico-Romanic Rhythm. 1908.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L166">
            <bib> No. 2. Carmen Arvale Seu Martis Verber, or The Tonic Laws of Latin Speech and
                Rhythm. 1908.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L167">
            <bib> No. 3. The Sacred Tripudium: The Accentual and Rhythmic Norm of Italico-Romanic
                Speech and Verse. 1909.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L168">
            <bib> No. 4. Italico-Keltic Accent and Rhythm and Italico-Keltic Speech Unity.
                1909.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L169">
            <bib> No. 5. The Literary Saturnian: The Stichic Norm of Italico-Keltic, Romanic, and
                Modern Rhythm. Part I: Livius Andronicus. 1910.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L170">
            <bib> No. 6. The Literary Saturnian: Part II: Naevius and the Later Italic Tradition.
                1910.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L171">
            <bib> No. 7. Indoeuropean Rhythm. 1912.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L172">
            <bib> No. 8. The Origin of Verse. 1915.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L173">
            <bib> No. 9. The Indoeuropean Superstress and the Evolution of Verse. 1917.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L174">
            <bib> No. 10. The Old-Latin and Old-Irish Monuments of Verse.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L175">
            <bib> Guentert, Hermann. Über Reimwortbildungen in Arischen und Altgreichischen.
                Indogermanische Bibliothek abt. 3, Untersuchungen, vol. 1. Heidelberg: Carl Winter,
                1914. 258 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L176">
            <bib> Kurylowicz, Jerzy. "Accent and Quantity as Elements of Rhythm." Poetics II (A17),
                pp. 163-72.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L177">
            <bib> -----. "Indo-European Metrical Studies." Poetics I (A16), pp. 87-98.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L178">
            <bib> -----. "The Quantitative Meter of Indo-European." Indo-European and Indo-
                Europeans. Ed. George Cardona et al. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press,
                1970. pp. 421-29.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L179">
            <bib> Leumann, Ernst. Neue Metrik. Berlin and Leipzig, 1920. 67 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Further citations to Leumann's works may be found in Emmerick (L1478). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L180">
            <bib> -----. "Die neueren Arbeiten zur indogermanischen Metrik." Zeitschrift für
                vergleichende Sprachforschung 52, nos. 3/4 (1924): 161–93;</bib>
            <notes> rpt as an offprint, Göttingen, 1924. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L181">
            <bib> -----. "Zur indischen und indogermanischen Metrik." ANTI PON: Festschrift Jacob
                Wackernagel. Göttingen, 1923. pp. 78–102.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L182">
            <bib> -----. "Über die einheimischen Sprachen von Ostturkestan im frühen Mittelalter."
                Zeitschrift der deutschen morgenlandischen Gesellschaft 61 (1907): 648–58; 62</bib>
            <notes> (1908): 83–110. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L183">
            <bib> McNeill, I. "The Metre of the Hittite Epic." Anatolian Studies 13 (1963):
                237-42.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L183">
            <bib> a Meid, Wolfgang. Dichter und Dichtkunst in indogermanischer Zeit. Innsbrucker
                Beiträge zur Sprachwissenschaft, no. 20. Innsbruck, 1978. 25 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L184">
            <bib> Meillet, A[ntoine]. Les Origines indoeuropéenes des mètres grecs. Paris: Les
                Presses Universitaires de France, 1923. 79 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L185">
            <bib> Miller, D. Gary. "Traces of Indo-European Metre in Lydian." Studies Presented to
                Professor Roman Jakobson by His Students. Ed. Charles E. Gribble. Cambridge, Mass.:
                Slavica Publishers, 1968. pp. 207-21.</bib>
            <notes>Confirms Meillet's four criteria for an Indo-European source of a meter: fixed
                syllable-number, fixed cadence, variation of quantity in the opening clausula, and
                obligatory caesura. Legal documents were preserved in this meter. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L186">
            <bib> Nagy, Gregory. Comparative Studies in Greek and Indic Meter. Harvard Studies in
                Comparative Literature, no. 33. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press,
                1974.</bib>
            <notes> Rev. by West in Phoenix 28 (1974): 458, which review he later said was "per-
                haps too sceptical." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L187">
            <bib> Schmitt, Rüdiger. Dichtung und Dichtersprache in indogermanischer Zeit. Wiesbaden,
                1967.</bib>
            <notes> Chapter 10, "Indogermanische Metrik" (pp. 307–13), reviews the principal
                theories. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L188">
            <bib> -----. Indogermanische Dichtersprache und Namengebung. Innsbrucker Beiträge zur
                Sprachwissenschaft, no. 10. Innsbruck, 1973.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L188">
            <bib> a Tischler, Johann. Zur Reduplikation im indogermanischen. Innsbrucker Beiträge
                zur Sprachwissenschaft, no. 16. Innsbruck, 1976. 30 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L189">
            <bib> Vigorita, John F. "Indo-European Comparative Metrics." DAI 34 (1974): 7216A
                (U.C.L.A.).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L190">
            <bib> -----. "The Indo-European Origins of the Greek Hexameter and Distich." Zeitschrift
                für vergleichende Sprachforschung 91 (1977): 288-99.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L191">
            <bib> -----. "The Indo-European 12-Syllable Line." Zeitschrift für vergleichende
                Sprachforschung 90 (1976): 37-46.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L192">
            <bib> Watkins, Calvert. "Indo-European Metrics and Archaic Irish Verse." Celtica 6
                (1963): 194-249.</bib>
            <notes>Criticized by K. Itsumi in Classical Quarterly 32 (1982): 59-60. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L193">
            <bib> -----. "Indo-European Origins of a Celtic Metre." Poetics I (A16), pp.
                99–118.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L194">
            <bib> -----. "Syntax and Metrics in the Dipylon Vase Inscription." Studies in Greek,
                Italic, and Indo-European Linguistics. Ed. Anna M. Davies and W. Meid. Innsbruck:
                Institut für Sprachwissenschaft der Universitet Innsbruck, 1976. pp. 431-41.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L195">
            <bib> West, M. L. "Indo-European Metre." Glotta 51 (1973): 161-87.</bib>
            <notes>Further support of the hypothesized Indo-European base-meter, which may be
                inferred if not reconstructed from the oldest surviving verse-texts in Indian,
                Iranian, Greek, Slavic, Celtic, Italic, Germanic, Hittite, Lydian, and Tocharic.
                Conclusions: The Indo-Europeans came first, in verse, to "the principle of
                isosyllabism. Out of all the possible lengths of line, a few emerged as the fa-
                vorites. The measure was marked off by a pause at the end . . . and more
                conspicuously by a long-drawn-out antepenultimate or penultimate syllable, with a
                short syllable before it to set it off, and ux (or sometimes x, but not -x) after
                it. That was all" [the x denoting an indeterminate quantity between long and short].
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L196">
            <bib> Westphal, Rudolph. Allgemeine Metrik der indogermanischen und semitischen Völker
                auf Grundlage der vergleichen Sprachwissenschaft mit einem Excursus "Der griechische
                Hexameter in der deutschen Nachbildung" von H. Kruse. Berlin, 1892. 514 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L197">
            <bib> -----. "Zur vergleichenden Metrik der indogermanischen Völker." Zeitschrift für
                vergleichende Sprachforschung 9 (1860): 437-58.</bib>
            <notes>See also: M230. CELTIC (IRISH AND WELSH) </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L198">
            <bib> Arbois de Jubainville, Henry d'. "Des Rapports de la Versification du vieil
                irlandais avec la versification romane." Romania 8 (1879): 145–54; 9 (1880):
                177-84.</bib>
            <notes>A response to Bartsch (L200). Followed by Paris (L244). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L199">
            <bib> Atkinson, Robert. On Irish Metric. Dublin, 1884. 32 pp.</bib>
            <notes> An offprint of his inaugural lecture at Trinity College. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L200">
            <bib> Bartsch, K. "Keltische und romanische Metrik." Zeitschrift für romanische
                Philologie 3 (1879): 359-84.</bib>
            <notes> Responses by H. d'Arbois de Jubainville and Gaston Paris, "La Versification
                irlandaise et la versification romane" (L198 and L244). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L201">
            <bib> Bell, David. "The Problem of Translation." Introduction to Dafydd ap Gwilym: Fifty
                Poems. Ed. H. Idris Bell and David Bell. London, 1942. pp. 63–103. See also pp.
                43-62.</bib>
            <notes> Includes a discussion of G. M. Hopkins. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L202">
            <bib> Bell, H. Idris. "Cynghanedd and the Welsh Metrical Tradition." In Thomas Parry. A
                History of Welsh Literature. Tr. H. Idris Bell. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1955. pp.
                121-26.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L203">
            <bib> -----. The Nature of Poetry as Conceived by the Welsh Bards. Oxford: Clarendon
                Press, 1955. 27 pp.</bib>
            <notes> An offprint of his 1955 Taylorian lecture. Useful background information.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L204">
            <bib> Bergin, Osborn. "Irish Metrical Faults." Ériu (Supplement) 17 (1955):
                259-93.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L205">
            <bib> -----. "Metrica: (1) Notes on Meyer's Primer of Irish Metrics; (2) The Alleged
                Riming of Long With Short Syllables." Ériu 8 (1916): 161-69.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L206">
            <bib> -----. "Metrica: (3) The Alleged Unvoicing of dh-, d-; (4) The Alliteration of th;
                (5) The Principles of Alliteration." Ériu 9 (1921–23): 77-84.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L207">
            <bib> Best, R. I. "Metrics." Bibliography of Irish Philology and of Printed Irish
                Literature. Dublin: Browne and Nolan for the National Library of Ireland, 1913; rpt
                New York: Johnson Reprints, 1970. pp. 52-54.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L208">
            <bib> Bowen, Geraint. Mynegai i Cerdd Dafod sef Celfyddyd Barddoniaeth Gymraeg, John
                Morris-Jones. Aberystwyth, 1947. 23 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L209">
            <bib> Burca, Sean de. "The Metron in Celtic Verse." Eigse 14 (1971): 131-51.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L210">
            <bib> Byrne, J. Patrick. "Sound in Modern Irish Poetry." Queen's Quarterly 47 (1940):
                55-66.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L211">
            <bib> Carney, James. "Three Old Irish Accentual Poems." Ériu 22 (1971): 23-80.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L212">
            <bib> Davies, A. Talfan. "William Barnes, Gerard Manley Hopkins, Dylan Thomas: The
                Influence of Welsh Prosody on Modern English Poetry." Proceedings of the Third
                Congress of the Comparative Literature Association. The Hague: Mouton, 1962. pp.
                90–122.</bib>
            <notes> More on the Welsh than the English. Davies gives probably the fullest account of
                Welsh verseforms to be found conveniently; he then examines the efforts of the three
                English poets to adapt them. Very informative. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L213">
            <bib> Davies, J[ohn] Glyn. "Metrical Analysis of the BM Text [of an early Welsh Hymn to
                the Virgin]." Anglia 36 (1912): 121-26.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L214">
            <bib> -----. Welsh Metrics. London: Constable, 1911.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L215">
            <bib> Dillon, Myles. "Irish Poetry." In his Early Irish Literature. Chicago: University
                of Chicago Press, 1943. pp. 149-89.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L216">
            <bib> Dunn, Charles W. "Celtic Prosody." Princeton (A18), pp. 109-12.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L217">
            <bib> -----. "Celtic [Versification]." Wimsatt (A20), pp. 136-47.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L218">
            <bib> Evans, J[ohn] J[ames]. Llawlyfr y Cynganeddion. [Wales: National Eisteddfod
                Association,] 1939, 1951, 1960. 73 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A manual of meters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L219">
            <bib> Henry, P. L. "A Celtic-English Prosodic Feature." Zeitschrift für celtische
                Philologie 29 (1962): 91-99.</bib>
            <notes> On "circular concatenation." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L220">
            <bib> Humphries, Rolfe. Green Armor on Green Ground: Poems in the Twenty-four Official
                Welsh Meters and Some, in Free Meters, on Welsh Themes. New York: Charles Scribner's
                Sons, 1956. 72 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Of interest. Very brief Introduction and Appendices. See L262. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L221">
            <bib> Hyde, Douglas. Irish Poetry: An Essay in Irish with Translation in English and a
                Vocabulary. Dublin, 1902. 152 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L222">
            <bib> Jackson, K. "Incremental Repetition in the Early Welsh Englyn." Speculum 16
                (1941): 304-21.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L223">
            <bib> Jones, R. M. "Mesurau Cerdd Dafod." Bulletin of the Board of Celtic Studies
                (Cardiff, Wales) 27 (1978): 533-51.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L224">
            <bib> Jones, T. Gwynn. "Alliteration: Welsh and Scandinavian." Aberystwyth Studies 13
                (1934): 1–10.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L225">
            <bib> Knott, Eleanor. An Introduction to Irish Syllabic Poetry of the Period 1200–1600.
                2nd ed. Dublin: Institute for Advanced Studies, 1957.</bib>
            <notes> Meters and sonal devices are catalogued and discussed on pp. 1–20. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L226">
            <bib> Lehmann, Ruth P. M. and W. P. An Introduction to Old Irish. New York: MLA,
                1975.</bib>
            <notes> Sections 91–95, pp. 139–43, touch on versification. Bibliography. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L227">
            <bib> Loth, Joseph. La Métrique galloise depuis les plus anciens textes jusqu'à nos
                jours. 2 vols. in 1. Paris, 1900-2.</bib>
            <notes>Vol. 1 is criticized severely by Morris-Jones for forty pages and then dismissed
                as "ludicrous" in L237. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L228">
            <bib> MacDonagh, Thomas. "The Irish Mode." Literature in Ireland: Studies Irish and
                Anglo-Irish. Dublin: Talbot Press, 1916. pp. 64-82.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L228">
            <bib> a Meid, Wolfgang. Dichter und Dichtkunst im alten Irland. Innsbrucker Beiträge zur
                Sprachwissenschaft, no. 2. Innsbruck, 1971.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L229">
            <bib> Melia, Daniel F. "'Empty Figures' in Irish Syllabic Poetry." PQ 56 (1977): 285–
                300.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L230">
            <bib> Meyer, Kuno. "On Debide Rhyme." Ériu 7 (1914): 10-12.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L231">
            <bib> -----. A Primer of Irish Metrics. Dublin: Hodges, Figgis, 1909. 63 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L232">
            <bib> -----. "Quantitierender Gleichklang in der dritten Strophenzeile irischer
                Gedichte." Zeitschrift für celtische Philologie 10 (1915): 398-402.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L233">
            <bib> -----. "The Rules of Assonance in Irish Poetry." Ériu 6 (1912): 103-11.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L234">
            <bib> -----. "Quantitative Assonance." Ibid., pp. 154-56.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L235">
            <bib> -----. Über die ältest irische Dichtung. I: Rhythmische Alliterierenden
                Reimstrophen. II: Rhythmische Alliterierende Reimlose Strophen. In Abhandlungen der
                königlich Preussischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, philosophisch-historische
                Klasse, nos. 6 and 10. Berlin, 1913, 1914. 60 and 40 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Texts, with introductions, notes, and indices. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L236">
            <bib> Morris-Jones, Sir John. Cerdd Dafod [Poetic Art]. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1925;
                London, 1930. 382 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A verse manual of five sections on Matter, Language, Form, Cynghanedd, and
                Measures. The latter two concern sound-patterning and available types of me- ters in
                Welsh, but the third section on Form treats the necessity and types of meters in
                language as diverse as Old English, Finnish, Sanskrit, Latin, and He- brew. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L237">
            <bib> -----. "Welsh Versification." Zeitschrift für celtische Philologie 4 (1903):
                106-42.</bib>
            <notes>A scourging critique of Loth (L227). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L238">
            <bib> Murphy, Gerard. Early Irish Metrics. Dublin, 1961.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L239">
            <bib> Ó Cuív, Brian. "Linguistic Terminology in the Medieval Irish Bardic Tracts."
                Transactions of the Philological Society, 1965, pp. 141-64.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L240">
            <bib> -----. "The Phonetic Basis of Classical Modern Irish Rhyme." Ériu 20 (1966): 94–
                103.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L241">
            <bib> -----. "Some Developments in Irish Metrics." Éigse 12 (1967–68): 273-90.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L242">
            <bib> O'Molloy, Francis. "De Prosodia et Carminum generibus." In Grammatica Latino-
                Hibernica. Rome, 1677. Rpt as an Appendix to Loth (L227).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L243">
            <bib> ----. De Prosodia Hibernica: On Irish Prosody. Tr. Tomás O'Flannghaile. Dublin:
                Gill &amp; Son, 1908. 114 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L244">
            <bib> Paris, Gaston. "La Versification irlandaise et la versification romane, II."
                Romania 9 (1880): 184-91.</bib>
            <notes>A response to Bartsch (L200); follows d'Arbois de Jubainville (L198). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L245">
            <bib> Parry, Thomas. A History of Welsh Literature. Tr. H. Idris Bell. Oxford: Clarendon
                Press, 1955. 534 pp.</bib>
            <notes> See the appendices and sections passim on versification. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L246">
            <bib> -----. "The Welsh Metrical Treatise Attributed to Einion Offeriad." Proceedings of
                the British Academy 47 (1961): 177-95.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L247">
            <bib> Parry-Williams, T. H. "The Bardic Tradition." Welsh Review 6 (1947): 249–53;
                commentary, pp. 265-68.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L248">
            <bib> -----. "Welsh Poetic Diction." Proceedings of the British Academy 32 (1946):
                243-76.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L249">
            <bib> Rhys, John David. Cambrobrytannicae Cymraecaeve Linguae Institutiones. . . .
                London, 1592. 304 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Mentioned by both Thomas Gray and Conybeare. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L250">
            <bib> Roberts, Griffith. [Welsh Grammar.] Milan, 1567; rpt Carmarthen: W. Spurrell &amp;
                Son, 1927.</bib>
            <notes> In Welsh. Part Four treats the Welsh meters. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L251">
            <bib> Stern, Ludwig Chr. "über die neuirische Rhythmik." Zeitschrift für celtische
                Philologie 5 (1905): 283-89.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L252">
            <bib> Stokes, Whitley. "On the Metre Rinnard and the Calendar of Oengus as Illustrating
                the Irish Verbal Accent." Révue Celtique 6 (1883–85): 273-97.</bib>
            <notes>Resp. by Thurneysen. -----. "On Irish Metric." Révue Celtique 6 (1883–85):
                298-308. Response to an asperitous inaugural lecture of this title by Robert
                Atkinson. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L253">
            <bib> Strachan, J. "An Old-Irish Metrical Rule." Ériu 1 (1904): 191-208.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L254">
            <bib> Sveinsson, Einar O. "An Old Irish Verse Form Wandering in the North." Proceedings
                of the Seventh Viking Congress. Ed. Bo Almqvist and David Greene. London: Viking
                Society, 1976. pp. 141-52.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L255">
            <bib> Thurneysen, Rudolf. "Le Mètre irlandais Rinnard." Révue Celtique 7 (1886): 87–
                90.</bib>
            <notes> Response to Stokes. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L256">
            <bib> -----. "Mittelirische Verslehren." In Irische Texte. Ed. Whitley Stokes and E.
                Windisch. Leipzig, 1891. Vol. 3, pp. 1–182. Commentary on the texts begins on p.
                107; the catalogue of metrical forms is listed on pp. 138–66 and indexed on pp.
                171-77.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L257">
            <bib> -----. "Der Weg vom dactylischen Hexameter zum epischen Zehnsilber der Franzosen."
                Zeitschrift für romanische Philologie 11 (1887): 306-26.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L258">
            <bib> -----. "Zu den mittelirischen Verslehren." In Zu irischen Handschriften und
                Litteraturdenkmalern. Abhandlungen der philologisch-historische Klasse, königliche
                Gesellschaft [Akademie] der Wissenschaften zu Göttingen, vol. 14, no. 2. Berlin,
                1912. pp. 59-90.</bib>
            <notes> Supplement to L256. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L259">
            <bib> -----. "Zur irischen Accent- und Verslehre." Révue Celtique 6 (1883–85):
                309-47.</bib>
            <notes>Detailed response to and expansion upon Zimmer. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L260">
            <bib> -----. "Zur irischen Metrik." Zeitschrift für celtische Philologie 11 (1916):
                34-38.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L261">
            <bib> -----. "Zu Verslehre II." Zeitschrift für celtische Philologie 17 (1928):
                263-76.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L262">
            <bib> Towner, Annemarie E. "Welsh Bardic Meters and English Poetry." Massachusetts
                Review 6 (1965): 614-24.</bib>
            <notes>A discursive review of Humphries (L223) touching also on Thomas and Hop- kins.
                Tone-color is particularly emphasized. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L263">
            <bib> Travis, James. Early Celtic Versecraft: Origin, Development, Diffusion. Ithaca,
                N.Y.: Cornell University Press, 1973. 166 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L264">
            <bib> -----. "Intralinear Rhyme and Consonance in Early Celtic and Early Germanic
                Poetry." Germanic Review 18 (1943): 136-46.</bib>
            <notes>The elaborate, ornamental sound-patterning of Eddic and Skaldic verse in Ice-
                land derives from Irish influence, not Welsh. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L265">
            <bib> -----. "Parallels in Poetic Device Between the Old French Epic and the Old Welsh
                Elegy." PMLA 59 (1944): 1–6.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L266">
            <bib> -----. "The Relations Between Early Celtic and Early Germanic Alliteration."
                Germanic Review 17 (1942): 99–104.</bib>
            <notes> "Technically, Old Irish alliteration is an advance over Germanic Stabreim." The
                Germanic form served only to unite half-lines into long-lines aa (the
                alliteration-pattern is ax : ax), while the Irish form conjoined half-lines xa ab/bc
                into longer sequences than the single line (the pattern is cd/de ). ef/fg. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L267">
            <bib> Williams, Gwyn. "Appendix A: Welsh Versification." An Introduction to Welsh
                Poetry. London: Faber and Faber, 1953. pp. 232-47.</bib>
            <notes>The book is actually a full history of Welsh verse. Note also the final Appendix
                on Pronunciation. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L268">
            <bib> Williams, Trevor. Swyn y glec: llawlyfr ar y gynghanedd ar gyfer plant ysgol.
                Liverpool, 1966. 64 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L269">
            <bib> Windisch, Ernst. "Ein mittelirisches Kunstgedicht über die Geburt des königs Aed
                Sláne. Mit Beiträge zur irischen Metrik." Berichte über die Verhandlungen der
                königlich sächsischen Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften, philologisch-historische
                Klasse, zu Leipzig, vol. 36. Leipzig, 1884. pp. 191-243.</bib>
            <notes>The section on versification begins on p. 221.</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L270">
            <bib> Zimmer, Heinrich. Keltische Studien II: Über altirische Betonung und Verskunst.
                Berlin, 1884. 208 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>
    </chapter>
</bibliography>
