<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="APPENDIX 1: ITALIC">

        <item id="L753">
            <bib>Aae, Gustaf. Le Trimètre de Victor Hugo: Étude de versification française. Lund,
                1909. 190 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L754">
            <bib>Anderson, H. Ueber den Einfluss von Metrum, Assonanz, und Reim, auf die Sprache den
                altfranzösischen Dichter. Bonn, 1874.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L755">
            <bib>Aubertin, Charles. La Versification française et ses nouveaus théoriciens. Paris,
                1898. 328 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L756">
            <bib>Baehr, R. Einführung in die französische Verslehre. Munich, 1970.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L757">
            <bib>Banville, Théodore de. Petit traité de poésie française. Paris, 1909. 328 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L758">
            <bib>Bartsch, Karl. "Die Reimkunst der Troubadours." Jahrbuch für romanische und
                englische Literatur 1 (1859): 171-97.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L759">
            <bib>Beauchemin, N. "Le Rythme d'un poème d'Alain Grandbois." Parent (L915), pp. 233–44.
                Discussion follows, pp. 261-70.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L760">
            <bib>Becker, P. A. Ueber den Ursprung der romanischen Versmasse. Strassburg, 1890.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L761">
            <bib>-----. Zur Geschichte der "Vers libres" in der neufranzösischen Poesia. Halle,
                1888. From Zeitschrift für romanische Philologie 12 (1888): 89–125.</bib>
            <notes> Finds its ultimate origin in Greek dramatic Choruses. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L762">
            <bib>Becq de Fouquières, Louis. Traité élémentaire de prosodie française. 3rd ed. Paris:
                Delagrave, n.d. 152 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L763">
            <bib>-----. Traité général de versification française. Paris: G. Charpentier, 1879. 399
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L764">
            <bib>Bellanger, L. Études historiques et philologiques sur la rime française. Paris and
                Anjou, 1876.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L765">
            <bib>Benloew, Louis. Précis d'une théorie des rhythmes. Paris: A. Franck, 1862.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L766">
            <bib>Biadene, L. Morfologia del sonetto nei secoli xiii e xiv. Studi di Filologia
                Romanza, no. 10. Rome, 1889. 234 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in MLN 4 (1889): 151-55.</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L767">
            <bib>Bishop, Lloyd. "Phonological Correlates of Euphony." French Review 49 (1975):
                11-22.</bib>
            <notes> Disappointed with Grammont's work (L834), Bishop identifies three major
                principles of sound-patterning: Identity (repetition of same phonemes in vari- ous
                complex patterns), Proximity (patterns of similar phonemes), and Progres- sion
                (patterns of related phonemes in an order which would inscribe a line on the
                phonetician's chart of sounds--high to low, front to back, etc.). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L768">
            <bib>Boisjoslin, J. de. Esquisse d'une histoire de la versification française. Amiens,
                1885.</bib>
            <notes> Taken from the Revue de la société des études historiques, November-December
                1884. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L769">
            <bib>Bowra, Sir Maurice. "Dante and Arnaut Daniel." Speculum 27 (1952): 459-74.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L770">
            <bib>Brandin, L. M., and W. G. Hartog. A Book of French Prosody. London: Blackie
                &amp;amp; Son, 1904. 284 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L771">
            <bib>Bray, R. "L'Introduction des vers mêlés sur la scène classique." PMLA 66 (1951):
                456-84.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L772">
            <bib>Bremond, Henri. Les Deux Musiques de la Prose. Paris: Le Divan, 1924.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L773">
            <bib>Brémont, Léon. L'Art de dere les vers suivi d'une étude et d'une conference sur
                l'adaptation musicale. Paris: Charpentier, 1903. 342 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L774">
            <bib>Brun, Marcel. Les Techniques de la poésie classique. Réalmont, 1973. 361 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L775">
            <bib>Burger, Michel. Recherches sur la structure et l'origine des vers romane. Geneva
                and Paris, 1957. 188 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Romanic Review 50 (1959): 203-5.</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L776">
            <bib>Carroll, Carleton W. "A Comparative Structural Analysis of Arnaut Daniel's 'Lo Ferm
                Voler' and Peire Vidal's 'Mout m'es Bon e Bel.'" Neophilologus 54 (1970):
                338-46.</bib>
            <notes>Rhyme-scheme analysis of these two sestinas. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L777">
            <bib>Cassagne, Albert. Versification et métrique de Charles Baudelaire. Paris: Hachette,
                1906. 126 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L778">
            <bib>Casterán, Ricardo. "Les Rapports de la syntaxe et de la versification dans Phèdre."
                Langue et Littérature: Actes du VIIIe Congres de la Fédération Internationale des
                Langues et Littératures Modernes. Paris: Société d'Éditions "Les Belles Lettres,"
                1961. pp. 271-74.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L779">
            <bib>Chastaing, Maxime. "La Brillance des voyelles." Archivum Linguisticum 14 (1962):
                1–13.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L780">
            <bib>-----. "Le Symbolisme des voyelles: Les 'i.'" Journal de psychologie normale et
                pathologique 55 (1958): 403-23.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L781">
            <bib>Chatelain, Henri. Recherches sur le vers français au XVe siècle: Rimes, mètres, et
                strophes. Paris: Honoré Champion, 1908. 269 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A compendious catalogue of forms, divided into three parts: the first sets forth
                the phonology of the rhyming vowels in fifteenth-century French verse; the second
                cites all the known instances of stanza forms, arranged by rhyme- scheme; the third
                offers concluding observations on the patterns of assonance, rhyme, meter, and
                stanza that developed in the century. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L782">
            <bib>Chaytor, H. J. "On the Disposition of the Rimes in the Sestina." MLQ 3 (1900):
                127-28.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L783">
            <bib>Chesters, Graham. "Sound and Imagery in Baudelaire." Language and Style 8 (1975):
                264-83.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L784">
            <bib>Clarke, Charles C. Concerning French Verse: An Essay. New Haven: Yale University
                Press, 1922. 209 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L785">
            <bib>Coculescu, P. S. Lyrisme et structures sonores: Nouvelles Méthodes d'analyse des
                rythmes appliquées à Atala de Chateaubriand. Paris, 1930.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L786">
            <bib>Cohen, Helen L. The Ballade. New York: Columbia University Press, 1915. 381
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> A history of the form in France and England, fourteenth through nineteenth
                centuries. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L787">
            <bib>-----. Lyric Forms from France: Their History and Their Use. New York: Harcourt,
                Brace and Company, 1922.</bib>
            <notes> The Ballade, Chant Royal, Rondeau, Triolet, Villanelle, and Sestina in Eng- land
                and France, fourteenth through nineteenth centuries. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L788">
            <bib>Cohen, Jean. Structure du langage poétique. Paris, 1966. 231 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Bibl. Discussed by Genette in Figures of Literary Discourse, </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L789">
            <bib>Combarieu, Jules. Les Rapports de la musique et de la poésie considérées au point
                de vue de l'expression. Paris: F. Alcan, 1894.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L790">
            <bib>Court, Raymond. "Rhythme, tempo, mesure." La Revue d'esthétique 27 (1974):
                143-59.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L791">
            <bib>Cressot, Marcel. Le Style et ses techniques. Presses Universitaires de France,
                1947; rpt 1974.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L792">
            <bib>Croix, A. P. de la. L'Art de la poésie française et latine, avec une idée de la
                musique sous une nouvelle methode, omnia in pondere, numero &amp; mensura. Lyon,
                1694. 662 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L793">
            <bib>Czerny, Zygmunt. "Le Vers libre français et son art structural." Poetics I (A16),
                pp. 249-79.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L794">
            <bib>Davidson, F. J. A. "The Origin of the French Alexandrine." MLN 16 (1901): cols.
                77-84.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L795">
            <bib>Décaudin, M. "Le Vers d'Apollinaire." Parent (L915), pp. 163-72.</bib>
            <notes>Discussion follows, p. 173. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L796">
            <bib>Delbouille, Paul. Poésie et sonorités: La Critique contemporaine devant le pouvoir
                suggestif des sons. Paris: Société d'Éditions "Les Belles Lettres," 1961.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L797">
            <bib>-----. "Recherches récentes sur la valeur suggestive des sonorités." Parent (L915),
                pp. 141–55. Discussion follows, pp. 156-62.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L798">
            <bib>Deloffre, Frédéric. Le Vers français. Paris, 1969. 178 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A pocket-sized student handbook. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L799">
            <bib>-----. "Versification traditionnelle et versification libérée d'après un recueil
                d'Yves Bonnefoy." Parent (L915), pp. 43–55. Discussion follows, pp. 56-64.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L800">
            <bib>Demers, Jeanne. "Les Sonorités dans le poème 'en acte.'" Études françaises 5
                (1969): 31-49.</bib>
            <notes> Functions performed by the heard poem. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L801">
            <bib>Diez, Friedrich. "Ueber den epischen Vers." Altromanische Sprachdenkmale. Bonn:
                Eduard Weber, 1846. pp. 73–132.</bib>
            <notes> Includes a bibliography on the source of the French alexandrine. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L802">
            <bib>Djoudjeff, Stoyan. "Esquisse d'une méthode musicologique pour l'étude des vers
                populaires." To Honor Roman Jakobson: Essays on the Occasion of his Seventieth
                Birthday. 3 vols. The Hague: Mouton, 1966. Vol. 1, pp. 523-40.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L803">
            <bib>Dondo, Mathurin M. Vers Libre a logical development of French verse. Diss.,
                Columbia University, 1922. Paris: É. Champion, 1922. 87 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L804">
            <bib>-----. "Vers Libre." PMLA 49 (1934): 310-26.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L805">
            <bib>Dorchain, Auguste. L'Art des vers. Paris, n.d. 424 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L806">
            <bib>Dragonetti, R. La Technique poétique des trouvères dans la chanson courtoise.
                Bruges, 1960.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L807">
            <bib>Droz, E. "Salomon Certon et ses amis: Contribution a l'histoire du vers mesuré."
                Humanisme et Renaissance 6 (1939): 178-97.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L808">
            <bib>Duc, Lucien. Étude raisonnée de la versification française. Paris, 1889.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L809">
            <bib>Duhamel, Georges, and C. Vildrac. Notes sur la technique poétique. 2nd ed. Paris:
                Champion, 1925.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L810">
            <bib>Du Meril, Edelstand. Essai philosophique sur le principe et les formes de la
                versification. Paris: Brockhaus et Avenarius, 1841. 230 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L811">
            <bib>Dumesnil, René. "Le Rythme musical et ses rapports avec le rythme des vers." Le
                Rythme musical: Essai historique et critique. Paris: La Colombe, 1949. pp.
                133-43.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L812">
            <bib>Edeline, Francis. "Limerick et rime riche." Approches de l'art: Mélanges
                d'esthetique et de science de l'art offerts à Arsène Soreil. Brussels: La
                Renaissance du Livre, 1973. pp. 211-15.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L813">
            <bib>Eichthal, Eugène d'. Du Rythme dans la versification française. Paris: A. Lemerre,
                1892. 55 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L814">
            <bib>Elwert, W. Theodor. Französische Metrik. Munich, 1961; 3rd ed. 1970. Translated as:
                Traité de versification française des origines à nos jours. Paris, 1965. 210
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L815">
            <bib>-----. "Fremdsprachige Einsprengsel in der Dichtung." Festschrift Wilhelm Giese:
                Beiträge zur romanistik und allgemeinen Sprachwissenschaft. Ed. Harald Haarmann and
                Michael Studemund. Hamburg: Buske, 1972. pp. 513-45.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L816">
            <bib>-----. "Mallarmé entre la tradition et les vers libre, ce qu'en disent ses vers de
                circonstance." Parent (L915), pp. 123–38. Discussion follows, pp. 139-40.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L817">
            <bib>Enneccerus, M. Versbau und gesanglicher Vortrag des ältesten französischen Liedes.
                Frankfurt, 1901. 121 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L818">
            <bib>Ernault, Emile. L'Ancien vers breton. Paris, 1912.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L819">
            <bib>Fauriel, Claude Charles. Histoire de la poesie provençale. 3 vols. Paris: J.
                Labitte, 1846; Leipzig, 1847.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L820">
            <bib>Feller, J. Traité de versification wallone, basé sur la versification française.
                Liége, 1928. 398 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L821">
            <bib>Filliolet, Jacques. "Problématique du vers libre." Langue française 23 (1974):
                63-71.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L822">
            <bib>Flescher, Jacqueline. "French [Versification]." Wimsatt (A20), pp. 177-90.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L823">
            <bib>Formont, M., and A. Lemerre. Le Vers français: Versification et poétique. Paris,
                1937. 212 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L824">
            <bib>Fotitch, Tatiana. "Romance Prosody." Princeton (A18), pp. 713-15.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L825">
            <bib>Fraisse, Paul. Les Structures rythmiques: Étude psychologique. Louvain, 1956.</bib>
            <notes> Experiments on grouping of temporal sensations. Last chapter discusses music and
                poetry. Good bibliography. -----. Psychologie du rythme. Paris: P.U.F., 1974. -----.
                Psychologie du temps. Paris: PUF, 1957; tr. Jennifer Leith as The Psychology of
                Time. New York: Harper and Row, 1963. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L826">
            <bib>François, Alexis. Les Originis lyriques de la phrase moderne. Étude sur la prose
                cadencée dans la littérature française du dix-huitième siècle. Paris: Presses
                Universitaires, 1929.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L827">
            <bib>Freymond, E. "über den reichen Reim bei altfranzösichen Dichtern bis zum Anfang des
                XIV Jahrhundert." Zeitschrift für romanische Philologie 6 (1882): 1–36,
                177-215.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L828">
            <bib>Galino, T. Musique et versification française au Moyen-Âge. Leipzig, 1890. 39
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L829">
            <bib>Gauthier, Michel. Système euphonique et rythmique du vers français. Paris:
                Klincksieck, 1974. 164 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L830">
            <bib>Gavronsky, Serge. "French Versification." Modern French Poetry: A Bilingual
                Anthology. Ed. and tr. Patricia Terry and Serge Gavronsky. New York: Columbia
                University Press, 1975. pp. 4–16.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L831">
            <bib>Gershman, Herbert S. "Children's Rhymes and Modern Poetry." French Review 44
                (1971): 539-48.</bib>
            <notes>The functions of rhyme. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L832">
            <bib>Gosset, Arthur. A Manual of French Prosody. London, 1884.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L833">
            <bib>Grammont, Maurice. Petit traité de versification française. 2nd ed. Paris,
                1946.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L834">
            <bib>-----. Le Vers français: Ses Moyens d'expression, son harmonie. Paris: Delagrave,
                1913; 4th ed. 1937.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L835">
            <bib>Gramont, Ferdinand de, comte. Sextines, précédés de l'histoire de la sextine dans
                les langues dérivées du Latin. Paris: A. Lemerre, 1872. 68 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L836">
            <bib>-----. Les Vers français et leur prosodie. Paris, 1876. 340 pp.</bib>
            <notes> ---- Grasserie, Raoul de la. Études de grammaire comparée. 16 vols. Paris: Jean
                Maison- neuve. The relevant volumes in the series are: </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L837">
            <bib>-----. Essai de rythmique comparée. Vol. 13, 1892</bib>
            <notes> (rpt from Le Muséon 10–11 (1891–1892). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L838">
            <bib>-----. Analyses métriques et rythmiques. Vol. 14, 1893. 198 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L839">
            <bib>-----. Des unités rythmiques supérieures au vers. Vol. 15, 1894.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L840">
            <bib>-----. Des Principes scientifiques de la versification française. Vol. 16, 1900.
                444 pp.</bib>
            <notes> See also </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L841">
            <bib>-----. "De La Strophe et du poème dans la versification française, spécialement en
                vieux français." Bulletin historique et philologique du comité des travaux
                historiques et scientifiques, 1893, p. 181 ff.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L842">
            <bib>Grimaud, Michel. "Métrique et stylistique chez Victor Hugo: Apologie du e dit
                muet." French Review 51 (1977): 15-21.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L843">
            <bib>Guillaume, Gabriel. Le Verbe, le phrase, et les vers. Vol. 2 of Récréations et
                recherches linguistiques et stylistiques. Paris: Picard, 1967-68.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L844">
            <bib>Guilliaume, Jules L. Le Vers français et les prosodies modernes. Brussels, 1898.
                226 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L845">
            <bib>Guiraud, Pierre, "L'Esthetique du vers français." In his Essais de stylistique.
                Paris: Klincksieck, 1969. pp. 231-44.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L845">
            <bib> a -----. Langage et versification d'après l'oeuvre de Paul Valéry. Paris:
                Klincksieck, 1953.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L845">
            <bib> b -----. "La métrique des 'Romances sans paroles.'" In his Essais de stylistique.
                Paris: Klincksieck, 1969. pp. 265-76.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L845">
            <bib> c -----. "Pour une sémiologie de l'expression poétique." In his Essais de
                stylistique. Paris: Klincksieck, 1969. pp. 217-30.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L845">
            <bib> d -----. "La Rime et les sources médiévales de la poésie formelle." In his Essais
                de stylistique. Paris: Klincksieck, 1969. pp. 245-63.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L846">
            <bib>-----. La Versification. Paris: Presses Universitaires de France, 1970; 2nd ed.
                1973. 128 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L847">
            <bib>Hatzfeld, Helmut A. A Critical Bibliography of the New Stylistics (1900–1952)
                Applied to the Romance Literatures. University of North Carolina Studies in
                Comparative Literature, no. 5. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina, 1953. See
                pp. 136–42, 169–75, 230-32.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L848">
            <bib>Hecq, Gaëtan M. La Ballade et ses derivés. Brussels, 1891.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L849">
            <bib>-----. La Poétique française au Moyen Âge et à la Renaissance. Brussels and Paris,
                1896. 253 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L850">
            <bib>Henry, Victor. Contribution à l'étude des origines du décasyllabe roman. Paris,
                1886. 47 pp. Rev: in Romania 15 (1886): 137-38.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L851">
            <bib>Hohfeld, A. R. "Studies in French Versification." MLN 8 (1893): cols. 10–17,
                257–72;</bib>
            <notes> republished as a pamphlet at Baltimore, 1893. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L852">
            <bib>Holyoake, Sydney J. An Introduction to French Sixteenth Century Poetic Theory:
                Texts and Commentary. Manchester: Manchester University Press; New York: Barnes
                &amp; Noble, 1972. 226 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L853">
            <bib>Hudson, Margaret E. The Juxtaposition of the Accents at the Rime in French
                Versification. Diss., University of Pennsylvania, 1927. Philadelphia, 1927. 105
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L854">
            <bib>Humiston, Clinton C. A Comparative Study of the Metrical Technique of Ronsard and
                Malherbe. Diss., University of Minnesota, 1935. University of California
                Publications in Modern Philology, vol. 24, no. 1. Berkeley: University of California
                Press, 1941. 180 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L855">
            <bib>Jaffré, Jean. "Prosodie et signification." Langue française 23 (1974):
                119-27.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L856">
            <bib>Jakobson, Roman, and Claude Lévi-Strauss. "Les Chats de Charles Baudelaire."
                L'Homme: Revue française d'anthropologie 2 (1962): 5–21.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L857">
            <bib>Jeanroy, Alfred. Les Origines de la poésie lyrique en France au Moyen Âge. Paris,
                1889; 2nd ed. 1904; 3rd ed. 1925. 540 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L858">
            <bib>Jones, P. Mansell. "The First Theory of the 'Vers Libre.'" MLR 42 (1947): 207–
                14.</bib>
            <notes> Supports Gustave Kahn's view in his 1887 Les Paladis nomades. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L859">
            <bib>-----. "Who Wrote the First 'Vers Libre'?" Cornhill Magazine 162 (1946–47):
                154-60.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L860">
            <bib>Kastner, L. E. "The Epic Caesura in the Poetry of the Trouvères and of the
                Troubadours." MLQ 6 (1903): 119-22.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L861">
            <bib>-----. "Histoire des termes techniques de la versification française." Revue des
                langues romanes 47 (1904): 5–28.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L862">
            <bib>-----. A History of French Versification. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1903. 312
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Archiv 112 (1904): 230-34.</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L863">
            <bib>Kawczinski, Max. Essai comparatif sur l'origine et l'histoire des rythmes. Paris,
                1889. Rev: in American Journal of Philology 40 (1919): 358-71.</bib>
            <notes>An important treatise on the origin of Romance versification. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L863">
            <bib> a Kibedi Varga, A. "Rythme et signification poétiques." Revue d'esthétique n.s.
                3–4 (1965): 265-86.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L864">
            <bib>-----. "Syntaxe et rythme chez quelques poètes contemporains." Parent (L915), pp.
                175–88. Discussion follows, pp. 189-95.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L865">
            <bib>Klausenburger, Jurgen. "A Study of OF Versification." In his French Prosodics and
                Phonotactics. Tübingen: Max Niemeyer, 1970. pp. 22-27.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L866">
            <bib>Knauer, Karl. "Die klangaesthetische Kritik des Wortkunstwerks am Beispiele
                französischer Dichtung." Deutsche Vierteljahrschrift für Literaturwissenschaft und
                Geistesgeschichte 25 (1937): 69-91.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L867">
            <bib>Köhler, Friedrich. Die Alliteration bei Ronsard. Münchener Beiträge zur romanischen
                und englischen Philologie, no. 20. Erlangen and Leipzig, 1901. 152 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L868">
            <bib>Körting, Gustav, ed. Encyklopaedie und Methodologie der romanische Philologie, mit
                besonderer berücksichtigung des französischen und italienischen. 3 vols. Heilbronn:
                G. Henninger, 1884–88.</bib>
            <notes> See vol. 2, part 2, chapter 3 (p. 408 ff) on "Rhythmik." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L869">
            <bib>Krappe, Alexander H. Alliteration in the "Chanson de Roland" and in the "Carmen de
                prodicione Guenonis." Diss., University of Chicago, 1919. Iowa City: The Athens
                Print Shop, 1921. 82 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L870">
            <bib>Kressner, A. Leitfaden der französischen Metrik nebst einem Anhange über die
                altfranzösischen epischen Style. Leipzig, 1880.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L871">
            <bib>Kristeva, Julia. "Constraintes rythmiques et langage poétique." Löwen und
                Sprachtiger: Akten des VIII Linguistischen Kolloquiums, Löwen. Ed. Rudolf Kern.
                Louvain: Peeters, 1976. pp. 215-41.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L872">
            <bib>Lalo, Charles. "The Aesthetic Analysis of a Work of Art: An Essay on the Structure
                and Superstructure of Poetry." JAAC 7 (1949): 275-93.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L873">
            <bib>Landry, Eugène. La Théorie du rythme et le rythme du français déclamé. Paris, 1911.
                427 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L874">
            <bib>Lausberg, Heinrich. "Zur altfranzösischen Metrik." Archiv 191 (1955):
                183-217.</bib>
            <notes>Pp. 183–202 are rpt in Ernst and Neuser (L337), pp. 89–114. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L875">
            <bib>Le Hir, Yves. Les Drames bibliques de 1541 à 1600: Études de langue, de style, et
                de versification. Grenoble, 1974.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L876">
            <bib>-----. Esthétique et structure du vers français, d'après les theoriciens du XVIe
                siècle à nos jours. Paris, 1956. 275 pp. Rev: in MLR 52 (1957): 602-3.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>





        <item id="L877">
            <bib> -----. "La Versification de François Mauriac." Parent (L915), pp. 65-76.</bib>
            <notes> Discussion follows, pp. 77-84. </notes>
        </item>





        <item id="L877a">
            <bib> Lipski, John M. "Rimbaud as Phonetician?: Color Choices in 'Voyelles.'" Lingua e
                stile 9 (1974): 323-39.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L878">
            <bib>Longree, Georges H. F. "The Rhetoric of a Picture-Poem." PTL 1 (1976): 63-84.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L879">
            <bib>Lote, Georges. "La Césure dans l'Alexandrin français." Revue de phonétique 3
                (1913–14): 221-57.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L880">
            <bib>-----. Histoire du vers français. 3 vols. Paris, 1949-56.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L881">
            <bib>-----. "La Silence et la ponctuation dans l'Alexandrin français." Revue de
                phonétique 1 (1911): 114–37, 232-59.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L882">
            <bib>Lote, L. L'Alexandrin d'après la phonétique experimentale. Paris, 1913.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L883">
            <bib>Lubarsch, E. O. Französische Verslehre mit neuen Entwicklungen für die theoretische
                Begründung der französischen Rhythmik. Berlin, 1879.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L884">
            <bib>Lüdtke, M. "La Versification latine et française à la lumière de la théorie de
                l'information." Parent (L915), pp. 299–304.</bib>
            <notes> Discussion follows, pp. 305-10.</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L885">
            <bib>Lusson, Pierre, and Jacques Roubaud. "Mètre et rythme de l'Alexandrin ordinaire."
                Langue française 23 (1974): 41-53.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L886">
            <bib>McDevitt, Mildred M. La Métrique de Francis Jammes vue dans le cadre de celle de
                ses contemporains et de ses prédecesseurs immediats. Boston, 1959. 226 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L887">
            <bib>Marcou, P. B. "The Origin of the Rule Forbidding Hiatus in French Verse." PMLA 11
                (1896): 331-35.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L888">
            <bib>Marcus, Solomon. "Trois Types d'écarts syntaxiques et trois types de figures dans
                le langage poétique." Cahiers de linguistique théorique et appliquée 7 (1970): 181–
                87.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L889">
            <bib>Marouzeau, J. "L'Usure des onomatopoées." Le Français moderne 3 (1935):
                289-92.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L890">
            <bib>Martin, Eugène-Louis. Les Symétries du français litteraire. Paris, 1924. 289
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L891">
            <bib>Martinon, Philippe. Les Strophes: Études historique et critique sur les formes de
                la poésie lyrique en France depuis la Renaissance. Paris: H. Champion, 1911; enl.
                ed. 1912. 615 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Organized by form, with a hundred-page condensation of the information in the
                last Appendix. Covers Marot (d. 1543) through the nineteenth century. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L892">
            <bib>Matzke, John E. "A Study of the Versification and Rimes of Hugo's Hernani. MLN 6
                (1891): cols. 336-41.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L893">
            <bib>Maulbetsch, Ursula. "Studien zur Rolle des Alexandriners im 'Vers libre.'"
                Romanische Forschungen 79 (1967): 489-500.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L894">
            <bib>Maus, Friedrich W. Peire Cardenal's Strophenbau. Marburg, 1882, 1884.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L895">
            <bib>Mazaleyrat, Jean. "Élan verbal et rythme ternaire dans l'Alexandrin." Le Français
                moderne: Révue de linguistique française 40 (1972): 335-39.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L896">
            <bib>-----. Élements de métrique française. Paris: A. Colin, 1974. 232 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L897">
            <bib>-----. Pour une étude rythmique du vers français moderne: Notes bibliographiques.
                Paris, 1963.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L898">
            <bib>-----. "La Tradition métrique dans la poesie d'Eluard." Parent (L915), pp.
                25-33.</bib>
            <notes> Discussion follows, pp. 34-42. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L899">
            <bib>Menemencioglu, Mme. "La Recherche de l'expressivité dans la poésie de Henri
                Micheaux." Parent (L915), pp. 219–30. Discussion follows, p. 231.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L900">
            <bib>Meschonnic, Henri. "Fragments d'une critique du rythme." Langue française 23
                (1974): 5–23.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L901">
            <bib>Moldaver, P. "La Versification d'André Spire d'après un de ses poèmes." Parent
                (L915), pp. 271–79. Discussion follows, pp. 280-82.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L902">
            <bib>Morier, Henri. "Le Moment de l'ictus." Parent (L915), pp. 85–116. Discussion
                follows, pp. 117-22.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L903">
            <bib>-----. Le Rythme du vers libre symboliste étudié chez Verhaeren, Henri de Régnier,
                Vielé-Griffin, et ses relations avec le sens. Geneva: Les Presses académiques,
                1943.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L904">
            <bib>Mornet, Daniel. L'Alexandrin français dans la deuxième moitié du XVIIIe siècle.
                Toulouse, 1907.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L905">
            <bib>Müller, K. E. Über accentuirend-metrische Vers in der französischen Sprache der 16
                bis 19 Jahrhunderts. Rostock, 1882.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L906">
            <bib>Naetebus, Gotthold. Die nichtlyrischen Strophenformen des Altfranzösischen.
                Leipzig, 1891.</bib>
            <notes> Naetebus defines "nonlyric" strophes as those in which lines which correspond in
                place in isometrical stanzas and show similarity of meter differ in rhyme; he views
                such stanzas as meant for speaking not singing. No one has applied this kind of
                analysis to lyric. . . . Mölk keys some of his work in Repertoire to Naetebus.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L907">
            <bib>Nagel, Heinrich. Die metrischen verse Jean Antoine de Baif's. Diss., Leipzig,
                1878.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L908">
            <bib>Naïs, H. "Les Caractères de l'evolution du vers au XVIe siècle." Parent (L915), pp.
                283–90. Discussion follows, pp. 305-10.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L909">
            <bib>-----. "Le Décasyllable et l'Alexandrin en France au XVIe siècle." Actas XI Congres
                Internacional de Linguistica y Filologia Romanicas. Ed. Antonio Quilis. Madrid,
                1968. Vol. 3, pp. 1653-67.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L910">
            <bib>Nasta, M. "La Metrice générative de rhythmes et les structures verbales de la
                phrase poématique." Actes du Xe Congres International des Linguistes. Ed. A. Graur
                et al. Bucarest: Ed. Acad. R. S. R., 1970. Vol. 3, pp. 17-26.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L911">
            <bib>Nyrop, Kristoffer. Fransk Verslaere i Omrids. Copenhagen, 1910; 2nd rev. ed. 1929.
                118 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L912">
            <bib>Orth, Ferdinand. Über Reim und Strophenbau in der altfranzösischen Lyrik. Diss.,
                Strassburg. Cassel: Ernst Hühn, 1882. 75 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L913">
            <bib>Ovidio, Francesco d'. Studi sulla più antica versificazione francese. Rome,
                1920.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L914">
            <bib>Parent, M. "XVIe siècle et XXe siècle: Des Recherches semblables, des trouvailles
                nouvelles." Parent (L915), pp. 291–98. Discussion follows, pp. 305– 10.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L915">
            <bib>Parent, Monique, ed. Le Vers Français au 20e siècle. Paris: C. Klincksieck, 1967.
                323 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Sixteen papers, followed by a summary plenary discussion, pp. 311-22</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L916">
            <bib>Patterson, W. F. Three Centuries of French Poetic Theory: A Critical History of the
                Chief Arts of Poetry in France (1328–1630). Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press,
                1935.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L917">
            <bib>Paulhan, Jean. Clef de la poésie, qui permet de distinguer le vrai du faux en toute
                observation ou doctrine touchant le rime, le rhythme, le vers, le poète et la
                poésie. Paris, 1944.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L918">
            <bib>Pfrommer, Walter. Grundzüge der Strophenentwicklung in der französischen Lyrik von
                Baudelaire zu Apollinaire. Diss., Tübingen, 1963. 185 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L919">
            <bib>Pierson, Paul. Métrique naturelle du langage. Paris: F. Vieweg, 1884. 260 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L920">
            <bib>Pitou, S. "Sixteenth- and Seventeenth-Century Poets and Poetry in Pierre Richelet's
                La Versification Françoise, 1672." MLN 65 (1950): 456-62.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L921">
            <bib>Polovina, P. "Le Rythme, la phrase et la rime dans 2000 vers d'Aragon." Parent
                (L915), pp. 197–215. Discussion follows, pp. 216-17.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L922">
            <bib>-----. "Sur le rapport des traits de démarcation du vers." Actes du Xe Congres
                International des Linguistes. Ed. A. Graur et al. Bucarest: Ed. Acad. R. S. R.,
                1969–70. Vol. 3, pp. 3–16.</bib>
            <notes> Includes discussion. On demarcation of line-ends by aural features. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L923">
            <bib>Porter, M. E. "The Genesis of Alexandrin as a Metrical Term." MLN 51 (1936):
                528-35.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L924">
            <bib>Pratt, Waldo S. The Music of the French Psalter of 1562. Columbia University
                Studies in Musicology, no. 3. New York: Columbia University Press, 1939.</bib>
            <notes> Chapters 4–7 treat Meters, Line-Structure, and other aspects of versification.
                The psalter was immensely influential both inside and outside France. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L925">
            <bib>"Provençal Versification." North British Review 53 (1871): 317-50.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L926">
            <bib>Przyluski, J. "Le Rythme et l'improvisation poétique." Journal de psychologie 31
                (1934): 801-8.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L927">
            <bib>Purczinsky, J. "Germanic Influence in the Saint Eulalia." Romance Philology 19
                (1965): 271-75.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L928">
            <bib>Quicherat, Louis Marie. Mélanges de philologie. Paris: Hachette, 1879. 368
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> A very extensive collection of essays on Latin and French linguistics and versi-
                fication. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L929">
            <bib>-----. Petit traité de versification française. Paris, 1866. More than 15
                subsequent editions through 1915. 137 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L930">
            <bib>-----. Traité de versification française. 2nd ed. Paris, 1850. 584 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L931">
            <bib>Ratermanis, J. B. "À propos de l'harmonie des vers." PQ 30 (1951): 194-205.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L932">
            <bib>Remillard, Vincent L. "Rhyming Vowel Preferences in Selected French Verse,
                1688–1792: An Aspect of Enlightenment Poetics." DAI 39 (1978): 2322A (Penn.
                State).</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L933">
            <bib>Rickard, P. "Semantic Implications of Old French Identical Rhyme." Neuphilologische
                Mitteilungen 66 (1965): 355-401.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L934">
            <bib>Riffaterre, Michael. "Describing Poetic Structures: Two Approaches to Baudelaire's
                'Les Chats.'" Yale French Studies 36–37 (1966): 200-42.</bib>
            <notes>A reaction to Jakobson and Lévi-Strauss (L856). Riffaterre vigorously attacks
                their structuralist method and offers in its place a methodology for seeing the poem
                as a "whole act of communication" which takes into account the re- sponses of a
                number of readers. See the critique of this method by Hendricks (F88). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L935">
            <bib>Ripert, É. La Versification de Frédéric Mistral. 1917. 160 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L936">
            <bib>Ritter, Otto. Die Geschichte der französischen Balladenformen. Diss., Jena. Halle:
                M ax Niemeyer, 1914. 208 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L937">
            <bib>Rochat, A. "Étude sur le vers décasyllable dans la poésie française au Moyen Âge."
                Jahrbuch für romanische und englische Literatur 11 (1870): 65-93.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L938">
            <bib>Roche, P.-I. la. "Rythme et expressivité dans un poème de Pierre Emmanuel." Parent
                (L915), pp. 245–60. Discussion follows, pp. 261-70.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L939">
            <bib>Romains, Jules, and G. Chennevière. Petit traité de versification française. 12th
                ed. Paris, 1923.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L940">
            <bib>Rousselot, Jean. "D'Aubigne, prosodiste novateur." Europe: Revue littéraire
                mensuelle 563 (1976): 20-26.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L941">
            <bib>Ruwet, Nicolas. Language, musique, poésie. Paris: Éditions du Seuil, 1972. 247
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Includes four essays in structural and linguistic analysis of poetry, especially
                one analyzing rhythm and harmony in Baudelaire. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L941">
            <bib> a -----. "Sur un vers de Charles Baudelaire." Linguistics, no. 17 (1965), pp.
                69-77.</bib>
            <notes> Examine rhythmic complexity and the relation of sound to sense. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L942">
            <bib>Rychner, Jean. "Observations sur la versification du Couronnement de Louis." In La
                Technique littéraire des "Chansons de geste." Paris: Société d'Éditions "Les Belles
                Lettres," 1959. pp. 161-82.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L943">
            <bib>Saran, Franz. Der Rhythmus des französischen Verses. Halle, 1904. 455 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L944">
            <bib>Scarfe, Francis. The Art of Paul Valéry: A Study in Dramatic Monologue. London:
                Heinemann, 1954.</bib>
            <notes> See esp. Part One, Section II, (vi). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L945">
            <bib>Scheel, Hans L. "Zur Theorie und Praxis der Versforschung, I: Neuere Arbeiten zur
                Verstheorie und zur romanischen Versforschung." II: Romanistiches Jahrbuch 18
                (1967): 38–55; 21 (1970): 54-74.</bib>
            <notes> Review articles </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L946">
            <bib>Schenk, Albert. Études sur la rime dans "Cyrano de Bergerac" de Rostand. Diss.,
                Kiel, 1900. 109 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L947">
            <bib>Schmidt, Julius. "Die rhythmische Gestalt des Alexandriners bei Corneille und bei
                Racine." Zeitschrift für französische Sprache und Literatur 53 (1929–30):
                39-76.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L948">
            <bib>-----. Der Rhythmus des französischen Verses. Wiesbaden, 1968. 53 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L949">
            <bib>Scholz, Martin. "Die Alliteration in der altprovenzalischen Lyrik." Zeitschrift für
                romanische Philologie 37 (1913): 385-426.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L950">
            <bib>Seaman, David W. "The Development of Visual Poetry in France." Visible Language 6
                (1972): 19-44.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L951">
            <bib>-----. "French Concrete Poetry: The Development of a Poetic Form, from its Origins
                to the Present Day." Diss., Stanford University, 1970.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L952">
            <bib>Servien, Pius. Essai sur les rythmes toniques du français. Paris, 1925.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L953">
            <bib>-----. Lyrisme et structures sonores. Paris, 1930.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L954">
            <bib>-----. Les Rythmes comme introduction physique à l'esthétique. Paris, 1930.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L955">
            <bib>Sheldon, Edward S. "Some Remarks on the Origin of Romance Versification."
                Anniversary Papers by Colleagues and Pupils of George Lyman Kittredge. Boston: Ginn
                and Company, 1913. pp. 37-46.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L956">
            <bib>Short, M. H. "Linguistic Criticism and Baudelaire's 'Les Chats.'" Journal of
                Literary Semantics 2 (1973): 79-93.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L957">
            <bib>Smith, Nathaniel B. Figures of Repetition in the Old Provençal Lyric: A Study of
                the Style of the Troubadours. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1976.
                317 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L958">
            <bib>Sørensen, Hans. La Poésie de Paul Valéry: Étude stylistique sur "La Jeune Parque."
                Copenhagen, 1944. 382 pp.</bib>
            <notes> + Indexes. Syntax is treated in chapter 4, metrics in chapter 5 (pp. 252–98).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L959">
            <bib>Souza, Robert de. Questions de métrique: Le Rythme poétique. Paris, 1892. 304
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L960">
            <bib>-----. Du Rythme en français. Paris, 1912. 103 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L961">
            <bib>Spiker, Claude C. "The Ten-Syllable Rhyming Couplet." West Virginia University
                Philological Papers 1 (1929): 41-47.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L961">
            <bib> a -----. His diss at Chicago 1922 on the historical development of the
                caesura.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L962">
            <bib>Spire, A. Plaisir poétique et plaisir musculaire: Essai sur l'évolution des
                techniques poétiques. Paris: José Corti; New York: Vanni, 1949.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L963">
            <bib>Spoerri, Theophil. Französische Metrik. Munich: Max Hueber, 1929.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L964">
            <bib>Stengel, Edmund. "Lehre von der romanische Sprachkunst: Romanische Verslehre." In
                Grundriss der romanische Philologie. 2 vols. Ed. Gustav Gröber. Strasburg,
                1888–1902. Vol. 2, part 1, pp. 1–90.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L965">
            <bib>-----. "Der Strophenausgang in den ältesten französischen Balladen und sein
                Verhältnis zum Refrain und Strophengrundstock." Zeitschrift für französische Sprache
                und Literatur 18 (1896): 85–114.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L966">
            <bib>Storost, W. Geschichte der altfranzösischen und altprovenzalischen Romanzenstrophe.
                Romanistische Arbeiten, no. 16. Halle, 1930. 116 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L967">
            <bib>Stramwitz, E. Strophen- und Vers-Enjambement im Altfranzösischen. Greifswald,
                1886.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L968">
            <bib>Strauss, C. A. "L'Origine et sens du vers Claudélien." PMLA 64 (1949): 15-25.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L969">
            <bib>Suberville, Jean. Histoire et théorie de la versification française. Paris, 1940;
                2nd rev. ed. 1946. 253 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L970">
            <bib>Suchier, Walther. Französische Verslehre auf historischer Grundlage. Tübingen: Max
                Niemeyer, 1952; 2nd ed. 1963. 247 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L971">
            <bib>Sully-Prudhomme, René François Armond. Reflexions l'art des vers. Paris: Lemerre,
                1892. 85 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L972">
            <bib>Thieme, Hugo P. Essai sur l'histoire du vers français. Paris: Libraire ancienne
                Honoré Champion, 1916. 432 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L973">
            <bib>-----. "Rhythm." Mélanges d'histoire littéraire général et comparée . . .
                Baldensperger. Paris: H. Champion, 1930. Vol. 2, pp. 275-83.</bib>
            <notes>Traces "the evolution of versification towards the single principle, called
                rhythm," through three stages: physical, physical-mechanical-intellectual, and
                purely intellectual. The last stage lies beyond all artificial rules or prosodic
                laws, beyond all versification, and was reached by French poets before English.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L974">
            <bib>-----. "Some Recent Works on French Versification." MLN 21 (1906): 55-57.</bib>
            <notes> Twelve books are reviewed. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L975">
            <bib>-----. The Technique of the French Alexandrine: A Study. Ann Arbor: Inland Press,
                1899. 68 pp.</bib>
            <notes> His dissertation at Johns Hopkins University in 1897. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L976">
            <bib>Thomas, A. "La Versification de la chirurgie provençale de Raimon D'Avignon."
                Romania 11 (1882): 203-12.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L977">
            <bib>Thomas, W. Le Décasyllabe roman et sa fortune en Europe. Lille, 1904. 201 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L978">
            <bib>Tierney, Frank M. "An Introduction to the Rondeau: A Definition and Analysis."
                Inscape (Ottawa) 8, 1 (1970): 22-51.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L979">
            <bib>-----. "The Origin and Growth of the Rondeau in France." Inscape (Ottawa) 8, 2
                (1970): 18-48.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L980">
            <bib>Tisseur, Clair. Modestes Observations sur l'art des versifier. Lyon: Bernoux, 1893.
                355 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L981">
            <bib>Tobler, Adolf. Vom französischen Versbau alter und neuer Zeit. Leipzig, 1880;
                steadily expanded up to 177 pp. in the fifth edition, 1910. The second German
                edition was translated into French as Le Vers français ancien et moderne. Paris,
                1885; rpt Geneva: Slatkine Reprints, 1972. 207 pp.</bib>
            <notes> My copy is the 1885 Fr. tr. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L982">
            <bib>Träger Ernst. Geschichte der Alexandriners. Diss., Leipzig, 1889.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L983">
            <bib>Trannoy, A. I. La Musique des vers: Harmonie, rythme, sonorité, fluidité, melodie.
                Paris: Delagrave, 1929.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L984">
            <bib>Turnell, Martin. "Jules Laforgue: Observations on the Theory and Practice of Free
                Verse." Cornhill Magazine 163 (1947–48): 74-90.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L985">
            <bib>Vaissière, Jacqueline. "On French Prosody." Quarterly Progress Report, MIT Research
                Laboratory of Electronics 114 (1974): 212-24.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L986">
            <bib>Valéry, Paul. "Concerning the 'Cimetière Marin.'" Southern Review 4 (1938):
                156-65.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L987">
            <bib>Deleted.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L988">
            <bib>Verrier, Paul. "L'Écart d'isochronisme dans le rythme." Journal de psychologie 19
                (1922): 289-321.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L989">
            <bib>-----. L'Isochronisme dans le vers français. Paris: F. Alcan, 1912. 51 p.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L990">
            <bib>-----. "Isochronisme et anacruse." Revue de phonétique 3 (1913–14): 381-95.</bib>
            <notes>Attacks Grammont (L834), who replies in Revue 4 (1914): 59–64; rejoinder by
                Verrier, 64–70; final word by Grammont, 70. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L991">
            <bib>-----. "La Mesure des durées rythmiques dans les vers." Revue de phonétique
                2(1912):69-75.</bib>
            <notes> As in music, so in poetry the only constant amid the chaos is the marked time of
                the measure, the interval between the demarcations. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L992">
            <bib>-----. "Metrische Fragen." Neuphilologische Mitteilungen 35 (1934): 145–58; rpt in
                Ernst and Neuser (L337), pp. 8–21.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L993">
            <bib>-----. "La Quantité." Revue de phonétique 4 (1917): 134-50.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L994">
            <bib>-----. "Les Variations intensive du rythme." Journal de psychologie normale et
                pathologique 11 (1914): 195 ff.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L995">
            <bib>-----. Les Variations temporelles du rythme. Paris, 1913.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L996">
            <bib>-----. Le Vers français 3 vols. Paris: H. Didier, 1931-32.</bib>
            <notes>Rev: by Heusler in AnzfdA 52 (1933): 122–32, rpt. in his Kleine Schriften (1943),
                483-97.</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L997">
            <bib>Villey, Pierre. "Marot et le premier sonnet français." Revue d'histoire littéraire
                de la France 27 (1920): 532-47.</bib>
            <notes>The earliest extant French sonnet dates from 1536. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L998">
            <bib>Vincenz, Andrei. "'Rythme intérieur' et information poétique." Revue roumaine de
                linguistique 14 (1969): 163-78.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L999">
            <bib>Werf, Hendrik van der. The Chansons of the Troubadours and Trouveres; a Study of
                the Melodies and their Relation to the Poems. Utrecht: A. Oosthoek, 1972. 166
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> Should be alphabetized under V- </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1000">
            <bib> Wexler, P. J. "Distich and Sentence in Corneille and Racine." Fowler (A14), pp.
                100-17.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1001">
            <bib>-----. "On the Grammetrics of the Classical Alexandrine." Cahiers de lexicologie 4
                (1964): 61-72.</bib>
            <notes> Notes toward a method of analysis which could take full account of the me- ter's
                constraints on both syntax and lexical selection in the line--a "leximetric" or
                "grammetric" notation. This, I believe, will be the direction of prosodic in- quiry
                in the future. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1002">
            <bib> Willem, A. Étude méthodique des genres lyriques. Frameries, 1924. 87 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1003">
            <bib> Windelberg, Marjorie. "Formulaic Flexibility and Metrical Irregularity in the
                Chanson de Roland." Diss., University of North Carolina, 1978.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1004">
            <bib> Wright, A. J. "Verlaine's Art Poétique Re-Examined." PMLA 74 (1959): 268-75.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1005">
            <bib> Wulff, Fredrik. La Rythmicité de l'Alexandrin français. Lunds Universitets
                Årsskrift, vol. 36, no. 6. Lund, 1900. 79 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1006">
            <bib> -----. Om Oredan i den Modärna Franska Värsläran. Lunds Universitets Årsskrift,
                n.s. 1, v. 23, no. 5. Lund: C. W. K. Gleerup, 1927.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1007">
            <bib> Zaleski, Z. L. "La Vie comparée de deux formes: Le Sonnet et le rondeau." Stil-
                und Formprobleme in der Literatur: Proceedings of the Seventh Congress of the IFMLL.
                Ed. Paul Böckemann. Heidelberg: Carl Winter, 1959. pp. 103-7.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1008">
            <bib> Zschalig, Heinrich. Die Verslehre von Fabri du Pont und Thomas Sibilet: Ein
                Beitrag zur alteren Geschichte der französischen Poetik. Heidelberg and Leipzig,
                1884; rpt Geneva: Slatkine Reprints, 1971. 80 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1009">
            <bib> Zumthor, Paul. Langue et techniques poétiques à l'epoque romane (XIe–XIIIe
                siècles). Paris, 1963. 224 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Spanish and Portuguese </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1010">
            <bib> Alonso, Dámaso. "Poesia correlativa inglesa en los siglos XVI y XVII." Filologia
                moderna 2 (1961): 1–47.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1011">
            <bib> -----. Poesía española: Ensayo de metodos y limites estilisticos. Madrid,
                1950.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1012">
            <bib> Alonso, Dámaso, and Carlos Bousoño. Seis calas en la expresión literaria española.
                Madrid, 1951, 1963.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1013">
            <bib> Arjona, J. H. "Defective Rhymes and Rhyming Techniques in Lope de Vega's Autograph
                Comedias." Hispanic Review 23 (1955): 108-28.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1014">
            <bib> Baehr, Rudolf. Spanische Verslehre auf historischer Grundlage. Tübingen,
                1962.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1015">
            <bib> Balaguer, Joaquin. Apuntes para una historia prosódica de la métrica castellana.
                Santo Domingo, 1974. 269 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1016">
            <bib> Balbín Lucas, Rafael de. Sistema de rítmica castellana. Madrid, 1962. 357
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1017">
            <bib> Barra Lastarria, Eduardo de la. Elementos de métrica castellana. Santiago de
                Chile, 1887. 104 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1018">
            <bib> -----. Estudios sobre la versificacion castellana. Santiago de Chile, 1887. 101
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1019">
            <bib> Bartina, Sebastian. Verso y versificación: Tratado de métrica castellana.
                Barcelona, 1955. 216 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1020">
            <bib> Benot y Rodriguez, Eduardo. Prosodia castellana i versificación. 3 vols. Madrid,
                1892.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1021">
            <bib> Bilac, Olavo. Tratado de versificaçao. 7th ed. Rio de Janiero, 1938. 212 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1022">
            <bib> Brenes-Mesen, R. "El ritmo de la prosa española." Hispania 21 (1938): 47-52.</bib>
            <notes> Finds that the normal rhythmic unit in prose is octosyllabic, as in the verse.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1023">
            <bib> Brewster, Paul G. "Metrical, Stanzaic and Stylistic Resemblances Between Malayan
                and Western Poetry." Revue de littérature comparée 32 (1958): 214-22.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1024">
            <bib> Camara, J. Mattoso. "Imperfect Rimes in Brazilian Poetry." Word 2 (1946): 131–
                35.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1025">
            <bib> Carballo Picazo, Alfredo. Métrica española. Madrid, 1956. 161 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A bibliography of Spanish versification from the fifteenth to the twentieth
                century: 1203 citations of general and specialized studies with Index. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1026">
            <bib> Carvalho, Amorim de. Tratado de versificaçao portuguesa. Porto, 1941.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1027">
            <bib> Castilho, Antonio Feliciano de. Tratado de metrificaçao portugueza . . . . Lisbon,
                1851</bib>
            <notes>; 2nd ed. 1858; 1867; 1874; 5th ed. rpt in his Obras completas, vols. 56– 57,
                1908. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1028">
            <bib> P., E. M. D. V. D. Preface to François Auguste René, vicomte de Chateau- briand.
                Ensayo sobre la versificacion mas propia para la epopeya en las lenguas modernas,
                hecho en la traduccion del primer libro de Los mártires, ó Triunfo de la religion
                cristiana, poema frances escrito en prosa poética por F. A. de Chateaubriand.
                Madrid, 1816. 208 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1029">
            <bib> Chociay, Rogério. Teoria do verso. Sao Paulo, 1974. 211 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1030">
            <bib> Clarke, Dorothy C. Une bibliografia de versificación española. University of
                California Publications in Modern Philology, vol. 20, no. 2. Berkeley: University of
                California Press, 1937. pp. 57–126.</bib>
            <notes> Cf. Carballo Picazo (L1025). </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1031">
            <bib> -----. A Chronological Sketch of Castilian Versification Together with a List of
                its Metric Terms. University of California Publications in Modern Philology, vol.
                34, no. 3. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1952. pp. 279-381.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1032">
            <bib> -----. "The Early Seguidilla." Hispanic Review 12 (1944): 211-22.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1033">
            <bib> -----. "Imperfect Consonance and Acoustic Equivalence in Cancionero Verse." PMLA
                64 (1949): 1114-22.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1034">
            <bib> -----. "On Iriarte's Versification." PMLA 67 (1952): 411-19.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1035">
            <bib> -----. "Metric Problems in the Cancionero de Romances." Hispanic Review 23 (1955):
                188-99.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1036">
            <bib> -----. "Miscellaneous Strophic Forms in the Fifteenth-Century Court Lyric."
                Hispanic Review 16 (1948): 142-56.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1037">
            <bib> -----. Morphology of Fifteenth-Century Castilian Verse. Pittsburgh: Duquesne
                University Press, 1964. 233 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1038">
            <bib> -----. "Nebrija on Versification." PMLA 72 (1957): 27-42.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1039">
            <bib> -----. "Notes on Villasandino's Versification." Hispanic Review 13 (1945):
                185-96.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1040">
            <bib> -----. "On the Versification of Alberto Lista." Romanic Review 43 (1952):
                109-16.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1041">
            <bib> -----. "Remarks on the Early Romances and Cantares." Hispanic Review 17 (1949):
                89–123.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1042">
            <bib> -----. "Some Observations on Castilian Versification of the Neoclassic Period
                [1750–1830]." Hispanic Review 20 (1952): 223-39.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1043">
            <bib> -----. "The Spanish Octosyllable: Galician-Portuguese and Provençal Origins."
                Hispanic Review 10 (1942): 1–11.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1044">
            <bib> -----. "Versification in Alfonso el Sabio's Cantigas." Hispanic Review 23 (1955):
                83-98.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1045">
            <bib> Corriente, F. "Accento y cantidad en la fonologia del hispano-arabe: Observaciones
                estandisticas en torno a la naturalez del sistema metrico de la poesia popular
                andalusi." Al-Andalus: Revista de las esculas de estudios arabes de Madrid y Granada
                41 (1976): 1–13.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1046">
            <bib> Cortazar, Eduardo de. "Observaciones sobre versificación." Revista de españa 91
                (1883): 332–46; 92 (1883): 206–21; 93 (1883): 80–100.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1047">
            <bib> Da Silva Correia, Joao. A rima e a sua acçao linguistica e ideologica. Lisbon,
                1930.</bib>
            <notes> Grammont's (L834) method applied to Portuguese verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1048">
            <bib> Davison, Ned J. Sound Patterns in a Poem of José Martí: An Examination of Phonemic
                Structures and Poetic Musicality. Salt Lake City: Damuir Press, 1975. 118 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1049">
            <bib> Deus, Joao de. Prosódia portugueza: Estudio prévio da orthographia. Coimbra, 1909.
                98 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1050">
            <bib> Díez Echarri, Emiliano. Teorías métricas del siglo de oro, apuntes para la
                historia del verso español. Madrid, 1949; rpt 1970. 355 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1051">
            <bib> Diez, Friedrich. "Form." Über die erste portugiesische Kunst- und Hofpoesie. Bonn:
                Eduard Weber, 1863. pp. 36-72.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1052">
            <bib> Domínguez Caparrós, José. Contribucion a la historia de las teorías métricas en
                los siglos XVIII y XIX. Madrid: Impr. Aguirre, 1975. 544 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1053">
            <bib> Elementos formales en la lirica actual. [Santander, Spain: Universidad
                Internacional Menandez Pelayo, 1967.] 227 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Thirteen essays on historical metrics. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1054">
            <bib> Espinosa, Aurelio M. "Notes on the Versification of El Misterio de los Reyes
                Magos." Romanic Review 6 (1915): 378-401.</bib>
            <notes>Response by Lang, "A Correction," in 7 (1916): 345–49; replay by E. in 8 (1917):
                88-98.</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1055">
            <bib> Fitz-Gerald, John D. "Versification of the Cuaderna Via as Found in Berceo's Vida
                de Santa Domingo de Silos." Diss., Columbia University, 1906. Rpt New York: AMS
                Press, 1966. 112 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1056">
            <bib> Fonseca, José de. Tratado de versificaçao portugueze.</bib>
            <notes> Cited in Gayley and Scott (L46) but not listed in either NUC or BMC. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1057">
            <bib> Gale, G. R. "Sebastián de Córdoba's Poetic Craftsmanship." MLN 84 (1969):
                308-14.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1058">
            <bib> García Calvo, Agustín. Del ritmo del lenguaje. Barcelona, 1975. 89 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1059">
            <bib> Gillet, Joseph E., and E. B. Williams. "Tragedia de los Amores de Eneas y de la
                Rena Dido." PMLA 46 (1931): 353–431. "Versification," pp. 364-67.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1060">
            <bib> Gilman, S. "The Poetry of the Poema and the Music of the Cantar." PQ 51 (1972):
                1–11.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1061">
            <bib> Gitlitz, David M. "Hacia una definición empirica de la aliteración." Nueva revista
                de filologia hispánica 22 (1973): 85-90.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1062">
            <bib> Hall, R. A., Jr. "Old Spanish Stress-Timed Verse and the Germanic Superstratum."
                Romance Philology 19 (1965): 227-34.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1063">
            <bib> Henriquez Urenña, Pedro. La versificación irregular en la poesía española. Madrid,
                1920. 338 pp.; 2nd ed. 1933 with last word of title castellana; revised and rpt. as
                Estudios de versificación española. Buenos Aires: Universidad de Buenos Aires
                Departmento Editorial, 1961. Rev: by W. P. Ker in MLR 18 (1923): 226-29.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1064">
            <bib> Herrera Zapién, Tarsicio. La métrica latinizante: estudio acerca de la teoría y la
                práctica de los metros latinos en italiano, frances, inglés, alemán y castellano:
                ejemplos traducidos métricamente al castellano. Ciudad Universitaria, México:
                Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México, Instituto de Investigaciones Filológicas,
                1975. 225 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A comparative account of the transmission of the classical Latin meters through
                medieval Latin into the modern Western languages--German, Italian, Spanish, Romance,
                and English--with attention to the competing theories of meter and the modern
                attempts to imitate classical quantitative verse. Designed expressly for the Spanish
                reader. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1065">
            <bib> Hilborn, H. W. "Calderón's Silvas." PMLA 58 (1943): 122-48.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1066">
            <bib> Lang, Henry R. "Notes on the Metre of the Poem of the Cid." Romanic Review 5
                (1914): 1–30, 295–349; 8 (1917): 241–78, 401-33.</bib>
            <notes>Critique by Espinosa in 8 (1917): 88-98. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1067">
            <bib> -----. "The Metrical Forms of the Poem of the Cid." PMLA 42 (1927): 523–
                603.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1068">
            <bib> Lapesa, R. "El endecasilabo en los conetos de santillana." Romance Philology 10
                (1957): 180-85.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1069">
            <bib> Le Gentil, P. "Discussions sur la versification espagnole médiévale--à propos d'un
                livre récent." Romance Philology 12 (1958): 1–32.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1070">
            <bib> Leonard, W. E. "The Recovery of the Metre of the Cid." PMLA 46 (1931):
                289-306.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1071">
            <bib> López Estrada, Francisco. Métrica española del siglo XX. Madrid, 1974. 226
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1072">
            <bib> McSpadden, George F. "Phonetics, Intonation, Metrics, and Stylistics." Patterns of
                Literary Style. Ed. Joseph Strelka. University Park: Pennsylvania State University
                Press, 1971. pp. 116-29.</bib>
            <notes>Praises the work of Navarro (L1082) in acoustics and metrics. The last two
                sections of this article present analysis of sound-spectrograph recordings of some
                poetry but mainly sentences from the Don Quijote. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1073">
            <bib> Malkiel, M. R. Lida de. "Notas para el texto de la Vida de Santa Oria." Romance
                Philology 10 (1956): 28-33.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1074">
            <bib> Mapes, E. K. "Innovation and French Influence on the Metrics of Ruben Darío." PMLA
                49 (1934): 310-26.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1075">
            <bib> Mariner Bigorra, Sebastian. "Hacia una métrica estructural." Revista española de
                linguistica 1 (1971): 299-334.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1076">
            <bib> Méndez Bejarano, Mario. La ciencia del verso: teoria general de la versificación
                con aplicaciones à la métrica española. Madrid, 1907; 2nd ed. 1908. 454 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1077">
            <bib> Milá y Fontanals, Manuel. "Historia literaria del decasilabo y endecasilabo
                anapésticos." Revista histórica-latina, no. 7 (1875), pp. 181–92;</bib>
            <notes> rpt. in his Obras completas. Barcelona, 1893. pp. 324-44.</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1078">
            <bib> Morley, S. Griswold. "Recent Theories About the Meter of the Cid." PMLA 48 (1933):
                965-80.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1079">
            <bib> -----. Studies in Spanish Dramatic Versification of the Siglo de Oro. University
                of California Publications in Modern Philology, vol. 7, no. 3. Berkeley: University
                of California Press, 1918.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1080">
            <bib> Myers, O. T. "Assonance and Tense in the Poema del Cid." PMLA 81 (1966):
                493-98.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1081">
            <bib> -----. "Syntactic and Formal Correlates with Rhythm in the Spanish Octosyllable."
                Romance Philology 20 (1967): 478-88.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1082">
            <bib> Navarro-Tomás, J. Métrica española: Reseña histórica y descriptiva. Syracuse,
                N.Y.: Syracuse University Press, 1956. 556 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1083">
            <bib> Nelson, Dana A. "Syncopation in El Libro de Alexandre." PMLA 87 (1972):
                1023-38.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1084">
            <bib> Nelson, Lowry, Jr. "Spanish [Versification]." Wimsatt (A20), pp. 165-76.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1085">
            <bib> Olsen, Carroll L. "Rhythmical Patterns and Syllabic Features of the Spanish
                Sense-Group." Proceedings of the Seventh International Congress of Phonetic
                Sciences. Ed. André Rigault and R. Charbonneau. The Hague: Mouton, 1972. pp.
                990-96.</bib>
            <notes>Tabulates types and frequencies of stress-patterns in nearly 1500 sample phrases,
                the most common being uu/u. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1086">
            <bib> Parker, J. H. "The Chronology of the Plays of Juan Pérez de Montalván." PMLA 67
                (1952): 186-210.</bib>
            <notes>Based on metrical tests. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1087">
            <bib> -----. "The Versification of the Comedies of Antonio de Solís y Rivadeneyra."
                Hispanic Review 17 (1949): 308-15.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1088">
            <bib> Pimenta, A. Tratado de versificaçao portugueza. Lisbon, 1928.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1089">
            <bib> Predmore, R. L. "El tiempo en la poesía de Antonio Machado." PMLA 63 (1948):
                696-711.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1090">
            <bib> Quilis, Antonio. Métrica española. 2nd ed. Madrid, 1973. 194 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1091">
            <bib> Riquer, M. de. Resumen de versificación española. Barcelona, 1950.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1092">
            <bib> Rosario, Rubén del. El endecasílabo español. San Juan, 1944.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1093">
            <bib> Roubaud, Jacques. "Mètre et vers: Deux Applications de la métrique générative de
                Halle-Keyser." Poétique: Revue de théorie et d'analyse littéraires 7 (1971): 366–
                87.</bib>
            <notes> Application to Troubadour and Castillian (Arte Mayor) verse. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1094">
            <bib> Saavedra Molina, Julio. El octosílabo castellano. Santiago de Chile, 1945. 169
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1095">
            <bib> -----. Tres grandes metros: el eneasilabo, el tredecasilabo y el endecasilabo.
                Santiago de Chile, 1946. 125 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1096">
            <bib> Schökel, L. A. Estética y estilística del ritmo poético. Barcelona, 1959.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1097">
            <bib> Smith, C. "On Sound Patterning in the Poema de mio Cid." Hispanic Review 44
                (1976): 223-37.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1098">
            <bib> Smith, C. C. "La Musicalidad del Polifemo. Revista de filologia española 44
                (1961): 139-66.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1099">
            <bib> Stern, Samuel M. Hispano-Arabic Strophic Poetry. Ed. L. P. Harvey. Oxford:
                Clarendon Press, 1974.</bib>
            <notes> Chapter 2 on Form. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1100">
            <bib> Szoverffy, Joseph. "A Preliminary Survey of Medieval Spanish and Portuguese
                Hymnody." Classical Folia 24 (1970): 187-253.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1101">
            <bib> Turner, Ronald C. "An Automated Procedure for Quantification of Rhythmical
                Patterning in Spanish." Linguistics, no. 121 (1974), pp. 89-98.</bib>
            <notes> The routine devised here calculates "rhythmical tightness," via phonetic tran-
                scription and the Entropy theorem in information theory. See Kondratov (L1321).
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1102">
            <bib> -----. "Rhythmical Ordering as a Parameter of Linguistic Style." Pacific Coast
                Philology 5 (1970): 67-72.</bib>
            <notes> A computer program is presented which scans verbal texts for rhythmical or-
                derliness ("tightness" or "looseness"), the conception of rhythm being based on the
                Shannon entropy equations in information theory. And though the proce- dure tells us
                nothing about meter, it does employ the metrical concept of the "foot" in
                tabulation, and its final rankings of texts (as to degree of rhythmical- ness) match
                very well our intuitive judgments of "poetry" versus "novel" and "speech." The
                underlying question raised is whether or not the brain itself de- rives (then
                predicts) such characteristic curves of rhythmicity for verbal texts. Sample texts
                are Spanish. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1103">
            <bib> Vaz Ferreira, Carlos. Sobre la percepción métrica. Buenos Aires, 1956. 180
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1104">
            <bib> Vicuña Cifuentes, Julio. Estudios de métrica española. Santiago, 1929. 264
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1105">
            <bib> Wallis, Ethel E. "The Trimodal Structure of a Folk Poem." Word 26 (1970):
                170-93.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1106">
            <bib> Ware, N. J. "The Testimony of Classical Names in Support of Metrical Regularity in
                the Libro de Alexandre." Hispanic Review 35 (1967): 211-26.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1107">
            <bib> Wilson, E. M. "Coplas contradictorias: the Perils of Double-Edged Verses."
                Hispanic Review 37 (1969): 228-37.</bib>
            <notes>See also: E1121, L75. Italian </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L110">
            <bib> 8 Amrein-Widmer, Martha. Rhythmus als Ausdruck inneren Erlebens in Dantes Divina
                Commedia. Diss., Zurich, 1932.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L110">
            <bib> 8a Avalle, D'Arco Silvio. Preistoria dell'endecasillabo. Milan, 1963.</bib>
            <notes> MOVED here from L1126 </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1109">
            <bib> Balbi, F. Della versificazione italiana. Milan, 1881. 63 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1110">
            <bib> Baratella, Francesco. Compendio dell'arte ritmica [1447]. Rpt in Collezione di
                opere inedite o rare. Bologna: G. Romagnoli, 1869. pp. 177-240.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1111">
            <bib> Barengo, G. Della versificazione italiana. Venice, 1854.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1112">
            <bib> Baxter, Arthur H. The Introduction of Classical Metres into Italian Poetry and
                their Development to the Beginning of the Nineteenth Century. Diss., Johns Hopkins
                University, 1898. Baltimore: John Murphy, 1901. 33 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1113">
            <bib> Beccaria, G. L. Ritmo e melodia nella prosa italiana: Studie ricerche sulla prosa
                d'arte. Florence, 1964. 334 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Rev: in Romance Philology 19 (1966): 615-18.</notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1114">
            <bib> Bertinetto, Pier Marco. Ritmo e modelli ritmici: Analisi computazionale dell
                funzioni periodiche nella versificazione Dantesca. Torino, 1973. 169 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1115">
            <bib> Biadene, L. Il collegamento delle stanze mediante la rima nella canzone dei secoli
                XIII e XIV. Florence, 1885. 16 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1116">
            <bib> Biai, Emilia. "Aspetti stilistica e metrici delle rime dell'Ariosto." Rassegna
                della letteratura italiana 79 (1975): 46-52.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1117">
            <bib> Boyde, P. "A Note on Dante's Metric and Versification." In Dante's Lyric Poetry.
                Ed. K. Foster and P. Boyde. 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1967. Vol. 1, pp.
                xliv–lv.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L111">
            <bib> 7a Canepari, Luciano. "Elementi prosodici: Classificazione e notazione." Lingua e
                stile 11 (1976): 479-91.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1118">
            <bib> Capovilla, Guido. "Le ballate del Petrarca e il codice metrico due-trecentesco:
                Casi di connessioni interne e di monostrofismo nella ballate italiana 'antica.'"
                Giornale storico della letteratura italiana 154 (1977): 238-60.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1119">
            <bib> Casini, Tommaso. Sulle forme metriche italiane. Florence, 1884; 2nd ed. (titled La
                forme . . . ), 1900. 111 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1120">
            <bib> Cavallini, Giorgio. "La Metrica parte integrante del significato." Studium 73
                (1977): 213-26.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1121">
            <bib> Cetti, Carlo. L'arte di poetare. Como, 1958. 94 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1122">
            <bib> Contini, G. "Innovazioni metriche italiane Fra Otto e novecento." Forum Italicum 3
                (1969): 171-85.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L112">
            <bib> 2a Cremante, Renzo. "Nota sull''enjambement.'" Lingua e stile 2 (1967):
                377-91.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1123">
            <bib> Cremante, Renzo, and Mario Pazzaglia, eds. La metrica. Bologna: Società editrice
                il Mulino, 1972. 513 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A compendious anthology. Part I: Metrical Theory; Part II: Italian Metrics. Part
                I contains sections on "Problems in Versification," "Meter, Rhyme, Euphony,"
                "Typology and Scansion," and "Meter, Syntax, and Signification." Very extensive
                Bibliography. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1124">
            <bib> Dante Alighieri. Dante's Treatise "De Vulgari Eloquentia" Translated into English,
                with Explanatory Notes. Tr. A. G. F. Howell. London, 1890.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1125">
            <bib> -----. Literary Criticism of Dante Alighieri. Ed. and tr. Robert S. Haller.
                Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1973.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1126">
            <bib> MOVED to L1108a</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1127">
            <bib> Di Cupua, Francesco. Appunti sul "cursus" o ritmo prosaico nelle opere latine di
                Dante Alighieri con note critiche sull'epistole dantesche. Castellammare,
                1919.</bib>
            <notes> On the cursus in Dante's Latin prose. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1128">
            <bib> -----. "Il ritmo prosaico in Petronio." Giornale italiano di filologia 1 (1948):
                37-55.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1129">
            <bib> Di Girolamo, Costanzo. "Questioni metriche: La teoria di Halle e Keyser e le sue
                possibili applicazioni italiane." Belfagor 31 (1976): 224-31.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1129a">
            <bib> Durante, M. "Prosa ritmica, alliterazione e accento nelle lingue dell'Italia
                antica." Ricerche linguistische 4 (1958): 61-98.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1130">
            <bib> Elwert, W. Theodor. Italienische Metrik. Munich, 1968.</bib>
            <notes> Translated as Versificazione italiana dalle origini ai giorni nostri. Firenze,
                1973. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1131">
            <bib> Falconi, L. Metrica classica, o metrica barbara? Vienna, 1885.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1132">
            <bib> Federzoni, Giovanni. Dei versi e dei metri italiani. Bologna, 1904; 4th ed.
                1912.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1132a">
            <bib> Ferrarino, P. "L'alliterazione." Rendiconte delle sessioni della R. Academia delle
                Scienze dell'Instituto di Bologna, Classe di Scienze Morali, sect. 4, vol. 2 (1938–
                39), pp. 93–175.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1133">
            <bib> Finzi, Giusseppi. Principii di stilistica versificazione e metrica italiana con un
                dizionarietto di modi errati. Turin, 1887.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1134">
            <bib> Flamini, Francesco. Notizia storica dei versi et metri italiani dal medioevo al
                tempi nostri. Leghorn, 1919.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1135">
            <bib> Fubini, M. Metrica e poesia, lezioni sulle forme metriche italiana. Milan,
                1962.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1136">
            <bib> Garlanda, Federico. L'alliterazione nel dramma shakespeariano e nelle poesia
                italiana. Rome, 1906. 77 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Only twelve of the seventy-seven pages in this study are devoted to Shake-
                speare, and the great bulk of these consists of long sample passages. Italian po-
                etry is discussed from Dante to Carducci, the major part on the former. Slight.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1137">
            <bib> Giamatti, A. Bartlett. "Italian [Versification]." Wimsatt (A20), pp. 148-64.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1138">
            <bib> Gifford, George H. "Metrical Patterns in the Divine Comedy." A Dante Symposium in
                Commemoration of the 700th Anniversary of the Poet's Birth (1265–1965). Chapel Hill:
                University of North Carolina Press, 1965. pp. 75-85.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1139">
            <bib> Grandgent, C. H. "Dante's Verse." SP 17 (1920): 1–18.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1140">
            <bib> Gray, L. H. "Possible Trochaic Dimeters in Non-Latin Italic and in Gaulish
                Inscriptions." American Journal of Philology 63 (1942): 433-43.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1141">
            <bib> Guarnerio, P. E. Manuale di versificazione italiana. Milan, 1893.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1142">
            <bib> Guoli, D. "La rima e la poesia italiana." Nuova antologia, 1876.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1143">
            <bib> Ker, W. P. "Dante Guido Guinicelli, and Arnaut Daniel." MLR 4 (1909): 145–
                52.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1144">
            <bib> -----. "De Superbia Carminum." MLR 13 (1918): 292–96; rpt. in his Form and Style
                in Poetry (B115), pp. 332-37.</bib>
            <notes>On the Dantean hendecasyllable ("the noblest line") and the heptasyllable. A
                study in comparative verseforms. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1145">
            <bib> Kleinhenz, Christopher. "Stylistic Gravity: Language and Prose Rhythms in
                Decameron I, 4." Humanities Association Review 26 (1975): 289-99.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1146">
            <bib> Kurzweil, Edouard. Traité de la prosodie de la langue italienne, basé sur
                l'analyse étymologique des mots. Paris, 1862. 58 pp.</bib>
            <notes> A short explanation of accentuation rules in a tonic versification for French
                readers unaccustomed to such. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1147">
            <bib> Leonetti, Pasquale. Storia della tecnica del verso italiano. Rome, 1933.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1148">
            <bib> -----. La tecnica del verso dialettale popularesco dei primorddi. Naples,
                1934.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1149">
            <bib> Levi, Attilio. Della versificazione. Genoa, 1931.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1150">
            <bib> -----. "Della versificazione italiana." Archivum Romanticum 14 (1930):
                449-526.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1151">
            <bib> Lisio, Giuseppe. L'arte del periodo nelle opere volgari di Danti Alighieri e del
                secolo XIII. Bologna, 1902.</bib>
            <notes> Analyzes rhythmic cadences in Dante's vernacular writings vis à vis Latin prose
                rhythms. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1152">
            <bib> -----. Studio su la forma metrica della canzone italiana nel secolo XIII. Imola,
                1895. 48 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1153">
            <bib> Lollis, C. de. Saggi sulla forma poetica italiana dell' ottocento. Bari, 1929. 290
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1154">
            <bib> Mari, Giovanni. Riassunto e dizionarietto di ritmica italiana. Turin, 1901. 159
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1155">
            <bib> Melodia, G. Studi sulle rime del Petrarca. Catania, 1909. 187 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1156">
            <bib> Murari, R. Ritmica e metrica razionale italiana. Milan, 1891, 1909; 4th ed. 1927.
                230 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1157">
            <bib> Mussafia, A. "Sul metro di due componimenti poetici di Filippo de Beaumanoir, ed.
                Suchier." Romania 15 (1886): 423-30.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1158">
            <bib> Napoli, Donna Jo. "The Metrics of Italian Nursery Rhymes." Language and Style 11
                (1978): 40-58.</bib>
            <notes> To the general Halle-Keyser rule that no Stress Maximum may fall in a W po-
                sition, Napoli adds one Correspondence Rule specifically for Italian: the first S
                position in a line is "optionally and frequently" realized by an unstressed sylla-
                ble. The nursery rhymes are often composed in half-lines, ambiguously iambic or
                trochaic, the trochaic analysis having some advantage. Also noted are line
                structures of "metrical nesting" and "metrical mirror-images." </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1159">
            <bib> Ovidio, Francesco d'. "La metrica della canzone secondo Dante." In his Saggi
                Critici. Naples, 1878. pp. 416-36.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1160">
            <bib> -----. Versificazione italiana e arte poetica medioevale. Milan, 1910. 750
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1161">
            <bib> -----. Versificazione romanza, poetica e poesia medioevale. 3 vols. Naples,
                1932.</bib>
            <notes> These are also vols. 10–11 of his Opere. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1162">
            <bib> Parodi, E. G. "Observazioni sul 'cursus' nelle opere latine e volgari del
                Boccaccio." In Studii su G. Boccaccio. Florence, 1913. p. 232 ff.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L116">
            <bib> 2a Pazzaglia, Mario. "Figure metriche pascoliane: i novenari di castelvecchio."
                Lingua e stile 7 (1972): 47-80.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L116">
            <bib> 2b -----. "Note sulla metrica delle prime canzoni dantesche." Lingua e stile 3
                (1968): 319-31.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1163">
            <bib> -----. "Rassegna di studi di metrica italiana." Lettere italiane 29 (1977):
                207-32.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1164">
            <bib> -----. "Ricerche sulla versificazione." Lingua e stile 5 (1970): 457-85.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1165">
            <bib> -----. Teoria e analisi metrica. Bologna, 1974. 268 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1166">
            <bib> -----. Il verso e l'arte della canzone del "De Vulgari Eloquentia." Florence,
                1968.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1167">
            <bib> Platania d'Antoni, R. Rimario universale della lingua italiana. Acireale, 1892.
                592 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1168">
            <bib> Rivers, Elias L. "Certain Formal Characteristics of the Primitive Love Sonnet."
                Speculum 33 (1958): 42-55.</bib>
            <notes> Part I examines metrical and syntactic patterns; the texts are poems of Gia-
                como da Lentino, author of the earliest extant sonnets. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L116">
            <bib> 8a Sansone, G. E. "Assaggio di simmetrie petrarchesche." Lingua e stile 6 (1971):
                223-40.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L116">
            <bib> 8b -----. "Per un'analisi strutturale dell'endecasillabo." Lingua e stile 2
                (1967): 179-97.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1169">
            <bib> Scaglione, A. D. "Periodic Syntax and Flexible Meter in the Divina Commedia."
                Romance Philology 21 (1967): 1–22.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1170">
            <bib> Schmitt, John. "La metrica di Fra Jacopone." Studi medievali 1 (1904–5): 515
                ff.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1171">
            <bib> Serretta, M. Endecasillabi crescenti nella poesia italiana delle origini e nel
                canzoniere del Petrarca. Milan, 1938. 245 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1172">
            <bib> Solerti, Angelo. Manuale di metrica classica italiana ad accento ritmico. Turin,
                1886. 103 pp.</bib>
            <notes> Differentiates accento grammaticale from accento ritmico in quantitative verse.
            </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1173">
            <bib> Spongano, R. Nozione ed esempi di metrica italiana. Bologna, 1966.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1174">
            <bib> Steadman, John M. "Verse Without Rime: Sixteenth-Century Italian Defences of Versi
                Sciolti." Italica 41 (1964): 384-402.</bib>
            <notes>An analysis of the theoretical defences of unrhymed verse in Italy by Trissino,
                Muzio, and Giraldi. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1175">
            <bib> Tatlock, J. S. P. "Dante's Terza Rima." PMLA 51 (1936): 895-903.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1176">
            <bib> Taylor, Robert L. Alliteration in Italian. Diss., Yale University, 1900. New
                Haven: Tuttle, Morehouse, &amp; Taylor, 1900. 151 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1177">
            <bib> Tecnica e teoria letteraria. Ed. G. Getto et al. Milan, 1948. 281 pp.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1178">
            <bib> Tempo, Antonio da. Summa artis rithmici [ca. 1332]. Rpt. as Trattato della rime
                volgari in Collezione di opere inedite o rare. Bologna: G. Romagnoli, 1869, pp.
                67–175</bib>
            <notes>, with a long preceding Introduction. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1179">
            <bib> Tolomei, Claudio. Versie regole della nuovo poesia. 1539.</bib>
            <notes> The first Renaissance attempt to render the classical quantitative meters into a
                modern language. </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1180">
            <bib> Toynbee, Paget. "Appendix C: Dante and the Cursus." Dantis Alagherii Epistolae:
                The Letters of Dante. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1920. pp. 22–47. Taken in part from
                MLR 13 (1918): 420-30.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1181">
            <bib> -----. "The Bearing of the Cursus on the Text of Dante's De Vulgari Eloquentia."
                Proceedings of the British Academy 10 (1921–23): 359-77.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1182">
            <bib> Tozer, H. F. "An Essay on the Metre of the Divina Commedia." Contributions to the
                Textual Criticism of the Divina Commedia. Ed. Edward Moore. Cambridge: Cambridge
                University Press, 1889. pp. 713-23.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1183">
            <bib> Valesio, Paolo. "Problemi di metrica: une esperimento di tipologia italo-russa."
                Lingua e stile 1 (1966): 305-21.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1184">
            <bib> Verde, R. Studio sulle rime del Petrarca. Catania, 1939.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1185">
            <bib> Vincent, E. R. "Dante's Choice of Words." Italian Studies 10 (1955): 1–18.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1186">
            <bib> Vittori, Fiorenza. "Perche la metrica?" Italianistica: Rivista di letteratura
                italiana 6 (1977): 380-86.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1187">
            <bib> Vossler, Karl. "Stil, Rhythmus und Reim in ihrer Wechselwirkung bei Petrarca und
                Leopardi." Miscellanea di studi critici in onore di Arturo Graf. Bergamo, 1903. pp.
                453-81.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1188">
            <bib> Wheelock, James T. S. "Alliterative Functions in the Divina Commedia." Lingua e
                stile 13 (1978): 373-404.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1189">
            <bib> Wild, Friedrich. "über die Verstechnik der Verfassers der me. Umdichtung von
                Boccaccios 'De Claris Mulieribus.'" Neusprachliche Studien: Festgabe Karl Luick. In
                Die Neuren Sprachen, Supplement 6. Marburg: N. G. Elwert, 1925. pp. 90– 99.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>



        <item id="L1190">
            <bib> Wilkins, E. H. "The Invention of the Sonnet." MP 13 (1915–16): 463-94.</bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>



        <item id="L1191">
            <bib> Zambaldi, [?]. Il ritmo dei versi italiani. Turin, 1875. </bib>
            <notes/>
        </item>
    </chapter>
</bibliography>
