<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
  <chapter title="APPENDIX C: POETRY AND MUSIC AS METRICAL ANALOGUES">


    <item id="N1">
      <bib> Adams, Stephen J. "Ezra Pound and Music." DAI 37 (1977): 7746A.</bib>
      <notes> Three relationships of music to verse are discerned: as subject, as structure, and as
        element of melopoeia. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N2">
      <bib> Alexander, John M. "'Ut Musica Poesis' in Eighteenth Century Aesthetics." English
        Miscellany 24 (1973–74): 129-52.</bib>
      <notes>This profuse essay treats not the structural correspondences of poetry and music but
        rather the similar effects on the emotions which the eighteenth century at- tributed to
        them. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N3">
      <bib> Amis, George T. "The Meter and Meaning of Nashe's 'Adieu, Farewell Earths Blisse.'"
        English Literary Renaissance 9 (1979): 78–85.</bib>
      <notes> Yvor Winters took the song's meter as iambic trimeter, J. V. Cunningham as iambs and
        amphimacers, but if we recognize the song as song, we will see that its lines alternate
        between four and three stresses, the four-stress line being the norm, as in nearly all
        Western music. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N4">
      <bib> Armour, Eugene. "The Melodic and Rhythmic Characteristics of the Music of the
        Traditional Ballad Variants Found in the Southern Appalachians." DAI 22 (1962): 4368A (New
        York University).</bib>
      <notes> Analysis of random tunes of the Child ballads in Cecil Sharp's English Folk Songs from
        the Southern Appalachians produced 187 tunes in 14 melodic modes and extensive statistical
        information on intervals, contours, syncopation, and rhythmic figures. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N5">
      <bib> Booth, Mark W. "The Art of Words in Songs." Quarterly Journal of Speech 62 (1976):
        242-49.</bib>
      <notes>Intent to explicate the relation of lyrics to their accompanying music, Booth
        differentiates the words in songs from true oral poetry and from written texts of poems. It
        comes to this: poetry can Make It New, whereas songs can only reinforce the known: they
        "must say things that are . . . generally familiar sim- plifications." Long discussion of
        devices for repetition. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N6">
      <bib> Boswell, George W. "Metrical Alteration in Folksinging." Journal of American Folklore 85
        (1972): 248-59.</bib>
      <notes>Changes of meter within the performance of a folksong are sometimes im- provisations or
        free variations but also demonstrate the control of text over tune in ballads. The article
        examines over a hundred examples. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N7">
      <bib> -----. "Pitch: Musical and Verbal in Folksong." Yearbook of the International Folk Music
        Council 9 (1977): 80–88.</bib>
      <notes> Boswell wishes to compare the pitch-pattern of a ballad tune with that of the vowels
        in a reading of its text, but since phonetics experts themselves are un- certain of precise
        vowel heights, he is forced to graph out a number of "for- mants" (energy fields and levels)
        both separately and in combination. The low- est formant alone matches most closely.
      </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N8">
      <bib> -----. "Reciprocal Controls Exerted by Ballad Texts and Tunes." Journal of American
        Folklore 80 (1967): 169-74.</bib>
      <notes>For sheer compression of specific information on the interaction of linguistic and
        musical patterns this essay has no equal. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N9">
      <bib> -----. "Shaping Controls of Ballad Tunes Over Their Texts." Tennessee Folklore Society
        Bulletin 17 (1951): 9–18.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N10">
      <bib> -----. "Stanza Form and Music-Imposed Scansion in Southern Ballads." Southern Folklore
        Quarterly 31 (1967): 320-31.</bib>
      <notes>A discursive catalogue of the meters and accompanying time-signatures of the Child
        ballads; the most common setting by far is 4/4 time, since it points up dipodic stressing.
        Boswell considers it a moot point that text controls tune. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N10">
      <bib> a -----. "Verse and Music in the Sacred Harp." Southern Folklore Quarterly 34 (1970):
        53–61.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N11">
      <bib> Brennecke, Ernest, Jr. "Dryden's Odes and Draghi's Music." PMLA 49 (1934): 1–36.</bib>
      <notes> An analysis of the 1687 "Song for St. Cecilia's Day" as compared to the earlier and
        less-orchestrated "Alexander's Feast," to show how Dryden mastered the techniques of vocal
        polyphony, antiphony, and sequence in the construction of his choral ode. This meticulous
        study shows Dryden's grasp of the demands of pure verbal phrasing and of pure melodic
        structure, and the concessions of the two forms to fit each other when melded, to be a very
        sure grasp indeed. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N12">
      <bib> Bridges, Robert. Preface to his Ode for the Bicentennary Commemoration of Henry Purcell,
        with other poems and a preface on the musical setting of poetry. London: Elkin Mathews,
        1896. pp. 5–18</bib>
      <notes>. Rpt. as On the Musical Setting of Poetry. No. 21 of his Collected Essays, Papers,
        &amp;amp;c. London: Oxford University Press, 1927– 35. Vol. 9, pp. 3–16. See also No. 22, "A
        Practical Discourse on Some Principles of Hymn- Singing"; No. 24, "English Chanting"; and
        No. 26, "Psalms Noted in Speech- Rhythm" in the same volume. Bridges defends the publication
        of his Ode as a poem (divested of its music) by denying that "declamatory" music "is able
        satisfactorily to interpret" poetry. He adduces eight reasons, generally to the effect that
        the rhythmic and inflectional systems for music and speech are different. "The repetitions
        in music and po- etry are incompatable." The reader should see N58 and may then wish to
        consult: </notes>
    </item>


    <item id="N13">
      <bib> Byard, Herbert. "Robert Bridges: Church Musician." Music &amp;amp; Letters 53 (1972):
        44-55.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N14">
      <bib> Bronson, Bertrand H. "The Interdependence of Ballad Tunes and Texts." California
        Folklore Quarterly 3 (1944): 185–207</bib>
      <notes>; rpt. in The Critics and The Ballad. Ed. MacEdward Leach and T. P. Coffin. Carbondale:
        Southern Illinois University Press, 1963. pp. 77–102. Instances of various sorts of problems
        in determining form. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N15">
      <bib> -----. "Literature and Music." Relations of Literary Study. Ed. James Thorpe. New York:
        MLA, 1967. pp. 127-50.</bib>
      <notes>See pp. 134–42: Bronson shows to what extremes of felicity and infelicity po- etic
        texts can be taken when set to music, and in particular he shows how much Herrick's poems
        will suffer when deprived of their unique typographic form and set to some common meter. Yet
        on the other hand some Herrick verses can be set to a ballad tune with unexpected ease,
        suggesting that perhaps Herrick knew some ballad music. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N16">
      <bib> -----. "On the Union of Words and Music in the 'Child' Ballads." Western Folklore 11
        (1952): 233-49.</bib>
      <notes>Historical scholarship suggests that a tune is not transmitted intact but in a se- ries
        of variants, all close relatives of a "melodic family," even as a ballad text will show
        considerable variation yet preserve intact a general, kernel idea. Many texts may be set to
        a given tune, so that the old Gregorian conception of musical modes seems not to be borne
        out. About tempo we know little, but iambic-trochaic meters usually fall into triple
        (actually dotted duple) time when given temporal values, the stresses being naturally
        lengthened a bit. Much valuable information in this ranging article. Cf. Coffin (E864).
      </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N17">
      <bib> -----. "Traditional Ballads Musically Considered." Critical Inquiry 2 (1975):
        29-42.</bib>
      <notes> With graceful erudition, Bronson offers a series of observations on the relations of
        text and tune in the evolution of the ballad; some of the remarks are bril- liant
        suggestions. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N18">
      <bib> Brown, Calvin S. Music and Literature: A Comparison of the Arts. Athens, Ga.: University
        of Georgia Press, 1948.</bib>
      <notes> Rev.: in Comparative Literature 2 (1950): 370-73.The major monograph by the major
        authority in the field. Chapters 2 and 3 (the first of these on "Rhythm and Pitch") face
        most directly the metrical fea- tures in speech, verse, and music; thereafter, chapters 5,
        6, and 7 discuss the setting of words to music. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N19">
      <bib> -----. "Musico-Literary Research in the Last Two Decades." Yearbook of Comparative and
        General Literature, no. 19 (1970), pp. 5–27.</bib>
      <notes> An invaluable general review essay, cogently organized, assessing the best and the
        lastest work in each area. Metrical studies are treated on pp. 24-25. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N20">
      <bib> Brown, John. A Dissertation on the Rise, Union, and Power, the Progressions,
        Separations, and Corruptions, of Poetry and Music. London: L. Davis &amp; C. Reymers,
        1763.</bib>
      <notes> An early comparative treatise on dance and song in the ancient and modern languages,
        both Oriental and Occidental. Section 13 treats the most contem- porary forms. There are
        stray remarks on meter on pp. 228, 235, 236n. See Flasdieck (N52). </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N21">
      <bib> Bryan, Margaret B. "Recent Studies in Campion." English Literary Renaissance 4 (1974):
        404-11.</bib>
      <notes>A review article summarizing the most prominent work on Campion's music and metrics.
      </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N22">
      <bib> Burgess, Anthony. "Viewpoint." TLS, 13 October 1972, p. 1224.</bib>
      <notes> On the frustrations of writing lyrics to perfectly match a score, including the
        paucity of rhymes in English, which necessitate certain guiles: " . . . tragedy, / . . .
        glad you de-/cided to smile." </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N23">
      <bib> Butt, John. "English Music and English Verse." In his Pope, Dickens, and Others: Essays
        and Addresses. Edinburgh: University of Edinburgh Press, 1969. pp. 17– 38.</bib>
      <notes> A fund of fresh and acute observations based on direct and thoughtful inspec- tion of
        texts. Though verse and music share the same medium, time, and some of the same inflectional
        features, their union can only be productive through a series of graceful compromises. The
        poet cannot express the finest shades of nuance without music, but in music a longer time is
        required to establish an "idea" or mood clearly. If the verse is isostrophic then the poet's
        range is se- verely limited, though the musician's task is conversely simplified. Music can
        do nothing with rhyme, poetry, the fugue. Apparently, "musical form and verse form can only
        resemble each other when each is at its loosest." Com- promise, then, is the essence of the
        art. Examples from Campion and Dow- land. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N24">
      <bib> Campbell, Clare. "Music and Poetry, with Some Notes on Benjamin Britten's Setting of
        Words." Critical Quarterly 6 (1964): 253-63.</bib>
      <notes/>
    </item>



    <item id="N25">
      <bib> Childs, Barney. "Articulation in Sound Structures: Some Notes Toward an Analytic." Texas
        Studies in Literature and Language 8 (1966): 423-45.</bib>
      <notes>Many of the problems besetting prosodic analysis are also problems in musi- cology:
        "what is needed is a more powerful and inclusive concept of dealing with the phenomena of
        stress and articulation in any sound structure." The concept is pulse, "not heard but
        intensely felt by each performer and intricately bound up in each performer's physiological
        and psychological sense of time," hence apparently closely related to tempo, and a systemic
        feature set over against the counterpointed system of rhythm and meter. This aspect of
        timing may be denoted by the various typographical indicators of pause, though graphic cues
        are of little assistance to performance. The unit of prominence in any sound structure is an
        "energy construct," established by pulse, said energy being either direct or expectational.
        Childs' "notes toward" a fully coherent synthesis are very widely and astutely informed.
      </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N26">
      <bib> Childs, Robert B. "The Setting of Poetry in the English Madrigal, With an Edition of The
        Teares or Lamentacions of a Sorrowful Soule. DA 20 (1959): 1037A (Stanford).</bib>
      <notes> Includes metrics: thorough technical comparisons. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N27">
      <bib> Clinton-Baddeley, V. C. Words for Music. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1941.
        168 pp.</bib>
      <notes> Rev.: in Review of English Studies 19 (1943): 315-17. Amounts to a comprehensive
        history of the setting of English lyrics to music: widely informed, though discursive, hence
        only occasionally technical. Very close analyses must be looked for elsewhere. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N28">
      <bib> Colles, H[enry] C. Voice and Verse: A Study in English Song. London: Oxford University
        Press, 1928. 167 pp.</bib>
      <notes> The whole book is well worth a thorough perusal, but chapter 1, "The Nature of the
        Case," will suffice for those too busy for long reading, and who there- fore appreciate
        succinct but informed explanations--here, of the setting of po- ems to music. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N29">
      <bib> Cone, Edward T. "Words into Music: The Composer's Approach to the Text." Frye (A15), pp.
        3–15.</bib>
      <notes> An extremely valuable account, adroitly balanced between the too-general and the
        too-minute, giving us concrete, informative examples of the same poem (mainly by Goethe) set
        to music by two different hands and also the variety of aspects within a poem which a
        composer may choose to emphasize by a cer- tain melodic structure. But the most valuable
        point here is that a poem has no one "form" which must be adjusted to or discarded for the
        music; poems have a virtual infinity of latent forms, depending on the perspective, as is
        the case with architecture. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N30">
      <bib> Cooper, Grosvenor W., and Leonard B. Meyer. The Rhythmic Structure of Music. Chicago:
        The University of Chicago Press, 1960. 212 pp.</bib>
      <notes> I am appalled to report that I have seen Cooper and Meyer cited only twice in all the
        work on versification published since 1960. What is remarkable about their pioneering study
        is that--reversing the usual trend--they adopt the termi- nology of verse to explain music.
        The rhythmic structure (i.e. stress-patterns) of music they conceive as composed of a set of
        "architectonic levels," the group of each lower level comprising one unit of the group of
        the next higher level, these groups being termed iamb, trochee, anapest, dactyl, and
        amphimacer. This is a formidable book for anyone not a professional musicologist, but it
        must not be ignored by the metrist. But note Yeston (N140). </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N31">
      <bib> Crist, Bainbridge. The Art of Setting Words to Music. New York: Carl Fischer, 1944. 95
        pp.</bib>
      <notes> A pragmatic treatise by an eminent composer. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N32">
      <bib> Davidson, Audrey. "Milton on the Music of Henry Lawes." Milton Newsletter 2 (1968):
        19-23.</bib>
      <notes> From Milton's encomium on Lawes' settings, Davidson concludes that Milton was
        sensitive to the disposition of quantities in verse, as in music. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N33">
      <bib> Davis, Walter R. "Melodic and Poetic Structure: The Examples of Campion and Dowland."
        Criticism 4 (1962): 89–107.</bib>
      <notes> Two axioms may be established from Renaissance musical treatises: "the music should
        serve the words, not vice versa," and "a primary consideration was clar- ity: music should
        stress words in the development of the lyric's thought." Campion's lyrics show a logical,
        even dialectical structure of contrasts and bal- ances, whereas Dowland preferred the
        strategies of repetition and amplifica- tion, aiming for continuity and unity. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N34">
      <bib> Demmery, Morton. "The Hybrid Critic." Music &amp; Letters 37 (1956): 128-40.</bib>
      <notes>Would be one whose understanding of music was no less informed or incisive than his
        grasp of literary form. Demmery reviews the accomplishments of sev- eral twentieth-and
        eighteenth century (Musical) metrists, then indicates some of the characteristics wanted in
        our Perfect Critic by analyzing Dryden's 1687 "From Harmony, from heav'nly Harmony" (pauses,
        rhymes, meter) and its musical setting by Handel (1739). </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N35">
      <bib> Detweiler, Alan G. "Music and Poetry." British Journal of Aesthetics 1 (1961):
        134-43.</bib>
      <notes>An impressionistic argument that if one views music as a contentless patterning of pure
        sound, he must view poetry identically, whereas if one admits "thought-content" in poetry,
        he should admit its presence in music as well. The difficulty, we are told, is that music
        contains two kinds of content, a "de- scriptive content" and an "artistic content," and
        though the first is susceptible to verbalization the second, for some reason, is not: "it is
        precisely in words that musical thought cannot be expressed. . . . it is only possible to
        render mu- sical thought-content in terms of its own language, that is, by performance. No
        other way of expression is open to us." This way anarchy lies. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N36">
      <bib> Doughtie, Edward. "Sibling Rivalry: Music vs. Poetry in Campion and Others." Criticism
        20 (1978): 1–16.</bib>
      <notes> A discursive examination of Campion's settings, with the aim of a balanced view of his
        accomplishments and failures; Doughtie suggests that part of the motivation for some of the
        settings was that other composers had gotten set- tings of Campion's own songs into print
        even before he had. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N37">
      <bib> -----. "Words for Music: Simplicity and Complexity in the Elizabethan Air." Rice
        University Studies 51 (1965): 1–12.</bib>
      <notes> Assuming that formal simplicity is a requisite for a successful song, Doughtie
        analyzes aspects of structural and verbal simplicity/complexity in verse, show- ing how very
        weak meter may be overcome by vigorous music, and vice versa. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N38">
      <bib> Doughtie, Edward, ed. "Introduction." Lyrics from English Airs: 1592–1622. Cambridge,
        Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1970. pp. 1–41.</bib>
      <notes> Especially sections II and IV. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N39">
      <bib> Draper, John W. "Poetry and Music in Eighteenth-Century Aesthetics." Englische Studien
        67 (1932): 70-85.</bib>
      <notes> See pp. 78–79 for a survey of those writers who identified poetic meter with musical
        scale as correspondent forms of Harmony. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N40">
      <bib> Duckles, Vincent. "John Jenkins's Settings of Lyrics by George Herbert." Musical
        Quarterly 48 (1962): 461-75.</bib>
      <notes/>
    </item>



    <item id="N41">
      <bib> Duckles, Vincent, and F. B. Zimmerman. Words to Music: Papers on English
        Seventeenth-Century Song. Los Angeles: Clark Memorial Library, 1967.</bib>
      <notes> Two essays. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N42">
      <bib> Eldridge, Muriel T. "Thomas Campion: His Poetry and Music (1567–1620): A Study in
        Relationships." DA 19 (1958): 829A (Pennsylvania).</bib>
      <notes> A detailed analysis of Campion settings, including, inter alia, melodic phrasing,
        rhyme schemes, meter, and rhythm (rests, syncopation, stress-shifts, time- signatures, and
        key). </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N43">
      <bib> Engsberg, Richard C. "Two by Two: Analogues of Form in Poetry and Music." DAI 30 (1969):
        278A (New York University).</bib>
      <notes> Finds and explores similarities of form in the poetic line and the musical phrase, on
        multiple levels of analogy, in the work of Pope, Blake, Word- sworth, Browning, and Yeats.
      </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N44">
      <bib> Ericson-Roos, Catarina. The Songs of Robert Burns: A Study of the Unity of Poetry and
        Music. Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell, 1977. 144 pp.</bib>
      <notes> See section 2 of chapter 2 on Rhythm. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N45">
      <bib> Erskine, John. The Elizabethan Lyric. Columbia University Studies in English, no. 2. New
        York: Macmillan, 1903.</bib>
      <notes> Examines the lyric both as song (music) and poem (words) throughout the sixteenth
        century. Included, inter alia, are: "Lyric Quality and Lyric Form," "The Sonnet-series,"
        "The Song-books," and "Metrical Forms in the Elizabe- than Lyric." Lengthy bibliography.
      </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N46">
      <bib> Fabry, Frank J. "The Poetry of the Secular Polyphonic Vocal Forms in England
        (1588–1627)." DAI 25 (1965): 5255A (Texas).</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N47">
      <bib> -----. "Sidney's Poetry and Italian Song-Form." English Literary Renaissance 3 (1973):
        232-48.</bib>
      <notes>Proposition: it is through Sidney's translations of Italian songs that trochaic meter
        and feminine rhyme entered English poetry in the Renaissance. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N48">
      <bib> -----. "Sidney's Verse Adaptations to Two Sixteenth-Century Italian Art Songs."
        Renaissance Quarterly 23 (1970): 237-55.</bib>
      <notes>Reports the discovery of the Italian musical sources for two of Sidney's Cer- taine
        Sonnets; complete transcriptions and discussion of Sidney's skill at molding his English to
        the meters of both the music and the Italian texts are provided. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N49">
      <bib> Ferri, Mary M. "Modern Songs as Lyric Poetry: Euphony, Rhythm, Metre, and Rhyme." Style
        4 (1970): 245-51.</bib>
      <notes>Remarks on work by Paul Simon, Bob Dylan, and Leonard Cohen. Superfi- cial. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N50">
      <bib> Finney, Oliver J. "Thomas Campion, Music, and Metrics." DAI 36 (1976): 4506A
        (Kansas).</bib>
      <notes> From consideration of the musical settings of the Pléiade, Sidney's abortive ex-
        periments in quantitative metrics, Campion's Observations (wherein the term "beat" is used
        ambivalently for "stress" and "duration") and several of his late airs, Finney concludes
        that Campion adopted a temporal theory of metrics, using variations in note length in the
        music to indicate metrical deviations in the text. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N51">
      <bib> Fischer, Marianne. "Zum Stil der elizabethanischen Madrigale." Archiv 133 (1915):
        1–44.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N52">
      <bib> Flasdieck, Hermann M. John Brown (1715–1766) und seine "Dissertation on Poetry and
        Music." Studien zur englische Philologie, vol. 68. Halle: Max Niemeyer, 1924. 145 pp.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N53">
      <bib> Fowler, Rowena. "Music and Metre: Browning's 'Pietro of Abano.'" Music &amp; Letters 57
        (1976): 47-54.</bib>
      <notes> Several features of the poem--eight bars of music Browning appended to its conclusion,
        special stress marks, outlandish pronunciations required by rhymes, foreign words--jointly
        indicate that Browning intended the meter of the verse to correspond to a musical meter, and
        for (intentionally) ludicrous effect. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N54">
      <bib> Fox-Strangways, A. H. "Words and Music in Song." Essays and Studies 7 (1922): 30–
        56.</bib>
      <notes> The essay explores the relations of word to tune in a broad comparative view, but not
        technically: the chief interest here is the subjects which seem appropri- ate or
        inappropriate for song. The latter judgment rests on his assumption that "the root idea of a
        song is 'action.'" </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N55">
      <bib> Fuller, Roy. "Fascinating Rhythm." Southern Review 9 (1973): 857–72; rpt. in his
        Professors and Gods. London: Andre Deutsch, 1973. pp. 81-97.</bib>
      <notes> The allusion to Gershwin is emblematic: the subject of this article is the con-
        nection between the rhythm of lyrics (words, poems) and the rhythm of their musical scores.
        This leads to the larger question of Text and Performance, fixity and variation, meter and
        meaning--treated here in the work of Cam- pion, Gershwin, Coward, and Lowell. Remarks on
        free verse, scansions. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N56">
      <bib> Gibbon, John M. "The Influence of Music on Metre." Transactions of the Royal Society of
        Canada 23 (1929): 115-23.</bib>
      <notes>Seven of Sir Philip Sidney's poems have extant annotations indicating the tune they
        were set to, one of which is that of the current Dutch national anthem. Another is the
        Huguenot Battle Hymn in the Geneva Psalter (edited by Cal- vin), which was also used by Ben
        Jonson. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N57">
      <bib> -----. Melody and the Lyric from Chaucer to the Cavaliers. London: J. M. Dent; New York:
        E. P. Dutton, 1930; rpt. New York: Haskell House, 1964. 204 pp.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N58">
      <bib> Green, Andrew J. "Bridges' Odes for Music." Sewanee Review 49 (1941): 30-38.</bib>
      <notes> Bridges' essay "The Musical Setting of Poetry" is essential to a right under- standing
        and judgment of his two odes for music, for Bridges believed that the music should carry
        half, or more than half, the burden of meaning, leaving the text not as autonomous poetry
        but as "verse which should adumbrate a setting, blending perfectly with the music thereof."
      </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N59">
      <bib> Greer, David. "'What if a day'--An Examination of the Words and the Music." Music &amp;
        Letters 43 (1962): 304-19.</bib>
      <notes>The song is perhaps Campion's; see pp. 312–14 for remarks on its musical rhythm, which
        is relatively faithful to the normal speech-rhythm of the words. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N60">
      <bib> Gross, Harvey. "Music and the Analogue of Feeling: Notes on Eliot and Beethoven." The
        Centennial Review of Arts and Sciences 3 (1959): 269-88.</bib>
      <notes>The "music" of poetry is not a matter of sound-effects but of a pattern of ab- stract
        relationships, such as in syntax and prosody, which create structures of "tension,
        ambiguity, expectation, and fulfillment." These relationships exist in "affective states
        below the level of explicit meaning." Eliot's four-stress lines underneath his pentameters
        touch these more primitive, pre-cognitive levels in us. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N61">
      <bib> Hadow, Sir W. H. A Comparison of Poetry and Music. Cambridge: Cambridge University
        Press, 1926. 41 pp.</bib>
      <notes> Some stray remarks after p. 17. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N62">
      <bib> Hanscombe, Gillian. "John Donne and the Writing of Lyrics." Studies in Music 6 (1972):
        10-26.</bib>
      <notes> A very precise and extensive metrical/musicological analysis demonstrates ex- actly
        why and how "Donne's poems are too complete for melody." But has it ever been proven, in
        fact, that "he expected most of them to be set to music," as the author claims? </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N63">
      <bib> Hayes, Alfred. "The Relation of Music to Poetry." Atlantic Monthly 113 (1914): 59–
        69.</bib>
      <notes> "If [the musician] had adhered closely to the poet's metre, the musical effect would
        soon have become monotonous, and he is bound to make the musical effect his first
        consideration." </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N64">
      <bib> Heisch, Elizabeth A. "The Problem of Prosody in the Early English Opera, 1660– 1700: A
        Study of the Setting of Words to Music." DAI 32 (1972): 6377A (U.C.L.A.).</bib>
      <notes> The Restoration dramatic lyric, having lost its earlier, Renaissance weld to music
        based on the Humanist cosmology, deteriorated in power and effect un- der foreign
        influences, the "equivalence of note for syllable" being lost, and verse-rhythm in general
        being "submerged or dismembered." Imaginative lan- guage too is enslaved to convention.
      </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N65">
      <bib> Herbert, Rembert B., Jr. "An Analysis of Nine Holy Sonnets of John Donne Set to Music by
        Benjamin Britten." DAI 35 (1974): 2224A (American University).</bib>
      <notes> "We may feel that there is some essential fusion between a poem and a suc- cessful
        setting, but if we try to describe that fusion we cannot do so precisely. We in fact can
        speak only of a series of events in the musical medium for which we are able to posit
        analogous events in the verbal medium." </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N66">
      <bib> Hess, M. Whitcomb. "The Relation Between Music and Poetry." Personalist 15 (1934):
        140-47.</bib>
      <notes>Speaks of "the one essence in another kind." </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N67">
      <bib> Hollander, John. "Music and Poetry." Princeton (A18), pp. 533-36.</bib>
      <notes>A capsule history of the relations of the two modes from their earliest origin in the
        unified performances of music and dance through their long, gradual disso- ciation and
        eventual separation. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N68">
      <bib> -----. "A Poem for Music: Notes on the Composition of Philomel." Appendix to his Vision
        and Resonance (A13), pp. 289-302.</bib>
      <notes/>
    </item>



    <item id="N69">
      <bib> -----. "The Poem in the Ear." Yale Review 62 (1973): 486–506</bib>
      <notes>; rpt. in revised form as chapter 1 of his Vision and Resonance (A13), pp. 3–43.
        Section 2 of the essay reproduces the substance of E358. Section 3 offers fur- ther valuable
        reflections on the historical relations of music and poetry, par- ticularly in the
        Renaissance settings, the madrigals and ayres. The fallacy of musical scansion is also
        discussed. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N70">
      <bib> -----. The Untuning of the Sky: Ideas of Music in English Poetry, 1500–1700. Princeton:
        Princeton University Press, 1961</bib>
      <notes>; rpt. New York: W. W. Norton, 1970. Rev.: in College English 23 (1961): 164; in the
        Yale Review 50 (1961): 625–27; by Frank Kermode in The New Statesman 61 (1961): 840; in JEGP
        61 (1962): 151–55; in Anglia 79 (1961): 481–84; in Shakespeare Quarterly 13 (1962): 564– 66;
        in Études Anglaises 16 (1963): 80–81; in Review of English Studies n.s. 15 (1964): 307-10.
        Required reading, though the subject is not metrical adjustments in setting verse to music
        or even versification but rather that great metaphysics or ideol- ogy of Music which lay
        embedded in the Renaissance mind, residue of the long accretion of classical and medieval
        philosophy, and which informed so much of Renaissance poetry both in theory and practice.
        But see especially the Introduction and pp. 140–43, 206-20.</notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N71">
      <bib> Horn, Dorothy. "Tune Detecting in 19th Century Hymnals." Tennessee Folklore Society
        Bulletin 26 (1960): 99–109.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N72">
      <bib> Hunter, G. K. "The English Hexameter and the Elizabethan Madrigal." PQ 32 (1953):
        340-42.</bib>
      <notes> Praising Hendrickson (E175), Hunter shows how "the difficulty of singing Elizabethan
        airs and madrigals, in the absence of regularly distributed accents, using the normal
        accentuation of the words as the main guide to the rhythm, is exactly parallel to the
        difficulty of reading English hexameters by word- accent." </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N73">
      <bib> Irwin, John T. "Thomas Campion and the Musical Emblem." Studies in English Literature
        1500–1900 10 (1970): 121-41.</bib>
      <notes>Irwin believes, curiously, that previous characterizations of Campion as a "musical
        poet" are forms of condescending special pleading; to restore the bal- ance, he demonstrates
        complex phonemic patterning, a musical thematic structure, and the idea of music as constant
        symbol in "Now Winter Nights Enlarge." A complex essay, with an astonishingly minute
        explication, written from a subtle point of view. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N74">
      <bib> Johnson, Wendell Stacy. "Browning's Music." JAAC 22 (1963): 203-7.</bib>
      <notes>Four types of "musical" poems are analyzed: the fugue ("Master Hughes"), the toccata
        ("A Toccata of Galuppi's"), variations-on-a-theme ("Abt Vogler"), and the march
        ("Parleying"). Nearly all the detail-work here is prosodic. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N75">
      <bib> Joiner, Mary. "Another Campion Song?" Music &amp; Letters 48 (1967): 138-39.</bib>
      <notes>Campion's example in chapter 4 of the Observations in the Art of English Poesie (E134),
        "Harke how these winds," is in fact taken from a song of his own. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N76">
      <bib> Jones, Bill. "Is Music a Language?" British Journal of Aesthetics 10 (1970):
        162-68.</bib>
      <notes>Collateral reading. A rejection of the premisses of Deryck Cooke's The Lan- guage of
        Music; Jones denies the existence of specific musical "modes" which can be correlated to
        specific emotions or moods and described by precise ad- jectives or, indeed, any verbal
        formulation. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N77">
      <bib> Jones, John A. "The Analogy of Eighteenth Century Music and Poetry: Bach and Pope." The
        Centennial Review of Arts and Sciences 21 (1977): 211-35.</bib>
      <notes>In the Baroque era, the analogies were: (1) "representative meter" in poetry to
        "word-painting" in music; (2) the parallelisms of rhyme to the line-by-line echoing of
        thorough bass; (3) thematic development in poetry by variation, addition, or illustration,
        to motif development in music by expansion; and (4) balanced antithesis in poetry to
        simplified two-part composition in music. In the Classical era, the balance and closure of
        the heroic couplet was formally analogous to the Classical phrase in music, but functionally
        the analogue was not the couplet-form but the introduction of the first-person-subjective
        point of view. See pp. 219–21 on representative meter. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N78">
      <bib> Kastendieck, Miles M. England's Musical Poet, Thomas Campion. New York: Oxford
        University Press, 1938; rpt. New York: Russell &amp; Russell, 1963. 203 pp.</bib>
      <notes> Based on his dissertation at Yale University in 1932. Rev.: in MLR 35 (1940): 537–40;
        in Review of English Studies 15 (1939): 99– 101; in MLN 54 (1939): 632. A study not only of
        the achievements Campion attained in setting specific texts to specific songs, but of
        Campion's life and thought in general, and even of the wider Renaissance attitudes toward
        music. Wider in scope than Mac- Donagh (E302), and still a valuable source on Campion.
      </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N79">
      <bib> Kenyon, Max. "Modern Metres." Music &amp; Letters 28 (1947): 168-74.</bib>
      <notes>Though his definitions of meter and rhythm are disappointing (the former is "bare
        mathematical time succession of sounds," the latter "what the soul makes of them"), Kenyon
        suggests, more centrally, that the relationship of musical meter and rhythm to simplicity
        and complexity is inverse; as meters are sim- plified the possibilities for rhythmic
        complexity and subtlety expand. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N80">
      <bib> Kime, Mary W. "Lyric and Song: Seventeenth-Century Musical Settings of John Donne's
        Poetry." DAI 31 (1970): 730A (Denver).</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N81">
      <bib> Kinsley, James. "The Music of the Heart." Renaissance and Modern Studies 8 (1964):
        6–52.</bib>
      <notes> A wide-ranging though not unified discussion of: the modes of union between poetry and
        music in the eighteenth century, especially the libretto; the theo- retical work of Beattie
        and others on musical mimesis, music as a language, and association of ideas; the classical
        ideal of simplicity in lyric; and the work by Burns in traditional songs and folk-poetry.
      </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N82">
      <bib> Krause, Sydney J. "Whitman, Music, and Proud Music of the Storm." PMLA 72 (1957):
        705-21.</bib>
      <notes>Musical ideas and scores were for Whitman more a subject than a method-- more a source
        of emotional inspiration than a structural pattern for rhythm. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N83">
      <bib> List, George. "An Ideal Marriage of Ballad Text and Tune." Midwest Folklore 7 (1957):
        95–112.</bib>
      <notes> Extensive close analysis of the verbal-melodic "fit." </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N84">
      <bib> Lord, Harvey G. "Toward a Theory of the Relationship between Words and Music in Songs:
        Emphasis on Thomas Campion." DAI 39 (1978): 899A (Connecticut).</bib>
      <notes> An inductive study of the successful use of word-painting, conjunction of meter in
        text and music, stanza-structure, melodic patterns, and syntax in fit- ting words to music.
        Short, but dense. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N85">
      <bib> Lowbury, Edward, Timothy Salter, and Alison Young. Thomas Campion: Poet, Composer,
        Physician. New York: Barnes &amp; Noble, 1970.</bib>
      <notes> A synoptic study of the career and works of England's greatest composer-poet. Persons
        interested specifically in the intriguing question of how metered verse is set into (or
        against) a musical score, and with what effects, should go directly to Chapter 3. Chapter 5
        explicates and places in context the Observations in the Art of English Poesie (E134);
        Chapter 11 gives the same for Campion's other work on musical theory. In between the whole
        oeuvre is surveyed. Bibliogra- phy. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N86">
      <bib> Lyons, Dorothy M. "Music in the Poetry of Thomas Campion." Diss., Boston College,
        1937.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N87">
      <bib> Mace, D. T. "Musical Humanism, the Doctrine of Rhythms, and the Saint Cecilia Odes of
        Dryden." Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institute 27 (1964): 251– 92.</bib>
      <notes> A long and very widely informed study of the process whereby the doctrine of rhythmus
        [metrical mimesis, the expression of emotion by appropriate metrical variation] came to
        replace harmony in the Restoration as the ideal for poetry set to music and hence as the
        informing principle of Dryden's great Odes. Mace shows rhythmus to be a crucial concept in
        subsequent eighteenth-century prosodic theory, and he traces in detail its antecedent
        development in England, France, and Italy. An impressive and important study. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N88">
      <bib> McGrady, R. J. "Henry Lawes and the Concept of 'Just Note and Accent.'" Music &amp;
        Letters 50 (1969): 86–102.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N89">
      <bib> McIntosh, William A. "The Harmonic Muse: Musical Currents in Literature 1450– 1750." DAI
        35 (1974): 3692A (Virginia).</bib>
      <notes> Notwithstanding the dates cited in its title, this thesis surveys the influences of
        Boethius' musicae instrumentalis, humana, and mundana on Chaucer, Campion, Spenser,
        Shakespeare, Dryden, and Auden. Detailed analysis of Handel's set- tings of Dryden's St.
        Cecilia odes and Britten's settings for Auden's similar odes. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N90">
      <bib> Malcolm, Alexander. A Treatise of Musick, Speculative, Practical, and Historical.
        Edinburgh: J. Osborn, 1721; rpt. New York: Da Capo Press, 1970.</bib>
      <notes> Treats the parallel of music to poetry without any direct consideration of pros- ody
        at all. For a review essay, see Music &amp; Letters 33 (1952): 226-31.</notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N91">
      <bib> Marrocco, W. Thomas. "The Fourteenth-Century Madrigal: Its Form and Contents." Speculum
        26 (1951): 449-57.</bib>
      <notes>Examination of rhyme-schemes shows that the forms of the early madrigal were extremely
        diverse and irregular. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N92">
      <bib> Maynard, Winifred. "The Lyrics of Wyatt: Poems or Songs?" Review of English Studies n.s.
        16 (1965): 1–13, 245-57.</bib>
      <notes>A wide-ranging search of the three major collections of Elizabethan songs, compared
        with Wyatt's verses, reveals the extraordinary difficulty of trying to match tunes to texts
        (Maynard is reticent about his criteria for acceptability of fit), though it does appear
        that about fifty of Wyatt's lyrics were definitely meant to be sung. Since many tunes match
        many texts more or less acceptably, we must rely on the correspondence of several kinds of
        evidence taken to- gether to establish matchings. One wants to see a musicologist rewrite
        this study. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N93">
      <bib> Mellers, Wilfrid. "Words and Music in Elizabethan England." The Age of Shakespeare. Vol.
        2 of The Penguin Guide to English Literature. Ed. Boris Ford. Baltimore: Penguin, 1956. pp.
        386-415.</bib>
      <notes/>
    </item>



    <item id="N94">
      <bib> Milner, R. "Music and Poetry in the Sixteenth Century." Études Anglaises 9 (1956):
        28-33.</bib>
      <notes> A noteworthy review of the published proceedings of two conferences held in Paris in
        1953 and 1954 on poetry and music in Renaissance England, Musique et Poésie du XVIe Siècle
        and La Musique Instrumentale de la Renaissance. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N95">
      <bib> -----. "The Study of Elizabethan Music." Études Anglaises 6 (1953): 214-26.</bib>
      <notes>See p. 221 for a scansion of some lines from Campion. Bibliography. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N95">
      <bib> a Morris, Brian. "'Not, Siren-like, to tempt': Donne and the Composers." John Donne:
        Essays in Celebration. Ed. A. J. Smith. London: Methuen, 1970. pp. 219-58.</bib>
      <notes/>
    </item>



    <item id="N96">
      <bib> Mumford, Ivy L. "The Canzone in Sixteenth-Century English Verse with Particular
        Reference to Wyatt's Rendering of Petrarch's Canzoniere." English Miscellany 11 (1960):
        21-32.</bib>
      <notes> "Wyatt alone, of the English Petrarchists, attempted the canzone, and in so doing
        seems for the first time content to express the subject-matter independ- ently of the
        prosodic scheme." He altered the form so radically because of complex metrical and musical
        requirements in the Italian. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N97">
      <bib> -----. "Musical Settings to the Poems of Henry Howard, Earl of Surrey." English
        Miscellany 8 (1957): 9–20.</bib>
      <notes> Settings (in various stages of corruption) are extant for only five of Surrey's po-
        ems; the author gives full details of transmission. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N98">
      <bib> -----. "Musical Settings to the Poems of Sir Thomas Wyatt." Music &amp; Letters 37
        (1956): 315–22; 39 (1958): 262-64.</bib>
      <notes>The tunes for two of the lyrics--"Hevyn and erth and all" and "Blame not my
        lute"--having only recently been discovered, they are here submitted to analy- sis. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N99">
      <bib> -----. "Sir Thomas Wyatt's Verse and Italian Musical Sources." English Miscellany 14
        (1963): 9–26.</bib>
      <notes> The principal sources are the frottola of the improvisatore Serafino Ciminelli
        d'Aquila and the Petrarchan canzonière. ---- Music &amp; Literature in England in the
        Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries. Los Angeles: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library,
        University of California, 1953. 55 pp. Contains two papers: James E. Phillips's survey of
        theories on the union of "Poetry and Music in the Seventeenth Century," and Bertrand H.
        Bronson's discernment of two fundamental trends in "Some Aspects of Music and Literature in
        the Eighteenth Century." </notes>
    </item>


    <item id="N100">
      <bib>Phillips, James E., "Survey of theories on the union of "Poetry and Music in the
        Seventeenth Century," in -----. "Sir Thomas Wyatt's Verse and Italian Musical Sources."
        English Miscellany 14 (1963): 9–26.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>


    <item id="N101">
      <bib> Bronson, Bertrand H.,"Some Aspects of Music and Literature in the Eighteenth Century."
        in -----. "Sir Thomas Wyatt's Verse and Italian Musical Sources." English Miscellany 14
        (1963): 9–26.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>

    <item id="N102">
      <bib> Nash, Winifred H. "The Inter-Relations of Music and Poetry." Diss., Boston University,
        1931.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N103">
      <bib> Oliva, Joseph. "Structure of Music and Structure of Language: A Semiotic Study." DAI 38
        (1978): 4138A (State University of New York at Buffalo).</bib>
      <notes> Applies Paul Garvin's "functional empiricism" method. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N104">
      <bib> Parks, Edna. The Hymns and Hymn-Tunes Found in the English Metrical Psalters. New York:
        Coleman-Ross, 1966. 114 pp.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N105">
      <bib> Pattison, Bruce. Music and Poetry of the English Renaissance. London: Methuen,
        1948.</bib>
      <notes> A standard source having much broader scope than its title indicates. It should be
        read entire, but probably chapter 5 will most directly interest the metrist. See N129.
      </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N106">
      <bib> -----. "Sir Philip Sidney and Music." Music &amp; Letters 15 (1934): 75-81.</bib>
      <notes> Discusses Italian meters near the end. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N107">
      <bib> Peltz, Catharine W. "Thomas Campion, an Elizabethan Neo-Classicist." MLQ 11 (1950):
        3–6.</bib>
      <notes> By virtue of "his insistence on the importance of form," chiefly metrical. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N108">
      <bib> Pollock, Georgiana. "The Relationship of Music to Leaves of Grass." College English 15
        (1954): 384-94.</bib>
      <notes>Rejects the view that Whitman used music as an analogue for the form of his poetry;
        rather, we are told, what he took over from opera was the techniques of the recitative,
        including hovering stress and extra-metrical syllables. "The re- lationship of music to
        Leaves of Grass lies in the resemblance of Whitman's rhythm to the semi-musical rhythm of
        recitative rather than to the even- measured rhythm of pure music." </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N109">
      <bib> Raymond, George L. Rhythm and Harmony in Poetry and Music: Together with Music as a
        Representative Art. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1894; 2nd rev. ed. 1909.</bib>
      <notes> Part six of the author's "System of Comparative Aesthetics." Here he conceives poetry
        and music as being similar in that both are "composed of elements of sound appealing to the
        ear in the order of time." His conception of meter is Accentual rather than Quantitative.
        Chapters 2–11 concern poetry, though on the whole, they represent little more than a primer
        of verseform inflated by grandiose metaphysical speculations. Chapter 13, however, on
        'Analogies be- tween the Use of Quality and Pitch in Poetry and Music' is worthy of note, as
        are the remarks on clucking hens in Beethoven's Third, p. 316. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N110">
      <bib> Raynor, Henry. "Framed to the Life of the Words." Music Review 19 (1958): 261– 72.</bib>
      <notes> On the English Lutenists. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N111">
      <bib> Rhoads, Kenneth W. "The Musical Elements of T. S. Eliot's Four Quartets." DAI 30 (1970):
        5454A (Michigan State).</bib>
      <notes> These are mainly structural, of course, but Rhoads gives considerable attention to
        rhythm (and meter) as well, finding jazz rhythms in Sweeney Agonistes, for example, and a
        sophisticated counterpointing of accentual against syllabic rhythms in the mature verse.
      </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N112">
      <bib> Richardson, David A. "The Golden Mean in Campion's Airs." Comparative Literature 30
        (1978): 108-32.</bib>
      <notes>On Campion's unfailing sense of decorum, and his "balanced middle style" in setting
        texts. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N113">
      <bib> Roberts, David R. "The Music of Milton." PQ 26 (1947): 328-44.</bib>
      <notes>A wide-ranging study which explicates the key components of Milton's poetic
        rhythm--variety and continuous movement--in order to set them against the com- posers of his
        day (and in the century following). The similarity is apparent, even had we not already
        known of Milton's considerable training and interest in music. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N114">
      <bib> Rogerson, Brewster. "Ut Musica Poesis: The Parallel of Music and Poetry in
        Eighteenth-Century Criticism." DA 12 (1946): 308 (Princeton).</bib>
      <notes> Whereas the French seventeenth-century theories of the relations of these arts were
        based on the concept of mimesis, the British eighteenth-century theorists preferred the
        concept of expressiveness. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N115">
      <bib> Sachs, Curt. "Rhythm and Tempo: An Introduction." Musical Quarterly 38 (1952):
        384-98.</bib>
      <notes>Collateral reading. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N116">
      <bib> Sampson, H. Grant. "Mimetic Relationships Between Music and Literature in England."
        Humanities Association Review 25 (1974): 197-210.</bib>
      <notes>An accurate title would have been "The Collapse of the Theory of Imitation (Which Was
        the Basis of Musical Mimesis of the Text) In Favor of the Theory of Expression, In England,
        In the Renaissance and After." The shift was iso- lated by John Hollander. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N117">
      <bib> Samson, Patricia. "Words for Music." Southern Review (Australia) 1 (1963): 46-52.</bib>
      <notes> Discusses semantic effects in several of Donne's Holy Sonnets set to music by Benjamin
        Britten and by Dorian LeGallienne, and in Campion's songs. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N118">
      <bib> Scher, Steven P. "How Meaningful is 'Musical' in Literary Criticism?" Yearbook of
        Comparative and General Literature no. 21 (1972), pp. 52-56.</bib>
      <notes> A penetrating critique of critical abuse of the descriptive term "musical" as ap-
        plied to poetry; Scher agrees with René Wellek that literary criticism's adop- tion of terms
        from another field has had very unfortunate consequences. Dis- cussion of several examples
        of usage is followed by Scher's own scheme: the term may refer to poetic qualities of "the
        acoustic, the evocative, or the struc- tural." In general he finds the two arts not very
        similar. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N119">
      <bib> Schleiner, Louise. "The Composer as Reader: A Setting of George Herbert's 'Altar.'"
        Musical Quarterly 61 (1975): 422-32.</bib>
      <notes>The musical structure of John Playford's 1671 setting mimes the architectonic and
        metrical structure of the pattern-poem. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N120">
      <bib> Schueller, Herbert M. "Literature and Music as Sister Arts: An Aspect of Aesthetic
        Theory in Eighteenth-Century Britain." PQ 26 (1947): 193-205.</bib>
      <notes>Actually the relationship is better described as "mother-daughter" (respec- tively).
        The Augustan conception was not at all that music has a meaning of its own to express,
        different from meanings communicable by words, but rather that music could embellish or
        augment the sense of poetry by expressive sounds imitating the tones of the human voice
        (joy, grief, tenderness, etc.). On correspondences of structure (meter and measure) in the
        two "languages," the two organizations of pure sound, see p. 197. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N121">
      <bib> -----. "The Renaissance Forerunners of the Neoclassic Lyric." MLN 62 (1947):
        310-16.</bib>
      <notes>The Neoclassical conception of the lyric is derived in part from the Renais- sance
        madrigal and air, since these embodied, in their shortness of line, close rhyme, and
        metrical/stanzaic regularity, the qualities of "conciseness, polish, and cadence." </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N122">
      <bib> Schuman, Sharon. "The Myth of Spontaneity: Musical and Metrical Rhythms in the Songs of
        Thomas Campion." Diss., University of Chicago, 1975.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N123">
      <bib> Sharp, Cecil J. "Rhythmical Forms and Melodic Figures." English Folk Song: Some
        Conclusions. London: Simpkin &amp; Co., 1907. pp. 73-88.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N124">
      <bib> Siemens, Reynold. "If Music and Sweet Poetry Agree: Thomas Ford's 'Since First I Saw
        Your Face.'" Renaissance Quarterly 21 (1968): 153-61.</bib>
      <notes>An exhibition of the graceful strength and simplicity of both the verse and the music
        of Ford's well-known air; each can stand alone without support though both fit together
        well: the melodic contour enhances the semantic develop- ment without becoming over-obvious
        or extreme. An informed explication. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N125">
      <bib> Smith, Hallet. Elizabethan Poetry: A Study in Conventions, Meaning, and Expression.
        Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1952.</bib>
      <notes> The fifth chapter gives a summary of the relations of "Poetry and Music," with some
        remarks on quantitative verse at pp. 50–54, 270-72.</notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N126">
      <bib> Srawley, Stephen. "A Note on Musical and Poetic Rhythm." Agenda 10, 4–11, 1 (1972–73):
        114-22.</bib>
      <notes>Discusses the use of repetition in music as it varies from that in verse, con- cluding
        with the author's musical score for Charles Tomlinson's "Da Capo" and discussion. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N127">
      <bib> Sternfeld, Frederick W. "Poetry and Music--Joyce's Ulysses." Frye (A15), pp. 16–
        54.</bib>
      <notes> Identifies three types of relation: (1) a musical tune in the mind of the poet,
        preceding, shaping, and perhaps generating the poem (especially where a new text is set to
        an old melody; (2) other musical techniques which the poet is in- directly aware of and may
        employ (e.g. irregular lineation); and (3) music as theme or symbol in verse. Diverse
        examples. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N128">
      <bib> Stetson, R. H. "The Teaching of Rhythm." Musical Quarterly 9 (1923): 181-90.</bib>
      <notes>Proposes employing the terminology of versification (iambs, trochees, etc.) to
        facilitate the teaching of musical rhythms. Frequent examples from nursery rhymes and
        stress-verse. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N129">
      <bib> Stevens, John E. "The Elizabethan Madrigal: 'Perfect Marriage' or 'Uneasy Flirtation'?"
        Essays and Studies 11 (1958): 17-37.</bib>
      <notes> A revisionist critique of Pattison (N105) ten years after: Stevens, skeptical of any
        "union" of words with music in the Renaissance, argues that poems were only rarely written
        to be set to music by showing that for Elizabethan compos- ers literally "any words would
        do." In fact, "no poet with half an ear could have learnt anything about poetry from hearing
        his verses set to madrigal mu- sic." </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N130">
      <bib> -----. Music and Poetry in the Early Tudor Court. London: Methuen; Lincoln: University
        of Nebraska Press, 1961.</bib>
      <notes> Rev.: in MLR 57 (1962): 240–41; in Anglia 79 (1962): 484–87; in Medium Ævum 31 (1962):
        220–22; in College English 25 (1964): 307; in MLQ 25 (1964): 494–96; in JEGP 63 (1964):
        337–41; in Comparative Literature 15 (1964): 276–78; in Review of English Studies n.s. 14
        (1963): 186-89.</notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N131">
      <bib> Tovey, Donald F. "Words and Music: Some Obiter Dicta." In his The Main Stream of Music
        and Other Essays. New York: Oxford University Press, 1949. pp. 202– 19.</bib>
      <notes> </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N132">
      <bib> Wade, Bonnie C. "Prolegomenon to the Study of Song Texts." Yearbook of the International
        Folk Music Council 8 (1976): 73-88.</bib>
      <notes> Beginning on p. 79 the author discusses structure, particularly the crucial question
        whether structure per se is meaningful. A full "poetic scansion" of Child #13 is compared to
        a marking of a performance, and though Wade does not clearly differentiate stress and
        duration, she can show that singing alters the stress-patterns in the verse. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N133">
      <bib> Wallaschek, R. "On the Difference of Time and Rhythm in Music." Mind n.s. 4 (1895):
        28-35.</bib>
      <notes> The first two paragraphs at least--distinguishing the subjective "time-sense" from
        objective rhythm--are essential reading. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N134">
      <bib> Weiss, Wolfgang. "Die Airs im Stilwandel." Anglia 87 (1969): 201-16.</bib>
      <notes/>
    </item>



    <item id="N135">
      <bib> Wellek, Albert. "Relationship Between Music and Poetry." JAAC 21 (1962): 149– 56.</bib>
      <notes> " . . . is historically, at least in our occidental music, simply fundamental. . . . "
        Absolute music is a relatively late phenomenon. See p. 153 on primitive reci- tative song
        and p. 155 on setting poetic texts. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N136">
      <bib> Wilson, Katherine M. Sounds and Meaning in English Poetry. London: Jonathan Cape, 1930.
        353 pp.</bib>
      <notes> Rev.: by Empson in New Criterion 10 (1931): 529–34; in London Mercury 24 (1931): 181;
        in TLS, 2 October 1930, p. 777. Pace the title, this is a book mainly about music, and only
        less so about poetry. Its central premise is that music arises from the natural inflections
        of speech, and thus poetry also shows a residue of inflection (pitch) and cadence patterns.
        Much of what is found here will be recognized as technical even though pre- sented as urbane
        conversation. Much on Campion and Spenser, pitch-patterns, and devices of sound. Well worth
        an afternoon digression. See also E411. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N137">
      <bib> Winkelman, Donald M. "Poetic/Rhythmic Stress in the Child Ballads." Keystone Folklore
        Quarterly 12 (1967): 103-17.</bib>
      <notes>The author reinforces his opinion that "on the whole, the ballad tune is a more potent
        shaping force than its verbal counterpart" with examples of wrenched prose accents in lines
        resulting from the musical stressings, then re- verses himself, when he realizes that
        auditors generally don't mind wrenched ac- cents in the lines of songs, concluding that "the
        forces of musical and spoken rhythms are too evenly matched to generalize about domination
        by one or the other." </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N138">
      <bib> -----. "Some Rhythmic Aspects of the Child Ballad." New Voices in American Studies. Ed.
        Ray B. Browne. Lafayette, Ind.: Purdue University Press, 1966. pp. 151-62.</bib>
      <notes>Identifies a "Law of Symmetry" in the musical rhythm of ballads: no significant unit is
        not repeated, counterpoised, or matched. The problem of verse- and musical-accent is
        discussed on p. 155 ff. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N139">
      <bib> Yeats, W. B. "Speaking to the Psaltery." The Monthly Review, May 1902; rpt. in his
        Essays and Introductions. New York: Macmillan, 1961, 1968. pp. 13–27.</bib>
      <notes> (See also the final page of "Modern Poetry," p. 508.) Miss Florence Farr's skillful
        strumming of the psaltery (a medieval harp-like instrument with sounding-board) seemed to
        Yeats the perfect accompaniment for his verse, freeing it of all the unpleasant compromises
        forced upon it when fully set to music. </notes>
    </item>



    <item id="N140">
      <bib> Yeston, Maury. The Stratification of Musical Rhythm. New Haven: Yale University Press,
        1976.</bib>
      <notes> Should be consulted after Cooper and Meyer (N30), whose work is criticized on pp.
        28–32 here. </notes>
    </item>
  </chapter>
</bibliography>
