<?xml-model href="brogan.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<bibliography>
    <chapter title="APPENDIX D: LIST OF WORKS CONSULTED">

        <div title="I: English"/>

        <item id="O1">
            <bib> Alston, R. C. "Prosody." A Bibliography of the English Language from the Invention
                of Printing to the Year 1800.</bib>
            <notes> A Corrected Reprint of Vols. I–X. Ilkey: Janus Press, 1974. Vol. VI, pp. 88–92.
            </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="O2">
            <bib> Attridge, Derek. Well-Weighed Syllables. London: Cambridge University Press, 1974.
                (E112)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="O3">
            <bib> Bailey, James. Toward a Statistical Analysis of English Verse. Lisse (The
                Netherlands): Peter de Ridder Press, 1965. (E469)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="O4">
            <bib> Bailey, Richard W., and Dolores M. Burton. English Stylistics: A Bibliography.
                Cambridge, Mass.: M.I.T. Press, 1965.</bib>
            <notes> Citation data in this work is frequently erroneous; annotations are intermittent
                but occasionally very long. </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="O5">
            <bib> Baird, Lorrayne Y. "Style Including Versification and Puns." A Bibliography of
                Chaucer, 1964–1973. Boston: G. K. Hall, 1977. pp. 58–61.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="O6">
            <bib> Bjorklund, Beth. A Study in Comparative Prosody: English and German Jambic
                Pentameter. Stuttgart: Akademischer Verlag Hans-Dieter Heinz, 1978. (E818)</bib>
            <notes> A useful bibliography containing 444 entries on English and German prosody
                (especially the latter, historically), with some lesser interest in Russian.
            </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="O7">
            <bib> Bliss, A. J. "Prosody and Prose Rhythm." The New Cambridge Bibliography of English
                Literature. Ed. George Watson. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1974. cols.
                33–52.</bib>
            <notes> Unfortunately, the NCBEL reprinted CBEL citations without verification, and
                consequently the citation data in NCBEL is often unreliable. Nor is there any
                distinction between trivial and important entries in this very long list of brief
                titles. But the abridged, one-volume edition of the NCBEL recently an- nounced for
                publication should improve in the reliability of its citation data, based on
                corrections supplied by this writer. </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="O8">
            <bib> British Museum Subject Catalog of Modern Books Acquired. London, 1881–1960
                (excepting 1951–55).</bib>
            <notes> S.v. "Poetry: Prosody." </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="O9">
            <bib> Chandler, Albert R., and E. N. Barnhart. "Experiments on Affective Reactions and
                Form." A Bibliography of Psychological and Experimental Aesthetics, 1864–1937.
                Berkeley: University of California Press, 1938. pp. 83–90.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="1O">
            <bib> Comprehensive Dissertation Index. Ann Arbor: Xerox University Microfilms. Volumes
                for 1861–1978.</bib>
            <notes> Subject headings searched: Aesthetic(s), Alliteration, Assonance, Ballad Metre,
                Blank Verse, Couplet, Foot, Form, Free Verse, Iambic, Line, Lyric, Meter, Metre,
                Metrical, Ode, Poem, Poetic, Poetics, Poetry, Prosody, Rhyme-Rime, Rhythm, Sonnet,
                Sound, Stanza, Structure, Style, Stylistics, Syntax, Verse, Versification. </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="11">
            <bib> Ebisch, Walther, and Levin L. Schucking. "Shakespeare's Language, Vocabulary,
                Prosody, and Style." A Shakespeare Bibliography. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1931. pp.
                79– 94.</bib>
            <notes> Also in Supplement for the Years 1930–1935 to A Shakespeare Bibliography.
                Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1937. pp. 29–31. </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="12">
            <bib> Fry, Donald K. "Beowulf" and "The Fight at Finnsburh": A Bibliography.
                Charlottesville: The University Press of Virginia, 1969.</bib>
            <notes> S.v. "Meter" (188 entries) and "Diction" (128 entries) in the Subject-Index.
            </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="13">
            <bib> Gabel, Gernot U., and G. R. Gabel. Dissertations in English and American
                Literature: Theses Accepted by Austrian, French, and Swiss Universities,
                1875–1970.</bib>
            <notes> Hamburg: the author, 1977. 198 pp. </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="14">
            <bib> Griffith, Dudley D. "Style Including Versification" and "Language." Bibliography
                of Chaucer 1908–1953. Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1955. pp.
                116–42.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="15">
            <bib> Hammond, Eleanor C. "Linguistics and Versification." Chaucer: A Bibliographical
                Manual. New York: The Macmillan Company, 1908;</bib>
            <notes> rpt. New York: Peter Smith, 1933. pp. 464–509. (K149) </notes>
        </item>

        <item id="16">
            <bib> Huckabay, Calvin. "Style and Versification." John Milton: An Annotated
                Bibliography 1929– 1968. Pittsburgh: Duquesne University Press, 1960;</bib>
            <notes> rpt. 1969. pp. 327–39. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="17">
            <bib> International Index to Periodicals. New York: H. W. Wilson Company, 1907–65.</bib>
            <notes> After 1965 the series title changes to Social Sciences and Humanities Index
                until 1974; after 1974 the title is Humanities Index, as the previously composite
                in- dex is divided into two annual volumes. Valuable as a resource because it cov-
                ers, especially in the earlier years, a considerable number of both scholarly and
                popular journals that the MLA did not include. Relevant subject headings vary from
                decade to decade, but the most productive are: Alliteration, English
                Language--Rhythm, English Language--Rime, English Language--Versification, English
                Language--Old English, English Language--Middle English, Poetics, Rime, Shakespeare,
                William-- Versification, Versification. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="18">
            <bib> Jochum, K. P. S. W. B. Yeats: A Classified Bibliography of Criticism. Urbana,
                Ill.: University of Illinois Press, 1978.</bib>
            <notes> S.v. "Prosody," "Rhyme," and "Rhythm" in the Index. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="19">
            <bib> Kluewer, Jeffrey D. "An Annotated Check List of Writings on Linguistics and
                Literature in the Sixties." Bulletin of the New York Public Library 76 (1972):
                36–91.</bib>
            <notes> Given the restrictions of scope evident in its title, this checklist is the most
                thorough resource of its kind I have seen. Arranged alphabetically are 288 en-
                tries, nearly all of them annotated generously, followed by eleven Indexes: Bib-
                liographies, Collections, Theories of Language, Linguistics and Literary Criti-
                cism, Linguistic Schools, Prosody, Psycholinguistics, Qualitative Studies, Style and
                Stylistics, Syntax and Grammar, and Non-Prosodic Analysis of Literary Periods and
                Authors and Works. Index VI on Prosody (pp. 82–85) contains subsections indexing
                Meter and Rhythm, Phonology--Sound Texture, Sound and Meaning,
                Suprasegmentals--Performance, and Prosodic Analyses (by author and poem). The
                cross-referencing system used here is awkward, but the superabundance of indexes is
                more than compensatory. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="20">
            <bib> Kökeritz, Helge. Shakespeare's Pronunciation. New Haven: Yale University Press,
                1953. (C17)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="21">
            <bib> Lafourcade, Françoise. "Contribution à une bibliographie chronologique pour
                l'étude des théories sur la versification anglaise de 1550 à 1950." In Hommage à
                Paul Dottin. Caliban (Annales Publiées par la Faculté des Lettres et Sciences
                Humaines de Toulouse). N.s. 2, fascicle 1, no. 3 (Special Issue), 1966. pp. 271–317.
                (A27)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="22">
            <bib> Library of Congress Catalogs. Books: Subjects. Washington, D.C.: Library of
                Congress, 1955 (for 1950–54)--.</bib>
            <notes> Title varies. See the following principal headings for English: Alliteration,
                Blank Verse, Chaucer, Geoffrey--Versification, English Language-- Versification,
                Free Verse, Shakespeare, William--Versification, Versification. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="23">
            <bib> McNamee, Lawrence F. Dissertations in English and American Literature: Theses
                Accepted in English, American and German Universities 1865–1964. New York: R. R.
                Bowker, 1968.</bib>
            <notes> Also -----. Supplement One 1964–1968. New York, 1969, and -----. Supplement Two
                1969–1973. New York, 1974. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="24">
            <bib> Malof, Joseph. A Manual of English Meters. Bloomington: Indiana University Press,
                1970. (E581)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="25">
            <bib> Martin, Willard E., Jr. "Language" and "Metrics." A Chaucer Bibliography
                1925–1933. Durham: Duke University Press, 1935. pp. 33–37.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="26">
            <bib> Milic, Lewis T. Style and Stylistics: An Annotated Bibliography. New York: The
                Free Press, 1967.</bib>
            <notes> Uses a system of descriptors rather than prose annotations to indicate content.
            </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="27">
            <bib> Modern Humanities Research Association. Annual Bibliography of English Language
                and Literature. London: Modern Humanities Research Association, 1920–-.</bib>
            <notes> I have searched the volumes for 1920 through 1975, entire. See the annual
                section on "Metre"; beginning in 1971, the section on "Language, Literature, and the
                Computer"; and beginning in 1973, the section on "Stylistics." </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="28">
            <bib> Modern Language Association of America. International Bibliography. New York:
                Modern Language Association, 1920--.</bib>
            <notes> I have searched the volumes for 1920 through 1968, and the General, English,
                American, and Linguistics sections of volumes I and III for 1969 through 1978,
                entire. Unlike the MHRA bibliography, the Postmodern MLA has no section for the
                traditional subject of Versification, so the student of form must find his sources
                by the traditional method--reading from cover to cover. Vol- ume III on Linguistics
                contains a section on "Stylistics," and also a section on "Prosody
                (Suprasegmentals)." From the title of this latter section, one would expect it to
                treat aspects of speech (Pitch, Timing, Juncture)--which it does-- but it also
                includes articles on meter and versification, using "Prosody" in the old sense of
                the term, wherein versification was a subcategory of Grammar. But by preserving the
                old conception the MLA preserves the old confusions; it is difficult to imagine a
                rational justification for this organization. As of January 1979, however, the MLA
                Bibliographies for 1976–1977 are available for computer searching on a data base in
                the Lockheed system; a scan for all the variants of the keywords Prosody, Meter, and
                Versification should net most items of interest. Note also that there is a published
                Index to vols. 1–50 of PMLA, wherein see s.v. "Metre," "Rhythm," "Rime," and
                "Versification" (these are not restricted to English). </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="29">
            <bib> Mummendey, Richard. "Prosody." Language and Literature of the Anglo-Saxon Nations
                as Presented in German Doctoral Dissertations 1885–1950: A Bibliography.
                Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1954. pp.
                36–38.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="30">
            <bib> Mustanoja, Tauono F. "Chaucer's Prosody." Companion to Chaucer Studies. Ed. Beryl
                Rowland. New York: Oxford University Press, 1968. pp. 58–84. (K266)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="31">
            <bib> Nager, Rae Ann. "English: II. Bibliographical." Versification: Major Language
                Types. Ed. K. W. Wimsatt, Jr. New York: New York University Press for MLA, 1972. pp.
                204–16. (A28)</bib>
            <notes> Brief annotations for 126 well-known sources. -----. "A Selective Annotated
                Bibliography of Recent Work on English Prosody." Style 11 (1977): 136–70. (A29)
            </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="32">
            <bib> Omond, T. S. English Metrists. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1921; rpt. New York:
                Phaeton Press, 1968. (A5)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="33">
            <bib> Preminger, Alex, ed. The Princeton Encyclopedia of Poetry and Poetics. Enlarged
                ed. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1974. (A18)</bib>
            <notes> For the study of English versification the relevant articles (all of which con-
                clude with a bibliography) are the following: Accent, Alliteration, Alliterative
                Meter, Analysis, Assonance, Ballad Meter, Blank Verse, Cadence, Caesura, Christabel
                Meter, Classical Meters in Modern Verse, Conceptions of Poetics, Couplet, English
                Poetry, English Prosody, Explication, Form, Free Verse, Generative Metrics, Heroic
                Couplet, Hexameter, Linguistics and Poetics, Lyric Meter, Metrical Variation, Music
                and Poetry, Ode, Phenomenology, Poetic Diction, Poetry Reading, Poly- phonic Prose,
                Prose Poem, Prose Rhythm, Prosodic Notation, Prosody, Rhyme, Rules, Scansion,
                Sonnet, Sound in Poetry, Structure, Style, Stylistics, Texture, Theories of Poetry,
                Tone-Color, Verse and Prose. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="34">
            <bib> Roberts, Thomas J. "Literary-Linguistics: A Bibliography, 1946–1961." Texas
                Studies in Literature and Language 4 (1962): 625–29.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="35">
            <bib> Roth, Sister Mary Augustine, ed. Coventry Patmore's "Essay on English Metrical
                Law": A Critical Edition with a Commentary. Washington, D.C.: Catholic University of
                America Press, 1961. (E385)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="36">
            <bib> Schramm, Wilbur L. "Objective Studies of Verse: A Bibliography." Approaches to a
                Science of English Verse. University of Iowa Studies, Series on Aims and Progress of
                Research, no. 46. Iowa City: The University, 1935. pp. 76–82. (E428)</bib>
            <notes> Generous annotations on the major works up to 1935 which apply the meth- ods of
                Acoustics (Phonetics) to English versification. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="37">
            <bib> Sebeok, Thomas A., ed. Style in Language. Cambridge, Mass.: M.I.T. Press, 1960.
                (A19)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="38">
            <bib> Severs, J. Burke, ed., and continued by Albert E. Hartung. A Manual of Writings in
                Middle English 1050–1500. 5 vols. New Haven: Archon/Shoe String for the Connecticut
                Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1967–75.</bib>
            <notes> The successor to Wells. There is usually a subsection on Versification listed
                un- der each poem entry in the Bibliography in each volume, but as the section heads
                are extremely difficult to distinguish typographically I cannot recom- mend using
                these volumes extensively. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="39">
            <bib> Shapiro, Karl. A Bibliography of Modern Prosody. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins
                University Press, 1948. (A30)</bib>
            <notes> Long, discursive annotations, but relatively few entries. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="40">
            <bib> Shapiro, Karl, and Robert Beum. A Prosody Handbook. New York: Harper and Row,
                1965. (B195)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="41">
            <bib> Sipe, Dorothy L. Shakespeare's Metrics. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1968.
                (E1304)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="42">
            <bib> Smith, Gordon Ross. "The Art of Shakespeare: Language, Vocabulary, Prosody, and
                Style." A Classified Shakespeare Bibliography. University Park, Pa.: Pennsylvania
                State University Press, 1963. pp. 217–76 (A5124–A5615).</bib>
            <notes> Especially pp. 229– 31. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="43">
            <bib> Stevens, David H. "Metrics." Reference Guide to Milton from 1800 to the Present
                Day. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1930. pp. 275–78.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="44">
            <bib> Tarlinskaja, Marina. English Verse: Theory and History. The Hague: Mouton, 1976.
                (E673)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="45">
            <bib> Tempest, N. R. "Prosody and Prose Rhythm." The Cambridge Bibliography of English
                Literature. Ed. F. W. Bateson. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1940. Vol. 1,
                pp. 13–24.</bib>
            <notes> CBEL citation data is frequently inaccurate. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="46">
            <bib> Thompson, John. The Founding of English Metre. London: Routledge and Kegan Paul,
                1961. (E91)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>


        <div title="II: Other Languages"/>




         <item id="47">
            <bib> L'Année philologique: Bibliographie critique et analytique de l'antiquité
                gréco-latine. Vols. 1–. Paris: Sociétés d'Édition "Les Belles Lettres," 1927 (for
                1924–26)--.</bib>
            <notes> The annual bibliography for Classical Studies: see s.v. "Métrique, Rythmique,
                Prosodie." </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="48">
            <bib> Best, R. I. "Metrics." Bibliography of Irish Philology and of Printed Irish
                Literature. Dublin: Browne and Nolan for the National Library of Ireland, 1913; rpt.
                New York: Johnson, 1970. pp. 52–54. (L207)</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="49">
            <bib> Bibliographie de la littérature française du Moyen Âge à nos jours. Ed. René
                Rancoeur. Vol. 1--. Paris, 1966–-.</bib>
            <notes> S.v. "Généralités: Versification" and s.v. "Versification" in the Subject Index.
            </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="50">
            <bib> Bibliographie der französischen Literaturwissenschaft. Ed. Otto Klapp. Vol. 1–.
                Frankfurt on Main, 1960 (for 1956–58)--.</bib>
            <notes> S.v. "Généralités: Poésie." </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="51">
            <bib> Bibliographie Unselbständiger Literatur-Linguistik. Ed. Elke Suchan. Vol. 1–.
                Frankfurt on Main: Klosterman, 1976–.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="52">
            <bib> Carballo, Picazo, Alfredo. Métrica española. Madrid, 1956. 161 pp. (L1025)</bib>
            <notes> The most recent and comprehensive bibliography for Spanish. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="53">
            <bib> Clarke, Dorothy C. Une Bibliografia de versificación española. University of
                California Publications in Modern Philology, vol. 20, no. 2. Berkeley, 1937. pp.
                57–126.</bib>
            <notes> (L1030) </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="54">
            <bib> Gayley, Charles Mills, and Fred Newton Scott. An Introduction to the Methods and
                Materials of Literary Criticism. Boston: Ginn and Company, 1901.</bib>
            <notes> (L46) The "General Note" on pp. 487–518 lists innumerable sources for the study
                of comparative versification, including Greek, Latin, English, French, German,
                Italian, Spanish and Portuguese, Russian, Lapp, Finnish, Indian, Hebrew, Egyptian,
                Chinese, Japanese, Arabian, and Turkish. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="55">
            <bib> Gindin, S[ergei] I. Struktura stixotvornoi rechi: sistematicheskii ukazatel'
                literatury po obšchemu i russkomu stixovedeniju, izdannoi v SSSR na russkom jazyke,
                1958–1973. Institut russkogo jazyka AN SSSR, Problemnaja gruppa po eksperimental'noi
                i prikladnoi lingvistike, Predvaritel'nye publikatsii, Vypusk 94. Moscow, 1976. 140
                pp.</bib>
            <notes> (This is the "preliminary version"; citations for 1974 and Indexes are included
                in the "final version," namely) Issledovanija po teorii stixa. Otdel'nyi ottisk.
                Akademija Nauk SSSR, Institut russkoi literatury (Puškinskii dom). Leningrad:
                Otdelenie, 1978. pp. 152–221. (L1271a) </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="56">
            <bib> Hatzfeld, Helmut A. A Critical Bibliography of the New Stylistics (1900–1952)
                Applied to the Romance Literatures. University of North Carolina Studies in
                Comparative Literature, no. 5. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina,
                1953.</bib>
            <notes> (L847) See pp. 136–42, 169–75, 230–32. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="57">
            <bib> Hollander, Lee M. "General Commentaries on Skaldic Verse: Metrics, Style, Origins,
                Etc." A Bibliography of Skaldic Studies. Copenhagen: Ejnar Munksgaard, 1958. pp.
                27–55.</bib>
            <notes> (L693) </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="58">
            <bib> Jahresbericht über die Erscheinungen auf dem Gebiete der germanischen Philologie.
                Vols. 1–42; n.s. vols. 1–19. Berlin and Leipzig: [German Philological Society],
                1879–1939.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="59">
            <bib> Jahresberichte für neuere deutsche Litteraturgeschichte. Vols. 1–26. Stuttgart and
                Berlin, 1890– 1919.</bib>
            <notes> S.v. "Metrik." Continued as: </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="60">
            <bib> Jahresbericht über die wissenschaftlichen Erscheinungen auf dem Gebiete der
                neueren deutschen Literatur. N.s. vols. 1–19. Berlin and Leipzig, 1921–31.</bib>
            <notes> Publication suspended 1936–48. S.v. "Metrik." </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="61">
            <bib> Kayser, Wolfgang. Das sprachliche Kunstwerk: Eine Einführung in die
                Litteraturwissenschaft. Bern: A. Francke, 1948; 15th ed. 1971. pp. 391–418.</bib>
            <notes> (L425) The relevant sections of the bibliography are for chapters 3 and 8.
            </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="62">
            <bib> Lambrino, Scarlat. Bibliographie de l'antiquité classique, 1896–1914. Paris:
                Sociétés d'Édition "Les Belles Lettres," 1951.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="63">
            <bib> Lily, Ian K., and B. P. Scherr. "Russian Verse Theory Since 1960: A Commentary and
                Bibliography." International Journal of Slavic Linguistics and Poetics, no. 22
                (1976), pp. 75–116.</bib>
            <notes> (L1327) </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="64">
            <bib> Linguistic Bibliography/Bibliographie Linguistique. Published by the Permanent
                International Committee of Linguists Under the Auspices of the International Council
                for Philosophy and Humanistic Studies. Utrecht-Antwerp: Spectrum, 1937–1974</bib>
            <notes> (latest available). See Section 8 on "Prosody, Metre, Versification," beginning
                with the 1962 volume, and, less usefully, the section on "Stylistics," which has
                been included from the beginning of the series. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="65">
            <bib> Marouzeau, Jules. Dix Années de bibliographie classique: Bibliographie critique et
                analytique de l'antiquité gréco-latine par la periode 1914–1934. Paris: Sociétés
                d'Édition "Les Belles Lettres," 1927–28</bib>
            <notes>; rpt. New York: B. Franklin, 1969. </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="66">
            <bib> POETICS, POETYKA, POETIKA: First International Conference on Work-in-Progress
                Devouted to Problems of Poetics, Warsaw, 1960. Ed. Donald Davie et al. Warsaw:
                Polish Scientific Publishers, 1961.</bib>
            <notes> (A16) </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="67">
            <bib> POETICS, POETYKA, POETIKA: Third International Conference on Work-in-Progress
                Devoted to Problems of Poetics, Warsaw, 1964. Ed. Roman Jakobson et al. The Hague:
                Mouton, 1966.</bib>
            <notes> (A17) </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="68">
            <bib> Smith, G. S. "A Bibliography of Soviet Publications on Russian Versification Since
                1958." Russian Literature Triquarterly 6 (1973): 679–702.</bib>
            <notes> (L1375) </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="69">
            <bib> Thieme, Hugo P. Essai sur l'histoire du vers francais. Paris: Libraire ancienne
                Honoré Champion, 1916. 432 pp.</bib>
            <notes> (L972) </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="70">
            <bib> Wagner, Kurt. "Phonetik, Rhythmik, Metrik." Germanische Philologie: Ergebnisse und
                Aufgaben: Festschrift für Otto Behagel. Ed. Alfred Goetze, Wilhelm Horn, and
                Friedrich Maurer. Heidelberg: Carl Winter, 1934. pp. 3–18. </bib>
            <notes>(L636) Also Kuhn's following essay (L445). </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="71">
            <bib> Wimsatt, W. K., Jr., ed. Versification: Major Language Types. New York: New York
                University Press for MLA, 1970.</bib>
            <notes> </notes>
        </item>

         <item id="72">
            <bib> ÿhirmunskij, Viktor. Introduction to Metrics. The Hague: Mouton, 1966.</bib>
            <notes> (L1443) </notes>
        </item>
    </chapter>
</bibliography>
